<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-cap.593.4" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 https://code.ecoinformatics.org/code/eml/tags/RELEASE_EML_2_1_0/eml.xsd     eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://caplter.asu.edu/php/eml2_1_0/eml.xsd">

  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>asu_library</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>

  <dataset id="593.dataset">

    <alternateIdentifier system="asu_library">asu_collection_name_here</alternateIdentifier>
    <shortName>Sycamore Creek: algal biomass</shortName> 

    <title>Sycamore Creek Algal Biomass (Chlorophyll a and Ash Free Dry Mass), Phoenix Arizona, 1985 to 1988, 1991 to 1994, 2010 to 2013.</title>

    <creator id="593.creator.grimm">
      <positionName>co-principal investigator</positionName>
      <organizationName>School of Life Sciences</organizationName>
      <individualName><salutation>Dr</salutation><givenName>Nancy</givenName><givenName>B</givenName><surName>Grimm</surName></individualName>
    </creator>
    <creator id="593.creator.sabo">
      <positionName>co-principal investigator</positionName>
      <organizationName>School of Life Sciences</organizationName>
      <individualName><salutation>Dr</salutation><givenName>John</givenName><surName>Sabo</surName></individualName>
    </creator>
    <creator id="593.creator.marti">
      <organizationName>School of Life Sciences</organizationName>
      <individualName><givenName>Eugenia</givenName><surName>Marti</surName></individualName>
    </creator>
    <creator id="593.creator.fisher">
      <organizationName>School of Life Sciences</organizationName>
      <individualName><givenName>Stuart</givenName><surName>Fisher</surName></individualName>
    </creator>

    <metadataProvider id="593.metadataProvider.dong">
      <organizationName>School of Life Sciences</organizationName>
      <individualName><givenName>Xiaoli</givenName><surName>Dong</surName></individualName>
    </metadataProvider>
    <metadataProvider id="593.metadataProvider.pollard">
      <organizationName>School of Life Sciences</organizationName>
      <individualName><givenName>Lindsey</givenName><surName>Pollard</surName></individualName>
    </metadataProvider>

    <pubDate>2013-08-31</pubDate>

    <language>english</language>

    <abstract>
      <para>The primary objective of this project (2009-2013) is to understand how long-term climate variability and change influence the structure and function of desert streams via effects on hydrologic disturbance regimes. Climate and hydrology are intimately linked in arid landscapes; for this reason, desert streams are particularly well suited for both observing and understanding the consequences of climate variability and directional change. Researchers try to (1) determine how climate variability and change over multiple years influence stream biogeomorphic structure (i.e., prevalence and persistence of wetland and gravel-bed ecosystem states) via their influence on factors that control vegetation biomass, and (2) compare interannual variability in within-year successional patterns in ecosystem processes and community structure of primary producers and consumers of two contrasting reach types (wetland and gravel-bed stream reaches). This specific dataset was collected to understand changes of algal growth by month during the field season and same season in different years characterized by different hydrological regime. In 2009 and 2013, data was collected in both wetland reach and gravel reach to compare the difference of algal growth in two reach types in the same time of the year. Data collected in 1980s and 1990s include two reach types: riffle and run, and were also to understand the post-flood succession.</para>
    </abstract><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">biogeochemical patterns, processes, and human outcomes</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">human decisions and biodiversity</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">population studies</keyword><keywordThesaurus>IPA and Core Area CAP Data Portal Controler</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="place">sonoran desert</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">hydrology</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">chlorophyll a</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">long term</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">sycamore creek</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">biomass</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">biogeochemistry</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">desert stream</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">algae</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">ash free dry mass</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">afdm</keyword><keywordThesaurus>Creator Defined Keyword Set</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">caplter</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">central arizona phoenix longterm ecological research</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">arizona</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">caplter created</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">az</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">cap</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">arid land</keyword><keywordThesaurus>CAPLTER Keyword Set List</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet>

    
    
      
    

    <intellectualRights>
      
      <section>
        <para>Copyright Board of Regents, Arizona State University. This information is released to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes subject to the following restrictions:</para>
        <para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>While CAP LTER will make every effort possible to control and document the quality of the data it publishes, the data are made available 'as is'.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>CAP LTER cannot assume responsibility for damages resulting from mis-use or mis-interpretation of datasets or from errors or omissions that may exist in the data.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists that has resulted in data used in subsequent research.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>CAP LTER expects that any use of data from this server will be accompanied with the appropriate citations and acknowledgments.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>CAP LTER encourages users to contact the original investigator responsible for the data that they are accessing. Where appropriate, researchers whose projects are integrally dependent on CAP LTER data are encouraged to consider collaboration and/or co-authorship with original investigators.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>CAP LTER requests that users submit to the Global Institute of Sustainability, ASU, one copy of any publication resulting from the use of data obtained from this site.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>CAP LTER requests that users not redistribute data obtained from this site. However, links or references to this site may be freely posted.</para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>

    <distribution>
        <online><onlineDescription>CAPLTER Data Portal</onlineDescription><url>http://data.gios.asu.edu/cap/HarvestListFileShow.php?id=593</url></online>
    </distribution>

    <coverage id="593.coverage">
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Sycamore Creek Research Area</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-111.5254</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-111.5013</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>+33.7907</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>+33.7266</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1985-01-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1988-08-01</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1991-01-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1994-08-01</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2010-01-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2013-08-01</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>

    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>The Sycamore Creek is a Longterm Research Site, research will be ongoing</para>
      </description>
      <maintenanceUpdateFrequency>asNeeded</maintenanceUpdateFrequency>
    </maintenance>

    <contact id="593.contact.information_manager">
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>Global Institute of Sustainability, Arizona State University</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>POB 875402</deliveryPoint>
        <city>TEMPE</city>
        <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>85287-5402</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(480) 965 2975</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">(480) 965-8087</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>caplter.data@asu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    
    

    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Method Description:</title>
            <section>
              <title>Methods used for the 1985 to 1988, 1991 to 1994 sampling:</title>
              <para>Samples for epilithon standing stock and chlorophyll a are collected using a stratified random sampling design based on the number of habitat types (channel units) having substantially different epilithon biomass or type.  Within each habitat type that contains epilithon we need to collect a number of random samples within the study reach to calculate an average epilithon standing stock value for each habitat type.  However, the sample collection procedures differ depending on the habitat type.  For bedrock habitats, use a small cylinder of known area with a foam gasket attached to one end as the sampling template.  Push this template firmly against bedrock, vigorously scrape material using a wire brush, and suction scraped material into a bottle (using a turkey baster or large plastic syringe with tip cut off).  For rocks that can be picked up, choose 1-5 rocks (equivalent to a total planar area of about 100-200 cm2) and brush the rock surface thoroughly with a wire brush to loosen the epilithon and slurry the loosened material into a container.  After the epilithon has been removed, measure the approximate planar area of each rock brushed by tracing on a piece of paper (use paper from the same batch that has the same weight per unit area), cutting the tracings and weighing them.  If you are brushing more than 1 rock to obtain the desired sample area, combine all rocks collected at a particular sampling location into a single &#8220;pooled slurry&#8221; sample.  For fine-grained sediments the epilithon will be sampled as FBOM, unless it exits as a mat in which case it will be included as filamentous algae.</para>
              <para>In the laboratory the total volume of each slurry sample is determined and recorded.  Then one well-mixed subsample is measured out and filtered through a pre-combusted and tared glass fiber filter (47-mm diameter, Whatman GFF).  This filter is then dried at 60 C, weighed to determine dry mass, combusted (500 C) and reweighed to determine ash-free dry mass.  To compute standing stocks of epilithon for the entire stream, weight the averages for each habitat type by the relative proportions of each habitat type in the study reach.  Calculate all epilithon standing stocks both in terms of AFDM and dry mass per unit area.</para>
              <para>A second well-mixed subsample of the slurry is then measured out and filtered through another pre-combusted, 47-mm diameter GFF filter for chlorophyll a determination (place filter in aluminum foil packet, label, and freeze until analysis).</para>
              <para>Chlorophyll a measurement.  Chlorophyll a will be determined by hot ethanol extraction using the method of Sartory and Grobbelaar (Sartory, D. P. and J. E. Grobbelaar. 1984.  Extraction of chlorophyll a from freshwater phytoplankton for spectrophotometric analysis.  Hydrobiologia 114:177-187). Keep samples in the dark at all times, at least in low light when working on them. If the sample is kept in the dark, only 1.3% of the chlorophyll degrades with the 5 min. hot extraction and 24-hour storage.  Use test tubes that have the tube numbers scribed on the side with a diamond pencil (ethanol eventually extracts tube numbers written in sharpie, diamond pencils are about $15 at Carolina Biological Supplies) for filter extraction.  Place the filter, scrapped material from known area, or even an entire rock, in a container with a known volume (10 mL ethanol in screw cap tubes works well) of 95% ethanol.  Mark the location of the meniscus on the side of the tube with sharpie, and place a marble or loose cap on top of the tube.  Heat the tube at 79oC for 5 minutes, then mix and cool for 24 h in the dark (can be at room temperature, and can be sealed once cooled if screw cap tubes are used).  After extraction, use additional 95% ethanol to bring up to mark on side of tube if ethanol has evaporated, then mix.  Clear sample by centrifugation, filtration, or settling.  Analyze sample with spectrophotometric analysis at 665 and 750 nm using a 1 cm spectrophotometer cuvette (method in Standard Methods with different extinction coefficient for ethanol and conversion for chlorophyll per unit area).  If adsorption is over 1.5 absorbance units, dilute sample.  Add 0.1 mL of 0.1 N HCl for each 10 mL of extractant after the first reading and let sample sit for 90 s to phaeophytinize all chlorophyll before reading.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <title>Methods used for the 1985 to 1988, 1991 to 1994 sampling:</title>
              <para>Field procedure:</para>
              <para>Each algal type with an estimated percent cover equal (=) or less (&gt;) than 20% was collected (n=5 per type) within each reach.  Samples were collected using a plexiglass core measuring 5.6 cm in diameter.  Each sample was placed in either a urine cup or whirlpack and kept in the freezer until processed. Five rocks were also collected at random from each stream reach to analyze for algal/ biofilm.</para>
              <para>Laboratory procedure:</para>
              <para>Sediment samples were divided in half to run for chlorophyll and AFDM. Rock samples were scrubbed in a glass dish using a toothbrush. Excess water in each field sample container was filtered into folded 110 mm GF/A filters into a 200ml beaker.  Algae from scrubbed rocks were also poured through GF/A filters.  Algae remaining on dish and rocks were washed into filters using as little DI water as possible. Filters were cut in half for analysis of chlorophyll a and AFDM. Sediment along with half of the respective filters was placed together into a 200 mL beaker. Filters from rocks were also placed in 200 mL beakers.  20 mL of reagent grade methanol was added to beakers. Beakers were placed in water bath and allowed to boil at 80-85 celsius degrees for 2-4 minutes. Next, extract from each sample was poured into separate 100 ml beakers.  Methanol addition and boiling was repeated until no green pigment was visible on sediment, filter, or in extract. After final extraction, the total volume of extract collected for each sample was filtered through a GF/F filter (a GF/A was used for samples collected in 2010-2013).  Filtered extract was poured into a graduated cylinder.  The volume of extract was increased to the nearest 20 ml line by adding methanol. Volume was recorded and samples covered with parafilm to minimize evaporation. Absorbance values of extracts were measured at 750, 666, and 480 nm before and after acidification (see table below) using a Beckman DU copy right 530 Spectrophotometer.</para>
              <para>EXTRACT VOL -&gt; ACID ADDITION</para>
              <para>40 mL -&gt; 2.2 mL [40 mL] HCl</para>
              <para>60 mL -&gt; 2.2 mL [60 mL] HCl</para>
              <para>80 mL -&gt; 4.4 mL [40 mL] HCl</para>
              <para>100 mL -&gt; 2.2 mL [40 mL] HCl + 2.2 mL [60 mL] HCl</para>
              <para>120 mL -&gt; 4.4 mL [60 mL] HCl</para>
              <para>140 mL -&gt; 4.4 ml [40 mL] HCl + 2.2 mL [60 mL] HCl</para>
              <para>Chlorophyll calculations are made as follows:</para>
              <para>Chl a (mg/m^2) = 219. 2(D666-D666a) * v / A</para>
              <para>Where 219.2 is the absorption coefficient for chlorophyll a in methanol times the conversion from ug/cm2 to mg/m2; v is extraction volume in mL; A is  area of the sampled substrate, 12.315 cm2, half the area of collected core;  D666 is absorbance at 666 minus absorbance at 750 before acidification, and D666a is absorbance at 666 minus absorbance at 750 after acidification.</para>
              <para>AFDM</para>
              <para>Remaining gravel and filter samples were placed in labeled aluminum tins and allowed to dry in drying oven at 60 celsius degrees for at least 48 hours. Samples were removed, cooled and weighed for dry mass. Tins were covered individually with aluminum foil and placed in the muffle furnace to ash at 550 celsius degrees for 2 hours. Ashed samples were allowed to cool, then wet with DI water before placing in the drying oven for 48 hours at 60 celsius degrees. Samples were weighed again to determine ashed mass.</para>
              <para>AFDM calculations are made as follows:</para>
              <para>AFDM (g/m^2) = (Dry mass &#8211; Ashed mass)*10,000/ sample area (cm^2)</para>
              <para>Where substrate area = 12.315 cm^2 (half the area of collected core)</para>
            </section>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>

    <project id="syc_creek.grimm_sycamore_creek">
      <title>Long-term climate variability and ecosystem response in a desert stream, Sycamore Creek AZ.</title>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.grimm">
        <individualName><salutation>Dr</salutation><givenName>Nancy</givenName><givenName>B</givenName><surName>Grimm</surName></individualName>
        <role>principal investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.sabo">
        <individualName><salutation>Dr</salutation><givenName>John</givenName><surName>Sabo</surName></individualName>
        <role>principal investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.Pollard">
        <individualName><givenName>Lindsey</givenName><surName>Pollard</surName></individualName><role>research specialist</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.McGehee">
        <individualName><givenName>Jeremiah</givenName><surName>McGehee</surName></individualName><role>undergraduate student</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.Worth">
        <individualName><givenName>Erin</givenName><surName>Worth</surName></individualName><role>undergraduate student</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.Holland">
        <individualName><givenName>Emma</givenName><surName>Holland</surName></individualName><role>undergraduate student</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.Crenshaw">
        <individualName><givenName>Chelsea</givenName><surName>Crenshaw</surName></individualName><role>post-doc</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.hale">  
        <individualName><givenName>Rebecca</givenName><surName>Hale</surName></individualName>
        <role>former lab member</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.wong">  
        <individualName><givenName>Christina</givenName><surName>Wong</surName></individualName>
        <role>former lab member</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.dong">  
        <individualName><givenName>Xiaoli</givenName><surName>Dong</surName></individualName>
        <role>graduate student</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.burgess">  
        <individualName><givenName>Edward</givenName><surName>Burgess</surName></individualName>
        <role>former lab member</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.elrod">  
        <individualName><givenName>Kate</givenName><surName>Elrod</surName></individualName>
        <role>former lab member</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.kochert">  
        <individualName><givenName>Cathy</givenName><surName>Kochert</surName></individualName>
        <role>former lab member</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.olsen">  
        <individualName><givenName>Nick</givenName><surName>Olsen</surName></individualName>
        <role>research technician</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.moratto">  
        <individualName><givenName>Sarah</givenName><surName>Moratto</surName></individualName>
        <role>former lab member</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.turnbull">  
        <individualName><salutation>Dr</salutation><givenName>Laura</givenName><surName>Turnbull</surName></individualName>
        <role>lab member</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel id="syc_creek.personnel.earl">  
        <individualName><salutation>Dr</salutation><givenName>Stevan</givenName><surName>Earl</surName></individualName>
        <role>lab member</role>
      </personnel>
      <abstract>
        <para>The primary objective of this project is to understand how long-term climate variability influences the structure and function of desert streams.  Climate and hydrology are intimately linked in arid landscapes; for this reason, desert streams,  such as our study sites at Sycamore Creek, AZ, are particularly well suited for both observing and understanding the consequences of climate variability and directional change. Arid regions are characterized by high interannual variation in precipitation, and these climate patterns drive the overall disturbance regime (in terms of flooding and drying) and nutrient status of desert stream ecosystems.  At long time scales, the number and size of floods in a given year or cluster of years dictate nutrient delivery to streams from the surrounding catchment, and also influence the biogeomorphic structure of the stream-riparian corridor.  Embedded within this decadal-scale hydrologic regime, flash floods scour stream channels and initiate a series of rapid successional changes by benthic algae and macroinvertebrates at short time scales (i.e., within a year). An important goal of this research is to determine how recovery following discrete events is influenced by both stream nutrient status and channel structure and to thus better understand how long-term climate variability and change guide the interactions among slow (biogeomorphic change) and fast (post-flood succession) features and processes characteristic of desert stream ecosystems.</para>
      </abstract>
    </project>

    <otherEntity id="593.otherEntity.593_algalBiomass_1985_to_2013">
      <entityName>Algal growth in hydrological regime by month, 1985 to 1988, 1991 to 1994, and 2010 to 2013</entityName>
      <entityDescription>List of Included Files: 593_algalBiomass_1985_to_1994.csv, 593_algalBiomass_2010_to_2013.csv, 593_algalSampleCode.csv</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>593_algalBiomass_1985_to_2013.zip</objectName>
        <size unit="byte">49000</size>
        <compressionMethod>zip</compressionMethod>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat><formatName>PC ZIP Archive</formatName></externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution><online><url>http://data.gios.asu.edu/datasets/cap/593_algalBiomass_1985_to_2013.zip</url></online></distribution>
      </physical>
      <coverage id="593.datatable.coverage">
        
        <temporalCoverage>
          <rangeOfDates>
            <beginDate>
              <calendarDate>1985-01-01</calendarDate>
            </beginDate>
            <endDate>
              <calendarDate>1988-08-01</calendarDate>
            </endDate>
          </rangeOfDates>
        </temporalCoverage>
        <temporalCoverage>
          <rangeOfDates>
            <beginDate>
              <calendarDate>1991-01-01</calendarDate>
            </beginDate>
            <endDate>
              <calendarDate>1994-08-01</calendarDate>
            </endDate>
          </rangeOfDates>
        </temporalCoverage>
        
        <temporalCoverage>
          <rangeOfDates>
            <beginDate>
              <calendarDate>2010-01-01</calendarDate>
            </beginDate>
            <endDate>
              <calendarDate>2013-08-01</calendarDate>
            </endDate>
          </rangeOfDates>
        </temporalCoverage>
      </coverage>
      <attributeList id="593.all_csv_file_columns_defined_combined">
        
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_1985_to_1994.attribute.Year"><attributeName>Year</attributeName><attributeDefinition>The year when the sample was taken in the field</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_1985_to_1994.attribute.Month"><attributeName>Month</attributeName><attributeDefinition>The month when the sample was taken in the field</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_1985_to_1994.attribute.Date"><attributeName>Date</attributeName><attributeDefinition>The date when the sample was taken in the field</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_1985_to_1994.attribute.Site"><attributeName>Site</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Sites where samples were collected, in the following options: 1 and 2</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_1985_to_1994.attribute.sampleType"><attributeName>sampleType</attributeName><attributeDefinition>code for different types of algal samples</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_1985_to_1994.attribute.CHLa_MEAN"><attributeName>CHLa_MEAN</attributeName><attributeDefinition>mean concentration of Chl a. Unit: mg/m^2</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_1985_to_1994.attribute.CHLa_SE"><attributeName>CHLa_SE</attributeName><attributeDefinition>standard error of Chl a samples. NA, if only one sample was collected</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_1985_to_1994.attribute.AFDM_MEAN"><attributeName>AFDM_MEAN</attributeName><attributeDefinition>mean concentration of AFDM. Unit: g/m^2</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_1985_to_1994.attribute.AFDM_SE"><attributeName>AFDM_SE</attributeName><attributeDefinition>standard error of AFDM samples. NA, if only one sample was collected</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_2010_to_2013.attribute.year"><attributeName>year</attributeName><attributeDefinition>The year when the sample was taken in the field </attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_2010_to_2013.attribute.month"><attributeName>month</attributeName><attributeDefinition>The month when the sample was taken in the field</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_2010_to_2013.attribute.date"><attributeName>date</attributeName><attributeDefinition>The date when the sample was taken in the field</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_2010_to_2013.attribute.site"><attributeName>site</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Sites where samples were collected, in the following options: BMW, SS and RV </attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_2010_to_2013.attribute.sampleType"><attributeName>sampleType</attributeName><attributeDefinition>code for different types of algal samples</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_2010_to_2013.attribute.reach"><attributeName>reach</attributeName><attributeDefinition>reach where samples were collected; &#8220;W&#8221;- wetland reach; &#8220;G&#8221;- gravel reach </attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_2010_to_2013.attribute.CHLa_MEAN"><attributeName>CHLa_MEAN</attributeName><attributeDefinition>mean concentration of Chl a. Unit: mg/m2</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_2010_to_2013.attribute.CHLa_SE"><attributeName>CHLa_SE</attributeName><attributeDefinition>standard error of Chl a samples. NA, if only one sample was collected </attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_2010_to_2013.attribute.AFDM_MEAN"><attributeName>AFDM_MEAN</attributeName><attributeDefinition>mean concentration of AFDM. Unit: g/m2</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalBiomass_2010_to_2013.attribute.AFDM_SE"><attributeName>AFDM_SE</attributeName><attributeDefinition>standard error of AFDM samples. NA, if only one sample was collected</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        
        <attribute id="593.593_algalSampleCode.attribute.code"><attributeName>code</attributeName><attributeDefinition>the code for a particular algal type</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
        <attribute id="593.593_algalSampleCode.attribute.description"><attributeName>description</attributeName><attributeDefinition>the description of the particular algal type represented by the code</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>CHANGE_LATER_THIS_IS_A_PLACE_HOLDER</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <entityType>compressed folder (zip)</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
  </dataset>
</ns0:eml>