<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-pie.405.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=PIE,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <alternateIdentifier>EST-PR-SO-ZoopSurv.01</alternateIdentifier>
    <title>Zooplankton surveys using plankton tows along transects in the Plum Island Sound estuary</title>
    <creator id="pers-1">
      <organizationName>Plum Island Ecosystems LTER Program</organizationName>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Anne</givenName>
        <surName>Giblin</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>MBL</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>7 MBLSt</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Woods Hole</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
    </creator>
    <creator id="pers-2">
      <organizationName>Plum Island Ecosystems LTER Program</organizationName>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Peter</givenName>
        <surName>Milligan</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>School for Marine Science and Technology</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>University of Massachusetts Dartmouth</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>706 Rodney French Blvd</deliveryPoint>
        <city>New Bedford</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02744</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
    </creator>
    <creator id="pers-3">
      <organizationName>Plum Island Ecosystems LTER Program</organizationName>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Charles</givenName>
        <surName>Hopkinson</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>229 Marine Sciences</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <administrativeArea>GA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>30602</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>Plum Island Ecosystems LTER Program</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Woods Hole</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7485</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>pie_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://pie-lter.ecosystems.mbl.edu</onlineUrl>
    </metadataProvider>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Hap</givenName>
        <surName>Garritt</surName>
      </individualName>
      <role>additional investigator</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Jane</givenName>
        <surName>Tucker</surName>
      </individualName>
      <role>additional investigator</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2013</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>Zooplankton were collected in spring and late summer/fall at four stations representing the salinity gradient in the Parker River-Plum Island Sound estuary. Two size classes, &gt;335 micron and &gt;150 micron, were collected by net tows. Conductivity or salinty and temperature were recorded for each sample. Samples were concentrated to less than 250 mls and preserved in70% EtOH. For taxonomy, sample splits were taken such that a minimum of 250 individuals were present, and counted under a dissecting microscope. Individuals were identified to the lowest taxonomic level possible, generally to species. Adult copepods were additionally characterized by sex.</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>LTER</keyword>
      <keyword>PIE</keyword>
      <keyword>Plum Island Ecosystems</keyword>
      <keyword>Massachusetts</keyword>
      <keyword>Parker River</keyword>
      <keyword>Plum Island Sound</keyword>
      <keyword>population dynamics</keyword>
      <keyword>zooplankton</keyword>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>Acceptance and utilization of PIE-LTER data requires that:</para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The Principal Investigator be sent a notice stating reasons for acquiring any data and a description of the publication intentions.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The Principal Investigator of the data set be sent a copy of the report or manuscript prior to submission and be adequately cited in any resultant publications</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>A copy of any resultant publications should be sent to: 
            <literalLayout>
Principal Investigator
Ecosystems Center
Marine Biological Laboratory
Woods Hole, MA 02543
</literalLayout></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url>http://ecosystems.mbl.edu/PIE/data/EST/EST-PR-SO-ZoopSurv.html</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage id="GEO-1">
        <geographicDescription>Plum Island Sound, near Ipswich Bay Yacht Club (IBYC), Ipswich, MA</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-70.789676</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-70.789676</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>42.706588</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>42.706588</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage id="GEO-2">
        <geographicDescription>Lower Parker River, near Old Town Landing (OTL), Newbury, MA</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-70.836217</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-70.836217</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>42.761663</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>42.761663</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage id="GEO-3">
        <geographicDescription>Parker River, below Mill River confluence and above Railroad Bridge, Newbury, MA</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-70.87203</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-70.87203</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>42.755449</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>42.755449</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage id="GEO-4">
        <geographicDescription>Upper Parker River, near Triton High School, Newbury, MA</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-70.914366</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-70.914366</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>42.750348</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>42.750348</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2001-04-08</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2011-08-23</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>On going collections</para>
        <para>Version 01: 30Sep2013, metadata and data created to comply with importation to Drupal and LTER PASTA. Used MarcrosExportEML_HTML (working)pie_excel2007_Sep2013.xlsm 9/30/13 2:57 PM for QA/QC to EML 2.1.0</para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact id="im" system="knb">
      <positionName>Data Manager</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Woods Hole</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7485</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>pie_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://pie-lter.ecosystems.mbl.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <organizationName>Plum Island Ecosystems LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Woods Hole</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7485</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>pie_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://pie-lter.ecosystems.mbl.edu</onlineUrl>
    </publisher>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>
EXPERIMENTAL DESIGN AND METHODS: 
Zooplankton samples are collected and processed by PIE researchers according to the following:

NOTE: Only data from the &gt; 335&#181; and &gt;150&#181;  sample fractions are contained in this dataset.

Collections for plankton monitoring are done annually in the early Spring and late Summer, seasons of high and low discharge respectively. Collections are typically synchronized to occur during the same weeks as dawn/dusk whole system metabolism studies, sediment benthic flux studies and whole estuary nutrient transect water collections. Planktonic collections generally occurr during mid-low ebb tides.
Plankton are collected at four sites in the estuary representing varying salinities from near fresh water to near seawater.
The four site names were 
P2 (MON-PLNKT-EST-PR-21.75), P5 (MON-PLNKT-EST-PR-14), OTL (Old Town Landing, MON-PLNKT-EST-PR-10.5) and IBYC (Ipswich Bay Yacht Club, MON-PLNKT-EST-SO-2.5).
 
Sample collection
Four  plankton size classes are collected at each site, whole water, 20&#181;, 150&#181; and 335&#181;. 
The 20u sample is collected from the surface water using a calibrated bucket and pouring known volumes of water through a Sea Gear, 25 cm diameter, 20 u student plankton net. The cod end sample is transferred into a 500 ml wide mouth Nalgene container.
The 150u and 335u samples are collected via plankton tow using Sea Gear, 50 cm diameter, 150 or 335u plankton nets with General Oceanics Inc. Model 2030R mechanical flowmeters for measuring water volumes. The cod end samples from the 150 and 335 u nets were transferred into 1000 ml wide mouth Nalgene containers. All samples were stored in a cooler for transport back to the field station for preservation.
Plankton nets were towed for 30 &#8211; 300 seconds to ensure enough material for identification without exceeding the maximum amount that could be preserved adequately in 250 ml bottles.
 
For the small 20u student plankton net, buckets of known water volume were poured into the net and recorded.

For the larger plankton net tows, 150u and 335u with General Oceanics Flowmeter attached across the diameter of the hoop (0.5m), Start and stop counts were recorded prior to and after the plankton tow.

Calculations using Model 2030R standard flowmeter rotor:

10 counts are equal to 1 rotor revolution on the graphic labels on all flowmeters.
The cts/sec. Is &#8220;counts per second&#8221; and must not be used as revolutions per second for calculations.
Standard Speed Rotor Constant = 26,873

A. DISTANCE in meters = (Difference in COUNTS X Rotor Constant) / 999999
(Example: Where the graph may indicate 100 cts/sec this is also equal to 10
revolutions/sec). Therefore please ensure the correct units are being used when
measuring and calculating.

B. SPEED in cm/sec = (Distance in meters X 100) / Time in seconds

C. VOLUME cubic meters =( (3.14 X (Net Diameter)^2 ) X Distance) / 4


Sample preservation
Whole water
25 ml was sub sampled, saved in a wide mouth 250 ml polyproplylene bottle and 75 ml of 95% EtOH added for final 70% EtoH sample solution.

20u, 150u and 335u samples
To decrease the volume, the 20u, 150 u and 335u plankton material was filtered through 20u mesh Nitex and the filtered material was saved in a labeled wide mouth 250 ml polyproplylene bottle and preserved with EtOH to make a final conc of 70% EtOH (ie. 25 ml sample and 75 ml 95% EtOH for 1:3 ratio water to EtOH). The samples were rinsed down on the 20 u Nitex using the corresponding ambient site water from the 20u filtrate fraction.



Taxonomy and counts of zooplanton samples from 2001-2011 were performed by Peter Milligan, in the laboratory o fDr.  Jefferson Turner at UMass Dartmouth, as follows:

Samples were reduced to aliquots of at least 250 animals with a Folsom plankton splitter, and animals are counted under a dissecting microscope and identified to the lowest possible taxon. In most cases, this will be to species; adult copepods will be additionally characterized by sex. Counts of all copepodite stages of a given copepod genus will be combined. Copepod nauplii will not be identified to genus or species because nauplii species cannot be reliably identified to those levels by using a dissecting microscope. Meroplankters cannot be identified to genus or species in most cases, and such organisms will be identified to the lowest reliable taxon, such as barnacle nauplii, fish eggs, or gastropod veligers. Concentrations of total zooplankton and all identified taxa are calculated based on the number of animals counted, multiplied by the aliquot concentration factor, and divided by the volume of filtered by the net.  

 For instance, if 400 animals were counted in a 1/256 split, and the volume filtered was 4.2 cubic meters, then the calculation would be 400 x 256 = 102,400, and 102,400 divided by 4.2 = 24,381 animals per cubic meter. 
</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>Plum Island Ecosystems Long-Term Ecological Research (PIE LTER) Program</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Anne</givenName>
          <surName>Giblin</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Woods Hole</city>
          <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7488</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>agiblin@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Lead PI</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Hap</givenName>
          <surName>Garritt</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Woods Hole</city>
          <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7485</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>pie_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Information Manager</role>
      </personnel>
      <abstract>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>
The Plum Island Ecosystems (PIE) LTER is an integrated research, education and outreach program whose goal is to develop a predictive understanding of the long-term response of watershed and estuarine ecosystems at the land-sea interface to changes in climate, land use and sea level. The principal study site is the Plum Island Sound estuary, its coupled Parker, Rowley and Ipswich River watersheds and the adjacent coastal ocean, the Gulf of Maine. The PIE LTER focuses on how several aspects of global change influence organic matter and inorganic nutrient biogeochemistry and estuarine foodwebs. The inputs of organic matter and nutrients from land, ocean and marshes interact with the external drivers (climate, land use, river discharge, sea level) to dictate the extent and degree of nutrient and organic matter processing and determine the spatial patterns of estuarine productivity and trophic structure.
</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </abstract>
      <funding>
        <para>This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation under Grants OCE-9726921, OCE-0423565, OCE-1058747, OCE-1238212. Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed in the material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.</para>
      </funding>
      <studyAreaDescription>
        <coverage>
          <geographicCoverage>
            <geographicDescription>The Plum Island Ecosystems (PIE) LTER site, is located in northeastern Massachusetts, 42.72 N, 70.85 W. The PIE LTER lies at the interface of a thinly soiled, formerly glaciated New England land mass and the highly productive Gulf of Maine. Three watersheds comprise the estuarine drainage basin: Parker (155 km2), Rowley (26 km2) and Ipswich (404 km2). The Ipswich River watershed is highly urbanized with Boston "bedroom" communities encroaching in the headwater region while the Parker is less urbanized and retains a higher proportion of forest.</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-71.2198</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-70.7568</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>42.8276</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>42.4965</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>0</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>100</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </geographicCoverage>
        </coverage>
      </studyAreaDescription>
    </project>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>EST-PR-SO-ZoopSurv.csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Zooplankton surveys using plankton tows along transects in the Plum Island Sound estuary</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>EST-PR-SO-ZoopSurv.csv</objectName>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>http://ecosystems.mbl.edu/PIE/data/EST/data/EST-PR-SO-ZoopSurv.csv</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute id=" att0.1">
          <attributeName>DATE</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DATE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>date of sampling (dd-mon-yyyy)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>dd-mon-yyyy</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.2">
          <attributeName>STATION ID</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>STATION ID</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>location sampled, either specific station or bounding box</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>location sampled, either specific station or bounding box</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.3">
          <attributeName>STATION NAME KM</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>STATION NAME KM</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>station name indicating distance upstream from mouth of Plum Island Sound (km 0)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>station name indicating distance upstream from mouth of Plum Island Sound (km 0)</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.4">
          <attributeName>SITE</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>SITE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>descriptive site names [IBYC = Ipswich Bay Yacht Club, OTL = Old Town Landing, P5 = Parker R. site 5(retired name), P2 = Parker R. site 2 (retired name)]</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>IBYC</code>
                    <definition>Ipswich Bay Yacht Club</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>OTL</code>
                    <definition>Old Town Landing</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>P5</code>
                    <definition>Parker R. site 5(retired name)</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>P2</code>
                    <definition>Parker R. site 2 (retired name)</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.5">
          <attributeName>LAT</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>LAT</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Latitude of sample location in NAD 83 geographic coordinates (decimal degrees)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.6">
          <attributeName>LON</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>LON</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Longitude of sample location in NAD 83 geographic coordinates (decimal degrees)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.7">
          <attributeName>DIST</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DIST</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>distance upstream from the mouth of the estuary</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.8">
          <attributeName>SAMPLE NAME</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>SAMPLE NAME</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Zooplankton specific subsample name</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Zooplankton specific subsample name</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.9">
          <attributeName>TIME</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>TIME</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>time of sample collection</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>hh:mm</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.10">
          <attributeName>TEMP</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>TEMP</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>temperature (oC)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <interval>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </interval>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.11">
          <attributeName>SAL</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>SAL</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>salinity (ppt)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>partPerThousand</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.12">
          <attributeName>COND</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>COND</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Specific conductivity (mS/cm)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>millisiemenPerCentimeter</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.13">
          <attributeName>COUNT START</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>COUNT START</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>count of flowmeter revolutions marking starting point of net tow</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.14">
          <attributeName>COUNT END</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>COUNT END</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>count of flowmeter revolutions marking end point of net tow</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.15">
          <attributeName>COUNT DIFF</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>COUNT DIFF</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>difference in start and end counts on flowmeter, used to calculate volume</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.16">
          <attributeName>TOW TIME</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>TOW TIME</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>duration of tow (sec)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>second</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.17">
          <attributeName>VOLUME</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>VOLUME</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>total volume of water filtered for analysis (L)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>liter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.18">
          <attributeName>SIZE FRACTION</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>SIZE FRACTION</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>either &gt; 150&#181; or &gt; 335&#181; size classes</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>either &gt; 150&#181; or &gt; 335&#181; size classes</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.19">
          <attributeName>SUBSAMPLE FRAC</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>SUBSAMPLE FRAC</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>fraction of entire sample volume counted</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.20">
          <attributeName>TAXON</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>TAXON</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>taxon to lowest level identified (F=female, M=male, A=adult, J=juvenile)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>taxon to lowest level identified (F=female, M=male, A=adult, J=juvenile)</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.21">
          <attributeName>NUMBER COUNTED</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>NUMBER COUNTED</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>number of individuals counted in subsample</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.22">
          <attributeName>NUMBERperTOW</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>NUMBERperTOW</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>total number of individuals per tow</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.23">
          <attributeName>ABUNDANCE</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>ABUNDANCE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>number of individuals per volume (#/m3)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>numberPerMeterCubed</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>NA = sample or value missing or lost</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>1762</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <unitList>
        <unit id="partPerThousand" multiplierToSI="1" name="partPerThousand" parentSI="" unitType="dimensionless">
          <description>ratio of two quantities as parts per thousand (1:1000)</description>
        </unit>
        <unit id="millisiemenPerCentimeter" multiplierToSI="0.00001" name="millisiemenPerCentimeter" parentSI="siemenPerMeter" unitType="conductance">
          <description>conductivity unit</description>
        </unit>
      </unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>