<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-and.4541.3" system="&#10;     http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/data/mastercatalog.cfm?topnav=97" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0&#10;     http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=AND,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <alternateIdentifier>HF020</alternateIdentifier>
    <title>A Study of Hyporheic Characteristics Along a Longitudinal Profile of Lookout Creek, Oregon, 2003</title>
    <creator>
      <organizationName>Andrews Forest LTER Site</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Forest Ecosystems and Society Department in Forestry</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>Oregon State University</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>201K Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Corvallis</city>
        <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-8480</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>lterweb@fsl.orst.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/</onlineUrl>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Jeffery</givenName>
        <givenName>J.</givenName>
        <surName>Ninnemann</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <city>Bellingham</city>
        <administrativeArea>WA</administrativeArea>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone>360-756-9308</phone>
      <phone>360-661-3546</phone>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Jeffery</givenName>
        <givenName>J.</givenName>
        <surName>Ninnemann</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <city>Bellingham</city>
        <administrativeArea>WA</administrativeArea>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone>360-756-9308</phone>
      <phone>360-661-3546</phone>
    </metadataProvider>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Steven</givenName>
        <givenName>M.</givenName>
        <surName>Wondzell</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Pacific Northwest Research Station; Corvallis Forestry Sciences Lab; 3200 SW Jefferson Way</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Corvallis</city>
        <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>97331</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone>541-758-8753</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>swondzell@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.fsl.orst.edu/lwm/aem/people/wondzell</onlineUrl>
      <role>Other Researcher</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Roy</givenName>
        <surName>Haggerty</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Dept. of Geosciences;Wilkinson 104;Oregon State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Corvallis</city>
        <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>97331</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone>541-737-1210</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>haggertr@geo.oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.geo.oregonstate.edu/people/faculty/haggertr.htm</onlineUrl>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Michael</givenName>
        <givenName>N.</givenName>
        <surName>Gooseff</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Dept. of Civil &amp; Environmental Engineering</deliveryPoint>
        <city>University Park</city>
        <administrativeArea>PA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>16802</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone>814.867.0044</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>mng2@psu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <electronicMailAddress>mgooseff@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://water.engr.psu.edu/gooseff/</onlineUrl>
      <role>Other Researcher</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2013-09-09</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>Time series of tracer (Rhodamine WT) concentration data representing a "break-through curve" resulting from a single, multi-scale tracer test conducted along the length of Lookout Creek, from its 2nd-order headwaters through its 5th-order main stem.  The longitudinal tracer test involved an in-stream injection of Rhodamine WT over 78 hrs, followed by monitoring at eight downstream locations for five months, starting in mid-June 2003 through the middle of November 2003. The injection site was located below the upper Old Growth Trail bridge.  The monitoring sites include one downstream of the injection site, above and below the Cold Creek confluence, below the lower Old Growth Trail bridge, below Mack Creek confluence, above and below McRae Creek confluence, and at the HJA headquarters. Three additional inter-order tracer tests (IOTT) were carried out between each of the major stream confluences along Lookout Creek.  The injection site for the McRae Creek IOTT was located below the McRae Cr. confluence and was monitored just downstream, at the end of the main floodplain, and at HJA headquarters. The injection site for the Mack Creek IOTT was located below the Mack Cr. confluence and was monitored just downstream, at an unnamed tributary midway between Mack Cr. and McRae Cr., and above the McRae Cr. confluence. The injection site for the Cold Creek IOTT was located below the Cold Cr. confluence and was monitored just downstream, at Longer Cr., and at the lower Old Growth Trail bridge. Concentration break through curves are available for all of the monitoring sites for the longitudinal and inter-order tracer tests.  Flux break through curves are available for most of the monitoring sites.  STAMMT-L model estimates for hyporheic exchange is listed for most of the monitoring sites.</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Geology/geomorphology</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Hydrology/Water</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Hyporheic zone</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Andrews Experimental Forest site
								thesaurus</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>Data Use Agreement:</para>
<para> Any Andrews Experimental Forest data set and accompanying metadata available on these web pages can be downloaded for academic, research, recreational, and other professional purposes. Permission to download data sets is granted to the Data User without a fee subject to the following terms. The Data User will: </para>
<para><itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para> notify the designated contact (e.g., Principle Investigator or Data Set Contact) when any derivative work based on or derived from the data and documentation is distributed;
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para> notify users that such derivative work is a modified version and not the original data and documentation distributed by the Andrews LTER;
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para> not redistribute original data and documentation; 
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para> acknowledge the support of the Andrews LTER and appropriate NSF Grant numbers in any publications using these data and documentation. (See general acknowledgement below and see web page for specific data citation for each study data set);
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para> send two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the data and documentation to the following address:  Andrews Experimental Forest LTER Program, c/o Don Henshaw, Forestry Sciences Lab, 3200 SW Jefferson Way, Corvallis, OR 97331
		</para></listitem>		
</itemizedlist></para>
<para> By using or copying these data and documentation, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Andrews Experimental Forest LTER Site shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement. Thank you for your cooperation. We hope your collaboration with our site is a productive one!</para>
<para> Disclaimer:  While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is". The Andrews Experimental Forest LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of data sets.</para>
<para>General acknowledgement:  Data were provided by the HJ Andrews Experimental Forest research program, funded by the National Science Foundation's Long-Term Ecological Research Program (DEB 08-23380), US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, and Oregon State University. </para></intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/lter/data/abstract.cfm?dbcode=HF020&amp;topnav=135</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Lookout Creek Catchment</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.25276000</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.11756400</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>44.23357900</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>44.21329300</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>426</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>1036</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2003-06-14</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2003-11-15</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <purpose>
      <para>The primary goal of this research project is to quantitatively measure the temporal scales of hyporheic exchange along a stream network.  Our goal is to examine how hyporheic exchange varies with increasing stream size.  Many previous studies focus on single stream reaches or on several reaches of similar sized streams, whereas we examined the residence time of water in the hyporheic zone over increasing length scales in a single stream.   Prior work with tracer data and analysis using a transient storage model with an exponential residence time distribution (RTD) suggests that hyporheic parameters, primarily volume and mean residence time, are both spatially and temporally scale-dependent.  However, recent work hypothesizes that the scale-dependence may be partially addressed by using a power-law RTD (Haggerty et al., 2002). Our research tests this hypothesis with several multi-scale tracer tests in a single stream.</para>
    </purpose>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para> An update history is logged and maintained with each new
									version of every dataset. </para>
        </section>
      </description>
      <maintenanceUpdateFrequency>notPlanned</maintenanceUpdateFrequency>
      <changeHistory>
        <changeScope>Initial database level metadata entry from Word document using Administrative Interface.</changeScope>
        <oldValue>Version1</oldValue>
        <changeDate>2007-07-13</changeDate>
      </changeHistory>
      <changeHistory>
        <changeScope>Upoaded metadata and data to SQL using move_xls programs.</changeScope>
        <oldValue>Version2</oldValue>
        <changeDate>2008-03-05</changeDate>
      </changeHistory>
      <changeHistory>
        <changeScope>Have not heard from Jeff Ninneman since 2006.  Tried to contact him in 2008.  Am making this database available online and uploading to PASTA.</changeScope>
        <oldValue>Version3</oldValue>
        <changeDate>2013-09-09</changeDate>
      </changeHistory>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Andrews Forest LTER Program</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>3200 SW Jefferson Way </deliveryPoint>
        <city>Corvallis</city>
        <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>97331</postalCode>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(541) 750-7335</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>hjaweb@fsl.orst.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Roy</givenName>
        <surName>Haggerty</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Dept. of Geosciences;Wilkinson 104;Oregon State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Corvallis</city>
        <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>97331</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone>541-737-1210</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>haggertr@geo.oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.geo.oregonstate.edu/people/faculty/haggertr.htm</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <organizationName>Andrews Forest LTER Site</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Forest Ecosystems and Society Department in Forestry</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>Oregon State University</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>201K Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Corvallis</city>
        <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-8480</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>lterweb@fsl.orst.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/</onlineUrl>
    </publisher>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>Experimental Design - HF020</description>
      </methodStep>
      <sampling>
        <studyExtent>
          <description>&lt;para&gt;This study was conducted along the main stem of Lookout Creek in the H.J. Andrews. Monitoring sites included sites below the upper old growth trail bridge, above and below the Cold Cr. confluence, above and below the Mack Cr. confluence, above and below the McRae Cr. confluence, at the first valley constriction below the concrete bridge, and at the Headquarters. &lt;/para&gt;
&lt;para&gt;
The Longitudinal Tracer Test was conducted along the main stem of Lookout Creek. The injection site was located ~30 m downstream of the upper old growth trail bridge. There were eight monitoring sites below the injections site. Three fluorometer sites were stationed on Lookout Creek just up stream of Cold Cr., Mack Cr., and McRae Cr.. The fluorometers were 1032 m (Site 2), 4145 m (Site 6), and 8,907 m (Site 11) downstream of the injection site (as shown in Figure 1).  One ISCO sampler was located 84 m below the injection site (not shown on map). Four additional ISCO monitoring sites were established below each of the confluences and near the base of the basin. The ISCO monitoring sites were 1,137 m (Site 4), 5,126 m (Site 7), 9,327 m (Site 12), and 14,274 m (Site 14) (Figure 1). &lt;/para&gt;
&lt;para&gt;
Three additional tracer tests were also conducted between each major confluence within Lookout Creek.  These inter-order tracer tests encompassed changes in stream scale from a 3&lt;superscript&gt;rd&lt;/superscript&gt;-order drainage basin to a 5&lt;superscript&gt;th&lt;/superscript&gt;-order drainage basin. &lt;/para&gt;
&lt;para&gt;
The first inter-order tracer test was a conducted between the confluence of McRae Creek and the H.J. Andrews headquarters.  The injection site was located ~150 m downstream of the McRae Creek confluence (site 11).  This tracer test was monitored 5,367 m downstream at the H.J. Andrews headquarters with a fluorometer (Site 14). The concentration of dye was also monitored 1,465 m downstream by an ISCOtm sampler at a position in the stream where the geomorphology changes from a floodplain to a constrained valley (Site 13). An additional ISCO sampler was located 420 m below the injection site (Site 12).  &lt;/para&gt;
&lt;para&gt;
The second inter-order tracer test was a conducted between the confluence of Mack Creek and McRae Creek.  The injection site was located ~25 m downstream of the Mack Creek confluence (site 7).  This tracer test was monitored 3,457 m downstream above the McRae Cr. confluence with a fluorometer (site 10). It was also monitored 1,001 m downstream by an ISCOtm sampler at the largest tributary between Mack and McRae Cr (site 9).  An additional ISCO sampler was located 25 m below the injection site (Site 8).  &lt;/para&gt;
&lt;para&gt;
The third IOTT was a conducted between the confluence of Cold Creek and Mack Creek. .  The injection site was located ~10 m downstream of the Cold Creek confluence (site 3).  This tracer test was monitored 3,054 m downstream at a site above the Mack Cr. confluence with a fluorometer (site 6) and 2,105 m downstream by an ISCO sampler at Longer Cr.(site 5), the largest tributary between Mack and McRae Cr..  An additional ISCO sampler was located 46 m below the injection site (Site 4).  &lt;/para&gt; &lt;para&gt;Sampling frequency: a range of every 30 seconds to monthly&lt;/para&gt;</description>
        </studyExtent>
        <samplingDescription>
          <para>Stream discharge at the injection sites during the injections for the longitudinal tracer test and the inter-order tracer tests were measured by wading, using a Marsh-McBirney model 200 flow meter (Marsh-McBirney, Inc., Fredrick, MD, USA). Stream discharge during the duration of the tracer tests was measured at the USGS gauge house at the below headquarters on Lookout Creek. Hydrograph regressions were used with gauged watersheds within the H.J. Andrews to estimate a continuous discharge for all sites. Turner DesignTM model 10-AU fluorometers (Turner Designs, Inc, Sunnyvale, CA) were used to monitor concentrations at some sites.  All samples collected with ISCO auto samplers (ISCO, Inc., Lincoln, NE) were analyzed with the same Turner Designs fluorometers (Turner Designs, Inc, Sunnyvale, CA). Four continuous injection tracer experiments were performed over various lengths of Lookout Creek in the HJ Andrews Experimental Forest.</para>
        </samplingDescription>
        <spatialSamplingUnits>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Site 00 - LTT Injection</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.11756400</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.11756400</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.22178700</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.22178700</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>1036</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>1036</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Site 01 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Injection ISCO Site</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.11817300</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.11817300</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.22294400</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.22294400</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>1030</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>1030</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Site 02 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Above Cold Creek Site</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.12568300</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.12568300</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.22817900</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.22817900</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>926</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>926</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Site 03 - Cold Creek injection</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.12623100</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.12623100</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.22837200</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.22837200</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>914</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>914</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Site 04 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Below Cold Creek Site and</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.12684200</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.12684200</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.22854800</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.22854800</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>902</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>902</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Site 05 - Cold Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Longer Creek Si</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.14919500</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.14919500</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.23357900</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.23357900</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>774</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>774</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Site 06 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Above Mack Creek Site and</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.15956100</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.15956100</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.23203600</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.23203600</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>731</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>731</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Site 07 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Below Mack Creek Site</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.16831200</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.16831200</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.22768800</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.22768800</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>655</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>655</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Site 08 - Mack Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Injection ISCO</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.16888400</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.16888400</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.22796300</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.22796300</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>652</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>652</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Site 09 - Mack Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Middle Tributar</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.17916800</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.17916800</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.23037800</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.23037800</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>612</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>612</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Site 10 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Above McRae Creek Site an</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.20667900</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.20667900</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.23310400</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.23310400</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>559</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>559</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Site 11 - McRae Creek injection</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.21037000</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.21037000</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.23339000</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.23339000</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>548</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>548</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Site 12 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Below McRae Creek Site an</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.21483100</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.21483100</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.23216100</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.23216100</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>536</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>536</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Site 13 - McRae Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Floodplain Sit</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.22479300</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.22479300</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.22879000</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.22879000</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>499</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>499</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Site 14 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Headquarters Site and McR</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.25276000</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.25276000</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.21329300</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.21329300</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>426</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>426</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
        </spatialSamplingUnits>
      </sampling>
      <methodStep>
        <description>&lt;para&gt;Field Methods - HF020&lt;/para&gt;&lt;para&gt;The Longitudinal Tracer Test was conducted along the main stem of Lookout Creek. The injection site was located ~30 m downstream of the upper old growth trail bridge. There were eight monitoring sites below the injections site. Three fluorometer sites were stationed on Lookout Creek just up stream of Cold Cr., Mack Cr., and McRae Cr.. The fluorometers were 1032 m (Site 2), 4145 m (Site 6), and 8,907 m (Site 11) downstream of the injection site (as shown in Figure 1).  One ISCO sampler was located 84 m below the injection site (not shown on map). Four additional ISCO monitoring sites were established below each of the confluences and near the base of the basin. The ISCO monitoring sites were 1,137 m (Site 4), 5,126 m (Site 7), 9,327 m (Site 12), and 14,274 m (Site 14) (Figure 1).&lt;/para&gt;

&lt;para&gt;Three additional tracer tests were also conducted between each major confluence within Lookout Creek.  These inter-order tracer tests encompassed changes in stream scale from a 3&lt;superscript&gt;rd&lt;/superscript&gt;-order drainage basin to a 5&lt;superscript&gt;th&lt;/superscript&gt;-order drainage basin.&lt;/para&gt;

&lt;para&gt;The first inter-order tracer test was a conducted between the confluence of McRae Creek and the H.J. Andrews headquarters.  The injection site was located ~150 m downstream of the McRae Creek confluence (site 11).  This tracer test was monitored 5,367 m downstream at the H.J. Andrews headquarters with a fluorometer (Site 14). The concentration of dye was also monitored 1,465 m downstream by an ISCOtm sampler at a position in the stream where the geomorphology changes from a floodplain to a constrained valley (Site 13). An additional ISCO sampler was located 420 m below the injection site (Site 12).  &lt;/para&gt;

&lt;para&gt;The second inter-order tracer test was a conducted between the confluence of Mack Creek and McRae Creek.  The injection site was located ~25 m downstream of the Mack Creek confluence (site 7).  This tracer test was monitored 3,457 m downstream above the McRae Cr. confluence with a fluorometer (site 10). It was also monitored 1,001 m downstream by an ISCOtm sampler at the largest tributary between Mack and McRae Cr (site 9).  An additional ISCO sampler was located 25 m below the injection site (Site 8).  &lt;/para&gt;
&lt;para&gt;
The third IOTT was a conducted between the confluence of Cold Creek and Mack Creek.  The injection site was located ~10 m downstream of the Cold Creek confluence (site 3).  This tracer test was monitored 3,054 m downstream at a site above the Mack Cr. confluence with a fluorometer (site 6) and 2,105 m downstream by an ISCO sampler at Longer Cr. (site 5), the largest tributary between Mack and McRae Cr..  An additional ISCO sampler was located 46 m below the injection site (Site 4).  &lt;/para&gt;

&lt;para&gt;Longitudinal Tracer Test (tracer test 1), June 14, 2003 &lt;/para&gt;
&lt;para&gt;&lt;itemizedlist&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;1603.8 grams of Rhodamine WT (RWT, Fomulabs, Piqua, OH) was injected into the upper reaches of Lookout Creek for 78 h. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;Stream flow was measured by wading, using a Marsh-McBirney model 200 flow meter ~40 m downstream of the injection site, 7 hours prior to the tracer experiment, and daily for three consecutive days. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;RWT fluorescence data was collected at three downstream sample points using Turner Designs model 10 AU field fluorometers. All fluorometers were set up with a flow-through cell. Samples were also collected with programmable field auto samplers at additional sites. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;Data was collected on a 30-second interval for the first 8 to 10 days depending on the site. For the remainder of the experiment, stream water samples were collected with programmable field auto samplers for an additional 23 to 144 days. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;&lt;/itemizedlist&gt;&lt;/para&gt;

&lt;para&gt;Cold Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test (tracer test 2), July 8, 2003 &lt;/para&gt;
&lt;para&gt;&lt;itemizedlist&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;224.3 grams of Rhodamine WT (RWT, Fomulabs, Piqua, OH) was injected into Lookout Creek, below McRae Creek for 17 h. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;Stream flow was measured by wading, using a Marsh-McBirney model 200 flow meter ~40 m downstream of the injection site, 24 hours prior to the tracer experiment. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;RWT fluorescence data was collected at a downstream sample point using Turner Designs model 10 AU field fluorometer, set-up with a flow-through cell. Samples were also collected with programmable field auto samplers at additional sites. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;Data was collected on a 30-second interval for the first 2.3 days. For the remainder of the experiment, stream water samples were collected with programmable field auto samplers for an additional 12 days. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;

&lt;para&gt;Mack Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test (tracer test 3), August 7, 2003 &lt;/para&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;321 grams of Rhodamine WT (RWT, Fomulabs, Piqua, OH) was injected into Lookout Creek, below Mack Creek for 26 h. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;Stream flow was measured by wading, using a Marsh-McBirney model 200 flow meter ~10 m downstream of the injection site, 24 hours prior to the tracer experiment. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;RWT fluorescence data was collected at a downstream sample point using Turner Designs model 10 AU field fluorometer, set-up with a flow-through cell. Samples were also collected with programmable field auto samplers at additional sites. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;Data was collected on a 30-second interval for the first 3 days. For the remainder of the experiment, stream water samples were collected with programmable field auto samplers for an additional 12 days. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;&lt;/itemizedlist&gt;&lt;/para&gt;

&lt;para&gt;Cold Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test (tracer test 4), September 11, 2003 &lt;/para&gt;
&lt;para&gt;&lt;itemizedlist&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;296 grams of Rhodamine WT (RWT, Fomulabs, Piqua, OH) was injected into Lookout Creek, below Mack Creek for 24 h. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;Stream flow was measured by wading, using a Marsh-McBirney model 200 flow meter ~46 m downstream of the injection site, 2 hours prior to the tracer experiment. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;RWT fluorescence data was collected at a downstream sample point using Turner Designs model 10 AU field fluorometer, set-up with a flow-through cell. Samples were also collected with programmable field auto samplers at additional sites. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;
&lt;listitem&gt;&lt;para&gt;Data was collected on a 30-second interval for the first 4 days. For the remainder of the experiment, stream water samples were collected with programmable field auto samplers for an additional 41 days. &lt;/para&gt;&lt;/listitem&gt;</description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>Instrumentation - HF020</para>
          <para>The longitudinal tracer test and McRae Creek inter-order tracer test was facilitated by a Fluid Meter Inc. (FMI) DC injection pump (model # RHB1). The Mack Creek and Cold Creek inter-order tracer tests were conducted using a new Fluid Meter Inc. AC injection pump (model # QG150, with a Q1CKC pump head).  The discharges in the streams were measured using a Marsh-McBirney, Inc Flo-MateTM flow meter.  The concentration of RWT was measured using a Turner DesignTM model 10-AU fluorometers and Teledyne ISCOTM samplers.</para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>Processing Procedure - HF020</para>
          <para>In order to calculate flux breakthrough curves we needed to have a continuous record of discharge for each site. The discharge hydrographs of each site was estimated using a linear hydrograph regression from gauged watersheds within the H.J. Andrews. The hydrograph watershed regression was accomplished using point discharges gathered by Jeff Ninnemann and Charles Fardy throughout the summer and matched with one of the 10 gauged watersheds for a best fit linear regression. The linear relationship established between individual site discharges and watershed gauge datum was then used to estimate a discharge for each individual monitoring site.</para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>Long-Term Ecological Research</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Mark</givenName>
          <givenName>E.</givenName>
          <surName>Harmon</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Dept. of Forest Science;321 Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Corvallis</city>
          <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <phone>(541) 737-8455</phone>
        <phone>(978) 724-0045 ext 223</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>mark.harmon@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Sherri</givenName>
          <givenName>L.</givenName>
          <surName>Johnson</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>US Forest Service ;Pacific NW Research Station ;3200 SW Jefferson Way</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Corvallis</city>
          <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>97331</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <phone>(541) 758-7771</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>sherri.johnson@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <electronicMailAddress>sherrijohnson@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Julia</givenName>
          <givenName>A.</givenName>
          <surName>Jones</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Department of Geosciences; Wilkinson Hall 104</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Corvallis</city>
          <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>97331-5506</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <phone>(541) 737-1224</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>geojulia@comcast.net</electronicMailAddress>
        <electronicMailAddress>jonesj@geo.oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <onlineUrl>http://www.geo.oregonstate.edu/people/faculty/jonesj.htm</onlineUrl>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Thomas</givenName>
          <givenName>A.</givenName>
          <surName>Spies</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>USDA Forest Service;Pacific NW Research Station;3200 SW Jefferson Way</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Corvallis</city>
          <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>97331</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <phone>(541) 750-7354</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>tom.spies@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <electronicMailAddress>tspies@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Michael</givenName>
          <givenName>P.</givenName>
          <surName>Nelson</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
        </address>
        <phone>
        </phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>mpnelson@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <onlineUrl>http://www.michaelpnelson.com</onlineUrl>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Mark</givenName>
          <surName>Schulze</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>HJ Andrews Experimental Forest;PO Box 300</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Blue River</city>
          <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>97413</postalCode>
        </address>
        <phone>541-822-6336</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>mark.schulze@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <abstract>
        <para>The H.J. Andrews Experimental Forest is a living laboratory that provides unparalleled opportunities for the study of forest and stream ecosystems in the central Cascade Range of Oregon. Since 1980, as a part of the National Science Foundation Long Term Ecological Research (NSF-LTER) program, the Andrews Experimental Forest has become a leader in the analysis of forest and stream ecosystem dynamics.</para> 

<para>Long-term field experiments and measurement programs have focused on climate dynamics, streamflow, water quality, and vegetation succession. Currently researchers are working to develop concepts and tools needed to predict effects of natural disturbance, land use, and climate change on ecosystem structure, function, and species composition. </para>

<para>The Andrews Experimental Forest is administered cooperatively by the USDA Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, Oregon State University and the Willamette National Forest. Funding for the research program comes from the National Science Foundation (NSF), US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, Oregon State University, and other sources.</para></abstract>
      <funding>Data were provided by the HJ Andrews Experimental Forest research program, funded by the National Science Foundation's Long-Term Ecological Research Program (DEB 08-23380), US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, and Oregon State University. National Science Foundation: DEB0823380</funding>
      <studyAreaDescription>
        <descriptor citableClassificationSystem="false" name="Long-Term Ecological Research">
          <descriptorValue>The Andrews Forest is situated in the western Cascade Range of Oregon, and covers the entire 15,800-acre (6400-ha) drainage basin of Lookout Creek. Elevation ranges from 1350 to 5340 feet (410 to 1630 m). Broadly representative of the rugged mountainous landscape of the Pacific Northwest, the Andrews Forest contains excellent examples of the region's conifer forests and associated wildlife and stream ecosystems. These forests are among the tallest and most productive in the world, with tree heights of often greater than 250 ft (75 m). Streams are steep, cold and clean, providing habitat for numerous aquatic organisms.</descriptorValue>
        </descriptor>
      </studyAreaDescription>
    </project>
    <dataTable id="HF02001">
      <alternateIdentifier>1</alternateIdentifier>
      <entityName>HF02001</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Multi-scale tracer tests: Dye tracer test concentration breakthrough curves</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>HF02001_v2.csv</objectName>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url function="download">http://andlter.forestry.oregonstate.edu/ltermeta/ltersearch/dataaccess.aspx?docid=HF02001_v2.csv</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <coverage>
        <temporalCoverage>
          <rangeOfDates>
            <beginDate>
              <calendarDate>2003-06-14</calendarDate>
            </beginDate>
            <endDate>
              <calendarDate>2003-06-21</calendarDate>
            </endDate>
          </rangeOfDates>
        </temporalCoverage>
      </coverage>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute id="HF02001.DBCODE">
          <attributeName>DBCODE</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>FSDB Database Code</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">char(10)</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>HF020</code>
                    <definition>FSDB Database Code</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="HF02001.ENTITY">
          <attributeName>ENTITY</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Entity number</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(1,0)</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <interval>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>natural</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">1.0000</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">1.0000</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </interval>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="HF02001.SITE">
          <attributeName>SITE</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Monitoring site number</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">char(7)</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ordinal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TT-0</code>
                    <definition>Site 00 - LTT Injection</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TT-1</code>
                    <definition>Site 01 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Injection ISCO Site</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TT-2</code>
                    <definition>Site 02 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Above Cold Creek Site</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TT-3</code>
                    <definition>Site 03 - Cold Creek injection</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TT-4</code>
                    <definition>Site 04 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Below Cold Creek Site and</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TT-5</code>
                    <definition>Site 05 - Cold Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Longer Creek Si</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TT-6</code>
                    <definition>Site 06 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Above Mack Creek Site and</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TT-7</code>
                    <definition>Site 07 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Below Mack Creek Site</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TT-8</code>
                    <definition>Site 08 - Mack Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Injection ISCO</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TT-9</code>
                    <definition>Site 09 - Mack Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Middle Tributar</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TT-10</code>
                    <definition>Site 10 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Above McRae Creek Site an</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TT-11</code>
                    <definition>Site 11 - McRae Creek injection</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TT-12</code>
                    <definition>Site 12 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Below McRae Creek Site an</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TT-13</code>
                    <definition>Site 13 - McRae Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Floodplain Sit</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TT-14</code>
                    <definition>Site 14 - Longitudinal Tracer Test Headquarters Site and McR</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </ordinal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="HF02001.SITENAME">
          <attributeName>SITENAME</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Monitoring site name</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">char(15)</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ordinal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>CC_IOTT_AMC</code>
                    <definition>Cold Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Above Mack Creek Site #6</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>CC_IOTT_INJ</code>
                    <definition>Cold Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Injection ISCO Site #4</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>CC_IOTT_ALC</code>
                    <definition>Cold Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Longer Creek Site #5</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>LTT_ACC</code>
                    <definition>Longitudinal Tracer Test Above Cold Creek Site #2</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>LTT_AMC</code>
                    <definition>Longitudinal Tracer Test Above Mack Creek Site #6</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>LTT_AMcRC</code>
                    <definition>Longitudinal Tracer Test Above McRae Creek Site #10</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>LTT_BCC</code>
                    <definition>Longitudinal Tracer Test Below Cold Creek Site #4</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>LTT_BMC</code>
                    <definition>Longitudinal Tracer Test Below Mack Creek Site #7</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>LTT_BMcRC</code>
                    <definition>Longitudinal Tracer Test Below McRae Creek Site #12</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>LTT_HQ</code>
                    <definition>Longitudinal Tracer Test Headquarters Site #14</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>LTT_INJ</code>
                    <definition>Longitudinal Tracer Test Injection ISCO Site #1</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>MC_IOTT_AMcRC</code>
                    <definition>Mack Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Above McRae Creek Site #10</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>MC_IOTT_INJ</code>
                    <definition>Mack Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Injection ISCO Site #8</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>MC_IOTT_MT</code>
                    <definition>Mack Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Middle Tributary Site #9</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>McRC_IOTT_FP</code>
                    <definition>McRae Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Floodplain Site #13</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>McRC_IOTT_HQ</code>
                    <definition>McRae Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Headquarters Site #14</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>McRC_IOTT_INJ</code>
                    <definition>McRae Creek Inter-Order Tracer Test Injection ISCO Site #12</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </ordinal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="HF02001.TEST">
          <attributeName>TEST</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Longitudinal Tracer Test</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">char(10)</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>LTT</code>
                    <definition>Longitudinal Tracer Test</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>IOTT</code>
                    <definition>Inter-Order Tracer Test</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="HF02001.DATANUM">
          <attributeName>DATANUM</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Sample number</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(5,0)</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <interval>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>1.000000</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>natural</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">1.0000</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">27775.0000</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </interval>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="HF02001.DATE">
          <attributeName>DATE</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Date of measurement</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">datetime</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYY-MM-DD</formatString>
              <dateTimePrecision>1.000000</dateTimePrecision>
              <dateTimeDomain>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">6/1/2003 12:00:00 AM</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">11/15/2003 12:00:00 AM</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </dateTimeDomain>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="HF02001.TIME">
          <attributeName>TIME</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Time elapsed since the beginning of tracer test</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">int</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>1.000000</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>integer</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.0000</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">13300790.0000</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="HF02001.CONCEN">
          <attributeName>CONCEN</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Concentration of rhodamine wt, corrected to near zero from background fluorescence</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(6,3)</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <interval>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>micrograms per liter</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.010000</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>whole</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.0000</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">242.4100</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </interval>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="HF02001.MASSFLUX">
          <attributeName>MASSFLUX</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Mass flux rate of rhodamine at corresponding time</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(7,2)</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <interval>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>micrograms per second</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.010000</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>whole</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.0000</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">5967.2700</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </interval>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="HF02001.DISCHARGE">
          <attributeName>DISCHARGE</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Stream flow rate</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(5,1)</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <interval>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.100000</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>whole</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.0000</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">767.4000</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </interval>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="HF02001.BASIN_REG">
          <attributeName>BASIN_REG</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Best fit regression basin hydrograph used to estimate discharge of site</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">char(15)</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ordinal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>MACK</code>
                    <definition>Mack Creek guaged hydrograph used to estimate discharge using a linear hydrograph regression</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>USGS</code>
                    <definition>USGS guaged hydrograph used to estimate discharge using a linear hydrograph regression</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Direct USGS</code>
                    <definition>Direct USGS guaged hydrograph used for discharge</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>WS03</code>
                    <definition>WS03 guaged hydrograph used to estimate discharge using a linear hydrograph regression</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>WS02</code>
                    <definition>WS02 guaged hydrograph used to estimate discharge using a linear hydrograph regression</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Observed</code>
                    <definition>Direct discharge measurements used to estimate discharge with a linear interpolation between daily measurements</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </ordinal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="HF02001.TEMP">
          <attributeName>TEMP</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Water temperature</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(4,1)</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <interval>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.100000</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>whole</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.8000</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">19.9000</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </interval>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="HF02001.TF1">
          <attributeName>TF1</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Water temperature flag</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">char(1)</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code> &#160; </code>
                    <definition>Good value</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>M</code>
                    <definition>Missing value</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <constraint id="HF02001.PRIMARY">
        <primaryKey>
          <constraintName>PRIMARY</constraintName>
          <key>
            <attributeReference>HF02001.DATANUM</attributeReference>
            <attributeReference>HF02001.SITENAME</attributeReference>
          </key>
        </primaryKey>
      </constraint>
      <constraint id="HF02001.NOTNULL">
        <notNullConstraint>
          <constraintName>NOTNULL</constraintName>
          <key>
            <attributeReference>HF02001.BASIN_REG</attributeReference>
            <attributeReference>HF02001.CONCEN</attributeReference>
            <attributeReference>HF02001.DATANUM</attributeReference>
            <attributeReference>HF02001.DATE</attributeReference>
            <attributeReference>HF02001.DBCODE</attributeReference>
            <attributeReference>HF02001.DISCHARGE</attributeReference>
            <attributeReference>HF02001.ENTITY</attributeReference>
            <attributeReference>HF02001.MASSFLUX</attributeReference>
            <attributeReference>HF02001.SITE</attributeReference>
            <attributeReference>HF02001.SITENAME</attributeReference>
            <attributeReference>HF02001.TEST</attributeReference>
            <attributeReference>HF02001.TIME</attributeReference>
          </key>
        </notNullConstraint>
      </constraint>
      <numberOfRecords>0</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <ns2:unitList>
        <ns2:unit id="micrograms per liter" multiplierToSI="1" name="micrograms per liter" parentSI="unknown" unitType="massPerMassRate">
          <ns2:description>micrograms per liter</ns2:description>
        </ns2:unit>
        <ns2:unit id="liters per second" multiplierToSI="1" name="liters per second" parentSI="literPerSecond" unitType="volumetricRate">
          <ns2:description>liters per second</ns2:description>
        </ns2:unit>
        <ns2:unit id="micrograms per second" multiplierToSI="1" name="micrograms per second" parentSI="unknown" unitType="massPerMassRate">
          <ns2:description>micrograms per second</ns2:description>
        </ns2:unit>
        <ns2:unit id="degrees Celcius" multiplierToSI="273.18" name="degrees Celcius" parentSI="kelvin" unitType="temperature">
          <ns2:description>Degrees Celsius; a common unit of temperature; constantToSI=273.18</ns2:description>
        </ns2:unit>
        <ns2:unit id="number" multiplierToSI="1" name="number" parentSI="dimensionless" unitType="dimensionless">
          <ns2:description>dimensionless number, i.e., ratio, count</ns2:description>
        </ns2:unit>
      </ns2:unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>