<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-pie.249.2" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=PIE,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <alternateIdentifier>LTE-MP-LPA-elev_planter.02</alternateIdentifier>
    <title>Above- and belowground biomass of S. alterniflora in elevational marsh planter experiments</title>
    <creator id="pers-1">
      <organizationName>Plum Island Ecosystems LTER Program</organizationName>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Jim</givenName>
        <surName>Morris</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Dept of Biological Sciences</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>University of SC</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <administrativeArea>SC</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>29208</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
    </creator>
    <creator id="pers-2">
      <organizationName>Plum Island Ecosystems LTER Program</organizationName>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Karen</givenName>
        <surName>Sundberg</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Baruch Marine Field Laboratory</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>University of SC</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>PO Box 1630</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Georgetown</city>
        <administrativeArea>SC</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>29442</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>Plum Island Ecosystems LTER Program</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Woods Hole</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7485</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>pie_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://pie-lter.ecosystems.mbl.edu</onlineUrl>
    </metadataProvider>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Diana</givenName>
        <surName>Rodriguez</surName>
      </individualName>
      <role>additional investigator</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2013</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>Spartina alterniflora is grown in experimental elevation planters placed in draining ponds on the salt marsh platform. The planters are constructed from PVC pipes of varying lengths. All of the PVC pipes are open at the bottom, and flush to the mudflat surface of the pond, resulting in the tops of the pipes being situated at various relative elevations within the tidal range. Plants growing in the shorter PVC pipes are flooded for a longer duration of each tidal cycle than plants growing in the taller PVC pipes. The growth response of S. alterniflora when exposed to different flood frequencies is monitored by monthly estimates of biomass (determined non-destructively from plant heights) and by destructive 'harvesting' of all above- and belowground plant material at the end of the growing season.</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>PIE LTER</keyword>
      <keyword>Plum Island Ecosystems</keyword>
      <keyword>Massachusetts</keyword>
      <keyword>Rowley River</keyword>
      <keyword>primary production</keyword>
      <keyword>disturbance</keyword>
      <keyword>aboveground biomass</keyword>
      <keyword>belowground biomass</keyword>
      <keyword>marsh elevation</keyword>
      <keyword>salt marsh</keyword>
      <keyword>Spartina alterniflora</keyword>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>Acceptance and utilization of PIE-LTER data requires that:</para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The Principal Investigator be sent a notice stating reasons for acquiring any data and a description of the publication intentions.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The Principal Investigator of the data set be sent a copy of the report or manuscript prior to submission and be adequately cited in any resultant publications</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>A copy of any resultant publications should be sent to: 
            <literalLayout>
Principal Investigator
Ecosystems Center
Marine Biological Laboratory
Woods Hole, MA 02543
</literalLayout></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url>http://ecosystems.mbl.edu/PIE/data/LTE/LTE-MP-LPA-elev_planter.html</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage id="GEO-1">
        <geographicDescription>Law's Point on Rowley River, Rowley, MA, site 1 of PIE LTER Spartina alterniflora elevation planter experiment</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-70.84262</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-70.84262</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>42.73113</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>42.73113</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage id="GEO-2">
        <geographicDescription>Law's Point on Rowley River, Rowley, MA, site 2 of PIE LTER Spartina alterniflora elevation planter experiment</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-70.842534</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-70.842534</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>42.763164</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>42.763164</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2002-06-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2013-09-01</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
      <taxonomicCoverage>
        <generalTaxonomicCoverage>Organisms Studied</generalTaxonomicCoverage>
        <taxonomicClassification>
          <taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
          <taxonRankValue>Spartina</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonomicClassification>
            <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
            <taxonRankValue>alterniflora</taxonRankValue>
          </taxonomicClassification>
        </taxonomicClassification>
      </taxonomicCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>Collections occur approximately monthly from May through September. Database is updated once annually, usually in the winter. Study and data collection are ongoing as of Sept 2013.</para>
        <para>Version 01, 10Sep2013, metadata and data updated to comply with importation to Drupal and LTER PASTA. Used MarcrosExportEML_HTML (working)pie_excel2007_Sep2013.xlsm 9/10/13 12:02 PM for QA/QC to EML 2.1.0</para>
        <para>Version 02: April 18, 2014, 2013 data and metadata updated (Comments variable added) to comply with importation to Drupal and LTER PASTA. Research location name and description updated.Used MarcrosExportEML_HTML (working)pie_excel2007_Sep2013.xlsm 9/30/13 02:57 PM for QA/QC to EML 2.1.0</para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact id="im" system="knb">
      <positionName>Data Manager</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Woods Hole</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7485</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>pie_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://pie-lter.ecosystems.mbl.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <organizationName>Plum Island Ecosystems LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Woods Hole</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7485</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>pie_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://pie-lter.ecosystems.mbl.edu</onlineUrl>
    </publisher>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>
Experimental Elevation Planters:
There have been two experimental elevation planters located at Law's Pt. Each planter has 6 replicate pots each of 6 levels.  Pots are constructed from varying lengths (in 15-cm increments) of 6" diameter PVC pipe.  All of the PVC pipes are open at the bottom, and flush to the mudflat surface of the pond, resulting in the tops of the pipes being situated, step-wise, at various relative elevations within the tidal range.  The entire structure resembles a staircase.  The six replicate pots at the lowest level of the planters are ~0.5m above MSL.  Pots at the highest level of the planters are ~0.1-0.2m above MHHW. Planter A was established at Site#1 in 2002.  In 2008 two additional elevations were added to Planter A.  Planter A was dismantled after the 2009 experiment.  Planter P was established at Site#2 in 2006.  

Planting Protocol:
Replicate pots are filled with sediment from the draining pond in which they are situated in either late fall or early spring.  Between mid-April and mi-May, plugs of S. alterniflora are collected from the marsh platform near the planter, and transplanted into the pots.  Every attempt is made to ensure that all plugs are the same size (surface area and depth) and contain the same number of plants of about the same height.  However, often times the natural marsh is not yet well established, and there is variability within the initial plantings.  Marsh plugs are approximately 4-5" in diameter and 5-6" in depth.  In 2011 marsh plugs were 2" diameter x 6" deep, and in 2013 marsh plugs were 4" diameter x 6" deep.  

Monitoring Protocol:
Standing biomass in the replicate pots are estimated approximately monthly  in 2002, 2003, 2008-2011 and 2013. The height of each plant (excluding flowers) in each pot is measured and read (along with level and replicate information) into a digital recorder.  Plant height data are transcribed into an EXCEL spreadsheet, and processed with FORTRAN algorithms (Morris and Haskin, 1990, Ecology 71(6):2209-2217) to convert plant height to plant weight.   

Harvesting Protocol:
At the end of the growing season (mid-Aug to mid-Nov), the planter is 'harvested'.  The contents of each replicate pot (live shoots, dead shoots, roots, rhizomes, peat, sediment, dead belowground macro organic matter) are removed from the planter.  Shoots are clipped at the sediment surface, sorted into live and dead plants, counted, dried (60C) and weighed.  Belowground portions from each pot are seived  (2.5mm) to collect all plant material (live and dead), dried (60C) and weighed.  

Various monitoring , planting , and harvesting protocols  have been used throughout the years to accomodate  various experimental goals (e.g. fertilization, plant age, plant species, belowground biomass distribution, substrate type). Only data from untreated, single year replicates of S. alterniflora are included in this dataset. Following are exceptions to the general protocol described above.  In 2002, the harvest occured after all plants had senesced, therefore aboveground peak biomass was estimated from July plant height data.  In 2002 only half the pots were harvested.  In 2003, the harvest occured after all plants had senseced, therefore aboveground peak biomass was estimated from July plant height data.  In 2003, only half the pots were 1yr old.  In 2005, belowground material was sorted into live and dead, and only live belowground material was retained.  In 2006, plant density was not determined.  In 2011, a substrate experiment was conducted in the planter; only half the pots were filled with natural (control) sediments collected as described above.  Belowground material was seived to 1mm; only live roots and rhizomes were retained.  In 2013, plants were not harvested, therefore peak aboveground biomass was estimated from August plant height data.  

Elevations of the pots relative to NAVD88 are determined approximately annually by  FastStatic measurements using a Trimble 4800 receiver and TSC-1 controller (from UNAVCO www.unavco.org).

</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>Plum Island Ecosystems Long-Term Ecological Research (PIE LTER) Program</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Anne</givenName>
          <surName>Giblin</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Woods Hole</city>
          <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7488</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>agiblin@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Lead PI</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Hap</givenName>
          <surName>Garritt</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Woods Hole</city>
          <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7485</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>pie_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Information Manager</role>
      </personnel>
      <abstract>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>
The Plum Island Ecosystems (PIE) LTER is an integrated research, education and outreach program whose goal is to develop a predictive understanding of the long-term response of watershed and estuarine ecosystems at the land-sea interface to changes in climate, land use and sea level. The principal study site is the Plum Island Sound estuary, its coupled Parker, Rowley and Ipswich River watersheds and the adjacent coastal ocean, the Gulf of Maine. The PIE LTER focuses on how several aspects of global change influence organic matter and inorganic nutrient biogeochemistry and estuarine foodwebs. The inputs of organic matter and nutrients from land, ocean and marshes interact with the external drivers (climate, land use, river discharge, sea level) to dictate the extent and degree of nutrient and organic matter processing and determine the spatial patterns of estuarine productivity and trophic structure.
</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </abstract>
      <funding>
        <para>This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation under Grants OCE-9726921, OCE-0423565, OCE-1058747, OCE-1238212. Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed in the material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.</para>
      </funding>
      <studyAreaDescription>
        <coverage>
          <geographicCoverage>
            <geographicDescription>The Plum Island Ecosystems (PIE) LTER site, is located in northeastern Massachusetts, 42.72 N, 70.85 W. The PIE LTER lies at the interface of a thinly soiled, formerly glaciated New England land mass and the highly productive Gulf of Maine. Three watersheds comprise the estuarine drainage basin: Parker (155 km2), Rowley (26 km2) and Ipswich (404 km2). The Ipswich River watershed is highly urbanized with Boston "bedroom" communities encroaching in the headwater region while the Parker is less urbanized and retains a higher proportion of forest.</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-71.2198</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-70.7568</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>42.8276</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>42.4965</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>0</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>100</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </geographicCoverage>
        </coverage>
      </studyAreaDescription>
    </project>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>LTE-MP-LPA-elev_planter.csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Above- and belowground biomass of S. alterniflora in elevational marsh planter experiments</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>LTE-MP-LPA-elev_planter.csv</objectName>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>http://ecosystems.mbl.edu/PIE/data/LTE/data/LTE-MP-LPA-elev_planter.csv</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute id=" att0.1">
          <attributeName>PLANTER ID</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>PLANTER ID</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>current name of sampling station, following naming protocol</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>A</code>
                    <definition>planter A located at site#1 (LTE-MP-LPA_elevplanter01)</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>P</code>
                    <definition>planter P located at site#2 (LTE-MP-LPA_elevplanter02)</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.2">
          <attributeName>YEAR</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>YEAR</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>year</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>yyyy</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.3">
          <attributeName>AG DATE</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>AG DATE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>date aboveground biomass was collected</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>mm/dd/yyyy</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.4">
          <attributeName>BG DATE</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>BG DATE</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>date belowground biomass was collected</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>mm/dd/yyyy</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>dnc</code>
            <codeExplanation>dnc = data not collected</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.5">
          <attributeName>LEVEL</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>LEVEL</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>level of experimental planter</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>level of experimental planter</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.6">
          <attributeName>REP</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>REP</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>replicate</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>replicate</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.7">
          <attributeName>ELEV NAVD88</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>ELEV NAVD88</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>elevation of the level relative to NAVD88</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.8">
          <attributeName>AGL DENSITY</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>AGL DENSITY</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>aboveground live plant density</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>numberPerMeterSquared</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>dnc</code>
            <codeExplanation>dnc = data not collected</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.9">
          <attributeName>AGL BIOMASS</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>AGL BIOMASS</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>aboveground live biomass</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>dnc</code>
            <codeExplanation>dnc = data not collected</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.10">
          <attributeName>AGD BIOMASS</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>AGD BIOMASS</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>standing dead biomass</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>dnc</code>
            <codeExplanation>dnc = data not collected</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.11">
          <attributeName>BGT BIOMASS</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>BGT BIOMASS</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>total belowground biomass</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPerMeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>dnc</code>
            <codeExplanation>dnc = data not collected</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.12">
          <attributeName>COMMENTS</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>COMMENTS</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Information pertaining to individual data points</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Information pertaining to individual data points</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>dnc</code>
            <codeExplanation>dnc = data not collected</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>345</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <unitList>
        <unit id="gramPerMeterSquared" multiplierToSI="0.001" name="gramPerMeterSquared" parentSI="kilogramsPerSquareMeter" unitType="arealMassDensity">
          <description>grams per square meter</description>
        </unit>
      </unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>