<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-ntl.254.2" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
	<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
		<allow>
			<principal>uid=NTL,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
			<permission>all</permission>
		</allow>
		<allow>
			<principal>public</principal>
			<permission>read</permission>
		</allow>
	</access>
	<dataset>
		<alternateIdentifier system="NTL-DEIMS">5652</alternateIdentifier>
		<shortName>LOTTIG2</shortName>
		<title>North Temperate Lakes LTER: Northern Highlands Stream Chemistry Survey 2006</title>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Noah</givenName>
				<surName>Lottig</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin Madison</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>19810 County Rd. N</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Boulder Junction</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>54512</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">(715) 356-9494 x225</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>nrlottig@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Emily</givenName>
				<surName>Stanley</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">(608) 263-2567</phone>
			<phone phonetype="fax">(608) 265-2340</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>ehstanley@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<metadataProvider>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</metadataProvider>
		<pubDate>2010</pubDate>
		<language>english</language>
		<abstract>
			<para>We compared regional patterns in lake and stream biogeochemistry in the Northern
				Highlands Lake District (NHLD), Wisconsin, USA to ask how regional biogeochemistry differs
				as a function of the type of ecosystem considered (i.e., lakes versus streams); if
				lake-stream comparisons reveal regional patterns and processes that are not apparent from
				studies of a single ecosystem type; and if characteristics of streams and lakes scale
				similarly.&#194;&#160;Fifty-two streams were sampled using a stratified random design to determine
				regional distribution of 21 water chemistry variables during summer baseflow conditions.
				Sampling Frequency: once per site Number of sites: 52 </para>
		</abstract>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>acid neutralizing capacity</keyword>
			<keyword>ammonia</keyword>
			<keyword>calcium</keyword>
			<keyword>carbon</keyword>
			<keyword>carbon dioxide</keyword>
			<keyword>chloride</keyword>
			<keyword>dissolved inorganic carbon</keyword>
			<keyword>dissolved organic carbon</keyword>
			<keyword>inorganic nutrients</keyword>
			<keyword>iron</keyword>
			<keyword>magnesium</keyword>
			<keyword>manganese</keyword>
			<keyword>methane</keyword>
			<keyword>nitrate</keyword>
			<keyword>nitrogen</keyword>
			<keyword>ph</keyword>
			<keyword>phosphorus</keyword>
			<keyword>potassium</keyword>
			<keyword>sodium</keyword>
			<keyword>stream discharge</keyword>
			<keyword>water temperature</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>LTER Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>ANC</keyword>
			<keyword>Ca</keyword>
			<keyword>CH4</keyword>
			<keyword>Cl</keyword>
			<keyword>CO2</keyword>
			<keyword>DIC</keyword>
			<keyword>dissolved nitrogen</keyword>
			<keyword>dissolved phophorus</keyword>
			<keyword>dissolved reactive phosphorus</keyword>
			<keyword>DOC</keyword>
			<keyword>drivers</keyword>
			<keyword>Fe</keyword>
			<keyword>K</keyword>
			<keyword>landuse</keyword>
			<keyword>Mg</keyword>
			<keyword>Mn</keyword>
			<keyword>Na</keyword>
			<keyword>NH4</keyword>
			<keyword>NO3</keyword>
			<keyword>North Temperate Lakes - LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>NTL LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>SO4</keyword>
			<keyword>SRP</keyword>
			<keyword>stream chemistry</keyword>
			<keyword>stream survey</keyword>
			<keyword>sulphate</keyword>
			<keyword>watershed characteristics</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>NTL Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<intellectualRights>
			<section>
				<title>Data Policies</title>
				<para>Copyright Board of Regents, University of Wisconsin, Madison. This information is
					released to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes
					subject to the following restrictions: The Data User must realize that these data sets are
					being actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary
					to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the NTL lead Principal
					Investigator, leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu, to check on other uses of the data. Where
					appropriate, the Data User may be encouraged to consider collaboration and/or
					co-authorship with original investigators.</para>
				<para>The Data User must realize that the data may be misinterpreted if taken out of
					context. We request that you provide the NTL lead Principal Investigator, ATTN: Data
					Access, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 680 North Park St.,
					Madison, WI 53706 with a copy of any manuscript using the data so that it may be reviewed
					and comments provided on the presentation of our data.</para>
				<para>The Data User must acknowledge use of the data by an appropriate citation (see
					Citation) of the NTL-LTER database. A generic citation for our databases is: name of data
					set, North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research program, NSF, contact person for
					data set, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison. The data set name and
					contact person for each data set can be found in the metadata header of the online data
					sets.</para>
				<para>The Data User must send two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the
					data to the address above. We would like to include such manuscripts in our LTER
					publications list.</para>
				<para>The Data User must not redistribute original data and documentation without permission
					from Emily Stanley, lead Principal Investigator, (ehstanley@wisc.edu).</para>
				<para>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation,
					complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is".
					The North Temperate Lakes LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or
					misinterpretation of data sets. Data users should be aware that we periodically update
					data sets.</para>
				<para>Our goal is to release all long term data associated with core research areas within 2
					years of collection. These data and accompanying metadata will be available for download
					from the NTL-LTER web site.</para>
				<para>By using these data, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement.
					Thank you for your cooperation. </para>
			</section>
		</intellectualRights>
		<distribution>
			<online>
				<url function="information">http://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/node/5652</url>
			</online>
		</distribution>
		<coverage>
			<geographicCoverage>
				<geographicDescription>Northern Highlands Lake District, NE Wisconsin, Upper Peninusula, Michigan

	The NHLD (ca. 5000 km2) contains more than 7500 lakes and 1500 streams.&#194;&#160;The region is situated along the southern extent of the boreal peatlands and was strongly affected by the retreat of glaciers between 10,000 and 12,000 years ago, which left approximately 30 &#226;&#128;&#147; 50 m of sandy, noncalcareous till across the landscape.&#194;&#160;As a result of the porous nature of regional soils, groundwater flow, in addition to precipitation, is often an extremely important input to surface waters in the region.&#194;&#160;Lakes range from small dystrophic bog lakes less than 1 ha in area to systems &gt;2,500 ha, while streams range from small intermittent channels to large order systems such as the Wisconsin, Chippewa, and Wolf Rivers.&#194;&#160;Drainages within the NHLD flow either into the Mississippi River or the Laurentian Great Lakes.&#194;&#160;Land cover (2001 National Land Cover Data) is a predominantly a mix of deciduous and coniferous forest (52%), wetlands (28%), and lakes (13%).
&#194;&#160;
</geographicDescription>
				<boundingCoordinates>
					<westBoundingCoordinate>-90.228</westBoundingCoordinate>
					<eastBoundingCoordinate>-88.900</eastBoundingCoordinate>
					<northBoundingCoordinate>46.280</northBoundingCoordinate>
					<southBoundingCoordinate>45.585</southBoundingCoordinate>
				</boundingCoordinates>
			</geographicCoverage>
			<temporalCoverage>
				<rangeOfDates>
					<beginDate>
						<calendarDate>2006-06-20</calendarDate>
					</beginDate>
					<endDate>
						<calendarDate>2006-08-21</calendarDate>
					</endDate>
				</rangeOfDates>
			</temporalCoverage>
		</coverage>
		<maintenance>
			<description>
				<para>completed </para>
			</description>
		</maintenance>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
			<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Information Manager</positionName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<publisher>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</publisher>
		<pubPlace>North Temperate Lakes</pubPlace>
		<methods>
			<methodStep>
				<description>
					<section>
						<para> Site Selection Because lakes are a dominant feature of the region and stream
							characteristics could potentially differ based on their hydrologic connections to
							lakes, we classified streams into three categories as a function of their hydrologic
							connections to lakes. The first category was streams that had no lakes within the
							drainage network upstream of the sampling location. The second category was streams
							that originated from headwater lakes (i.e., no stream inlet but a stream outlet) and
							the headwater lake was the only lake in the drainage network above the sampling
							location. The final category had at least a single drainage lake (i.e., a lake with
							both stream inlet(s) and outlet) in the drainage network above the sampling location.
							We then used these categories to select sampling sites using a stratified random
							design for a variety of chemical and physical characteristics. All streams identified
							on 1:24,000 7.5 inch USGS topographical maps that crossed access points were selected
							as potential sampling locations and assigned to one of the three stream types. A
							stream could be classified by more than a single category depending on the sampling
							location within the drainage network. However, a single drainage network was never
							sampled more than once to ensure sample independence. Of the 500 possible sampling
							locations, 52 sites were selected and sampled. Sampling All streams were sampled 7-10
							channel widths upstream of an access point to minimize any influences caused by
							culverts and other features. Water samples were collected from the center of the
							channel using a peristaltic pump. Stream discharge was measured after Gore (2007)
							using cross sectional area and water velocity. Chemical Analyses All samples for both
							studies were collected and processed following the North Temperate Long Term
							Ecological Research (NTL-LTER) protocols (http://lter.limnology.wisc.edu). Filtering
							was done in the field using an in-line 0.45 &#206;&#188;m membrane filter. All samples were
							stored on ice and returned to the laboratory where they were preserved according to
							NTL-LTER protocols. Acid neutralizing capacity (ANC) was determined by Gran titration
							(APHA 2005).&#194;&#160;DOC was measured on a Shimadzu TOC-V carbon analyzer. Total nitrogen and
							phosphorus (unfiltered, TN and TP; filtered, TDN and TDP), nitrate+nitrite (NO3-N),
							and ammonium (NH4-N) were quantified with an Astoria-Pacific segmented flow
							auto-analyzer. Soluble reactive phosphorus (SRP) in streams was measured
							colormetrically on a Beckman DU-800 spectrophotometer (APHA 2005). Anions (Cl- and SO4
							2-) were measured using a Dionix DX-500 ion chromatograph and cations (Ca, Mg, Na, K,
							Fe, K, and Mn) on a Perkin Elmer ICP mass spectrometer Dissolved inorganic carbon
							(DIC) and pH were quantified differently in the lakes and stream data sets. For the
							lakes data, DIC was determined with a Shimadzu TOC-V carbon analyzer, whereas DIC for
							the streams dataset was determined by headspace equilibration of acidified water
							samples in the field and direct measurement of carbon dioxide (CO2) gas on a Shimadzu
							gas chromatograph (Cole et al. 1994). pH measurements for the lakes dataset were
							quantified on non-air equilibrated samples in the lab with a Accumet 950 pH meter
							while direct measurements were taken in the field for the streams dataset using a
							hand-held Orion model 266 pH meter that was allowed to equilibrated about 20 min in
							the center for the stream channel. Several variables presented in this study were
							determined from calculations based on measured values. In streams, dissolved organic
							nitrogen and phosphorus (DON and DOP, respectively) were determined by the difference
							between inorganic nutrients and total dissolved nutrients (e.g., DOP = TDP-SRP). We
							were unable to determine DON in lakes due to the lack of inorganic nitrogen data. It
							was assumed that DOP approximately equals TDP in lakes because dissolved inorganic
							phosphorus concentrations in the region are typically below detection limits in the
							epilimnion during the summer months and consequently not quantified (NTL-LTER
							unpublished data). </para>
					</section>
				</description>
			</methodStep>
		</methods>
		<project>
			<title>North Temperate Lakes LTER</title>
			<personnel>
				<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
				<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
				<address>
        <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
				<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<abstract>
				<para>North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research studies the ecology of lakes as
					one of a network of sites established by the National Science Foundation. We are
					interested in how biophysical setting, climate, and changing land use and cover interact
					to shape lake characteristics and dynamics over time (past, present, future). Our primary
					study sites include a set of seven northern Wisconsin and four southern Wisconsin lakes
					and their surrounding landscapes. The project, which started in 1981, is administered by
					the Center for Limnology at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. Perception of Long-Term
					Change: How and why have the lake districts changed, and how will they change in the
					future? Climatic Forcing of Change: What are the major ecological and social responses of
					lake districts to climate change? Interacting Drivers, Scales of Space and Time, and
					Regional Change: How do multiple interacting drivers affect regional change in lake
					districts at multiple scales? Ecosystem Services: Past, Present and Future: What are the
					magnitudes, interactions and potential future flows of ecosystem services in lake
					districts? </para>
			</abstract>
		</project>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>nhld_stream52_chem</entityName>
			<entityDescription>Northern Highlands Stream Chemistry Survey</entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>nhldstream52chem</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-ntl.254&amp;urlTail=ntl/data/5652_1_v1.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>site_name</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>name of site</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>name of site</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>name of site</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>site_id</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>unique site id</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>unique site id</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>unique site id</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>discharge</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>stream discharge</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>stream discharge</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>cubicFeetPerSecond</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>wtemp</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>water temperature</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>water temperature</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>cond</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>specific conductance </attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>specific conductance </attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microSiemenPerCentimeter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>ph</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>pH</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>pH</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>pH</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
								<bounds>
									<minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
									<maximum exclusive="false">14</maximum>
								</bounds>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>anc</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>acid neutralizing capacity</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>acid neutralizing capacity</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microEquivalentsPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>ca</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>Ca</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>calcium</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>ch4</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>CH4</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>CH4</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>cl</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>Cl</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>chloride</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>co2</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>CO2</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>CO2</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>fe</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>Fe</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>Fe</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>k</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>K</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>K</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>mg</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>Mg</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>Mg</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>mn</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>Mn</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>Mn</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>na</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>Na</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>Na</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>nh4</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>NH4 - N</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>NH4 - N</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>no3</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>NO3</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>NO3</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>so4</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>SO4</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>SO4</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>srp</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>soluble reactive phosphorus</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>soluble reactive phosphorus</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>tdn</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>total dissolved nitrogen</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>total dissolved nitrogen</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>tdp</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>total dissolved phosphorus</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>total dissolved phosphorus</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>tn</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>total nitrogen</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>total nitrogen</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>tp</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>total phosphorus</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>total phosphorus</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerLiter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>nhld_stream52_watershed</entityName>
			<entityDescription>Northern Highlands Stream Survey - Watershed Characteristics</entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>nhldstream52watershed</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-ntl.254&amp;urlTail=ntl/data/5652_2_v1.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>site_name</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>name of site</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>name of site</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>name of site</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>site_id</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>unique site id</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>unique site id</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>unique site id</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>latitude</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>latitude</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>latitude</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
								<bounds>
									<minimum exclusive="false">-90</minimum>
									<maximum exclusive="false">90</maximum>
								</bounds>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>longitude</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>longitude</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>longitude</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
								<bounds>
									<minimum exclusive="false">-180</minimum>
									<maximum exclusive="false">180</maximum>
								</bounds>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sampledate</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>sample date</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>sample date</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>date</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<dateTime>
							<formatString>yyyy-MM-dd</formatString>
						</dateTime>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sample_time</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>time of observation</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>time of observation</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>date</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<dateTime>
							<formatString>kkmm</formatString>
						</dateTime>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>wshed_area</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>watershed area</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>watershed area</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>kilometerSquared</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>wshed_pct_water</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>percentage water</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>percentage of watershed that is water</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>wshed_pct_forest</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>percentage forested</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>percentage of watershed that is forested</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>wshed_pct_wetland</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>percentage wetland</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>percentage of watershed that is wetland</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>wshed_pct_shrubland</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>percentage shrubland</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>percentage of watershed that is shrubland</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>wshed_pct_natgrass</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>percentage natural grass</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>percentage of watershed that is natural grass</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>wshed_pct_urban</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>percentage urban</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>percentage of watershed that is urban</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>wshed_pct_agric</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>percentage agricuture</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>percentage of watershed that is agricuture</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
	</dataset>
	<additionalMetadata>
		<metadata>
			<ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1     http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="uS/cm" constantToSI="0" id="microSiemenPerCentimeter" multiplierToSI="0.0001" name="microSiemenPerCentimeter" parentSI="siemenPerMeter" unitType="conductivityPerLength">
					<ns2:description>conductivity unit</ns2:description>
				</ns2:unit>
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="pH" id="pH" name="pH" unitType="">
					<ns2:description>pH</ns2:description>
				</ns2:unit>
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="ueq/L" id="microEquivalentsPerLiter" name="microEquivalentsPerLiter" unitType="">
					<ns2:description>Microequivalents per liter</ns2:description>
				</ns2:unit>
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="mg/l" constantToSI="0" id="milligramPerLiter" multiplierToSI="0.001" name="milligramPerLiter" parentSI="kilogramPerCubicMeter" unitType="massDensity">
					<ns2:description>milligrams / liter</ns2:description>
				</ns2:unit>
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="" constantToSI="0" id="kilometerSquared" multiplierToSI="1000000" name="kilometerSquared" parentSI="squareMeter" unitType="area">
					<ns2:description>square kilometers</ns2:description>
				</ns2:unit>
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="" id="percentage" name="percentage" unitType="">
					<ns2:description />
				</ns2:unit>
			</ns2:unitList>
		</metadata>
	</additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>