<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-jrn.20020610.9904" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=JRN, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Soil erosion pan</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>John</givenName>
      <surName>Anderson</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>
	Jornada LTER

	New Mexico State University

	P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>janderso@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <metadataProvider>
    <organizationName>The Jornada</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>2995 Knox Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-4842</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <onlineUrl>http://jornada.nmsu.edu</onlineUrl>
  </metadataProvider>
  <pubDate>1996</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>    [John Anderson added the following from info provided by Justin Van
    Zee and edited by Michelle Buonopane.]

    Overview:
       In semiarid ecosystems the diversity of plant functional types (
    grasses, shrubs, succulents, and so on) and of species may interact
    with the severe stresses imposed by the desert environment to influence
    ecosystem processes.  Erosion and transport of surface sediment by wind
    and water is one process that may be affected by the physical structure
    of the plant community.  The Jornada plant diversity experiment, in
    which the diversity and structure of the plant community have been
    manipulated in large (25 m x 25 m) plots, offers the opportunity to
    examine the relative importance of vegetation characteristics and
    landscape position in determining rates of sediment movement within
    the plots.  Soil erosion is also an important indicator of relative
    disturbance effects of the treatment manipulations.
       Each of the 48 plots of the plant diversity experiment contains
    5 pans or trays on the downslope side; these accumulate sediments and
    plant litter that are moving within the plots (carried by wind or by
    water).  Data have been collected on the amount of sediment accumulated
    in the pans during rainy and during dry seasons, with material sorted
    and weighed as fine ( less than 2 mm diameter) or coarse  more than 2 mm) mineral sediment,
    plant litter, or rabbit/jackrabbit pellets.  Previous statistical analyses
    found that the mass of material collected per plot is explained only poorly
    by the treatment (plant community manipulation) of the plot and by block
    (a rough indication of location on the slope).

    Objectives:
       We will test the relative significance of the following variables
    in explaining plot-level accumulations of sediment and litter: treatment,
    block, position on slope (the row, from 1 (top of slope) to 10 (bottom),
    in which the plot is located), the treatment of the plot immediately upslope
    from the plot, and indices of plant cover and volume (total and by
    functional group) from the plot-level sampling of vegetation (using
    fall 1997 data).
       In addition, we will test the significance of the following variables
    in explaining the accumulation of sediment and litter in individual pans
    within a plot:  all variables listed above for the plot, plus indices of
    the vegetative cover and volume located immediately upslope of the pan
    (weighted for distance from the pan itself).</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>completed</keyword>
    <keyword>disturbance</keyword>
    <keyword>erosion</keyword>
    <keyword>organic matter</keyword>
    <keyword>organic matter</keyword>
    <keyword>plant</keyword>
    <keyword>plant litter</keyword>
    <keyword>rabbit pellets</keyword>
    <keyword>soil</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Jornada Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout> From the stone pillars at the south entrance of the Jornada
 Experimental Range (USDA), follow the road west approximately
 4 miles to the first gate on the right (north). Go through this
 gate approximately one quarter mile, parking spot is on west side
 of road under power lines. The biodiversity site is on the right
 (east) side of the road across from the parking spot.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>Objectives:
The Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System (JIMS) provides protocol and services for data collection, verification, organization, archives, and distribution in accordance with recommendations and guidelines developed by the LTER Information Managers Committee (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html).

Disclaimer:
While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is". The Jornada Basin LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of data sets.

Quality Assurance Policy:
Data managers interact with researchers during the entire scientific process--from the initial planning of sampling designs and field data collection to archiving and distribution of data. The goal of data management is to build and maintain an archive of Jornada Basin LTER data files that are fully documented, error free, and organized in useful ways. Our protocol for data collection and processing seeks maximum interaction between researchers and data management personnel to avoid confusion and potential loss of data or problems with integrity of data; e.g., identification of historical site treatments that may impact a proposed study or incomplete data set variable descriptions. Site and Data Manager involvement begins during the Project Design phase with the completion of the Jornada Notification of Research form by the researcher prior to the start of work; this alerts both Site and Data Manager to the new study and potential LTER data sets. Upon initiation of a new study, the researcher completes Project Documentation that provides the second level of "metadata" documentation.
In the Data Collection phase, the data manager helps researchers design field and laboratory data sheets that facilitate data entry and analysis. Prior to JIMS data entry the investigator completes Data Set Documentation to provide the metadata that fully describe the data set. Both Project and Data set documentation are provided with the data set when it is requested or obtained from our Web site. JIMS data entry programs error-check and verify data as they are entered. Computer files are subjected to further verification by graphing and/or error-checking programs, and/or examination by field investigators. Final quality assurance of the data rests with the investigator who submits data for inclusion in the Data Management System. Direct communication with the Site Manager, or through a collaborating JRN P.I., is used to encourage the timely submission of documentation and of data by researchers.

Error-checked data files are stored with associated documentation files on the file server. Archived data files are maintained in ASCII format on 30-yr magneto-optical (MO) disks, portable hard drives, CD-R media, and DVD media to guard against loss of data access that can result from changing technology. This may also include proprietary binary format files to facilitate recovery of working versions. Image data are archived on 8mm tape. Routine tape data backups of the file server are done daily, weekly, and monthly. One set of off-site copies are maintained elsewhere on the NMSU campus of routine backup tapes, MO disks, CD disks, and DVD disks with a second set of MO, CD and DVD disks maintained off-campus in case of a catastrophe on campus. The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data manag ement staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data management staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

Policy on Submission of data:
Data submission into JIMS is expected from LTER researchers, LTER collaborators, and their graduate students where data and information is derived from publicly funded research in the U.S. LTER Network, totally or partially from LTER funds from NSF, Institutional Cost-Share, or Partner Agency or Institution where a formal memorandum of understanding with LTER has been established. Other Jornada Basin researchers are encouraged to submit their documented data for inclusion within JIMS to provide them with an archived backup, ensure its longevity, and provide online access to encourage synthesis efforts. Minimally, for non-LTER associated researchers, we request that publications be provided of research conducted on the Jornada Basin.
Initial documentation for a data set must be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager within 90 days of initiation of data collection. Documentation forms are available at http://jornada-www.nmsu.edu/site/dm/readme.php . These consist of Project Abstract and Data Set and Attribute documentation forms, which include objectives of the study, methods, as well as format and content of the data. All data collected during a calendar year should be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager prior to July first of the following year. First time data submissions must be submitted with updated standard Jornada Basin LTER forms previously submitted.

Data Access Policy:
Data will be made publicly available no later than 2 years after submission of the data unless an earlier date is specified by the principal investigator. In the event that an extension of the 2 year period is necessary, the principal investigator may petition the Jornada Basin LTER Executive Committee for a longer protected period. Graduate student research data will be available online after degree completion and they have the opportunity to publish their research.

Policies for re-use, distribution, or the production of derivatives:
Data re-use, distribution and production of derivative products are governed by the LTER Network data policies (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html) in the spirit of having the potential to increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines. Appropriate citation, acknowledgement, notification and collaboration are outlined and recommended. No commercial redistribution of data and derived products are allowed.

Data Acknowledgment Policy:
Please send notification to the Information Manager and Responsible Investigator(s) of the data sets you are downloading and your intended use.
Individuals and institutions utilizing data from the Jornada Basin LTER database are requested to place the following acknowledgment in any publication in which these data are mentioned:
Data sets were provided by the Jornada Basin Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) project. Funding for these data was provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210).

Please send 1 copy of any publication that cites Jornada Basin LTER data to:
     John P. Anderson
     Jornada Experimental Range
     P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
     New Mexico State University
     Las Cruces, NM 88003-0003</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <coverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>1996-06-04</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>1999-10-11</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout> mm/dd/yyyy - Date of Comment
 Int - Initials of person making Comment
 JPA = John P. Anderson
 PG = Peg Gronemeyer
 JL = Jim Lenz
 LFH = Laura F. Huenneke
 MAB = Michelle Buonopane
 KR = Ken Ramsey
 Changes/Updates - List any changes made to document

 mm/dd/yyyy Int Changes/Updates
 ---------- --- -----------------------------------------------
 01/10/1997 PG Form completed by investigator
 01/12/1997 JPA Entered into Data Management system
 08/07/1998 JPA Added Data Set Description
 06/13/2002 JL Added Dataset ID and Project ID sections.
 05/12/2003 MAB Edited all information; added data set information.
 08/20/2003 JPA Changed to Unrestricted as per LFH e-mail.
 09/26/2009 KR Changed termination date from April 2000 to
 10/11/1999 to reflect last date recorded in data
 file, per John Anderson. Reformatted Responsible
 Investigator section to reflect time associated
 with dataset.
 07/07/2010 KR Added comment that April 2000 samples are not
 available.
 11/17/2011 JPA Changed responsible investigator for contact person
 to John Anderson per Deb Peters</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Data</givenName>
      <surName>Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>PO Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>The Jornada</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout> Data are recorded on data sheets, then entered in the computer
 for analyses and graphing.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout> Label heavy duty plastic zip-loc bags with the date, plot number,
 and pan letter (A-E). The southern most pan is Pan A and
 continuing north to Pan B, Pan C, etc in each plot. Using either
 stiff index cards or mini dustpans and paintbrushes, scrape the
 contents of each pan into the corresponding bag. These then go
 back to the lab for processing. Any pans not flush with the ground
 should be emptied and then leveled with the ground. Bags are left
 open in laboratory to air dry. (No oven drying). The contents of
 each bag are then separated into 4 components using forceps and a 2
 mm seive: sediment with a diameter 2mm in diameter,
 plant litter, and rabbit pellets. These are weighed separately and
 recorded on the data sheet, entered into a spreadsheet, summarized
 in Excel, and analyzed in SAS.

 After project completion, pans are emptied as needed in order to
 maintain pan location in the case further studies are desired.
 Soils removed are dumped off-site.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
    <qualityControl>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout> History of Responsible investigator(s):
 Laura Huenneke, Jun1996-Oct1999
 *******************************

 April 2000 samples not yet processed.

 [Ken Ramsey, 07/07/2010]
 April 200 sample are not available.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </qualityControl>
  </methods>
  <project>
    <title>Jornada LTER</title>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
        <givenName>Debra</givenName>
        <surName>Peters</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-2777</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">575-646-5889</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>debpeter@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Lead Principal Investigator</role>
    </personnel>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Data</givenName>
        <surName>Manager</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Information Manager</role>
    </personnel>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>The Jornada Basin Long Term Ecological Research program, in collaboration with 
                         the USDA ARS Jornada Experimental Range, studies the causes and consequences of 
                         desertification: the broad scale expansion of woody plants into grasslands that 
                         results in more "desert like" conditions. We are interested in spatial and 
                         temporal variation in desertification dynamics, and how historic legacies, the 
                         geomorphic template, transport vectors (wind, water, animals), and environmental 
                         drivers (climate, land use, disturbance) interact with the patch structure of the 
                         vegetation to determine past, present, and future ecosystem dynamics across 
                         scales.
                        
                         Our study site is located in the northern Chihuahuan Desert, approximately 25 km 
                         northeast of Las Cruces, New Mexico, USA (+32.5 N, -106.8 W, elevation 1188 m). 
                         Annual precipitation is 24 cm and maximum temperatures average 13 C in January 
                         and 36 C in June. Our study site includes the 78,000 ha Jornada Experimental 
                         Range operated by the USDA Agricultural Research Service, and the 22,000 ha 
                         Chihuahuan Desert Rangeland Research Center (CDRRC) operated by New Mexico State 
                         University. The Jornada Basin LTER project was established in 1982, and is 
                         administered by New Mexico State University. This site is a member of the LTER 
                         Network, one of  more than 25 long term sites funded by the U.S. National Science 
                         Foundation.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <funding>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210)</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </funding>
  </project>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>bdsoiero.dat</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data file information for the following Jornada data set: Soil erosion pan</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>bdsoiero.dat</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <numHeaderLines>49</numHeaderLines>
          <numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
          <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>Tab-delimited</fieldDelimiter>
            <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url function="download">http://jornada-data.nmsu.edu/sites/jornada-data.nmsu.edu/files/data_files/bdsoiero.dat</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1996-06-04</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1999-10-11</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>DATE</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_erosion_pan_date</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>year month day</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>yyyymmdd</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>BLK</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_erosion_pan_blk</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Block number</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>N/A</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">6</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>PLOT</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_erosion_pan_plot</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Plot number</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>N/A</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">2</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">100</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>TRT</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_erosion_pan_trt</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Treatment</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C </code>
                  <definition> control, no vegetation removal or manipulation.  All species of all growth forms remain.</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>PG </code>
                  <definition> perennial grass removed; all perennial grasses removed, (Muhlenbergia, Dasychloa, Setaria, etc.)</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>RedL </code>
                  <definition> reduced minus Larrea; dominant of each growth form removed, only subordinates remain; Larrea removed as dominant shrub.</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>RedP </code>
                  <definition> reduced minus Prosopis; dominant of each growth form removed, only subordinates remain; Prosopis removed as dominant shrub.</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>S </code>
                  <definition> shrub removal; all shrubs removed (Larrea, Prosopis, Ephedra, etc.)</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>Simp </code>
                  <definition> simplified; only a single species (the dominant) of each growth form remaining, all subordinate species removed; plot contains only LATR, ZIAC, MUPO, and YUBA, ( Larrea, Zinnia, Muhlenbergia, and Yucca).</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>Ss </code>
                  <definition> subshrub removed; (Zinnia, Xanthocephalum, etc).</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>Succ </code>
                  <definition> succulent removed; all leave and stem succulents removed (Yucca, Opuntia, etc).</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Pan</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_erosion_pan_pan</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Pans</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Pans</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>SED</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_erosion_pan_sed_less_than_2mm</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Sediment with diameter </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>grams</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>SED more than2mm</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_erosion_pan_sed_greater_than_2mm</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Sediment with diameter  more than2mm
</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>grams</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>PLANT</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_erosion_pan_plant</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Plant litter</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>grams</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>RABB</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_erosion_pan_rabb</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Rabbit pellets</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>grams</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>NEO</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_erosion_pan_neo</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Neotoma pellets</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>grams</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>KRAT</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_erosion_pan_krat</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Kangaroo Rat pellets</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>grams</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Other</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_erosion_pan_other</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Other (see comments)</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>grams</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>IN</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_erosion_pan_in</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Initials of person processing samples </attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>LC</code>
                  <definition>LaDonna Carlysle</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>RR</code>
                  <definition>Rondi Robison</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>PG</code>
                  <definition>Peg Gronemeyer</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>MB </code>
                  <definition> Michelle Buonopane</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>NP </code>
                  <definition> Neil Paz</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>COMMENT</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_biodiversity_erosion_pan_comment</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Comments</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Comments</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit id="N/A" />
<ns2:unit abbreviation="" id="grams" name="grams" unitType=""><ns2:description /></ns2:unit>

    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>