<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.106.173743" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Long-Term Core Site Grasshopper Dynamics for the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico (1992-2001)</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>David</givenName>
      <surName>Lightfoot</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER, 167 Castetter Hall, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>dlightfo@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">9617</userId>
  </creator>
  <pubDate>2010</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>Grasshoppers are important animals in semi-arid environments, both as herbivores and as food resources for higher level consumer animals. Grasshoppers tend to be numerous and represented by many species in semi-arid environments, especially in desert grasslands. Grasshopper species range from environmental specialists, to environmental generalists. Grasshopper populations tend to change considerably from year to year, often in response to annual variation in rainfall and plant production. The purpose of this study was to monitor grasshopper species composition and abundance over a period of many years from black grama grassland, blue grama grassland, creosotebush shrubland, and pinyon/juniper woodland environments at the Sevilleta, in relation to seasonal and annual variation in precipitation and plant production. Data were collected for all individual species to provide information on community dynamics as well as population dynamics. The working research hypothesis for this study was that grasshopper populations in all environments will correlate positively to seasonal and annual variation in precipitation and plant production. Spring grasshopper populations will be especially high during El Nino years, and late summer populations especially high during La Nina years. This study was initiated in 1992, and is ongoing to the present time.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>populations</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>populations</keyword>
    <keyword>species</keyword>
    <keyword>productivity</keyword>
    <keyword>rain</keyword>
    <keyword>cores</keyword>
    <keyword>transects</keyword>
    <keyword>deserts</keyword>
    <keyword>grasslands</keyword>
    <keyword>grasshoppers</keyword>
    <keyword>grasses</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>Additional Study Area Information Study Area 1 Study Area Name: Goat Draw (Cerro Montosa) Site Location Description: Cerro Montosa draw, at north base of Cerro Montosa, Sierra Los Pinos. Soil: rocky loam.Slope/Aspect: variable steep slopes, all aspects. Vegetation Community: pinyon/juniper woodland, blue grama understory.Terrain/Physiography: rough, dissected erosional montane hills, slopes, and drainages.Geology/Lithology: variable, rhyolite. Hydrology - surface/groundwater: extensive steep arroyo drainages.Size: approximately 1 by 3 km.History (if known): grazed by cattle until 1973.Elevation: approximately 2,000 meters.Climate (general): semi-arid montane, summer rain. Study Area 2 Study Area Name: Five Points Creosotebush. Site Location Description: approximately 2km west of Five Points, McKenzie Flats.&#160;&#160; Soil: sandy loam.Slope/Aspect: slight north-facing slope.Vegetation Community: Chihuahuan Desert creosotebush/black grama grass.Terrain/Physiography: top of Palo Duro Canyon escarpment to south, gentle slope to north. Geology/Lithology: alluvial outwash, extensive caliche near surface.Hydrology - surface/groundwater: slight drainage to the north.Size: approximately 1 by 2 km.History (if known): intensively grazed by cattle until 1973. Elevation: approximately 1,600 meters.Climate (general): semi-arid, summer rain. Study Area 3 Study Area Name: Five Points Grass. Site Location Description: approximately 2km NW of Five Points, McKenzie Flats.&#160; Soil: sandy loam.Slope/Aspect: gentle rolling terrain.Vegetation Community: black grama grassland.Terrain/Physiography: gentle rolling terrain.Geology/Lithology: alluvial outwash, limestone and caliche.Hydrology - surface/groundwater: slight drainage to the west.Size: approximately 2 by 2 km.History (if known): intensivey grazed by cattle until 1973. Elevation: approximately 1,600 meters. Climate (general): semi-arid, summer rain. Additional Information on the Data Collection Period Data are collected in the early summer (April/May) and late summer (September/October). SEVILLETA LTER CORE SITE GRASSHOPPERSGrasshopper Species ListUpdated: 01/19/00 CODE, FRM L-H, LATIN NAME ACPI, G, U, Acantherus piperatusAGDE, GT, U, Ageneotettix deorumAMCOG, U, Amphitornus coloradusARCO, T, P, Arphia conspersaARPS, T, U, Arphia pseudonietanaAUEL, GT, U, Aulocara elliottiAUFE, GT, U, Aulocara femoratumBOAR, A, U, Bootettix argentatusBRMA, GT, U, Brachystola magnaCIPA, T, P, Cibolacris parvicepsCOCR, GT, U, Cordillacris crenulataCOOC, GT, U, Cordillacris occipitalisCOTE, T, U, Conozoa texanaDABI, GT, U, Dactylotum bicolorERSI, G, U, Eritettix simplexHATR, T, U, Hadtrotettix trifasciatusHERU, T, U, Heliaula rufaHEVI, A, U, Hesperotettix viridisHICA, T, U, Hippopedon capitoLAAZ, T, U, Lactista aztecaLEWH, T, U, Leprus wheeleriMEAR, A, U, Melanoplus aridusMEAZ, GT, U, Melanoplus arizonaeMEBO, A, U, Melanoplus bowditchiMEGL, GT, U, Melanoplus gladstoniMELA, GT, U, Melanoplus lakinusMEOC, GT, U, Melanoplus occidentalisMETE, G, U, Mermeria texanaOPOB, G, U, Opeia obscuraPAPA, G, U, Paropomala pallidaPHQU, GT, U, Phlibostroma quadrimaculatumPHRO, T, P, Phrynotettix robustusPSDE, GT, P, Psoloessa delicatulaPSTE, GT, P, Psoloessa texanaSCNI, A, U, Schistocerca nitensSYMO, G, U, Syrbula montezumaTRCA, T, U, Trimerotropis californicusTRFO, H, U, Tropidolophus formosusTRKI, T, U, Trachyrhachis kiowaTRPA, T, U, Trimerotropis pallidipennisTRPI, T, U, Trimerotropis pistrinariaXACO, T, P, Xanthippus corallipesXAMO, T, P, Xanthippus montanus</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/3093</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: Five Points Black Grama is on the transition between Chihuahuan Desert Scrub and Desert Grassland habitat. The site is subject to intensive research activity, including assessments of net primary productivity, phenology, and pollinator diversity, amongst other projects.&#160; It is the site of the unburned black grama (GU) component of the Burn NPP study.
On August 4, 2009, a lightning-initiated fire began on the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge. By August 5, 2009, the fire had reached the Five Points Black Grama site.&#160; Portions of this site were burned, but not the entirety.&#160; See individual projects for further information on the effects of the burn.
&#160;Vegetation: The Five Points Black Grama site is ecotonal in nature, bordering Chihuahuan Desert Scrub at its southern extent and Plains-Mesa Grassland at its northern, more mesic boundary. Characteristically, the dominant grass is black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda)., </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.736</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.736</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Five Points area emcompasses both the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote study sites.&#160; Five Points falls along the transition between the Chihuahuan Desert Scrub and Desert Grassland habitats.&#160; Both core sites are subject to intensive research activities, including NPP measurements, phenology observations, pollinator diversity studies, and ground dwelling arthropod and rodent population assessments.&#160; There are rain-out shelters for drought studies in both the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote sites.Vegetation: The Five Points Creosote site is characterized as Chihuahuan Desert Scrub, dominated by a creosote overstory, with broom snakeweed, purple pricklypear (Opuntia macrocentra), and soapweed yucca as co-occurring shrubs. The site is also characterized by numerous, dense, grass-dominated patches, reflecting proximity to the Five Points Black Grama Site.  Dominant grasses are black grama, fluffgrass (Dasyochloa pulchellum), burrograss (Scleropogon brevifolia), bushmuhly (Muhlenbergia porteri), and galleta (Pleuraphis jamesii).  Notable forbs include field bahia (Bahia absinthifolia), baby aster (Chaetopappa ericoides), plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala), Indian rushpea (Hoffmannseggia glauca), Fendlers bladderpod (Lesquerella fendleri), and globemallows (Sphaeralcea spp.)., siteid: 3</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Cerro Montosa Pinyon-Juniper site has been the location of major Sevilleta LTER research since 1989. Meteorological trends, net primary productivity, rodent and ground-dwelling arthropod populations, mycorrhizal responses to fertilizer, pinyon-juniper fruit and nut production, and pinyon mortality are all being investigated at this site. Previous studies have included analyses of pinyon tree rings for regional climate reconstruction.Vegetation: The vegetation is New Mexico Pinyon-Juniper Woodland, dominated by Colorado pinyon (Pinus edulis) and one-seed juniper (Juniperus monosperma), and accompanied by gray oak (Quercus grisea).  There is a diverse shrub component, including scrub live oak (Q. turbinella), mountain mahogany (Cercocarpus montanus), broom snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae), sacahuista (Nolina microcarpa), red barberry (Mahonia haematocarpa), Apache plume (Fallugia paradoxa), tree cholla (Opuntia imbricata), skunkbush (Rhus trilobata), and banana yucca (Yucca baccata).  Grass diversity is also high, and open spaces between trees are dominated by blue grama (Bouteloua gracilis), with hairy and sideoats grama (B. hirsuta and B. curtipendula) and black grama (B. eriopoda) also being significant. Other common grasses include purple threeawn (Aristida purpurea), wolftail (Lycurus phleoides), mountain and ring muhly (M. montanus and M. torreyi), and New Mexican porcupinegrass (Heterostipa neomexicana). Common forbs include small-flowered milkvetch (Astragalus nuttallianus), white sagebrush (Artemesia ludoviciana), Fendler&#8217;s arabis (Arabis fendleri), Fendler&#8217;s sandmat (Chamaesyce fendleri), New Mexico thistle (Cirsium neomexicanum), false pennyroyal (Hedeoma oblongifolia), bastard sage (Eriogonum wrightii), ping&#252;e rubberweed (Hymenoxys richardsonii), large four o&#8217;clock (Mirabilis multiflora), Fendler's penstemon (Penstemon fendleri), and globemallows (Sphaeralcea hastulata and S. wrightii). , </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.368</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.368</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1976</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1976</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Blue Grama core site is one of five core SEV LTER study sites. Meteorological trends, rodent abundance, pollinator diversity, phenology, and NPP are all being investigated. Additional studies have examined the Bootleg Canyon fire of 1998 and subsequent effects on the patch dynamics of grasses.Vegetation: Vegetation is characterized as Plains-Mesa Grassland, dominated by blue and black grama (Bouteloua gracilis and B. eriopoda) and galleta grass (Pleuraphis jamesii). , </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.631</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.631</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3348</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3348</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1670</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1670</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>1992-09-02</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>1998-05-28</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
      <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Sampling Design Physical Dimensions of Sampling Area: 50-meter by one-meter strip transects, between 6, alternating end-points of rodent trap lines on each of 5 rodent trapping webs at each of the 4 sites. Plot size: Each trapping web is 200-meters diameter, each grasshopper count strip is 50-meters long, by one-meter wide. Transect Length: 50-meters. Sample Unit A sample unit consists of 50 by 1-meter strip transect; 6 strip transects per web, 5 webs per site. Frequency of Sampling Samples are collected twice each year, early summer and late summer. Sample Size Sample size consists of 50-meter by one-meter strip transects. Measurement Techniques Visual counts of all grasshoppers on each strip transect. The observer slowly walks each transect, flushing grasshoppers ahead with a one-meter long - inch white PVC pipe. The observer records data on to a voice-activated micro-cassette recorder. Information recorded includes for each individual grasshopper: species, geneder, age class, and the substrate from which the grasshopper was flushed.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
  </methods>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>sev106_hopperdynamics_01222013.txt</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data for Core Site Grasshopper Dynamic Study</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>sev106_hopperdynamics_01222013.txt</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
          <numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
          <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            <quoteCharacter>double quote</quoteCharacter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url>http://sev.lternet.edu/sites/default/files/data/sev-106/sev106_hopperdynamics_01222013.txt</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1992-09-02</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2001-09-20</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Date</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>DATE</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Date samples collected</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>MM/DD/YY</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>period</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>PER</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Season and year of collection</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>SYY</code>
                  <definition> summer </definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>FYY</code>
                  <definition> fall</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Site</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>SITE</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Study site name</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>P</code>
                  <definition>pinyon</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C</code>
                  <definition>Creosotebush</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>G</code>
                  <definition>grass</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Web</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>WEB</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Rodent trapping web code (A-E)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Rodent trapping web code (A-E)</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Transect</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>TRN</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Grasshopper sampling strip transect number</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Grasshopper sampling strip transect number</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Species</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>SPECIES</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Grasshopper species code, 4-letter code- first 2 letters of the genus and first two letters of the species</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Grasshopper species code, 4-letter code- first 2 letters of the genus and first two letters of the species</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>gender</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>SEX</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Gender of grasshopper observed </attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>F</code>
                  <definition>female</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>M</code>
                  <definition>male</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>N</code>
                  <definition>nymph for immatures for which gender cannot be determined</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>NA </code>
                  <definition> not available</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Age class</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>AGE</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Age class of the observed grasshopper</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1</code>
                  <definition>early instar nymph</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>2</code>
                  <definition>mid instar nymph</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3</code>
                  <definition>late instar nymph</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>4</code>
                  <definition>adult</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>substrate</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>SUB</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The substrate on which the grasshopper was observed (soil or a plant species code)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The substrate on which the grasshopper was observed (soil or a plant species code)</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Count</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>CNT</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Counts of numbers of individual grasshoppers for which all other variables are the same</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Counts of numbers of individual grasshoppers for which all other variables are the same</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Comments</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>COMMENTS</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Notes or comments for a particular observation for information not included in other data variables</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Notes or comments for a particular observation for information not included in other data variables</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
</ns0:eml>