<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-arc.1420.6" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=ARC,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <alternateIdentifier>1989plantspecies.06</alternateIdentifier>
    <title>Vascular plant species list, Skip Walker's Toolik Lake permanent plot species data, Toolik Lake Field Station, North Slope, AK Arctic LTER 1989.</title>
    <creator id="pers-1">
      <organizationName>Arctic LTER Program</organizationName>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Donald</givenName>
        <surName>Walker</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Institute of Arctic Biology</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>University of Alaska Fairbanks</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Fairbanks</city>
        <administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>99775</postalCode>
      </address>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>Arctic LTER Program</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Woods Hole</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7496</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>arc_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://ecosystems.mbl.edu/ARC/</onlineUrl>
    </metadataProvider>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>N.C.</givenName>
        <surName>Barry</surName>
      </individualName>
      <role>Associated Researcher</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>1990</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>Vascular plant species list, Skip Walker's Toolik Lake permanent plot species data</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>species diversity</keyword>
      <keyword>species richness</keyword>
      <keyword>species lists</keyword>
      <keyword>populations</keyword>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>Acceptance and utilization of LTER data requires that:</para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The Principal Investigator be sent a notice stating reasons for acquiring any data and a description of the publication intentions.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The Principal Investigator of the data set be sent a copy of the report or manuscript prior to submission and be adequately cited in any resultant publications</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>A copy of any resultant publications should be sent to: 
            <literalLayout>
Principal Investigator
Ecosystems Center
Marine Biological Laboratory
Woods Hole, MA 02543
</literalLayout></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url>http://ecosystems.mbl.edu/ARC/meta_template.php?FileName=./terrest/plantinfo/1989plantspecies.html</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage id="GEO-1">
        <geographicDescription>Skip Walker's Toolik Lake permanent plot near Toolik Lake research site, located in the northern Arctic Foothills of the Brooks Range, Alaska (68 deg. 37' N, 149 deg. 37' W). See http://arcss.colorado.edu/data/arcss.html for map of plots</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-149.616</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-149.616</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>68.626</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>68.626</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1989-08-23</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1989-09-01</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>Version 2: Added title and atrribute information. 4Oct06 JL.</para>
        <para>Version 3: Added LTERNET Data Access server proxy for Excel and comma delimited data files.</para>
        <para>Version 4: Upadte LTERNET Data Access server proxy link for Excel and comma delimited data files. Changed from knb to das in url.</para>
        <para>Version 5: Updated metadata form to newer version (without site sheet). Fixed discrepency with header variable names. CH 25Jan2013 Updated to newer metadata with site sheet. CH March 2013.</para>
        <para>Version 6: Checked keywords against the LTER network preferred list and replaced non-preferred terms. Jim L 17Feb14</para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact id="im" system="knb">
      <positionName>Data Manager</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Woods Hole</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7496</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>arc_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://ecosystems.mbl.edu/ARC/</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <organizationName>ARC LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Woods Hole</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7496</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>arc_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://ecosystems.mbl.edu/ARC/</onlineUrl>
    </publisher>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>
This species data is extracted from a report on a summary of environmental, 
soil, and vegetation information collected from 81 study plots at the Toolik 
Lake research site, located in the northern Arctic Foothills of the Brooks 
Range, Alaska (68 deg. 37' N, 149 deg. 32' W).  It brings together for easy 
reference all the available information collected from the plots.  This 
information is being used for the classification, mapping and analysis of the 
geobotanical factors in the Toolik Lake and Imnavait Creek region.  A separate 
equivalent data report is available for 71 permanent plots at Imnavait Creek 
(Walker et al., 1987).
Methods and data summaries
     Reconnaissance survey, sampling dates, and plot locations
     A reconnaissance survey was conducted in August 1988 to define the primary 
vegetation types in the Toolik Lake area. Unknown plants were collected and many 
informal partial releve were sampled with reference to spectral signatures on a 
1:50,000-scale color-infrared photograph.  A total of 22 preliminary vegetation 
types were defined based on habitat and dominant species (Table 1).
     Formal releve sampling for the plots in this data report was done during 
the period 1-26 August 1989.  An attempt was made to sample at least three 
releve for each of the types defined in 1988, but this was not possible in all 
cases (Tables 1 and 2).  
     The plots were located in homogeneous areas of vegetation using the 
centralized replicate method of the Braun-Blanquet approach to vegetation 
classification (Mueller-Dombois and Ellenberg, 1974; Westhoff and van der 
Maarel, 1978).  
     Nearly all of the plots are permanently marked.  The exception is plot  
SWT-55.  The plots are marked with 48-inch (122-cm) wooden stakes, and aluminum 
tags at the base of the stakes with the plot numbers.  Some of the stakes have 
broken off since sampling.  We intend to replace all of 
the wooden stakes with tall plastic stakes.  
     Forty of the plots are located along transects as follows:
     1.  West-facing toposequence of Itkillik II glacial outwash and 
retransported hillslope deposits on the south side of Toolik Lake: (from top of 
hill) SWT-7, 8, 9, and 10.
     2.  East-facing toposequence of slope that includes Itkillik I and Itkillik 
glacial till and retransported hillslope deposits on the south side of Toolik 
Lake: SWT-18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 24, and 77.
     3.  South-facing toposequence on Itkillik II till and retransported 
hillslope  deposits on the west side of Toolik Lake: SWT-46, 45, 44, 41, 40, 43, 
39, 42, 38, and 37.  These are in mixed positions on stone-stripes and inter-
stripe sites.  Plots 38 and 37 are in a colluvial basin at the base of the hill.
     4.  North-facing toposequence on Itkillik II till and retransported 
hillslope  deposits:  SWT-48, 47, 49, 50, 51, 52, 53, 54 and 81.  Plot SWT 48 is 
on a ground-  squirrel mound, and most of the sequence is through a deep 
snowbed.  
     5.  Water-track transect on the south side of Toolik Lake: SWT-80, 32, 35, 
75, 78, 27, 79, 36, 73, 74, 64.  Plots SWT-80, 35, 74, and 64 are on frost 
scars.  
     The remaining plots were located around Toolik Lake to sample the diversity 
of vegetation types of the region (Figure 1, Table 2).  
     Sampling methods
          Plot size, species cover estimation, and photographs
          The plots have no fixed size because our main objective was to obtain 
a complete species list for each relief.  
          Photographs were taken of each plot (see Appendix).  Usually photos 
were taken of (1) the general site, (2) close-up of the vegetation, and (3) 
closeup of the soil. 
          Site factors
          The site of each plot was described according to the variables listed 
in Table 3 plus measurements of thaw depth, estimates of cover of bare soil, 
rocks, and the major plant growth forms.  These data are summarized in Table 4.
          Soils
               Field sampling
               Soil pits were dug adjacent to the plots and described and 
classified according to the U.S. soil taxonomy [Soil Survey Staff, 1975].  Soil 
samples were collected from each horizon and air dried in the laboratory.  Bulk 
density and soil moisture samples were taken from the sides of the soil pits or 
from large soil plugs for the wet soils using a 240-ml soil can. 
               Laboratory analysis
               Laboratory analyses were conducted at the Colorado State 
University Soil Testing Laboratory, Fort Collins.  The laboratory's routine 
analysis was run on all samples [pH (saturated paste); NO3 (KCl extract); P, K, 
Zn, Fe, Cu, Mn (NH4HCO3-DTPA extract); lime estimate, texture estimate (by 
hand); and organic matter (Walkley-Black or ash method).  Selected samples were 
analyzed for cation exchange capacity (C.E.C.); percentage gravel; particle size 
(hydrometer method), CaCO3 equivalent; Ca, Mg, Na, K (NH4OAc extract); and soil 
moisture retention (field capacity at 1/3 BAR and permanent wilting point at 15 
BAR).  These methods are described in Page et al. (1982) and Klute (1986).  The 
soils data are in Table 5.
          Vegetation
          A large area surrounding each plot marker was searched until no new 
species were encountered.  Estimates of vegetation cover used the Braun-Blanquet 
cover-abundance scale (r = rare; + = common but less than 1% cover; 1 = 1-5%; 2 
= 6-25%; 3 = 25-50%; 4 = 51-75%; 5= 76-100%).  Cover-abundance values are 
relatively broad subjective classes, and were determined by estimating cover 
within the general area of the stake.  Voucher collections were made for all 
vascular plants, bryophytes, and lichens occurring in the plot. Vascular plants 
were verified by Dr. Dave Murray, University of Alaska Herbarium.  Bryophytes 
were verified by Dr. Dale Vitt, University of Alberta.  Lichens were verified by 
Dr. Joanne Flock at the University of Colorado Herbarium.  Table 6 contains the 
raw species data.

Acknowledgments
This work was funded by the Department of Energy's R4D (Response, Resistance, 
and Resilience to, and Recovery from Disturbance in arctic ecosystems) 
(Grant No. DE-FG02-84ER60242.A006).  Curt Westburg, Nancy Auerbach, and 
Marilyn Walker assisted in the field.  Liz Arnold, Diane Andrews, Nan Lederer, 
Leanne Lestak, and Diane Lorenz assisted with the preparation of this report.
 
Notes: The tables and figure can be found in the full report which is available online 
at http://arcss.colorado.edu/data/arcss.html.
 
Reference Citations: Klute, A.  1986.  Methods of soil analysis, Part 1.  Physical and 
mineralogical methods.  Agronomy Series, No. 9, American Society of 
Agronomy, Inc.. and Soil Science Society of American, Inc. 
Madison, WI, 1188 pp.
Mueller-Dombois, D. And H. Ellenberg.  1974.  Aims and methods of
vegetation ecology.  New York: John Wiley and Sons, 547 pp.
Page, A.L., R.H. Miller, and D.R. Keeney (Eds.)  1982.  Methods of soil 
analysis, Part 2.  Chemical and microbiological properties.  Agronomy 
Series, No. 9, American Society of Agronomy, Inc.. and Soil Science 
Society of American, Inc.  Madison, WI, 1159 pp.
Soil Survey Staff.  1974.  Soil taxonomy of the National Cooperative 
Soil Survey.  Soil Conservation Service, U.S.  Department of Agriculture, 
754 pp.
Walker, D.A., N.D. Lederer, and M.D. Walker.  1987.  Permanent vegetation plots: 
site factors, soil physical and chemical properties, and plant species cover.  
Data report for R4D Program, U.S. Department of Energy.
Westhoff V. and E. van der Maarel.  1978.  The Braun-Blanquet approach.  In: 
Whittaker, R.H. (Ed.)  Classification of plant communities.  
Boston: Junk, pp. 617-726.  
</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </description>
        <protocol>
          <title>Protocol</title>
          <creator>
            <references>pers-1</references>
          </creator>
          <proceduralStep>
            <description>
              <para />
            </description>
          </proceduralStep>
        </protocol>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>Arctic Long-Term Ecological Research (ARC LTER) Program</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>John</givenName>
          <surName>Hobbie</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Woods Hole</city>
          <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7496</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>jhobbie@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Lead PI</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Gus</givenName>
          <surName>Shaver</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Woods Hole</city>
          <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7496</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>gshaver@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Lead PI</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Jim</givenName>
          <surName>Laundre</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Woods Hole</city>
          <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>02543</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7496</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>arc_imr@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Information Manager</role>
      </personnel>
      <abstract>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>
The goal of Arctic LTER project is to predict the future ecological characteristics of the site based upon our knowledge of the controls of ecosystem structure and function as exerted by physical setting and geologic factors, climatic factors, biotic factors, and the changes in fluxes of water and materials from land to water. To achieve this goal the Arctic LTER uses several approaches:

Long-term monitoring and surveys of natural variation of ecosystem characteristics in space and time. Includes: climate, plant communities and productivity, thaw depth, stream flow, chemistry of streams and lakes, temperatures of streams and lakes, lake chlorophyll lake productivity, zooplankton abundance. 

Experimental manipulation of ecosystems for years and decades. Includes: tundra warming, shading, and fertilizing, grazer exclusions, fertilization of lakes and streams, addition and subtraction of predators. 

Synthesis of results and predictive modeling at ecosystem and watershed scales. Includes: stream N cycling, lake physics, bioenergetics of fish populations, water movement and transfer of DOC and nutrients from land to water, soil respiration, cycling and storage of C in tundra under different scenarios of future climates.
</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </abstract>
      <funding>
        <para>This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation under Grants #DEB-981022, 9211775, 8702328; #OPP-9911278, 9911681, 9732281, 9615411, 9615563, 9615942, 9615949, 9400722, 9415411, 9318529; #BSR 9019055, 8806635, 8507493. Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed in the material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.</para>
      </funding>
      <studyAreaDescription>
        <coverage>
          <geographicCoverage>
            <geographicDescription>The Arctic LTER research site (68&#176;N and 149&#176;W) is in the foothills region of the North Slope of Alaska and includes the entire Toolik Lake watershed and the adjacent watershed of the upper Kuparuk River, down to the confluence of these two watersheds. This area is typical of the northern foothills of the Brooks Range, with continuous permafrost, no trees, a complete snow cover for 7 to 9 months, winter ice cover on lakes, streams, and ocean, and cessation of river flow during the winter. Tussock tundra vegetation of sedges and grasses mixed with dwarf birch and low willows form the dominant vegetation type with areas of drier heath tundra on ridge tops and other well-drained sites as well as areas of river-bottom willow communities.</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-149.75</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-149.0433</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>68.8</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>68.5</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>610</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>1360</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </geographicCoverage>
        </coverage>
      </studyAreaDescription>
    </project>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>1989plantspecies.csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Vascular plant species list, Skip Walker's Toolik Lake permanent plot species data, Toolik Lake Field Station, North Slope, AK Arctic LTER 1989.</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>1989plantspecies.csv</objectName>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-arc.1420&amp;urlTail=terrest/plantinfo/data/1989plantspecies.csv</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute id=" att0.1">
          <attributeName>Growth Form</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Growth Form</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Classification as to the plants growth form.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Classification as to the plants growth form.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id=" att0.2">
          <attributeName>Species Name</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Species Name</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Latin name of the plant</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Latin name of the plant</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>765</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>1989plantspecies.xls</entityName>
      <entityDescription>An excel file that has worksheets with the metadata and data.</entityDescription>
      <physical scope="document">
        <objectName>1989plantspecies.xls</objectName>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat>
            <formatName>Microsoft Excel</formatName>
          </externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution scope="document">
          <online>
            <url>http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-arc.1420&amp;urlTail=terrest/plantinfo/xlsfiles/1989plantspecies.xls</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <entityType>Microsoft Excel file</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
  </dataset>
</ns0:eml>