<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-nwt.105.7" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1    http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.1/eml.xsd">
	<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
		<allow>
			<principal>uid=NWT,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
			<permission>all</permission>
		</allow>
		<allow>
			<principal>public</principal>
			<permission>read</permission>
		</allow>
	</access>
	<dataset>
		<title>Streamflow for Green Lake 4, 1981 - ongoing.</title>
		<creator scope="document">
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Nel</givenName>
				<surName>Caine</surName>
			</individualName>
			<address scope="document">
	<deliveryPoint>INSTAAR, University of Colorado</deliveryPoint>
	<deliveryPoint>1560 30th Street</deliveryPoint>
	<deliveryPoint>UCB 450</deliveryPoint>
	<city>Boulder</city>
	<administrativeArea>Colorado</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>80309-0450</postalCode>
	<country>UNITED STATES</country>
</address>
		</creator>
		<metadataProvider>
			<organizationName>Niwot Ridge LTER</organizationName>
			<positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
			<address>
		<deliveryPoint>INSTAAR, University of Colorado</deliveryPoint>
		<deliveryPoint>1560 30th Street</deliveryPoint>
		<deliveryPoint>UCB 450</deliveryPoint>
		<city>Boulder</city>
		<administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea>
		<postalCode>80309-0450</postalCode>
		<country>USA</country>
	</address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">303-492-2594</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>lternwt@colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
			<onlineUrl>http://niwot.colorado.edu/</onlineUrl>
		</metadataProvider>
		<associatedParty id="12010" scope="system" system="FLS">
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Mark</givenName>
				<surName>Williams</surName>
			</individualName>
			<address>
		<deliveryPoint>INSTAAR, University of Colorado</deliveryPoint> 
		<deliveryPoint>1560 30th Street</deliveryPoint> 
		<deliveryPoint>UCB 450</deliveryPoint> 
		<city>Boulder</city> 
		<administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea> 
		<postalCode>80309-0450</postalCode>
	</address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">(303) 492-8830</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>mark.williams@colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
			<role>Data Contact</role>
		</associatedParty>
		<associatedParty id="12020" scope="system" system="FLS">
			<organizationName>Niwot Ridge LTER</organizationName>
			<positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
			<address>
		<deliveryPoint>INSTAAR, University of Colorado</deliveryPoint>
		<deliveryPoint>1560 30th Street</deliveryPoint>
		<deliveryPoint>UCB 450</deliveryPoint>
		<city>Boulder</city>
		<administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea>
		<postalCode>80309-0450</postalCode>
		<country>USA</country>
	</address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">303-492-2594</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>lternwt@colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
			<onlineUrl>http://niwot.colorado.edu/</onlineUrl>
			<role>Data Contact</role>
		</associatedParty>
		<pubDate>1993</pubDate>
		<abstract>
			<section>
				<title>Some of these data were published as a data report:</title>
				<para>Caine, N., and L. Buchanan. 1987. Streamflow data from the Green Lakes
					Valley, 1981-1986. University of Colorado Long-Term Ecological Research Data
					Report 87/4. 34 pp.</para></section>
			<para> This is a summary of discharges from the upper Green Lakes Basin, is based on
				stage records from the outlet of Green Lake 4, and consists of daily flow
				volumes.</para>
		</abstract>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>streamflow</keyword>
			<keyword>water level</keyword>
			<keyword>daily discharge volume</keyword>
			<keyword>hydrology</keyword>
			<keyword>starlogger</keyword>
			<keyword>sensor data</keyword>
			<keyword>outlet</keyword>
			<keyword>alpine</keyword>
			<keyword>Green Lake 4</keyword>
			<keyword>Green Lakes Valley</keyword>
			<keyword>Niwot Ridge LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>NWT</keyword>
		</keywordSet>
		<intellectualRights>
			<section>
				<title>Niwot LTER Data Policy</title>
				<para> The following acknowledgment should accompany any publication or 
					citation of these data: <itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para> Logistical support and/or data were provided by the 
								NSF-supported Niwot Ridge (NWT) Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) 
								project and the University of Colorado (CU) Mountain Research Station (MRS). </para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para> The user of NWT LTER data agrees to provide proper 
								acknowledgment with each usage of the data. Citation of 
								the name(s) of the investigator(s) responsible for the 
								data set, in addition to the generic statement above, 
								constitutes proper acknowledgment. Author(s) (including NWT investigators) 
								of published material that makes use of previously unpublished 
								NWT data agree to provide the NWT data manager with a PDF of 
								that material as soon as it becomes available. The user of NWT 
								data agrees not to resell or redistribute shared data.</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Disclaimer</title>
				<para> The NSF-supported NWT LTER project shall not be held liable for 
					improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained 
					herein, nor assumes liability for misuse, manipulation or distribution 
					of the data. These data  
					are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such. 
					The information contained in these data is dynamic and may change 
					over time. The user of these data should be aware that, 
					while efforts have been taken to ensure that these data are of the 
					highest quality, there is no guarantee of perfection for the data 
					contained herein and the possibility of errors exists. It is the 
					responsibility of the data user to use the data appropriately and 
					in a manner consistent with the limitations of data in 
					general and these data in particular. Users assume responsibility 
					to determine the usability of the dataset. NWT LTER gives no warranty, expressed or implied, as to 
					the accuracy, reliability, or completeness of these data. It is 
					strongly recommended that these data be directly acquired from 
					the NWT LTER server and not indirectly through other sources 
					that may have changed the data in some way. Although these data 
					have been processed successfully on computer systems at CU, no 
					warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the utility of 
					the data on other systems for general or scientific purposes, 
					nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. 
					This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and 
					aggregate use with other data.  </para>
			</section>
		</intellectualRights>
		<distribution>
			<online>
				<url function="download">http://niwot.colorado.edu/data_csvs/gl4disch.nc.data.csv</url>
			</online>
		</distribution>
		<coverage>
			<temporalCoverage>
				<rangeOfDates>
					<beginDate>
						<calendarDate>1981-06-12</calendarDate>
					</beginDate>
					<endDate>
						<calendarDate>2012-09-30</calendarDate>
					</endDate>
				</rangeOfDates>
			</temporalCoverage>
			<geographicCoverage>
				<geographicDescription>Study site was the stream outlet of Green Lake 4. Original data
					consisting of charts and hourly stage readings are stored at Research 
					Laboratory #3.</geographicDescription>
				<boundingCoordinates>
					<westBoundingCoordinate>-105.643 </westBoundingCoordinate>
					<eastBoundingCoordinate>-105.3753 </eastBoundingCoordinate>
					<northBoundingCoordinate>40.0615 </northBoundingCoordinate>
					<southBoundingCoordinate>39.9932 </southBoundingCoordinate>
					<boundingAltitudes>
						<altitudeMinimum>3022</altitudeMinimum> 
						<altitudeMaximum>3814</altitudeMaximum> 
						<altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
					</boundingAltitudes>
				</boundingCoordinates>
			</geographicCoverage>
		</coverage>
		<maintenance>
			<description>
				<para>The documentation section of this file was developed from the NWT LTER Data
					Directory (Symphony files DDABSTRA.WR1, DDDOCUME.WR1, DDMASTER.WR1,
					DDVARIAB.WR1; last updated 16 December 1991) by Susan Kindig and Rick Ingersoll
					in early November 1992. Additional information for the documentation section, as
					well as the header and data sections were supplied by Nel Caine on 8 January
					1993.[RCI, 13 January 1993] Minor modifications were made to the documentation
					section based on comments supplied by Nel Caine on 25 January 1993.[RCI, 25
					January 1993] This file was put under sccs control on 30 March 1993. See the
					appropriate history file for additional log information.[RCI 30 March 1993] Data
					for 1993 were provided by NC on 22 November 1993 and appended to the data
					section on 24 November 1993.[RCI 24 November 1993] Data for 1994 and 1995
					provided by NC were appended to the data section on 13 February 1996.[MAH 13
					February 1996] The reference to Caine 1995 was added to the citations section on
					6 May 1996.[MAH 6 May 1996] Data for 1996 provided by NC were appended to the
					data section on 26 August 1997.[MAH 26 August 1997] The investigator contact
					information was updated on 9 June 1999.[MAH 9 June 1999] Data for 1997 and 1998
					provided by NC were appended to the data section on 9 February 2000.[MAH 9
					February 2000] Data for 1999 and 2000 were appended to the data section on 28
					June 2001.[TMA 28 June 2001] Data for 2001 were appended to the data section on
					29 January 2002.[TMA 29 January 2002] 2001 Data for 16/10 through 31/10 values
					were updated with revised estimates based on a recession coefficient derived
					from the historical record as per Nel Caine's request, on 24 October 2002.[TMA
					24 October 2002] Data for 2002 were appended to the data section on 27 January
					2003.[TMA 27 January 2003] Data for 2003 were appended to the data section.[TMA
					19 July 2004] Data for 2004 were appended to the data section.[TMA 01 February
					2005] Data for 2006 were appended to the data section.[TMA 8 March 2007] The
					comments section was revised to include specific information for each year
					starting in 1997. All data were replaced with comma delimited columns and data
					for 2007 through 31 May 2010 were added. The variable list was updated to
					reflect inclusion of data and comment columns along with discharge volume.[HCH
					22 October 2010]Data for 1 June through 30 September 2010 were appended; title and
					keywords were edited.[HCH 14 December 2011] Data for 1 October 2010 
					through 30 September 2012 were appended; title, keywords, methods, and
					data formats were edited.[HCH 20 June 2013]</para>
				<para>begin 1981, ongoing, daily during the field season (usually late
					May to mid October).</para>
			</description>
		</maintenance>
		<contact>
			<organizationName>Niwot Ridge LTER</organizationName>
			<positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
			<address>
<deliveryPoint>Institute of Arctic and Alpine Research (INSTAAR)</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of Colorado</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>1560 30th Street</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>UCB 450</deliveryPoint>
<city>Boulder</city>
<administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>80309-0450</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">303-492-2594</phone> 
			<electronicMailAddress>lternwt@colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
			<onlineUrl>http://niwot.colorado.edu/</onlineUrl>
		</contact>
		<publisher>
			<organizationName>Niwot Ridge LTER</organizationName>
			<positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
			<address>
<deliveryPoint>Institute of Arctic and Alpine Research (INSTAAR)</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of Colorado</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>1560 30th Street</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>UCB 450</deliveryPoint>
<city>Boulder</city>
<administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>80309-0450</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">303-492-2594</phone> 
			<electronicMailAddress>lternwt@colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
			<onlineUrl>http://niwot.colorado.edu/</onlineUrl>
		</publisher>
		<methods>
			<methodStep>
				<description>
					<para>Citations: </para>
					<para>Caine, T.N. 1982. Water and sediment flows in the Green Lakes
						Valley, Colorado Front Range. Pp 13-22 In Halfpenny, J.C.(ed.). Ecological
						studies in the Colorado alpine. University of Colorado, Institute of Arctic
						and Alpine Research, Occasional Paper 37. 147 pp.</para>
					<para>Caine, N. 1984. Elevational contrasts in contemporary geomorphic activity
						in the Colorado Front Range. Studia Geomorphologica Carpatho-Balcanica 18:
						5-31.</para>
					<para>Caine, N. 1985. Sediment movement and storage on alpine slopes in the
						Colorado Rocky Mountains. Pp 115-137 In Abrahams, A.D.(ed.). Hillslope
						processes. Binghamton Symposium in Geomorphology, International Series 16.
						Boston: Allen and Unwin.</para>
					<para>Caine, N., and E.M. Thurman. 1990. Temporal and spatial variations in the
						solute content of an alpine stream, Colorado Front Range. Geomorphology 4:
						44-72.</para>
					<para>Caine, N. 1995. Snowpack influences on geomorphic processes in Green 
						Lakes Valley, Colorado Front Range. Geographical Journal 161: 55-68.</para>
					<para>Methods:</para>
					<para>Each day starts at 12:00 MST. Flows (Q) were derived from stage 
						records using the following formula for 1981-1996: Q = 0.00095 * Stage ^ 6.01633. 
						Flows were initially calculated in cfs and later converted to m3/sec. Stage
						was measured in feet on pipe at control section (6ft = top of pipe) at old
						weir 25 m downstream of lake. Daily flows were estimated from trapezoidal 
						integration of 25 hourly flows. Data for 12-23 June 1981 were estimated 
						from intermittent observations. Data for 17-21 July 1981 were interpolated
						because there was no record due to a jammed float. Data after 29 September
						1981 and prior to 2 October 1981 were estimated by recession to observation
						of 2 October 1981. Data for 27 May-28 June 1982 were estimated from inter-
						mittent observations because there was no continuous stage record. Data for
						3-15 June 1983 were estimated because there was no continuous record. Data 
						for 21-27 June 1983 were interpolated because the recorder drowned. Data 
						for 25 May-11 June 1984 were estimated because there was no continuous record. 
						Data for 24 May-4 June 1985 were estimated because there was no continuous 
						record. Record for 1987 ends unusually early. Data for 28-30 June 1988, 
						27 July-15 August 1988, and 22 September-4 October 1988 were estimated or
						interpolated by recession analysis. Data for 24-29 May 1989 were estimated
						from observations because there was no continuous record. Data for 31 May-
						11 June 1990 were estimated because there was no continuous record. Data 
						for 21 May-5 June 1991 were estimated because there was no continuous record.
						Data for 6-18 May 1992 were estimated because there was no continuous record.
						Data for 9-29 October 1992 were estimated from recession and weekly obser-
						vations. Data for 20-31 May 1993 were estimated from occasional field 
						observations prior to installation of F-recorder on site. Data for 13-28
						October 1993 were estimated by recession analysis and occasional field 
						observations following removal of recorder on 14 October 1993.
						Data for 5-21 June 1995 are based upon intermittent estimates of flow in 
						the channel and not a continuous record. Data for 4-31 October 1995
						are based on weekly observations of water level and recession characteristics 
						of late-season flows at this site and not a continuous record.
						Recorder installed June 13 1996, removed October 1 1996. The record was 
						missing for July 11 - 18 1996 and has been interpolated. Estimates prior 
						to June 13 1997 are based on occasional observations only; those after September 
						28 1997 are based on flow recession.</para>
						<para>1997 to 1998: Stages may be converted to discharges by the rating for this station:
						Q(l/s) = 0.0269 * [6 + (Stage/30.48)]^6.01633.</para>
						<para>1997:
						Recorded water levels should be corrected as follows to	give stage values:
						Stage (cm) = Level(cm) + corrxn - 100.
						June 3 to July 13: correction starts at 0.17 cm, changes by 0.1357 cm/day.
						July 13 to Aug 6: correction 5.6565 cm (constant).
						Aug 6 to Oct 9: correction changes by -0.0084 cm/day.
						Starlogger installed in channel 06/03/97 13:15 MST; removed 10/09/97 11:00 MST.</para>
						<para>1998:
						Recorded water levels should be corrected as follows to give stage values:
						Stage (cm) = Level(cm) - corrxn - 100.
						At 12:00 MST May 26, corrxn = 1.173 cm.
						May 26 to 11:00 MST, June 9  correction changes -0.2495 cm/day.
						June 9 to 12:00 MST July 4, correction is -2.31 cm (constant).
						July 4 to 07:00 July 16, correction changes by +0.29 cm/day.
						July 16 to 06:00 July 30, correction is +1.1143 cm (constant).
						July 30 to 21:45 Aug 7, correction changes by -0.1725 cm/day.
						After August 7, correction is -0.3773 cm (constant).
						Starlogger installed in channel 05/26/98 11:45 MST; removed 10/08/98 11:05 MST.
						Starlogger disconnected from sensor  08:35 to 08:45 MST 08/04/98 while
						WL-14 logger installed.
						No starlogger record 08/11 to 08/18 1998.
						For period 08/04 to 08/20, WL-14 record is available in file GL4-98-A.EZL 
						which contains date, time and water level (cm) records on a 10 minute interval. 
						This record can be used to estimate the *log record as:
						*log = 0.04666 + 0.0091*WL-14 (N = 1333, R2 = 0.948)</para>
						<para>1999 to 2012: Stages may be converted to discharges by the rating for this station:
						Q(l/s) = 11.97714 *  Stage^6.79756.</para>
						<para>1999:
						Recorded water levels (RL) should be corrected as follows to give stage values:
						Stage (m) = 2.025 * RL + 1.006.
						Starlogger installed in channel 05/27/99 11:00 MST; removed 10/05/98 12:05 MST.</para>
						<para>2000:
						Recorded water levels (RL) should be corrected as follows to give stage values:
						Stage (m) = 0.9937 * RL + 1.042.
						Starlogger installed in channel 10/05/00 13:35 MST; removed 12/10/00 10:15 MST.</para>
						<para>2001:
						Recorded water levels (RL) should be corrected as follows to give stage values:
						Stage (m) = 1.075 * RL + 0.988 (r2 = 0.9737; n = 57)
						based on field measurements from 15 May to 16 October.
						Starlogger installed in channel 15/05/01 12:15 MST; removed 16/10/01 9:50 MST.</para>
						<para>2002:
						Recorded water levels (RL) should be corrected as follows to give stage values:
						Stage (m) = 1.011 * RL + 0.98 (r2 = 0.9965; n = 54)
						based on field measurements from 6 May to October 21.
						Starlogger installed 6/05/02 10:30 MST; removed	22/10/02 10:30 MST.</para>
						<para>2003:
						Recorded water levels (RL) should be corrected as follows to give stage values:
						Prior to 13:00 MST, 30 May, subtract 0.0313 from RL to correct for a
						shift of stilling well at that time.
						Stage (m) = 1.106 * RL + 0.98 (r2 = 0.995; n = 8)
						based on field measurements from 27 May to 3 June.
						Stage (m) = 0.982 * RL + 1.021 (r2 = 0.991; n = 43)
						based on field measurements from 5 June to 25 September.
						Starlogger installed 27/05/03 10:25 MST; removed 9/10/03 11:15 MST.
						Sensor leads chewed 17:40 MST 12/07/03, missing record to 10:00 MST 15/07/03.</para>
						<para>2004:
						Recorded water levels (RL) should be corrected as follows to give stage values:
						Stage (m) = 0.9456 * RL + 1.1481 (r2 = 0.9773; n = 36)
						based on field measurements from 20 May to 26 August.
						Starlogger installed 20/05/03 12:50 MST; removed.</para>
						<para>2005:
						Recorded water levels (RL) should be corrected as follows to give stage values:
						Stage (m) = 1.051 * RL + 1.117 (r2 = 0.9855; n = 50)
						based on field measurements from June 9 to October 13, when logger record ends.
						Starlogger #7069 installed 19/05/05 13:30 MST; removed 13/10/05 10:40 MST.</para>
						<para>2006:
						Recorded water levels (RL) should be corrected as follows to give stage values:
						Record to 13:00 MST 01/06/06:
						Stage (m) = 1.0464*RL + 1.0543 (r2 = 0.9616; N = 7 (18/05 to 01/06)).
						Record from 13:00 MST 01/06/06:
						Stage (m) = 1.0237*RL + 1.0933 (r2 = 0.9936; N = 57 (08/06 to 12/10)).
						The calibration change seems to have been required because of a shift
						in the stilling well.
						Starlogger #7069 installed 18 May 2006, 14:35 MST; removed 12 October 2006, 08:45 MST.</para>
						<para>2007 to 2009:  Field measurements of water level (WL) are taken by reference to the
						top of the post supporting the stilling well on the right bank of the
						channel. Stage (S) is then defined as S = 210 - WL cm. Since the
						stilling well is installed and removed each season, the height of the
						pressure transducer below this reference level varies and needs to be
						recalibrated every season.</para><para>
						2007:
						Recorded water levels (RL) should be corrected as follows to give stage values:
						Stage (m) = 0.9527*RL + 1.1223 (r2 = 0.9548; N = 74).
						Starlogger #7069 installed 15 May 2007, 13:50 MST; removed 16 October 2007, 10:00 MST.
						The record is missing from 20:40 MST, 4 August to 10:00 MST, 21.August because of
						a problem with the logger connection.</para><para>
						2008:
						Recorded water levels (RL) should be corrected as follows to give stage values:
						Stage (m) = 1.0314*RL + 1.1304(r2 = 0.9868; N = 50).
						Because of difficulty locating the gauge site, the record does
						not start until June 24 2008, probably after the peak flow for 2008.
						Logger 7069 installed 24 June 2008, 15:10 MST; replaced 30 September 2008, 12:10 MST.
						Logger 2426 installed 30 September 2008, 12:50 MST.</para><para>
						2009:
						Recorded water levels (RL) should be corrected as follows to give stage values:
						From 30/12/2008 to 23/06/2009:
						Stage (m) = 1.87*RL + 1.07 (r2 = 0.9977; N = 9).
						From 23/06/2009 to 10/09/2009:
						Stage (m) = 0.8608*RL + 1.1264 (r2 = 0.9928; N = 61).
						Stage (m) = 0.8608*RL + 1.07825  i.e. an off-set
						correction of -.04815 from 12:30 25/06 to 9:00 09/07.
						From 10/09/2009 to 29/06/2009:
						Stage (m) = 2.1925*RL + 1.0311 (r2 = 0.995; N = 21).
						Records missing 11/06/09 to 18/06/09 and 08/09/09 to 10/09/09 because of 
						logger failure.</para><para>
						2010:
						All files are ASCII format, as retrieved from Starloggers #7069 and #2426.
						Fields (columns) in the record:
						Date and Time (MST);
						Maximum water depth (m) since last record
						Minimum water depth (m) since last record
						Mean water level (m) since last record
						Mean water temperature
						Mean logger temperature
						Mean logger voltage
						Recorded water levels (RL) should be corrected as follows to give stage values
						Stage (m) = 2.1953*RL  +  1.031	r2  =  0.995;   N  = 21
						(08:35 MST, 10/09/09 to 12:30 MST, 29/06/10) 
						Stage (m) = 1.037*RL  +  1.088	r2  =  0.979;   N  = 38
						(12:30 MST, 29/06/10 to 09:30 MST, 31/08/2010)
						From 01/15/10 to 02/13/10, the water level in the channel was below the pressure 
						transducer so flows between those dates are likely overestimated.</para><para>
						2011:
						All files are ASCII format, as retrieved from Starloggers #7069 and #2426.
						Fields (columns) in the record:
						Date and Time (MST);
						Maximum water depth (m) since last record
						Minimum water depth (m) since last record
						Mean water level (m) since last record
						Mean water temperature
						Mean logger temperature
						Mean logger voltage
						Recorded water levels (RL) should be corrected as follows to give stage values
						Stage (m)  =  2.2145*RL  +  1.027	r2  =  0.994;   N  = 49
						(from 09:30 MST, 31/08/2010 to 11:00 MST, 27/09/11).</para><para>
						2012:
						All files are ASCII format, as retrieved from Starloggers #7069 and #2426.
						Fields (columns) in the record:
						Date and Time (MST);
						Maximum water depth (m) since last record
						Minimum water depth (m) since last record
						Mean water level (m) since last record
						Mean water temperature
						Mean logger temperature
						Mean logger voltage
						Because of the failure of a signal conditioning/interface board in late 2011, multiple 
						calibrations were needed in 2012. These are not always reliable and much of the record 
						between October 2011 and July 2012 should be considered suspect.
						Available records of water levels (RL) have been corrected as follows to give stage values
						Stage (m)  =  2.0705*RL  +  1.062	r2  =  0.9924;   N  = 49
						(from 31/08/10 to 29/05/12) 
						Stage (m)  =  1.9316*RL  +  1.088	r2  =  0.984;   N  = 14
						(from 29/05/12 to 26/06/12)		
						Stage (m)  =  1.0244*RL  +  1.0258	r2  =  0.918;   N  = 12
						(from 26/06/12 to 12/07/12)
						Stage (m)  =  1.4921*RL  +  1.0419	r2  =  0.999;   N  = 5
						(from 12/07/12 to 19/07/12)
						Stage (m)  =  1.9646*RL  +  1.0468	r2  =  0.996;   N  =44
						(from 19/07/12 to 04/10/12)
						After 30 September 2011, many of the original data up to 22 May 2012 are suspect. 
						Date/time stamp failed 19 February 2012.
						The record after 31/08/10 is preliminary and subject to change when further data 
						are retrieved in mid-2013.</para>
				</description>
			</methodStep>
		</methods>			
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>gl4disch.nc.data.csv</entityName>
			<entityDescription>Streamflow for Green Lake 4, 1981 - ongoing.</entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>gl4disch.nc.data.csv</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution> 
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://niwot.colorado.edu/data_csvs/gl4disch.nc.data.csv</url> 
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>date</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>date</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>date</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>date</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<dateTime>
							<formatString>YYYY-MM-DD</formatString>
							<dateTimePrecision>1</dateTimePrecision>
							<dateTimeDomain>
								<bounds>
									<minimum exclusive="false">1981-06-12</minimum>
								</bounds>
							</dateTimeDomain>
						</dateTime>
					</measurementScale>
					<missingValueCode>
						<code>NaN</code>
						<codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
					</missingValueCode>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>daily discharge volume</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>daily discharge volume</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>daily discharge volume</attributeDefinition>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>cubicMeter</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
					<missingValueCode>
						<code>NaN</code>
						<codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
					</missingValueCode>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>Comments</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>comments</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>comments</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>site</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
					<missingValueCode>
						<code>NaN</code>
						<codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
					</missingValueCode>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
	</dataset>
</ns0:eml>