<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.195.88821" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Pino Gate Prairie Dog Study: Landscape-scale Ground-Dwelling Arthropod Plot Data from the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico (2000-2001)</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Ana</givenName>
      <surName>Davidson</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER, 167 Castetter Hall, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>davidson@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">8862</userId>
  </creator>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>David</givenName>
      <surName>Lightfoot</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER, 167 Castetter Hall, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>dlightfo@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">9617</userId>
  </creator>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Yang</givenName>
      <surName>Xia</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> Sevilleta LTER UNM Biology Department, MSC03 2020  1 University of New Mexico </deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>USA</country>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-8119</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>yxia@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Ana</givenName>
      <surName>Davidson</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER, 167 Castetter Hall, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>davidson@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">8862</userId>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <pubDate>2010</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>Keystone species have large impacts on community and ecosystem properties, and create important ecological interactions with other species.  Prairie dogs (Cynomys spp.), and banner-tailed kangaroo rats (Dipodomys spectabilis) are considered keystone species of grassland ecosystems, and create a mosaic of unique habitats on the landscape. These habitats are known to attract a number of animal species, but little is known about how they affect arthropod communities. Our research evaluated the keystone roles of prairie dogs and kangaroo rats on arthropods at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge in central New Mexico, USA.  We evaluated the impacts of these rodents on ground-dwelling arthropod and grasshopper communities in areas where prairie dogs and kangaroo rats co-occurred compared to areas where each rodent species occurred alone.  Our results demonstrate that prairie dogs and kangaroo rats have keystone-level impacts on these arthropod communities. Their burrow systems provided important habitats for multiple trophic and taxonomic groups of arthropods, and increased overall arthropod abundance and species richness on the landscape.  Many arthropods also were attracted to the aboveground habitats around the mounds and across the landscapes where the rodents occurred.  Detritivores, predators, ants, grasshoppers, and rare rodent burrow inhabitants showed the strongest responses to prairie dog and kangaroo rat activity. The impacts of prairie dogs and kangaroo rats were unique, and the habitats they created supported different assemblages of arthropods.  Where both rodent species occurred together on the landscape, there was great habitat heterogeneity and increased arthropod diversity.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>populations</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>habitats</keyword>
    <keyword>communities</keyword>
    <keyword>species</keyword>
    <keyword>biology</keyword>
    <keyword>pitfall traps</keyword>
    <keyword>arthropods</keyword>
    <keyword>grasshoppers</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>Additional Personnel in Collecting Data/SamplesJulie McIntyre assisted in field data collection.Additional Study Area InformationStudy Area Name: Pino GateStudy Area Location: The study site was located near the base of the Los Pinos mountains and directly adjacent to the nothern fencline of the SNWR at Pino GateElevation: 1600 mVegetation: Burrograss (Scleropogon brevifolius), sand dropseed (Sporobolus ryptandrus), and black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda) were the dominant vegetation.Soils: Deep clayey loam soilsGeology: On an upper bajada slope, in a broad swaleClimate: Long-term mean annual precipitation is 243 mm, about 60% of which occurs during the summer.  Long-term mean monthly temperatures for January and July are 1.5&#176;C and 25.1&#176;C, respectively.Site history: Historically, prairie dogs were common throughout the area, but were exterminated by the early 1970&#8217;s (John Ford, United States Department of Agriculture Wildlife Services, personal&#160; communication).  Gunnison&#8217;s prairie dogs began to re-colonize the study site from adjacent private land in 1998.  During our study, the colony occurred within a 5 ha area, near the base of the Los Pi&#241;os Mountains in an area with deep clayey loam soils.  The site has been long inhabited by kangaroo rats, and represents typical northern Chihuahuan Desert grasslandNorth Coordinate:34.406954South Coordinate:34.406954East Coordinate:106.606269West Coordinate:106.606269</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/1323</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2000-06-01</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2001-10-01</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>1/09/2009 -YX. The metadata was entered  by Yang Xia from metadata supplied by Ana Davidson1/17/2008 (Yang Xia) - updated and modified metadata to correct format; - Checked data for missing data points and errors</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
      <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Experimental DesignWe compared the ground-dwelling arthropods on plots occupied by: 1) both species (Pdog+Krat plot); 2) only kangaroo rats (Krat plot); and 3) both species, but where prairie dogs inhabited one half of the plot and kangaroo rats inhabited the other half (Transition plot).Sampling DesignThe landscape-scale plots were 180 m x 180 m.  On each landscape-scale plot, pitfall traps were installed using a 5 x 5 grid array and placed at 30 m intervals along each transect line.Field methodsThe pitfall traps were made of 10 oz plastic cups inserted into 12 oz cans, buried with the rim of the cup flush with the ground. Traps were filled with non-toxic propylene glycol as the trapping and preservation agent, and ceramic tiles (0.23 m x 0.23 m) were elevated over the traps.  Traps were opened for one month, both during spring (May) and fall (September), from spring 2000 through fall 2001.Laboratory ProceduresArthropod samples were sorted and identified in the laboratory.  Only ground-dwelling taxa were considered. The pitfall dataset resulted in 218 species (from both plot and mound samples).  Most taxonomic groups were identified to species, but weevils (Curculionidae), velvet ants (Mutillidae), and spider wasps (Pompilidae) were grouped at higher taxonomic levels and not included in species richness analyses. Nymphs of crickets, grasshoppers, and spiders could not be identified to species. Arthropod voucher specimens from this study were deposited in the collection of the Arthropod Division, Museum of Southwestern Biology (MSB) at the University of New Mexico (UNM).</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
  </methods>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>sev195_pdogarthroplot_01132009.txt</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data for Ground-Dwelling Arthropods at Prairie Dog Study</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>sev195_pdogarthroplot_01132009.txt</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url>http://sev.lternet.edu/sites/default/files/data/sev-195/sev195_pdogarthroplot_01132009.txt</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2000-06-12</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2001-10-05</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>PERIOD</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>PERIOD</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>season and year of collection</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>SYY</code>
                  <definition>summer</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>FYY</code>
                  <definition>fall</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>DATE</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>DATE</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Date of data collection</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>MM/DD/YYYY</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>PLOT</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>PLOT</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>landscape plot on which data was collected</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>PK</code>
                  <definition>prairie dog + kangaroo rat plot</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>T</code>
                  <definition> transition plot</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>K</code>
                  <definition>kangaroo rat plot</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>LINE</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>LINE</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>line (transect) on which data were collected</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>line (transect) on which data were collected</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>TRAP</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>TRAP</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>pitfall trap in which arthropods were collected</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>pitfall trap in which arthropods were collected</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>SPP</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>SPP</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>the first 3 letters of the code are the first 3 letters of the order, the 2nd set of 3 letters are the first 3 letters of the family, the 3rd set of 3 letters are the first three letters of the genus, and the 4th set of 3 letters are the first three letters of the species name</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>the first 3 letters of the code are the first 3 letters of the order, the 2nd set of 3 letters are the first 3 letters of the family, the 3rd set of 3 letters are the first three letters of the genus, and the 4th set of 3 letters are the first three letters of the species name</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>CNT</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>CNT</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>number of individuals of an arthropod species caught in a pitfall trap</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>number of individuals of an arthropod species caught in a pitfall trap</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
</ns0:eml>