<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-nwt.102.11" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.1/eml.xsd">
<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
<allow>
<principal>uid=NWT,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
<principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset>
<title>Streamflow for Albion camp, 1981 - ongoing.</title>
<creator>
	<individualName>
		<givenName>Nel</givenName>
		<surName>Caine</surName>
 </individualName>
<address>
	<deliveryPoint>Institute of Arctic and Alpine Research</deliveryPoint>
	<deliveryPoint>1560 30th Street</deliveryPoint>
	<deliveryPoint>UCB 450</deliveryPoint>
	<city>Boulder</city>
	<administrativeArea>Colorado</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>80309</postalCode>
	<country>UNITED STATES</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="business">(303)492-5053</phone>
<phone phonetype="secondary business">(303)492-8642</phone>
</creator>
<pubDate>1993</pubDate>
<abstract>
<para>
This is a summary of discharges from the Green Lakes Basin (7.1 km2 area) and is based on stage records from the control section in the channel,  about 50 m downstream of the culvert under the road at the Albion camp, and  consists of daily flow volumes. Initially, instrumentation consisted of a Leupold-Stevens A70 float recorder. The site was instrumented with an  Omnidata EZ900 data logger system interfaced to a Keller 1 psi pressure  transducer on 29 June 1993. In order to establish cross-calibration between  the 2 forms of instrumentation, both were planned to be used through 1994.</para>
</abstract>
<keywordSet>
<keyword>NWT</keyword>
<keyword>Colorado</keyword>
	<keyword>daily discharge</keyword>
	<keyword>hydrology</keyword>
	<keyword>streamflow</keyword>
	<keyword>water level</keyword>
	<keyword>Albion</keyword>
	<keyword>Green Lakes Valley</keyword>
	<keyword>daily discharge volume</keyword>
	<keyword>cr10x</keyword>
	<keyword>global water logger</keyword>
	<keyword>Niwot Ridge LTER</keyword>
</keywordSet>
<intellectualRights>
		<section>
			<title>Niwot LTER Data Policy</title>
			<para> The following acknowledgment should accompany any publication or 
				citation of these data: <itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para> Logistical support and/or data were provided by the 
							NSF-supported Niwot Ridge (NWT) Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) 
							project and the University of Colorado (CU) Mountain Research Station (MRS). </para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para> The user of NWT LTER data agrees to provide proper 
							acknowledgment with each usage of the data. Citation of 
							the name(s) of the investigator(s) responsible for the 
							data set, in addition to the generic statement above, 
							constitutes proper acknowledgment. Author(s) (including NWT investigators) 
							of published material that makes use of previously unpublished 
							NWT data agree to provide the NWT data manager with a PDF of 
							that material as soon as it becomes available. The user of NWT 
							data agrees not to resell or redistribute shared data.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Disclaimer</title>
			<para> The NSF-supported NWT LTER project shall not be held liable for 
				improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained 
				herein, nor assumes liability for misuse, manipulation or distribution 
				of the data. These data  
				are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such. 
				The information contained in these data is dynamic and may change 
				over time. The user of these data should be aware that, 
				while efforts have been taken to ensure that these data are of the 
				highest quality, there is no guarantee of perfection for the data 
				contained herein and the possibility of errors exists. It is the 
				responsibility of the data user to use the data appropriately and 
				in a manner consistent with the limitations of data in 
				general and these data in particular. Users assume responsibility 
				to determine the usability of the dataset. NWT LTER gives no warranty, expressed or implied, as to 
				the accuracy, reliability, or completeness of these data. It is 
				strongly recommended that these data be directly acquired from 
				the NWT LTER server and not indirectly through other sources 
				that may have changed the data in some way. Although these data 
				have been processed successfully on computer systems at CU, no 
				warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the utility of 
				the data on other systems for general or scientific purposes, 
				nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. 
				This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and 
				aggregate use with other data.  </para>
		</section>
	</intellectualRights>
<distribution>
	<online>
		<url function="download">http://niwot.colorado.edu/data_csvs/albdisch.nc.data.csv</url>
	</online>
</distribution>
<coverage>
<temporalCoverage>
<rangeOfDates>
<beginDate>
<calendarDate>1981-07-16</calendarDate>
</beginDate>
<endDate>
<calendarDate>2012-09-30</calendarDate>
</endDate>
</rangeOfDates>
</temporalCoverage>
<geographicCoverage>
	<geographicDescription>Study site was located in a control section in the channel about 50 m downstream of the culvert under the road at the Albion camp. Original data consisting of charts and hourly stage readings are stored at Research Laboratory #3.</geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates>
<westBoundingCoordinate>-105.643  </westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-105.3753 </eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>40.0615   </northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>39.9932   </southBoundingCoordinate>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
</coverage>
<maintenance>
<description>
	<para>The documentation section of this file was developed from the NWT LTER Data Directory (Symphony files DDABSTRA.WR1, DDDOCUME.WR1, DDMASTER.WR1, DDVARIAB.WR1; last updated 16 December 1991) by Susan Kindig and Rick Ingersoll in early November 1992. Additional information for the documentation section, as well as the header and data sections were supplied by Nel Caine on 8 January 1993.[RCI, 8 January 1993] Minor modifications were made to the documentation sections based on comments supplied by Nel Caine on 25 January 1993.[RCI, 25 January 1993] This file was put under sccs  control on 30 March 1993. See the appropriate history file for additional  log information.[RCI 30 March 1993] Data for 1993 were provided by NC on 22 November 1993 and appended to the data section on 23 November 1993. [RCI 23 November 1993] The 1993 data added on 23 November 1993 were  deleted and updated 1993 data provided by NC on 3 January 1994 were appended to the data section on 5 January 1994. Additional comments provided by Nel Caine were added to the documentation section at this time  as well.[RCI 5 January 1994] Minor editorial revisions supplied by  Nel Caine on 7 January 1994 were incorporated into the documentation  section on that date.[RCI 7 January 1994] Data for 30 and 31 December 1993 were provided by NC on 19 January 1994 and were appended to the data section on that date.[RCI 19 January 1994] Data for 1994 and 1995 were provided my NC in December 1995 and appended to the data section on 23 Janauary 1996.[MAH 23 January 1996] The reference to Caine 1995 was added to the citations section on 6 May 1996.[MAH 6 May 1996] Data for 1996 provided by NC were appended to the data section  on 26 August 1997.[MAH 26 August 1997] The investigator contact information was updated on 9 June 1999.[MAH 9 June 1999] Data for 1997 and 1998 were appended on 26 September 2000.[MAH 26 September 2000] Data for 1999 and 2000 were appended to the data section, also related comments were  appended to the comments section on 28 June 2001.[TMA 28 June 2001] Data for 2001 were appended to the data section on 29 January 2002.[TMA 29 January 2002] Data for 2002 were appended to the data section on 27 January 2003.[TMA 27 January 2003] Data for 2003 were appended  to the data section.[TMA 19 July 2004]  Data for 2004 were appended to the data section.[TMA 01 February 2005] Data for 2005 and 2006 were appended to the data section.[TMA 08 March 2006] The comments section was revised to include specific information for each year starting in 1997. All data were replaced with comma delimited columns and data for 2007 to 2009 were added. The variable list was updated to reflect  inclusion of date and comment columns along with discharge volume. [HCH 21 October 2010] Updated title and keywords and appended comments and data for 2010.[HCH 1 December 2011] Data for 1 October 2010 through 30 September 2012 were appended; title, keywords, methods, and data formats were edited.[HCH 20 June 2013]</para>
	<para>Ongoing, daily during field season (usually late May to mid October).</para>
</description>
</maintenance>
<contact>
<organizationName>Niwot Ridge LTER/University of Colorado</organizationName>
<positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>1560 30th Street, CB 450</deliveryPoint>
<city>Boulder</city>
<administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>80309</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<electronicMailAddress>lternwt@colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
</contact>
<publisher>
<organizationName>Niwot Ridge LTER/University of Colorado</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>1560 30th Street, CB 450</deliveryPoint>
<city>Boulder</city>
<administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>80309</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<electronicMailAddress>lternwt@colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
</publisher>
<methods>
<methodStep>
<description>
<section>
	<para>Each day starts at 12:00 MST. Flows (Q) were derived from stage records 
		using the following formulae for 1981 to 1996: Q = 0.00929 * Stage ^ 1.7453 
		(for stage LT 22 cm) and Q = 2.435E-06 * Stage ^ 4.4123 (for stage GT 22 cm). Either formula 
		could be used for stage = 22 cm. Flows were initially calculated in cfs and later
		converted to m3/sec. Daily flows were estimated from trapezoidal integration of
		25 hourly flows. Stage was in cm from lip of stilling well to top of post at
		control section (110 cm for 1981-1988 records; 113 cm for 1989 records; 97.5 cm
		for 1990 records; 95.5 cm for 1991 records; 117 cm for 1992 records) about 50 m 
		downstream of culvert under Green Lakes road at Albion camp. In May 1989, the 
		reference post downstream of the stilling well, used in previous years, was lost. 
		The stilling well was collapsing and unstable in 1990 and 1991; it was replaced 
		10 October 1991. There was no continuous record for 21 May - 5 June, 1983 period 
		so data were estimated. Patchy 1987 record after 14 August excluded. Daily flows 
		were interpolated for the following periods in 1988: 3 - 17 June and 30 August - 
		5 September. Data for 1 January were missing in the original logger record for
		both 1994 and 1995. Values were interpolated across the 24-hour gap for both of
		these instances, affecting the previous days record (i.e., 31 December 1993 and 1994)
		as well. The EZ900 record for 1993 (14 October - 29 December 1993) showed an almost
		linear drift in transducer signal of +0.0674 cm/day. This was removed from the
		record before conversion through the rating curves above. For the period of
		overlapping records (EZ900 and F recorder in September and October (low flows),
		the two estimates of daily discharges are related as: Q(EZ) = 0.9446 * Q(F) + 413
		with r = 0.994.
		Reservoir management at Lake Albion affects this record:
		Lake Albion valves open 9/3/93,
		Lake Albion valves closed 30/6/93 14:00 MST,
		Lake Albion valves open 5/11/93.
		Valves at the Lake Albion dam were opened on December 12, 1996.
		1997 to 2012: Stages may be converted to discharges by the rating for
		this station: Q(l/s) = 0.0408 * Stage^2.526.
		1997: 
		Recorded water levels should be corrected as follows to give stage values:  
		Stage (cm) = Recorded Level - 35.53 (SE = 0.06 cm).
		Valves on Lake Albion closed June 4, 1997 (Craig Skeie).
		1998: 
		Recorded water levels should be corrected as follows to give stage values:	
		Stage (cm) = Recorded Level - Correction.
		Stage correction at 00:00 hr 01/01/98 was 35.9155 cm.
		To 12:00 hr 06/01/98, correction changes by + 0.005423 cm/day.
		To 14:00 hr 06/18/98, correction = 36.737 cm.
		To 07:00 hr 08/02/98, correction changes by -0.02277 cm/day.
		To 12:00 hr 09/10/98, correction = 35.719 cm.
		To 04:00 hr 10/19/98, correction changes by + 0.1554 cm/day.
		To 12:00 hr 01/02/99, correction = 36.32 cm.
		1999: 
		Omnidata Easy Logger 900 records (RL) are in cm and should be corrected by: 
		Stage (cm) = RL - 36.32 cm (01/01/99 to 04/10/99).
		Stage (cm) = 1.036*RL - 2.304 cm (06/29/99 to 10/26/99).
		Stage (cm) = 1.036*RL - 2.63 cm (10/26/99 to 01/02/00).
		Global Water WL-14 Logger record contains instantaneous water levels
		(RL, cm) recorded on the hour. These should be corrected by:
		Stage (cm) = 0.994*RL - 2.304 cm (05/25/99 to 07/06/99).
		Valves at Lake Albion opened at about 12:00 MST, 05/02/99;
		closed at about 10:30 MST, 19/06/99.
		Lake Albion spilled late 29/06/99.
		2000: 
		Omnidata Easy Logger 900 records (RL) are in cm and should be corrected by: 
		Stage (cm) = 1.036*RL - const
		const = 2.526 cm (30/12/99 to 19/02/00),
		then increases by 0.007cm/d to 11/03/00,
		const = 2.79 cm (11/03/00 to 14/04/00).
		Stage (cm) = 1.001*RL - 2.79 (14/04/00 to 01/05/00).
		Stage (cm) = 1.0453*RL - 5.195 (02/05/00 to 16/11/00).
		High water levels of January 9, 10, 11 and 18, 19 seem to be associated
		with avalanche impacts on Lake Albion. These have not been used in
		estimating daily discharges.
		Valves at Lake Albion closed throughout 2000.
		2001:
		Omnidata Easy Logger 900 records (RL) are in cm and should be corrected by:
		Stage (cm) = 1.01*RL - 5.013 (5/10/00 to 8/01/02; r2 = 0.996; n = 84).
		Valves at Lake Albion were opened about 12:00 MST, 7 December 2001.
		Water levels after that time are uncertain because of high flows and ice
		and snow in the channel.
		2002:
		Omnidata Easy Logger 900 records (RL) are in cm and should be corrected by:
		Stage (cm) = 1.07*RL - 7.68 (10/5/00 to 26/11/02; r2 = 0.988; n = 159).
		Valves at Lake Albion were open from 7 December 2001 and not closed during 2002.
		Stilling well and pressure transducer cleaned and reset 10/10/02.
		Recorded water levels 8-12 November seem to be extremely high (ice and
		snow in channel?). They have not been used in estimating interval flows.
		2003:
		Omnidata Easy Logger 900 records (RL) are in cm and should be corrected	by:
		Stage (cm) = 1.042*RL - 7.48 (10/10/02 to 9/10/03; r2 = 0.997; n = 55).
		Valves at Lake Albion were open from 7 December 2001and closed 14 April
		2003, 09:00 MST.
		2004:
		Omnidata Easy Logger 900 records (RL) are in cm and should be corrected by:
		Stage (cm) = 0.981*RL - 7.681 (18/09/03 to 25/11/04; r2 = 0.988; n = 86).
		Valves at Lake Albion were closed through November 2004.
		Campbell CR10x records of water level are available for this site. These
		may be converted to stage by:
		Stage (cm) = 20.392*CRx - 3.5 (2/10/03 to 25/11/04; r2 = 0.9822; n = 81).
		2005:
		Campbell CR10x logger records (RL) are in cm. Until 12/06/2005, they
		should be converted to stage by:
		Stage (cm) = 20.392*CRx - 3.5 (2/10/03 to 25/11/04; r2 = 0.9822; n = 81).
		After 15/06/2005, this correction should be changed to:
		Stage (cm) = 20.257*CRx - 7.107 (16/06/05 to 29/09/05; r2 = 0.995; n = 45).
		Apparent high flows in the early hours of 12 May are due to ponding if
		water in snow cover over the channel as an upstream pond drained. The
		overestimate of flow volumes is estimated at 2620 m3 and daily flows
		have been corrected by this amount.
		Record missing from 14:30 MST, 12/06/2005 to 11:00 MST, 15/06/2005
		following mast collapse. After 15/06/05, water level calibration changes
		(see above).
		Water level record is missing from 08:00 MST, 21/11/2005 to 12:00,
		12/12/2005 after leads became disconnected from logger. A rough
		reconnect was made for the period 11:00 MST, 24/11/2005 to 12:00 MST,
		3/12/2005. For this period, stage has been estimated by:
		S = 20.257*CRx + 18.79.
		The resulting record should be treated with care since the calibration
		is based on only one point.For the entire period of missing record,
		daily flows seem to have been about 6400 m3/day (75 l/s).
		The valves at Lake Albion were closed throughout 2005.
		2006:
		Campbell CR10x logger records (RL) are in cm. They should be converted
		to stage by:
		Stage (cm) = 20.187*CRx - 9.5311 (22/09/05 to 16/11/06; r2 = 0.992; n = 74).
		Water level record is missing from 08:00 MST, 21/11/2005 to 12:00,
		12/12/2005 after leads became disconnected from logger. A rough
		reconnect was made for the period 11:00 MST, 24/11/2005 to 12:00 MST,
		3/12/2005. For this period, stage has been estimated by:
		S = 20.257*CRx + 18.79.
		The resulting record should be treated with care since the calibration
		is based on only one point.For the entire period of missing record,
		daily flows seem to have been about 6400 m3/day (75 l/s).
		The valve at Green Lake 3 was opened late-afternoon August 3, then wider
		on afternoon August 4 during repair work.
		The valves at Lake Albion were closed until 12:00 MST, August 23 and
		opened 	wider on August 25 to yield a flow of about 30 l/s.
		2007:
		Field measurements of water level (WL) are taken by reference to the
		upper lip of the stilling well adjacent to the supporting post. Stage
		(S) is then defined as  S = 115 - WL cm. The lip of the stilling well is
		presently 23.1 cm below the top of the supporting post which is the
		reference level for this site.
		Campbell CR10x logger records (RL) are in cm. They should be converted to stage by:
		Stage (cm) = 18.299*RL - 7.4314	(21/06/07 to 4/10/07; r2 = 0.990; n = 58).
		Because of a fastening broken by snow creep, the stilling well was
		unstable when dug out on 29 May 2007. It was stabilized on 31 May and
		the stage conversion (above) derives from records since then.
		2008:
		Field measurements of water level (WL) are taken by reference to the
		upper lip of the stilling well adjacent to the supporting post. Stage
		(S) is then defined as  S = 115 - WL (cm). The lip of the stilling well
		is presently 23.1 cm below the top of the supporting post which is the
		reference level for this site.
		Campbell CR10x logger records (RL) should be converted to stage as follows:
		For the record to February 1, 2008:
		Stage (cm) = 20.796*RL - 10.363	(r2 = 0.990; n = 58).
		For the record from April 4 2008:
		Stage (cm) = 18.234*RL - 7.4314	(r2 = 0.974; n = 70).
		On April 4 2008, the instrument mast was found to be unstable because of
		a broken supporting cable. This had stressed leads to the stilling well
		and so the record is missing for the following intervals:
		February 1 06:00 to April 4 14:00,
		April 11 22:00 to April 25 01:00,
		April 26 17:00 to April 29 16:00,
		May 10 08:00 to May 23 07:00.
		The records for other sensors than the flow sensor are available for
		many of these intervals but may be affected by the instability of the mast.
		2009:
		Field measurements of water level (WL) are taken by reference to the
		upper lip of the stilling well adjacent to the supporting post. Stage
		(S) is then defined as  S = 115 - WL (cm). The lip of the stilling well
		is presently 23.2 cm below the top of the supporting post which is the
		reference level for this site.
		Campbell CR10x logger records (RL) need to be converted to water level
		(stage). In 2009, they have been converted to stage (S) by:
		S(cm) = 20.006*RL - 11.651.
		This calibration is based on 70 field measurements taken between
		September 30 2008 and October 8 2009 (the 2009 water year).
		2010:
		Field measurements of water level (WL) are taken by reference to the 
		upper lip of the stilling well adjacent to the supporting post. Stage 
		(S) is then defined as  S = 115 - WL (cm). Until 30 May 2010, the lip 
		of the stilling well was 23.2 cm below the top of the supporting post 
		which is the reference level for this site. Because of a shift in the 
		stilling well during snowmelt, this changed to 22.9 cm on about 30 May 
		2010.
		Logger records (RL) need to be converted to water level (stage). 
		In 2010, they have been converted to stage (S) as follows:
		Before 0:00 hr, 30 May 2010:
		S(cm) = 20.00*RL - 11.62	r2 = 0.992	N = 70
		After 0:00 hr, 30 May 2010:
		S(cm) = 20.79*RL - 14.83	r2 = 0.993	N = 53
		Flow data estimated from interpolation are not based on stage records.
		2011:
		Field measurements of water level (WL) are taken by reference to the upper lip 
		of the stilling well adjacent to the supporting post. Stage (S) is then defined
		as S = 115.3 - WL (cm). The lip of the stilling well was 22.9 cm below the top
		of the supporting post, which is the reference level for this site.
		All original files are unedited ASCII format, as retrieved from Campbell CR10x
		logger.
		Logger records (RL) need to be converted to water level (stage). In 2011,
		they have been converted to stage (S) as follows.
		S(cm) = 20.259*RL - 14.332	r2 = 0.9893	N = 105
		This calibration is based on field measurement between 15 June 2010 and 15 
		September 2011.
		The logger record from 25 Oct 18:00 to 29 Oct 19:00 is probably affected by ice
		and snow in channel. For that period, flows have been interpolated.
		The logger record from 16 December 2010 to 2 June 2011 is missing. For that period,
		flows have been estimated by recession to February 28 2011 and then by linear
		interpolation between occasional field observations.
		The logger record ends on 15 September 2011 when the stilling well was replaced
		(see the record for WY 2012 for the rest of the month).
		2012:
		Field measurements of water level (WL) are taken by reference to the upper
		lip of the stilling well adjacent to the supporting post. Stage (S) is then
		defined as  S = 115 - WL (cm).
		All original files are unedited ASCII format, as retrieved from Global Water
		logger #092395374. This logger was installed 8 May 2012 and removed 4 October 2012.
		The flow record has been smoothed by a 7-term running mean (i.e. over a 0.5 hr interval).
		The smoothed logger records (RL) have been converted to water level (stage) by
		S(cm) = 1.0805*RL - 8.0095	r2 = 0.937	N = 86
	</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
</methods>
<dataTable id="albdisch.nc.data.csv">
	<entityName>albdisch.nc.data.csv</entityName>
		<entityDescription>Streamflow for Albion camp, 1981 - ongoing.</entityDescription>
<physical>
	<objectName>albdisch.nc.data.csv</objectName>
<dataFormat>
<textFormat>
<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
	<recordDelimiter>\r</recordDelimiter>
<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
<simpleDelimited>
<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
</simpleDelimited>
</textFormat>
</dataFormat>
	<distribution>
<online>
			<url function="download">http://niwot.colorado.edu/data_csvs/albdisch.nc.data.csv</url>
		</online>
</distribution>
</physical>
<attributeList>
	<attribute>
	<attributeName>date</attributeName>
	<attributeLabel>date</attributeLabel>
	<attributeDefinition>date</attributeDefinition>
	<measurementScale>
		<dateTime>
<formatString>YYYY-MM-DD</formatString>
</dateTime>
	</measurementScale>
	<missingValueCode>
		<code>none</code>
		<codeExplanation>not given</codeExplanation>
	</missingValueCode>
	</attribute>
	<attribute>
		<attributeName>daily discharge volume</attributeName>
		<attributeLabel>daily discharge volume</attributeLabel>
		<attributeDefinition>daily discharge volume</attributeDefinition>
		<measurementScale>
			<ratio>
				<unit>
					<standardUnit>cubicMeter</standardUnit>
</unit>
				<numericDomain>
<numberType>real</numberType>
</numericDomain>
			</ratio>
		</measurementScale>
		<missingValueCode>
			<code>none</code>
			<codeExplanation>not given</codeExplanation>
		</missingValueCode>
	</attribute>
	<attribute>
		<attributeName>notes</attributeName>
		<attributeLabel>notes</attributeLabel>
		<attributeDefinition>notes</attributeDefinition>
		<measurementScale>
			<nominal>
				<nonNumericDomain>
					<textDomain>
						<definition>notes</definition>
					</textDomain>
				</nonNumericDomain>
			</nominal>
		</measurementScale>
		<missingValueCode>
			<code>NaN</code>
			<codeExplanation>missing</codeExplanation>
		</missingValueCode>
	</attribute>
</attributeList>
</dataTable>
</dataset>
</ns0:eml>