<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-bnz.126.20" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0&#10;				http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
<allow>
<principal>uid=BNZ,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
<principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset>
<shortName>knb-lter-bnz.126.20</shortName>
<title>Height and diameter measurement of spruce in response to harvest: 1993 - 2002</title>
<creator>
<individualName>
<givenName>Tricia</givenName>
<givenName>L.</givenName>
<surName>Wurtz</surName>
</individualName>

<address>
<deliveryPoint>Boreal Ecology Cooperative Research Unit University of Alaska Fairbanks  School of Agriculture and Land Resources Management P.O. Box 756780</deliveryPoint>
<city>Fairbanks</city>
<administrativeArea>AK </administrativeArea>
<postalCode>99775-6780</postalCode>
<country>United States</country>
</address>


<electronicMailAddress>twurtz@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress>

</creator>
<creator>
<organizationName>Bonanza Creek LTER</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Boreal Ecology Cooperative Research Unit </deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of Alaska Fairbanks</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 756780 </deliveryPoint>
<city>Fairbanks</city>
<administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>99775</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">907-474-6364</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">907-474-6251</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>uaf-bnz-im-team@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
<onlineUrl>http://www.lter.uaf.edu</onlineUrl>
</creator>
<metadataProvider>
<organizationName>Bonanza Creek LTER</organizationName>
<positionName>Data Manager</positionName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Boreal Ecology Cooperative Research Unit </deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of Alaska Fairbanks</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 756780 </deliveryPoint>
<city>Fairbanks</city>
<administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>99775</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">907-474-6364</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">907-474-6251</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>uaf-bnz-im-team@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
<onlineUrl>http://www.lter.uaf.edu</onlineUrl>
</metadataProvider>

<pubDate>2003-09-02</pubDate>
<abstract>
<para>To document possible soil nitrogen mosaics before timber harvesting on three Alaskan boreal forest sites, maps of the distribution of understory green and Sitka alder stems were made.  Understory alders were regularly distributed throughout the northernmost site (Standard Creek), and very irregularly distributed at the southernmost site (Cooper Landing).  There were no consistent relations between alder stem location and total soil nitrogen.   In undisturbed forest, soils collected beneath alders tended to have more nitrogen than soils without alder, but after the sites were harvested, soil chemistry differed.  To examine the interactions of alder (Alnus crispa (Ait.) Pursh and A. sitchensis (Reg.) Rydb.) and white spruce (Picea glauca (Moench) Voss) on secondary successional sites, mixed plantations of white spruce and alder were established after each site was harvested.  Despite good survival, the planted alder grew poorly.  There were no differences between nursery-grown alder seedlings and alder wildlings in either growth or survival.  Though fifth-year survival and growth of white spruce were excellent on all sites, they were not related to either the pre-harvest distribution of naturally occurring alder or to alders planted in the mixed plantations.  Locational information and site maps are provided to encourage future evaluation of these plantations.</para>
</abstract>
<keywordSet>
<keyword>alder</keyword>
<keyword>spruce</keyword>
<keyword>recent harvest</keyword>
<keyword>harvests</keyword>
<keywordThesaurus>Stand Structure</keywordThesaurus>
</keywordSet>
<intellectualRights>
<section>
<title>Access to Data</title>
<para>While metadata will be freely available to those requesting it, the data manager will assure that any restrictions on access to data sets in the database will be enforced. Data will not be released without proper permission first being obtained from the investigator who generated the data. </para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Use of data</title>
<para> Researchers should receive adequate acknowledgment for the use of their data by others and should be provided with copies of publications using their data. Users of data from the data base must be aware that data is not to be sold or redistributed.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Citing Bonanza Creek LTER Datasets</title>
<para>It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. </para>
</section>
</intellectualRights>
<distribution id="distributionReference">
<online>
<url function="information">http://www.lter.uaf.edu/data_detail.cfm?datafile_pkey=126</url>
</online>
</distribution>
<coverage>

<temporalCoverage>
<rangeOfDates>
<beginDate>
<calendarDate>1993-06-01</calendarDate>
</beginDate>
<endDate>
<calendarDate>2002-06-01</calendarDate>
</endDate>
</rangeOfDates>
</temporalCoverage>
</coverage>
<maintenance>
<description>
<section>
<title>Status</title>
<para>Completed</para>
</section>
</description>
</maintenance>
<contact>
<organizationName>Bonanza Creek LTER</organizationName>
<positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Boreal Ecology Cooperative Research Unit </deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of Alaska Fairbanks</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 756780 </deliveryPoint>
<city>Fairbanks</city>
<administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>99775</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">907-474-6364</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">907-474-6251</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>uaf-bnz-im-team@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
<onlineUrl>http://www.lter.uaf.edu</onlineUrl>
</contact>
<publisher>
<organizationName>Bonanza Creek LTER</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Boreal Ecology Cooperative Research Unit </deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of Alaska Fairbanks</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 756780 </deliveryPoint>
<city>Fairbanks</city>
<administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>99775</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">907-474-6364</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">907-474-6251</phone>
</publisher>
<pubPlace>Bonanza Creek LTER</pubPlace>
<methods>
<methodStep>
<description>
<section>
<title>Methods</title>
<para>This study is being conducted at three sites along a north-south transect through central Alaska. The northernmost site, Standard Creek, is 15 mi (25 km) southwest of Fairbanks, with mean annual temperature of 26 degF (-3.2 degC) and mean annual precipitation of 10 in (26.5 cm) (fig. 1).  It is part of the "Eastern interior Alaska zone" of the Northern Forest Formation (Zasada and Packee 1995).  The site is on a gentle southeast-facing slope.  Before harvesting, it supported a mature, productive "closed white spruce forest" (Viereck et al. 1992) with paper birch and occasional balsam poplar.  Green alder was a major component of the understory, reaching a height of 16 ft (5 m). Other common understory plants were low-bush cranberry (Vaccinium vitis-idaea L.), fireweed (Epilobium angustifolium L.), Calamagrostis, highbush cranberry (Viburnum edule (Michx.) Raf.), and rose (Rosa acicularis Lindl.).  Soils at Standard Creek are well drained, moderately deep silty loams, with a parent material of micaceous loess underlain by Birch Creek schist (Rieger et al. 1963)  The mature late-successional white spruce stand at Standard Creek was likely to persist until the next major disturbance event: wildfire, insect infestation, or timber harvesting.  Sites such as Standard Creek are currently the main focus of timber harvesting operations in the Fairbanks area.  Pre-harvest Stem Mapping  At each site, a grid of thirty 56- by 56-ft (17- by 17-m) plots was established in units already laid out for timber sales.  (This plot size was chosen to accommodate a postharvest plantation of seven rows of seven trees at 8-ft (2.4-m) spacing.)   At Standard Creek and Trapper Creek, grids were continuous; at Cooper Landing, the grid was broken into three sections to avoid patches of hemlock leave trees and one large, dense alder thicket containing no merchantable trees.  The location of each live alder stem occurring in the 30-plot grid was recorded to the nearest foot, and its diameter at the forest floor recorded.  Soil Sampling  Two series of soil samples were collected.   In the first set, 50 cores were collected from each site: 5 from beneath each of five different clumps of alder and 5 from each of five locations supporting typical understory vegetation other than alder.  Because few alders occurred within the grid of study plots at Cooper Landing, alder soils were collected outside the grid at that site.   Cores extended from just below the litter layer down to and including the top 2 in (5 cm) of mineral soil; organic and mineral layers were sieved together before analysis.  After the alder stem maps were produced, and the sites harvested, a second set of samples was collected from 8- by 8-ft cells of known pre-harvest alder stem density.  Three cores were collected at randomly chosen locations in each cell; in this series, the organic soil layers were separated from and analyzed separately from the mineral soil layers.  Total nitrogen content, pH, soil organic matter content, phosphorus and potassium concentrations were determined.  A more detailed description of soil sample collection and analysis is given in Wurtz (1995b).  Harvesting Methods  The Standard Creek site was harvested by feller-buncher between November 1992 and February 1993.  The harvesting operation left a heavy load of slash that would have made planting at precise spacing difficult.  In May 1993, the slash was pushed into piles near the landings, by using a dozer with straight-edged blade.  At the Trapper Creek site, trees were widely spaced and interspersed with thickets of alder.  The hand-felling and rubber-tired skidding operation conducted there in March 1993 did not disturb the thickets enough to allow for planting.  Consequently, the site was scarified with a dozer and straight-edged blade in May 1993.  The operator was instructed to scrape alder stems off at the base, and to tear up the vegetative mat to a depth of about 8 in (20 cm).  Trees at the Cooper Landing site were felled in September 1992 with a tracked feller-buncher, and skidded to landings with a rubber-tired grapple skidder.  No site preparation was done at Cooper Landing.  Seed Collection-Seedling Production Methods  Alder seed was collected near each of the three sites in September 1991.   As alder cones ripen, they turn from green to brown, and the cones scales gradually separate, allowing seeds to disperse.  The rate at which this happens depends on the weather: warm sunny days lead to rapid ripening and dispersal, whereas cold cloudy days lengthen ripening time.  To maximize seed maturity, I delayed collecting cones as long as possible, collecting just before seed had begun to disperse.  After collection, cones were spread out and air-dried at room temperature until fully brown and open.  Shaking cones in paper bags separated the seeds from the cones.  Seeds were stored frozen in plastic bags before sowing.  Spruce seed came from collections of the State of Alaska and, for the Cooper Landing study site, the Chugach National Forest.  Recommended spruce cone collection and handling methods are described in Alden (1985) and Eremko et al. (1989). Containerized seedlings of both spruce and alder were produced on contract by Pelton Reforestation, Maple Ridge, B.C., in styroblock 415D containers.1  These containers are 1.5 in (4 cm) in diameter at the top, 6 in (15 cm) deep, have a volume of about 10 in3 (170 cm3).  There are 77 such cells per block.  Because of restrictions on shipping soil from Alaska to Canada, the alder growing medium was inoculated with soil collected from a stand of green alder growing near the nursery.  Seeds were sown in January 1992 in the greenhouse. Spruce seedlings were lifted in November of that year and kept frozen until shipping to Alaska in May 1993.  Alder seedlings were maintained in containers from January 1992 until May 1993, when they were lifted shortly before shipping.   At the time of lifting, they were 8 to 12 in (20 to 30 cm) tall, were well nodulated, and had been leafed-out for about 2 mo.  This was Pelton's first attempt at growing containerized alder, and fewer than the required number of alder were successfully produced.  I therefore used alder wildlings to fill in the remaining alder locations.  Wildlings were collected in April 1994 (before bud burst), along roadsides and in gravel pits near all three study sites.  Such disturbed  locations sometimes have large populations of  2- or 3-yr-old alder seedlings, often  unbranched, and often growing with little root entanglement.  I grasped the alders by the stem just above the soil surface and gently pulled them up, then shook the sand or soil from their roots.  The wildlings were well nodulated.  They were bundled in groups of 10 and their roots wrapped in wet newspaper followed by plastic wrap.  Wildlings were refrigerated in the dark until outplanting in June 1994.   At the time of collection, they ranged in height from 18 to 30 in (45 to 75 cm).</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>

</methods>
<dataTable>
<entityName>163_1555_ASTF_DATA_1993-2002.txt</entityName>
<entityDescription> SITE, SARAT, X, Y, NLOC, ELOC, REP, SDLG, HT93CM, I93MM, HT94CM, DI94MM,HT95CM, DI95MM, HT97CM,DI97MM, HY02CM, DI02MM</entityDescription>
<physical>
<objectName>163_1555_ASTF_DATA_1993-2002.txt</objectName>
<dataFormat>
<textFormat>
<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
<recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
<physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter>
<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
<simpleDelimited>
<fieldDelimiter>\t</fieldDelimiter>
</simpleDelimited>
</textFormat>
</dataFormat>
<distribution>
<online>
<url function="download">http://www.lter.uaf.edu/ascii/files/163_1555_ASTF_DATA_1993-2002.txt</url>
</online>
</distribution>
</physical>
<attributeList>
<attribute>
<attributeName>SITE</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>SITE</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Site ID</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>integer</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<nominal>
<nonNumericDomain>
<textDomain>
<definition>Site ID</definition>
</textDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>

</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>SARAT</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>SARAT</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Spruce/Alder Ratio</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>integer</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<ratio>
<unit>
<standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
</unit>
<numericDomain>
<numberType>real</numberType>

</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>

</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>X</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>X</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>With in Plot IDs</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>string</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<nominal>
<nonNumericDomain>
<textDomain>
<definition>With in Plot IDs</definition>
</textDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>

</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>Y</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>Y</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Spruce/Alder Ratio</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>string</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<nominal>
<nonNumericDomain>
<textDomain>
<definition>Spruce/Alder Ratio</definition>
</textDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>

</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>NLOC</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>NLOC</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Location for corner area</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>string</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<nominal>
<nonNumericDomain>
<textDomain>
<definition>Location for corner area</definition>
</textDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>

</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>ELOC</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>ELOC</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Location for corner area</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>string</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<nominal>
<nonNumericDomain>
<textDomain>
<definition>Location for corner area</definition>
</textDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>

</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>REP</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>REP</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Replication </attributeDefinition>
<storageType>string</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<nominal>
<nonNumericDomain>
<textDomain>
<definition>Replication </definition>
</textDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>

</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>SDLG</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>SDLG</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Seedling ID </attributeDefinition>
<storageType>string</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<nominal>
<nonNumericDomain>
<textDomain>
<definition>Seedling ID </definition>
</textDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>

</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>HT93CM</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>HT93CM</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Height of seedlings from 1993</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<ratio>
<unit>
<standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
</unit>
<numericDomain>
<numberType>real</numberType>

</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>.</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>DI93MM</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>DI93MM</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Diameter of seedling from 1993</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<ratio>
<unit>
<standardUnit>millimeter</standardUnit>
</unit>
<numericDomain>
<numberType>real</numberType>

</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>.</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>HT94CM</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>HT94CM</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Height of seedlings from 1994</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<ratio>
<unit>
<standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
</unit>
<numericDomain>
<numberType>real</numberType>

</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>.</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>DI94MM</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>DI94MM</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Diameter of seedling from 1994</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<ratio>
<unit>
<standardUnit>millimeter</standardUnit>
</unit>
<numericDomain>
<numberType>real</numberType>

</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>.</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>HT95CM</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>HT95CM</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Height of seedlings from 1995</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<ratio>
<unit>
<standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
</unit>
<numericDomain>
<numberType>real</numberType>

</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>.</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>DI95MM</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>DI95MM</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Diameter of seedling from 1995</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<ratio>
<unit>
<standardUnit>millimeter</standardUnit>
</unit>
<numericDomain>
<numberType>real</numberType>

</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>.</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>HT97CM</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>HT97CM</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Height of seedlings from 1997</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<ratio>
<unit>
<standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
</unit>
<numericDomain>
<numberType>real</numberType>

</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>.</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>DI97MM</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>DI97MM</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Diameter of seedling from 1997</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<ratio>
<unit>
<standardUnit>millimeter</standardUnit>
</unit>
<numericDomain>
<numberType>real</numberType>

</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>.</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>HT02CM</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>HT02CM</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Height of seedlings from 2002</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<ratio>
<unit>
<standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
</unit>
<numericDomain>
<numberType>real</numberType>

</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>.</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>DI02MM</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>DI02MM</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Diameter of seedling from 2002</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<ratio>
<unit>
<standardUnit>millimeter</standardUnit>
</unit>
<numericDomain>
<numberType>real</numberType>

</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>.</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
</attributeList>
</dataTable>
</dataset>
</ns0:eml>