<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-luq.94.3" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 C:/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><shortName>LUQMetadata94</shortName><title>Litterfall of the tabonuco forest before Hurricane Hugo</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Xiaoming</givenName><surName>Zou</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of Puerto Rico</organizationName><positionName>Principal Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute for Tropical Ecosystem Studies (ITES)</deliveryPoint><city>R&#237;o Piedras</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931-1910</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(510)643-3074(5335)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">voice</phone><electronicMailAddress>xzou@ites.upr.edu</electronicMailAddress></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Xiaoming</givenName><surName>Zou</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of Puerto Rico</organizationName><positionName>Principal Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute for Tropical Ecosystem Studies (ITES)</deliveryPoint><city>R&#237;o Piedras</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931-1910</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(510)643-3074(5335)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">voice</phone><electronicMailAddress>xzou@ites.upr.edu</electronicMailAddress></metadataProvider><language>english</language><abstract><para><literalLayout>We examined forest structure, tree species composition, litterfall rate, and leaf litter decomposition in a mid-successional forest (MSF) and an adjacent mature tabonuco forest (MTF) in the Luquillo Experimental Forest of Puerto Rico. Whereas the MTF site received limited human disturbance, the MSF site had been cleared for timber production by the beginning of this century and was abandoned after hurricanes struck the Luquillo Mountains in the 1920s and 1930s. We found that the MSF was dominated by successional tree species 50 yrs after secondary succession, and did not differ in tree basal area and litterfall rate from the MTF. Leaf decomposition rate in the MSF was higher than in the MTF, but this difference was small. Our results show that deforestation has long-term (&gt;50 years) influence on tree species composition and that leaf decomposition processes in secondary forest is relatively faster than recovery of tree species composition.</literalLayout></para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>secondary forest</keyword><keyword>tabonuco forest</keyword><keyword>forest recovery</keyword><keyword>leaf decomposition</keyword><keywordThesaurus>Assigned by Principal Investigator</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>primary productivity</keyword><keyword>disturbance patterns</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LTER Core</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>second forest</keyword><keyword>peer reviewed journal</keyword><keyword>tabonuco</keyword><keyword>el verde</keyword><keyword>decomposition</keyword><keyword>litter fall</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LEF LTER Data Sets</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>Nutrients and Carbon Dynamics</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LEF LTER Data Categories</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><title>ADEQUATE ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><para><literalLayout>The scientists, the LEF-LTER Program, and the USDA International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITF) must receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data by other scientists, and the LEF LTER program must receive two copies of any publication using that data. One copy will be placed at the IITF library and one copy will stay with the LEF LTER Data Manager. A suggested format for this acknowledgement will be distributed along with the requested data.</literalLayout></para><section><title>Acknowledgements for NSF Support.</title><para><literalLayout>The following paragraph should be included in the acknowledgements of all publications funded in any way by current and future LTER grants:</literalLayout><literalLayout>This research was performed under grant #DEB-0218039 from the National Science Foundation to the Institute of Tropical Ecosystem Studies (IEET), University of Puerto Rico, and the International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITFR) as part of the Long-Term Ecological Research Program in the Luquillo Experimental Forest. Additional support was provided by the Forest Service (U.S. Department of Agriculture) and the University of Puerto Rico.</literalLayout></para></section></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb94/metadata/lterdb94.htm#DATA</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage id="geoReference" scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF) covers 11,231 hectares and reaches 1079 m above sea level. It has a warm and wet climate and includes a variety of tropical habitats and forest types and streams, and a high diversity of plants and animals. A key feature of these ecosystems is disturbance. Hurricanes, landslides, and human disturbance have shaped the forest, and research by LUQ has stimulated a new appreciation of the significance of large-scale disturbances in tropical forested ecosystems and the key role of plants and animals in shaping the response to these events. Hurricanes occurring one and 10 years after LUQ began in 1988 provided landscape-scale natural experiments which are still followed closely.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-65.92</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-65.7</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>18.35</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>18.23</southBoundingCoordinate><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>20</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>1060</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Xiaoming</givenName><surName>Zou</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of Puerto Rico</organizationName><positionName>Principal Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute for Tropical Ecosystem Studies (ITES)</deliveryPoint><city>R&#237;o Piedras</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931-1910</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(510)643-3074(5335)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">voice</phone><electronicMailAddress>xzou@ites.upr.edu</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>Luquillo Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>University of Puerto Rico, Rio Piedras</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>P. O. Box 21910</deliveryPoint><city>San Juan</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931-1910</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787) 764 - 0000 (ext. 4940)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787) 772 -1481</phone><electronicMailAddress>nbrokaw@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://luq.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Forest structure and species composition 

A 1 ha plot (100 x 100 m) was randomly established in each of the MSF and MTF in 1980. Within each plot, twenty circular subplots (113 m2) were randomly located. All trees greater that or equal to 0.1 m in DBH (diameter at breath height) in each subplot were identified and the DBHs were recorded. 

Litterfall and ground litter biomass 

Twenty 1 m2 baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen were randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground. Litterfall was collected biweekly for 1 yr between November 1980 and October 1981. All litter samples were separated into leaves, flowers, fruit, wood, and miscellaneous materials (mostly bark), oven-dried at 70oC for 72 hrs, and weighed. Ground litter was collected from 0.25 m2 subplots in both the dry season (March, 40 subplots) and the wet season (September, 20 subplots) randomly located in each of the 1 ha plots. Each sample was separated into wood and miscellaneous categories, oven-dried at 70oC for 72 hrs, and weighed. 

Leaf decomposition 

A total of 140 litterbags were constructed among which 70 litterbags were filled with fresh leaves collected from the MSF and 70 from the MTF (Blair et al., 1990). These fresh leaves represented the tree species composition in natural litterfall in April at both sites. The species composition of litterfall was determined using leaffall in the 1-m2 randomly placed baskets in each plot. Fresh leaves were collected for each forest within 24 hours of senescence in May and sorted by species. Leaves of the 13 most common species from each forest, representing 82-91% of the total fresh leaf mass, were placed in 1-mm2 mesh fiberglass screen bags (0.2 by 0.25 m) in proportion to their biomass in litterfall (Table 1). Leaves of the remaining 25 species were put in a miscellaneous category and randomly selected to obtain a total of 10-g fresh leaf material (4.6 g mean oven-dry mass) in each bag. 

For each leaf type, 35 litterbags were placed equally in 5 randomly selected subsites in the 1 ha plots where leaves were collected. In order to separate the effects of leaf chemistry on leaf decomposition from those of biotic and abiotic environmental conditions between the two forests, the other 35 litterbags for both leaf types were together placed in a 10 x 10 m plot in the MTF at five randomly selected locations. The 1 ha plots covered an area with heterogeneous geographical locations including ridges and valleys, whereas the 0.01 ha plot was located on a ridge top and upper slope position. One randomly selected litterbag was collected after 0, 7, 14, 28, 60, 120, and 300 days in the field at each site from each plot. There were 2 (leaf types) x 2 (incubation sites) x 5 (replicates) x 7 (collections) = 140 litterbags. 

Small roots which had entered the litter bags were carefully removed in the laboratory. The remaining litter in each bag was oven dried at 70 &#176;C for 72 hours and weighed to determine dry mass loss. Dry litter was then ground with a Wiley mill through a 0.85 mm (20 mesh) stainless steel sieve. One gram of the ground leaf material from each litterbag was digested with H2O2 and concentrated HNO3 (Luh Huang and Schulte, 1985) before analyzing for P, K, Ca, and Mg content with an atomic absorption and emission spectrophotometer. Total C and N in leaf material were analyzed by direct combustion in a C-H-N analyzer (Carlo-Erba Model 1106). 

Data analyses 

Basal area, tree density, and leaffall for each species were calculated for each forest. Total litterfall rate and ground litter biomass of all species were also calculated for each forest. The analysis of variance (ANOVA) was employed to test the differences in basal area, tree density, leaffall rate, and ground litter biomass between the forests or the seasons (SAS, 1987). Leaf decay rates were calculated using a single exponential model Mt = M0e-kt, where Mt was the remaining mass of leaf materials in a litter bag at time t and M0 was itsinitial mass. Slope k was obtained using linear regression after taking the natural logarithms of the equation. Multivariate tests were used to examine differences in k values between the two forests and between sites (SAS, 1987). The significance level was set at a = 0.05.Percentage of initial weight remaining was calculated using oven-dried weight. Percentage of initial element remaining in litterbags was obtained by multiplying the ratio of total element at time t (t = 0, 7, 14, 28, 60, 120, and 300 days) to that at time 0 by 100. Total element content in a litterbag was calculated as the product of element concentration and the oven- dry weight. Differences in elemental concentrations between forests and among decomposing dates were tested with ANOVA. Where significant differences were obtained by ANOVA, Bonferroni t-test (SAS Inc., 1987) was used to compare these differences in elemental concentrations. The significance levels for ANOVA and Bonferroni t-test were both set at &#224; = 0.05. Plots of residuals vs. predicted values indicated that no variables significantly violated the homogeneity assumption, with the exception of K concentrations. A non-parametric analysis was employed by ranking K concentrations prior to performing ANOVA and Bonferroni t test.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep></methods><project scope="document"><title>Litterfall and Decomposition</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Xiaoming</givenName><surName>Zou</surName></individualName><role>Co-Principal Investigator</role></personnel><abstract><para><literalLayout>Understanding the long-term impact of deforestation on ecosystem structure and function of tropical forests may aid in designing future conservation programs to preserve biodiversity and sustain ecosystem productivity. We examine forest structure, tree species composition, litterfall (fine and coarse) due to Hurricane Hugo and subsequent fine annual litterfall inputs, litterfall rate, and leaf litter decomposition.  Prestoea montana (R. Grah.) Nichols, Dacryodes excelsa (Vahl.), and Cyrilla racemiflora. Hurricane Hugo (August, 1989) provided a unique opportunity to study effects of this type of natural disturbance on decomposition. With some modifications study was repeated in 1990 with some changes in the design which allowed for comparisons of short -term foliar litter biomass and nitrogen dynamics: (1) among the three species, (between the colorado and tabonuco forest types, (3) between riparian and upland sites, and (4) between pre- and post-hurricane environments.  History of litterfall and decomposition studies (MRCE experiment) at the Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF)  1) forest fertilization (complete versus none); 2) transplant experiments using common gardens at high and low elevation, with and without wind protection at high elevation. In addition, phenology of leaves was studied in the dwarf forest to determine the longevity of leaves in the canopy. The occurrence of Hurricane Hugo in September 1989, just as the forest plot fertilization experiments were to begin, neccesitated the addition of a hurricane debris-removal treatment as a second type of control in the lower elevation tabonuco forest. The hurricane also changed the nature of the study into one of looking at changes in forest composition and the recovery of forest productivity in response to fertilization and hurricane debris-removal. Seedling, sapling, herbaceous plant, and fern responses, as well as measurements of light availability and canopy closure were added to the originally planned measurements of tree diameter growth, leaf litter production, and fine root production and turnover. Another hurricane in 1998 (Hurricane Georges) presented an opportunity to look at the effects of removing only the woody debris (in new plots) versus removing all hurricane debris.  Funding for continued studies of the MRCE plots ended in 1998, but they were of such great value as a long-term experiment that they were incorporated into the LTER program.</literalLayout></para></abstract><funding><para><literalLayout>LTER</literalLayout></para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=LUQ,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>litttab1.txt</entityName><entityDescription>Mean Monthly leaffall rate of eight common species before Hugo</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>litttab1.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb94/data/litttab1.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReferencelitttab1.txt" scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1980-11-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>1981-10-01</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Forest structure and species composition 

A 1 ha plot (100 x 100 m) was randomly established in each of the MSF and MTF in 1980. Within each plot, twenty circular subplots (113 m2) were randomly located. All trees greater that or equal to 0.1 m in DBH (diameter at breath height) in each subplot were identified and the DBHs were recorded. 

Litterfall and ground litter biomass 

Twenty 1 m2 baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen were randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground. Litterfall was collected biweekly for 1 yr between November 1980 and October 1981. All litter samples were separated into leaves, flowers, fruit, wood, and miscellaneous materials (mostly bark), oven-dried at 70oC for 72 hrs, and weighed. Ground litter was collected from 0.25 m2 subplots in both the dry season (March, 40 subplots) and the wet season (September, 20 subplots) randomly located in each of the 1 ha plots. Each sample was separated into wood and miscellaneous categories, oven-dried at 70oC for 72 hrs, and weighed. 

Leaf decomposition 

A total of 140 litterbags were constructed among which 70 litterbags were filled with fresh leaves collected from the MSF and 70 from the MTF (Blair et al., 1990). These fresh leaves represented the tree species composition in natural litterfall in April at both sites. The species composition of litterfall was determined using leaffall in the 1-m2 randomly placed baskets in each plot. Fresh leaves were collected for each forest within 24 hours of senescence in May and sorted by species. Leaves of the 13 most common species from each forest, representing 82-91% of the total fresh leaf mass, were placed in 1-mm2 mesh fiberglass screen bags (0.2 by 0.25 m) in proportion to their biomass in litterfall (Table 1). Leaves of the remaining 25 species were put in a miscellaneous category and randomly selected to obtain a total of 10-g fresh leaf material (4.6 g mean oven-dry mass) in each bag. 

For each leaf type, 35 litterbags were placed equally in 5 randomly selected subsites in the 1 ha plots where leaves were collected. In order to separate the effects of leaf chemistry on leaf decomposition from those of biotic and abiotic environmental conditions between the two forests, the other 35 litterbags for both leaf types were together placed in a 10 x 10 m plot in the MTF at five randomly selected locations. The 1 ha plots covered an area with heterogeneous geographical locations including ridges and valleys, whereas the 0.01 ha plot was located on a ridge top and upper slope position. One randomly selected litterbag was collected after 0, 7, 14, 28, 60, 120, and 300 days in the field at each site from each plot. There were 2 (leaf types) x 2 (incubation sites) x 5 (replicates) x 7 (collections) = 140 litterbags. 

Small roots which had entered the litter bags were carefully removed in the laboratory. The remaining litter in each bag was oven dried at 70 &#176;C for 72 hours and weighed to determine dry mass loss. Dry litter was then ground with a Wiley mill through a 0.85 mm (20 mesh) stainless steel sieve. One gram of the ground leaf material from each litterbag was digested with H2O2 and concentrated HNO3 (Luh Huang and Schulte, 1985) before analyzing for P, K, Ca, and Mg content with an atomic absorption and emission spectrophotometer. Total C and N in leaf material were analyzed by direct combustion in a C-H-N analyzer (Carlo-Erba Model 1106). 

Data analyses 

Basal area, tree density, and leaffall for each species were calculated for each forest. Total litterfall rate and ground litter biomass of all species were also calculated for each forest. The analysis of variance (ANOVA) was employed to test the differences in basal area, tree density, leaffall rate, and ground litter biomass between the forests or the seasons (SAS, 1987). Leaf decay rates were calculated using a single exponential model Mt = M0e-kt, where Mt was the remaining mass of leaf materials in a litter bag at time t and M0 was itsinitial mass. Slope k was obtained using linear regression after taking the natural logarithms of the equation. Multivariate tests were used to examine differences in k values between the two forests and between sites (SAS, 1987). The significance level was set at a = 0.05.Percentage of initial weight remaining was calculated using oven-dried weight. Percentage of initial element remaining in litterbags was obtained by multiplying the ratio of total element at time t (t = 0, 7, 14, 28, 60, 120, and 300 days) to that at time 0 by 100. Total element content in a litterbag was calculated as the product of element concentration and the oven- dry weight. Differences in elemental concentrations between forests and among decomposing dates were tested with ANOVA. Where significant differences were obtained by ANOVA, Bonferroni t-test (SAS Inc., 1987) was used to compare these differences in elemental concentrations. The significance levels for ANOVA and Bonferroni t-test were both set at &#224; = 0.05. Plots of residuals vs. predicted values indicated that no variables significantly violated the homogeneity assumption, with the exception of K concentrations. A non-parametric analysis was employed by ranking K concentrations prior to performing ANOVA and Bonferroni t test.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReferencelitttab1.txt</references></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>biweekly</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Scientific name</attributeName><attributeLabel>Species</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>scientific name of eight common species in a mid-successional forest (MSF) and a maturetabonuco forest (MTF) in Puerto Rico. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>scientific name of eight common species in a mid-successional forest (MSF) and a maturetabonuco forest (MTF) in Puerto Rico. No data are missing in this field.</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>litterfall by species atmid-successional forest</attributeName><attributeLabel>MSF_g_m2_yr</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Annual leaffall rate (standard error) of the eight common species in a mid-successional forest (MSF) in Puerto Rico. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gramsPerMeterSquaredPerYear</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>litterfall by species ata mature tabonuco forest</attributeName><attributeLabel>MTF_g_m2_yr</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Annual leaffall rate (standard error) of the eight common species in a mature tabonuco forest (MTF) in Puerto Rico. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gramsPerMeterSquaredPerYear</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>litttab2.txt</entityName><entityDescription>Monthly separated leaffall rate of eight common species before Hugo</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>litttab2.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb94/data/litttab2.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReferencelitttab2.txt" scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1980-11-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>1981-10-01</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Forest structure and species composition 

A 1 ha plot (100 x 100 m) was randomly established in each of the MSF and MTF in 1980. Within each plot, twenty circular subplots (113 m2) were randomly located. All trees greater that or equal to 0.1 m in DBH (diameter at breath height) in each subplot were identified and the DBHs were recorded. 

Litterfall and ground litter biomass 

Twenty 1 m2 baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen were randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground. Litterfall was collected biweekly for 1 yr between November 1980 and October 1981. All litter samples were separated into leaves, flowers, fruit, wood, and miscellaneous materials (mostly bark), oven-dried at 70oC for 72 hrs, and weighed. Ground litter was collected from 0.25 m2 subplots in both the dry season (March, 40 subplots) and the wet season (September, 20 subplots) randomly located in each of the 1 ha plots. Each sample was separated into wood and miscellaneous categories, oven-dried at 70oC for 72 hrs, and weighed. 

Leaf decomposition 

A total of 140 litterbags were constructed among which 70 litterbags were filled with fresh leaves collected from the MSF and 70 from the MTF (Blair et al., 1990). These fresh leaves represented the tree species composition in natural litterfall in April at both sites. The species composition of litterfall was determined using leaffall in the 1-m2 randomly placed baskets in each plot. Fresh leaves were collected for each forest within 24 hours of senescence in May and sorted by species. Leaves of the 13 most common species from each forest, representing 82-91% of the total fresh leaf mass, were placed in 1-mm2 mesh fiberglass screen bags (0.2 by 0.25 m) in proportion to their biomass in litterfall (Table 1). Leaves of the remaining 25 species were put in a miscellaneous category and randomly selected to obtain a total of 10-g fresh leaf material (4.6 g mean oven-dry mass) in each bag. 

For each leaf type, 35 litterbags were placed equally in 5 randomly selected subsites in the 1 ha plots where leaves were collected. In order to separate the effects of leaf chemistry on leaf decomposition from those of biotic and abiotic environmental conditions between the two forests, the other 35 litterbags for both leaf types were together placed in a 10 x 10 m plot in the MTF at five randomly selected locations. The 1 ha plots covered an area with heterogeneous geographical locations including ridges and valleys, whereas the 0.01 ha plot was located on a ridge top and upper slope position. One randomly selected litterbag was collected after 0, 7, 14, 28, 60, 120, and 300 days in the field at each site from each plot. There were 2 (leaf types) x 2 (incubation sites) x 5 (replicates) x 7 (collections) = 140 litterbags. 

Small roots which had entered the litter bags were carefully removed in the laboratory. The remaining litter in each bag was oven dried at 70 &#176;C for 72 hours and weighed to determine dry mass loss. Dry litter was then ground with a Wiley mill through a 0.85 mm (20 mesh) stainless steel sieve. One gram of the ground leaf material from each litterbag was digested with H2O2 and concentrated HNO3 (Luh Huang and Schulte, 1985) before analyzing for P, K, Ca, and Mg content with an atomic absorption and emission spectrophotometer. Total C and N in leaf material were analyzed by direct combustion in a C-H-N analyzer (Carlo-Erba Model 1106). 

Data analyses 

Basal area, tree density, and leaffall for each species were calculated for each forest. Total litterfall rate and ground litter biomass of all species were also calculated for each forest. The analysis of variance (ANOVA) was employed to test the differences in basal area, tree density, leaffall rate, and ground litter biomass between the forests or the seasons (SAS, 1987). Leaf decay rates were calculated using a single exponential model Mt = M0e-kt, where Mt was the remaining mass of leaf materials in a litter bag at time t and M0 was itsinitial mass. Slope k was obtained using linear regression after taking the natural logarithms of the equation. Multivariate tests were used to examine differences in k values between the two forests and between sites (SAS, 1987). The significance level was set at a = 0.05.Percentage of initial weight remaining was calculated using oven-dried weight. Percentage of initial element remaining in litterbags was obtained by multiplying the ratio of total element at time t (t = 0, 7, 14, 28, 60, 120, and 300 days) to that at time 0 by 100. Total element content in a litterbag was calculated as the product of element concentration and the oven- dry weight. Differences in elemental concentrations between forests and among decomposing dates were tested with ANOVA. Where significant differences were obtained by ANOVA, Bonferroni t-test (SAS Inc., 1987) was used to compare these differences in elemental concentrations. The significance levels for ANOVA and Bonferroni t-test were both set at &#224; = 0.05. Plots of residuals vs. predicted values indicated that no variables significantly violated the homogeneity assumption, with the exception of K concentrations. A non-parametric analysis was employed by ranking K concentrations prior to performing ANOVA and Bonferroni t test.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReferencelitttab2.txt</references></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>biweekly</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Month of collection.</attributeName><attributeLabel>MONTH</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Month of collection. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Month of collection. No data are missing in this field.</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Year of collection</attributeName><attributeLabel>YEAR</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Year of collection. No data are missing in this field. (YYYY)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>YYYY</formatString></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Date of collection</attributeName><attributeLabel>DATE</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Date of collection (mm/dd/yy). No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>mm/dd/yy</formatString></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Weight of leaves of eight common species from a mature tabonuco forest plot 3</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT3MTF_LEAF_G_M2_D</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Weight of leaves from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 3; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Weight of of flowers of eight common species from a mature tabonuco forest plot 3</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT3MTF_FLOWER_G_M2_D</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>weight of flowers from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 3; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Weight of fruits of eight common species from a mature tabonuco forest plot 3</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT3MTF_FRUIT_G_M2_D</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>weight of fruits from twenty 1m2 baskets; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Weight wood of eight common species from a mature tabonuco forest plot 3</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT3MTF_WOOD_G_M2_D</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>weight of wood from twenty 1m2 baskets; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Weight of miscelaneousmaterial of eight common species from a mature tabonuco forest plot 3</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT3MTF_MISC_G_M2_D</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>weight of miscelaneousmaterial from twenty 1m2 baskets; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Weight of leaves of eight common species from a mid-secondary forest plot 4</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT4MSF_LEAF_G_M2_D</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Weight of leaves from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 4; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Weight of flowers of eight common species from a mid-secondary forest plot 4</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT4MSF_FLOWER_G_M2_D</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>weight of flowers from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 4; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>weight of fruits produced per day</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT4MSF_FRUIT_G_M2_D</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Calculated average weight of fruits produced per day from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 4; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Average weight of wood from a mature tabonuco forest plot 4</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT4MSF_wood_avg_g_m2_d</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Calculated average weight of wood produced per day from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 4; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Average weight of miscelaneous material from a mature tabonuco forest plot 4</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT4MSF_misc_avg_g_m2_d</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Calculated average weight of miscelaneousmaterial produced per day from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 4; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>litttab3.txt</entityName><entityDescription>Monthly separated ( by litterfall type) leaffall rate before Hugo</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>litttab3.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb94/data/litttab3.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReferencelitttab3.txt" scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1980-11-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>1981-10-01</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Forest structure and species composition 

A 1 ha plot (100 x 100 m) was randomly established in each of the MSF and MTF in 1980. Within each plot, twenty circular subplots (113 m2) were randomly located. All trees greater that or equal to 0.1 m in DBH (diameter at breath height) in each subplot were identified and the DBHs were recorded. 

Litterfall and ground litter biomass 

Twenty 1 m2 baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen were randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground. Litterfall was collected biweekly for 1 yr between November 1980 and October 1981. All litter samples were separated into leaves, flowers, fruit, wood, and miscellaneous materials (mostly bark), oven-dried at 70oC for 72 hrs, and weighed. Ground litter was collected from 0.25 m2 subplots in both the dry season (March, 40 subplots) and the wet season (September, 20 subplots) randomly located in each of the 1 ha plots. Each sample was separated into wood and miscellaneous categories, oven-dried at 70oC for 72 hrs, and weighed. 

Leaf decomposition 

A total of 140 litterbags were constructed among which 70 litterbags were filled with fresh leaves collected from the MSF and 70 from the MTF (Blair et al., 1990). These fresh leaves represented the tree species composition in natural litterfall in April at both sites. The species composition of litterfall was determined using leaffall in the 1-m2 randomly placed baskets in each plot. Fresh leaves were collected for each forest within 24 hours of senescence in May and sorted by species. Leaves of the 13 most common species from each forest, representing 82-91% of the total fresh leaf mass, were placed in 1-mm2 mesh fiberglass screen bags (0.2 by 0.25 m) in proportion to their biomass in litterfall (Table 1). Leaves of the remaining 25 species were put in a miscellaneous category and randomly selected to obtain a total of 10-g fresh leaf material (4.6 g mean oven-dry mass) in each bag. 

For each leaf type, 35 litterbags were placed equally in 5 randomly selected subsites in the 1 ha plots where leaves were collected. In order to separate the effects of leaf chemistry on leaf decomposition from those of biotic and abiotic environmental conditions between the two forests, the other 35 litterbags for both leaf types were together placed in a 10 x 10 m plot in the MTF at five randomly selected locations. The 1 ha plots covered an area with heterogeneous geographical locations including ridges and valleys, whereas the 0.01 ha plot was located on a ridge top and upper slope position. One randomly selected litterbag was collected after 0, 7, 14, 28, 60, 120, and 300 days in the field at each site from each plot. There were 2 (leaf types) x 2 (incubation sites) x 5 (replicates) x 7 (collections) = 140 litterbags. 

Small roots which had entered the litter bags were carefully removed in the laboratory. The remaining litter in each bag was oven dried at 70 &#176;C for 72 hours and weighed to determine dry mass loss. Dry litter was then ground with a Wiley mill through a 0.85 mm (20 mesh) stainless steel sieve. One gram of the ground leaf material from each litterbag was digested with H2O2 and concentrated HNO3 (Luh Huang and Schulte, 1985) before analyzing for P, K, Ca, and Mg content with an atomic absorption and emission spectrophotometer. Total C and N in leaf material were analyzed by direct combustion in a C-H-N analyzer (Carlo-Erba Model 1106). 

Data analyses 

Basal area, tree density, and leaffall for each species were calculated for each forest. Total litterfall rate and ground litter biomass of all species were also calculated for each forest. The analysis of variance (ANOVA) was employed to test the differences in basal area, tree density, leaffall rate, and ground litter biomass between the forests or the seasons (SAS, 1987). Leaf decay rates were calculated using a single exponential model Mt = M0e-kt, where Mt was the remaining mass of leaf materials in a litter bag at time t and M0 was itsinitial mass. Slope k was obtained using linear regression after taking the natural logarithms of the equation. Multivariate tests were used to examine differences in k values between the two forests and between sites (SAS, 1987). The significance level was set at a = 0.05.Percentage of initial weight remaining was calculated using oven-dried weight. Percentage of initial element remaining in litterbags was obtained by multiplying the ratio of total element at time t (t = 0, 7, 14, 28, 60, 120, and 300 days) to that at time 0 by 100. Total element content in a litterbag was calculated as the product of element concentration and the oven- dry weight. Differences in elemental concentrations between forests and among decomposing dates were tested with ANOVA. Where significant differences were obtained by ANOVA, Bonferroni t-test (SAS Inc., 1987) was used to compare these differences in elemental concentrations. The significance levels for ANOVA and Bonferroni t-test were both set at &#224; = 0.05. Plots of residuals vs. predicted values indicated that no variables significantly violated the homogeneity assumption, with the exception of K concentrations. A non-parametric analysis was employed by ranking K concentrations prior to performing ANOVA and Bonferroni t test.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReferencelitttab3.txt</references></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>biweekly</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Month of collection.</attributeName><attributeLabel>Month</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Month of collection. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Month of collection. No data are missing in this field.</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Year of collection</attributeName><attributeLabel>Year</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Year of collection. No data are missing in this field. (YYYY)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>YYYY</formatString></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Average weight of leaves from a mature tabonuco forest plot 3</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT3MTF_leaf_avg_g_m2_d</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Calculated average weight of leaves produced per day from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 3; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Average weight of flowers from a mature tabonuco forest plot 3</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT3MTF_flower_avg_g_m2_d</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Calculated average weight of flowers produced per day from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 3; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Average weight of fruits from a mature tabonuco forest plot 3</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT3MTF_fruit_avg_g_m2_d</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Calculated average weight of fruits produced per day from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 3; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Average weight of wood from a mature tabonuco forest plot 3</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT3MTF_wood_avg_g_m2_d</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Calculated average weight of wood produced per day from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 3; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Average weight of miscelaneous material from a mature tabonuco forest plot 3</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT3MTF_misc_avg_g_m2_d</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Calculated average weight of miscelaneousmaterial produced per day from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 3; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Average weight of leaves from a mature tabonuco forest plot 4</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT4MSF_leaf_avg_g_m2_d</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Calculated average weight of leaves produced per day from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 4; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Average weight of flowers from a mature tabonuco forest plot 4</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT4MSF_flower_avg_g_m2_d</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Calculated average weight of flowers produced per day from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 4; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Average weight of fruits from a mature tabonuco forest plot 4</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT4MSF_fruit_avg_g_m2_d</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Calculated average weight of fruits produced per day from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 4; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Average weight of wood from a mature tabonuco forest plot 4</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT4MSF_wood_avg_g_m2_d</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Calculated average weight of wood produced per day from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 4; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Average weight of miscelaneous material from a mature tabonuco forest plot 4</attributeName><attributeLabel>PLOT4MSF_misc_avg_g_m2_d</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Calculated average weight of miscelaneousmaterial produced per day from twenty 1m2 baskets from plot 4; baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>RateByMonth.txt</entityName><entityDescription>Monthly separated (all months) leaffall rate before Hugo</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>RateByMonth.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb94/data/RateByMonth.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReferenceRateByMonth.txt" scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1980-11-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>1981-10-01</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Forest structure and species composition 

A 1 ha plot (100 x 100 m) was randomly established in each of the MSF and MTF in 1980. Within each plot, twenty circular subplots (113 m2) were randomly located. All trees greater that or equal to 0.1 m in DBH (diameter at breath height) in each subplot were identified and the DBHs were recorded. 

Litterfall and ground litter biomass 

Twenty 1 m2 baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen were randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground. Litterfall was collected biweekly for 1 yr between November 1980 and October 1981. All litter samples were separated into leaves, flowers, fruit, wood, and miscellaneous materials (mostly bark), oven-dried at 70oC for 72 hrs, and weighed. Ground litter was collected from 0.25 m2 subplots in both the dry season (March, 40 subplots) and the wet season (September, 20 subplots) randomly located in each of the 1 ha plots. Each sample was separated into wood and miscellaneous categories, oven-dried at 70oC for 72 hrs, and weighed. 

Leaf decomposition 

A total of 140 litterbags were constructed among which 70 litterbags were filled with fresh leaves collected from the MSF and 70 from the MTF (Blair et al., 1990). These fresh leaves represented the tree species composition in natural litterfall in April at both sites. The species composition of litterfall was determined using leaffall in the 1-m2 randomly placed baskets in each plot. Fresh leaves were collected for each forest within 24 hours of senescence in May and sorted by species. Leaves of the 13 most common species from each forest, representing 82-91% of the total fresh leaf mass, were placed in 1-mm2 mesh fiberglass screen bags (0.2 by 0.25 m) in proportion to their biomass in litterfall (Table 1). Leaves of the remaining 25 species were put in a miscellaneous category and randomly selected to obtain a total of 10-g fresh leaf material (4.6 g mean oven-dry mass) in each bag. 

For each leaf type, 35 litterbags were placed equally in 5 randomly selected subsites in the 1 ha plots where leaves were collected. In order to separate the effects of leaf chemistry on leaf decomposition from those of biotic and abiotic environmental conditions between the two forests, the other 35 litterbags for both leaf types were together placed in a 10 x 10 m plot in the MTF at five randomly selected locations. The 1 ha plots covered an area with heterogeneous geographical locations including ridges and valleys, whereas the 0.01 ha plot was located on a ridge top and upper slope position. One randomly selected litterbag was collected after 0, 7, 14, 28, 60, 120, and 300 days in the field at each site from each plot. There were 2 (leaf types) x 2 (incubation sites) x 5 (replicates) x 7 (collections) = 140 litterbags. 

Small roots which had entered the litter bags were carefully removed in the laboratory. The remaining litter in each bag was oven dried at 70 &#176;C for 72 hours and weighed to determine dry mass loss. Dry litter was then ground with a Wiley mill through a 0.85 mm (20 mesh) stainless steel sieve. One gram of the ground leaf material from each litterbag was digested with H2O2 and concentrated HNO3 (Luh Huang and Schulte, 1985) before analyzing for P, K, Ca, and Mg content with an atomic absorption and emission spectrophotometer. Total C and N in leaf material were analyzed by direct combustion in a C-H-N analyzer (Carlo-Erba Model 1106). 

Data analyses 

Basal area, tree density, and leaffall for each species were calculated for each forest. Total litterfall rate and ground litter biomass of all species were also calculated for each forest. The analysis of variance (ANOVA) was employed to test the differences in basal area, tree density, leaffall rate, and ground litter biomass between the forests or the seasons (SAS, 1987). Leaf decay rates were calculated using a single exponential model Mt = M0e-kt, where Mt was the remaining mass of leaf materials in a litter bag at time t and M0 was itsinitial mass. Slope k was obtained using linear regression after taking the natural logarithms of the equation. Multivariate tests were used to examine differences in k values between the two forests and between sites (SAS, 1987). The significance level was set at a = 0.05.Percentage of initial weight remaining was calculated using oven-dried weight. Percentage of initial element remaining in litterbags was obtained by multiplying the ratio of total element at time t (t = 0, 7, 14, 28, 60, 120, and 300 days) to that at time 0 by 100. Total element content in a litterbag was calculated as the product of element concentration and the oven- dry weight. Differences in elemental concentrations between forests and among decomposing dates were tested with ANOVA. Where significant differences were obtained by ANOVA, Bonferroni t-test (SAS Inc., 1987) was used to compare these differences in elemental concentrations. The significance levels for ANOVA and Bonferroni t-test were both set at &#224; = 0.05. Plots of residuals vs. predicted values indicated that no variables significantly violated the homogeneity assumption, with the exception of K concentrations. A non-parametric analysis was employed by ranking K concentrations prior to performing ANOVA and Bonferroni t test.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReferenceRateByMonth.txt</references></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>biweekly</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>months</attributeName><attributeLabel>ALL_MONTHS</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>months</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>month, by name (january, february, etc)</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Year of collection</attributeName><attributeLabel>YEAR</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Year of collection. No data are missing in this field. (YYYY)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>YYYY</formatString></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Total rate of leaffall</attributeName><attributeLabel>TOTAL_G_M2_D</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Total monthly rate of leaffall from baskets lined with 1 mm2 mesh fiberglass screen; randomly placed in each 1 ha plot at 1 m above ground from which litterfall was collected biweekly for one year. No data are missing in this field.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsSquareMeterperDay</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><unitList><unit id="gramsSquareMeterperDay" /></unitList></additionalMetadata></ns0:eml>