<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-kbs.12.23" system="KBS LTER" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd"><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=KBS,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataset id="/datasets/15.eml"><title>Soil Invertebrates in Cropped and Successional Communities at the Kellogg Biological Station, Hickory Corners, MI </title><creator><positionName>Data Manager</positionName></creator><associatedParty><individualName><givenName>Michael</givenName><surName>Klug</surName></individualName><organizationName>Michigan State University</organizationName><address><city>Hickory Corners</city><administrativeArea>MI</administrativeArea><postalCode>49060</postalCode></address><electronicMailAddress>klug@kbs.msu.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>original investigator</role></associatedParty><associatedParty><individualName><givenName>Daniel</givenName><surName>Lawson</surName></individualName><organizationName>Johnson and Johnson</organizationName><address /><role>original investigator</role></associatedParty><pubDate>2013-05-30</pubDate><abstract><section><title>Dataset Abstract</title><para>Soil invertebrates were sampled from the main cropping system
experiment (KBS004) via 7.5 cm diameter soil cores. Invertebrates were
extracted using modified Tullgren funnels for microarthropods and
macroarthropods and Baermann funnels for soil nematodes (Freckman, UC-
Riverside). Arthropods are classified to the lowest proctical taxon and further
classified, when possible, to functional feeding specialization (e.g.,
fungivore, bacterivore).</para><para>original data source http://lter.kbs.msu.edu/datasets/15</para></section></abstract><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="place">LTER</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">KBS</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">Kellogg Biological Station</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">Hickory Corners</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">Michigan</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">Great Lakes</keyword></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>invertebrates</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>Data in the KBS LTER core database may not be published without written permission of the lead investigator or project director. These restrictions are intended mainly to preserve the primary investigators' rights to first publication and to ensure that data users are aware of the limitations that may be associated with any specific data set. These restrictions apply to both the baseline data set and to the data sets associated with specific LTER-supported subprojects.</para><para>All publications of KBS data and images must acknowledge KBS LTER support.</para></intellectualRights><coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>The areas around the Kellogg Biological Station in southwest Michigan</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-85.404699</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-85.366857</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>42.420265</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>42.391019</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><contact><organizationName>Kellogg Biological Station</organizationName><positionName>Data Manager</positionName><address><deliveryPoint>3700 East Gull Lake Drive</deliveryPoint><city>Hickory Corners</city><administrativeArea>Mi</administrativeArea><postalCode>49060</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>lter.data.manager@kbs.msu.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://lter.kbs.msu.edu</onlineUrl></contact><publisher><organizationName>KBS LTER</organizationName></publisher><methods><methodStep><description>Sampling Frequency: IrregularSoil macroinvertebrates are sampled on a seasonal basis corresponding to major activity periods; March, April and May, thereafter, intensity will decrease to bimonthly sampling through September. Macroinvertebrates will be collected with a 7.6 cm diameter soil corerdriven gently by hand to a depth of 20 cm. One core is taken at each of the 5 soil sampling stations per plot and all 5 cores are composited as one soil sample. Soil samples are removed from the coring device, placed in zip-lock bags and stored in coolers. Samples are then returned to the laboratory and stored at 40 &#176;C. Macroinvertebrates are recovered from soil cores within 48 h of collection by elutriation. The soil-root washer (Gilson Hydropneumatic Elutriator) is utilized to suspend soil subsamples in a vortex of water and compressed air which floats off soil and suspended organics. Eluent from the elutriator is passed over a series of sieves which retains material greater than 300 m. This retained material is preserved in 90% ethanol. Invertebrates are then hand-sorted from the collected debris under a dissecting scope (25x), preserved in 75% ethanol and identified to the lowest practical taxon.</description><protocol id="protocol_21"><title>Soil Invertebrates</title><creator><positionName>Data Manager</positionName></creator><distribution><online><url>http://lter.kbs.msu.edu/protocols/21</url></online></distribution></protocol></methodStep></methods></dataset></ns0:eml>