<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-luq.60.3" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 C:/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><shortName>LUQMetadata60</shortName><title>Location of trees in the Hurricane Recovery Plot (El Verde)</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Edwin</givenName><surName>Everham</surName></individualName><organizationName>Florida Gulf Coast University</organizationName><positionName>Program Leader/Assoc Professor</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>College of Arts and Sciences</deliveryPoint><city>Fort Myers</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33965-6565</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(404)590-7169</phone><phone phonetype="fax">voice</phone><electronicMailAddress>eeverham@fgcu.edu</electronicMailAddress></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Edwin</givenName><surName>Everham</surName></individualName><organizationName>Florida Gulf Coast University</organizationName><positionName>Program Leader/Assoc Professor</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>College of Arts and Sciences</deliveryPoint><city>Fort Myers</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33965-6565</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(404)590-7169</phone><phone phonetype="fax">voice</phone><electronicMailAddress>eeverham@fgcu.edu</electronicMailAddress></metadataProvider><language>english</language><abstract><para><literalLayout>This data set shows the Tag number, Quadrat location, Species code, diameter and XY coordinates of stems &gt;=10 cm D130 present at the time of Hurricane Hugo and in the first census. The data set is composed of two files both with the same file structure. In LFDP_C1treemap.txt the diameters (Fdiam) are as recorded in the field data. In LFDP_C1TREEMAPa.txt the stem diameters (Fdiam) were calculated to allocate "missed" stems (stems &gt;=10 cm D130) that were found in survey 2, 3 or Census 2 to Census 1 survey 1. We calculated the diameter the stem would have had, if it had been recorded at the same time the quadrat it was located in was assessed, in the appropriate survey for that stem size. To extrapolate the stem size back in time, we used the actual growth rate of that individual stem if more than one measurement was available. If only one diameter measurement was available we used the median growth rate for that species in the appropriate size class stems &gt;=10, &lt;30 cm D130). In our publications we will combine data sets LFDP_C1treemap.txt and LFDP_C1TREEMAPa.txt to make Census 1 and to reconstruct the forest for stems &gt;= 10 cm D130 at the time of Hurricane Hugo. We have divided the data into two separate files to ensure that when stem diameters are compared to future censuses the diameter data in LFDP_C1TREEMAPa.txt are not used to calculate growth rates. The last corrections to the Census 1 data were made in May 2001.  The National Science Foundation requires that data from projects it funds are posted on the web two years after any data set has been organized and "cleaned". The data from each census of the LFDP will be updated at intervals as each survey of the LFDP shows errors in the previous data collection. After posting on the web, researchers who are not part of the project are then welcome to use the data. Given the enormous amount of time, effort and resources required to manage the LFDP, obtain these data, and ensure data accuracy, LFDP Principal Investigators request that researchers intending to use this data comply with the requests below. Through complying with these requests we can ensure that the data are interpreted correctly, analyses are not repeated unnecessarily, beneficial collaboration between users is promoted and the Principle Investigators investment in this project is protected.     Submit to the LFDP PIs a short (1 page) description of how you intend to use the data; &#183; Invite LFDP PIs to be co-authors on any publication that uses the data in a substantial way (some PIs may decline and other LFDP scientists may need to be included); If the LFDP PIs are not co-authors, send the PIs a draft of any paper using LFDP data, so that the PIs may comment upon it; In the methods section of any publication using LFDP data, describe that data as coming from the "Luquillo Forest Dynamics Plot, part of the Luquillo Experimental Forest Long-Term Ecological Research Program"; Acknowledge in any publication using LFDP data the "The Luquillo Experimental Forest Long-Term Ecological Research Program, supported by the U.S. National Science Foundation, the University of Puerto Rico, and the International Institute of Tropical Forestry"; &#183; Supply the LFDP PIs with 10 reprints of any publication using LFDP data. &#183; Accept that the LFDP PIs can not guarantee that the LFDP data you intend to use, has not already been submitted for publication or published.</literalLayout></para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>plant community composition</keyword><keyword>plant diversity</keyword><keyword>puerto rico</keyword><keyword>luquillo forest dynamics plot (LFDP)</keyword><keyword>el verde field station (EVFS)</keyword><keyword>hurricane recovery plot (LFDP)</keyword><keyword>luquillo experimental forest (LEF)</keyword><keywordThesaurus>Assigned by Principal Investigator</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>population dynamics</keyword><keyword>primary productivity</keyword><keyword>disturbance patterns</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LTER Core</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>palms</keyword><keyword>peer reviewed journal</keyword><keyword>population dynamics</keyword><keyword>primary production</keyword><keyword>shrubs</keyword><keyword>environmental variables</keyword><keyword>tree growth</keyword><keyword>trees</keyword><keyword>moist</keyword><keyword>el verde big grid (LFDP)</keyword><keyword>herbs</keyword><keyword>disturbance</keyword><keyword>el verde</keyword><keyword>community composition</keyword><keyword>ferns</keyword><keyword>higher plants</keyword><keyword>human</keyword><keyword>hurricane</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LEF LTER Data Sets</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>Vegetation Dynamics</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LEF LTER Data Categories</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><title>ADEQUATE ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><para><literalLayout>The scientists, the LEF-LTER Program, and the USDA International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITF) must receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data by other scientists, and the LEF LTER program must receive two copies of any publication using that data. One copy will be placed at the IITF library and one copy will stay with the LEF LTER Data Manager. A suggested format for this acknowledgement will be distributed along with the requested data.</literalLayout></para><section><title>Acknowledgements for NSF Support.</title><para><literalLayout>The following paragraph should be included in the acknowledgements of all publications funded in any way by current and future LTER grants:</literalLayout><literalLayout>This research was performed under grant #DEB-0218039 from the National Science Foundation to the Institute of Tropical Ecosystem Studies (IEET), University of Puerto Rico, and the International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITFR) as part of the Long-Term Ecological Research Program in the Luquillo Experimental Forest. Additional support was provided by the Forest Service (U.S. Department of Agriculture) and the University of Puerto Rico.</literalLayout></para></section></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb60/metadata/lterdb60.htm#DATA</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage id="geoReference" scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF) covers 11,231 hectares and reaches 1079 m above sea level. It has a warm and wet climate and includes a variety of tropical habitats and forest types and streams, and a high diversity of plants and animals. A key feature of these ecosystems is disturbance. Hurricanes, landslides, and human disturbance have shaped the forest, and research by LUQ has stimulated a new appreciation of the significance of large-scale disturbances in tropical forested ecosystems and the key role of plants and animals in shaping the response to these events. Hurricanes occurring one and 10 years after LUQ began in 1988 provided landscape-scale natural experiments which are still followed closely.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-65.92</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-65.7</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>18.35</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>18.23</southBoundingCoordinate><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>20</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>1060</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Edwin</givenName><surName>Everham</surName></individualName><organizationName>Florida Gulf Coast University</organizationName><positionName>Program Leader/Assoc Professor</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>College of Arts and Sciences</deliveryPoint><city>Fort Myers</city><administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea><postalCode>33965-6565</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(404)590-7169</phone><phone phonetype="fax">voice</phone><electronicMailAddress>eeverham@fgcu.edu</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>Luquillo Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>University of Puerto Rico, Rio Piedras</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>P. O. Box 21910</deliveryPoint><city>San Juan</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931-1910</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787) 764 - 0000 (ext. 4940)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787) 772 -1481</phone><electronicMailAddress>nbrokaw@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://luq.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>During Census 1 survey 1, and Census 2, all stems &gt;=10 cm D130 were marked on a map of the 20 x 20 m quadrat in which they were located. We aimed for an accuracy of about 0.5 m. After the maps were complete the location of the stems relative to the Southwest corner of the LFDP was recorded using a map digitizer. This gave the X Y coordinates of each tree in meters from the origin at the Southwest corner of the LFDP. Unfortunately stems &gt;=10 cm D130 that were encountered in Census 1 surveys 2 and 3 were not located on a map so it wasn't until Census 2 that the XY coordinates could be determined. As a result some of the stems representing Census 1 have no X Y coordinates as they had died and disappeared before their location was established. In these cases we know only which quadrat and subquadrat the stem was located in.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep></methods><project scope="document"><title>Luquillo Forest Dynamics Plot (LFDP)</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Edwin</givenName><surName>Everham</surName></individualName><role>Program Leader/Assoc Professor</role></personnel><abstract><para><literalLayout>The processes that determine the plant species diversity and structure of tropical forest are still uncertain despite many years of investigation. A tropical forest characteristically has few common species and many rare species, with conspecifics often widely distributed throughout the forest. The potential for inter and intra-specific interactions are numerous, and it is difficult to determine which factors maintain species diversity or how rare species survive in the population.  Factors that we believe contribute to tropical forest structure and composition include the physical environment and past history of the forest, species-specific physiological requirements for light, nutrients and water necessary for growth, survival and reproduction, and pathogens and herbivores.  Despite the substantial amount of information available about these factors, we are still unable to accurately model the current composition of tropical forest or to predict its future response to human and natural disturbances.  The Luquillo Forest Dynamics Plot (LFDP), previously known as the Hurricane Recovery Plot (Zimmerman et. al. 1994) and the Luquillo long-term ecological research grid (Soil Survey 1995), is a 16-ha forest plot (SW corner 18  20' N, 65  49' W) located near El Verde Field Station. The plot is 500 m N-S and 320 m E-W and is divided into 400 20 x 20 m quadrats, with each quadrat sub divided into 16 5 x 5 m sub-quadrats.  The field station and LFDP are in the Luquillo Mountains of northeastern Puerto Rico, approximately 35 km southeast of San Juan.  Information from the LFDP contributes to the efforts of the Center for Tropical Forest Science (CTFS, Smithsonian) network of large tropical forest plots in order to improve our understanding of tropical forest and to predict its future.  Large plots (typically 50 ha) are required to cover local environmental variation, include sufficient numbers of individuals of both the common and rare species, and to determine plant spatial relationships.  Population monitoring is required over many years to elucidate tree life histories, species interactions and population changes in order to determine the forest response to environmental changes and disturbance.  The LFDP is unique among the CTFS sites as it has a history of land use disturbance and also hurricane damage. These two disturbance types interact and influence the community dynamics and species composition in the LFDP.  The Northern area (approximately two thirds of the plot) was disturbed by tree felling and farming until 1934 when the land was purchased by United States Department of Agriculture, Forest Service. The Southern third was not farmed and only suffered relatively light disturbance from selective logging. Aerial photographs taken in 1936 show differences in canopy cover caused by the patterns of land use history.  Clear patterns in the distribution of some species reflect this land use history (Thompson et. al. in press).  The distribution of species as a result of the land use history interacts with hurricane disturbance, as those species colonizing the northern part of the LFDP are more susceptible to hurricane damage (Zimmerman et. al. 1994). Major hurricanes struck the forest area of the LFDP in 1928 and 1932 and after a 66 year period with relatively little hurricane damage, the forest was struck by Hurricane Hugo in 1989 and Hurricane Georges in 1998, both hurricanes causing significant damage.  LFDP CENSUS HISTORY.  The LFDP was established in 1990 and the censuses are carried out in accordance with CTFS protocol (Condit 1998) with only minor variations.  The first assessment of stems &gt;= 10 cm D130  (diameter at breast height [DBH] of 130 cm from the ground) consisting of stems damaged by Hurricane Hugo (September 1989) was carried out from August 1990 to September 1991 (Everham 1996).  The first complete census of all stems &gt;=1 cm D130 lasted from August 1990 to September 1993.  This first census was ddivided into three surveys with the first survey (August 1990 to February 1992) comprising all free standing (excluding lianas) woody stems&gt;= 10 cm D130.  The second survey (overlapping the third survey) consisted of checks on a small number of quadrats in which a few large stems &gt;= 10 cm D130 were found that had been "missed" during the first survey.  The third survey of woody stems &gt;= 1 cm &lt;10 cm D130 was carried out between April 1992 and September 1993.  During Census 1 surveys 2 and 3 stems were found that were &gt;=10 cm D130 and, therefore, were most likely to have been present in the forest at the time of Census 1 survey 1.  In addition in Census 2 (November 1994 to October 1996), stems were found &gt;=3 cm D130 (&gt;=5 cm D130 for Cecropia schreberiana and Schefflera morototoni) which may have been missed in Census 1.   In order to include these "missed" stems in the appropriate census and survey we calculated what diameter the stem would have been at the time the quadrat in which it was located was initially assessed.  These "missed" stems were allocated to earlier censuses and census surveys based either upon the actual growth rate of that stem, if more than one measurement was available, or the median growthrate for that species.  The median growthrate was calculated for two size classes of stems &gt;=1, &lt;10 cm, or &gt;=10 to 30 cm D130.  Using the most appropriate growthrate the diameter of the "missed" stem was extrapolated back in time to estimate the stem diameter at the correct survey time in Census 1.  If the calculated diameter matched the size class for an earlier survey the stem was allocated to it with its estimated diameter.  Information for stems &gt;=10 cm D130 damaged during Hurricane Hugo was combined with data for stems &gt;=10 cm D130, in census 1 survey 1 together with "missed" stems recorded in later surveys to reconstruct the forest as it was at the time of Hurricane Hugo.  The reconstruction to represent the forest at the time of Hurricane Hugo did not include diameter extrapolations back to September 1989, but to the time at which the appropriate size class of stems were measured between August 1990 and September 1993. The palm Prestoea acuminata was allocated to earlier census surveys based upon the height of the point of measurement and additional observations.  Further details on the procedures for allocating these "missed" stems to the appropriate census surveys can be found in the descriptions in the relevant data files. The last corrections to the Census 1 this data were made in May 2001.  In all censuses individual stems of the specified size were tagged, identified and measured for D130.  On multiple stemmed plants, all stems were individually tagged and the group of stems representing an individual plant was recorded.  In the first and second census stems &gt;=10 cm D130 were mapped.  Following CTFS protocol we are conducting the censuses at 5 year intervals. The second census (November 1994 to October 1996) consisted of only one survey with all stems &gt;=1 cm D130 censused at the same time, although only stems &gt;=10 cm D130 were mapped.   The third census (funded by the Andrew Mellon Foundation) started in July 2000 and is expected to finish in April 2002.  In this third census, in addition to mapping stems &gt;=10 cm D130, we are also mapping the location of stems &gt;=1 cm D130.  :  R. DeLeon, J. Bithorn, M. Aponte, A.-L. M&#233;ndez, M. Estades, A. Estrada, S. Matta, plant taxonomist B. Boom, and data manager Eda Melendez. Many volunteers, too numerous to mention, were also a tremendous help with the census.  We thank the United States Department of Agriculture and Natural Resources Conservation Service, Lincoln, Nebraska, USA for the soil survey.  The International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITF) gave us access to their historical records and timber cruise surveys, and we thank Dr. Frank Wadsworth and Octavio Jodan who helped interpret them.  John Thomlinson helped prepare the digital maps of stem locations and the soil map. The aerial phhotographs were analyzed at The Harvard Forest, Harvard University.</literalLayout></para></abstract><funding><para><literalLayout>NSF</literalLayout></para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=LUQ,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>LFDP_treemapC1.txt</entityName><entityDescription>LFDP census 1 species, diameter and location</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>LFDP_treemapC1.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb60/data/LFDP_treemapC1.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReferenceLFDP_treemapC1.txt" scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1990-08-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2008</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>During Census 1 survey 1, and Census 2, all stems &gt;=10 cm D130 were marked on a map of the 20 x 20 m quadrat in which they were located. We aimed for an accuracy of about 0.5 m. After the maps were complete the location of the stems relative to the Southwest corner of the LFDP was recorded using a map digitizer. This gave the X Y coordinates of each tree in meters from the origin at the Southwest corner of the LFDP. Unfortunately stems &gt;=10 cm D130 that were encountered in Census 1 surveys 2 and 3 were not located on a map so it wasn't until Census 2 that the XY coordinates could be determined. As a result some of the stems representing Census 1 have no X Y coordinates as they had died and disappeared before their location was established. In these cases we know only which quadrat and subquadrat the stem was located in.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReferenceLFDP_treemapC1.txt</references></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>5 years</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Tag</attributeName><attributeLabel>TAG</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Unique number for each stem.These tags represent individual stems (including each stem on a multiple stemmed plant) not individual plants.Many numbers between-455 to 131126werenot used.No data is missing in this column.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Quadrat code number</attributeName><attributeLabel>QUAD</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Code represents the 20 x 20 m quadrat based upon its position in the rows and columns of the 16 ha grid. The first 2 digits form the column number counting quadrats from West to East and the second two digits form the row number counting quadrats South to North. Codes include 0101 first quadrat in southwest corner to 2525 last quadrat in North East corner. Leading zeros are not displayed so quadrats in columns 1-9 have only 3 digits. No data is missing in this column..</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Code represents the 20 x 20 m quadrat based upon its position in the rows and columns of the 16 ha grid. The first 2 digits form the column number counting quadrats from West to East and the second two digits form the row number counting quadrats South to North. Codes include 0101 first quadrat in southwest corner to 2525 last quadrat in North East corner. Leading zeros are not displayed so quadrats in columns 1-9 have only 3 digits. No data is missing in this column..</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Subquadrat number</attributeName><attributeLabel>SUBQUAD</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Code representing the position each of the 16-5m by 5 m subquadrat within each 20 m x 20 m quadrat. The code consists of 2 numbers. The first is the number of the plot counting from the southwest corner of the quadrat to the east. The second is the number of the subquadrat counting from the southwest corner to the north. See arrangement below:NW 14 24 34 44 NE13 23 33 3412 22 32 42SW 11 21 31 41 SENo data is missing in this column.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Code representing the position each of the 16-5m by 5 m subquadrat within each 20 m x 20 m quadrat. The code consists of 2 numbers. The first is the number of the plot counting from the southwest corner of the quadrat to the east. The second is the number of the subquadrat counting from the southwest corner to the north. See arrangement below:NW 14 24 34 44 NE13 23 33 3412 22 32 42SW 11 21 31 41 SENo data is missing in this column.</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>New species name</attributeName><attributeLabel>NEWSPP</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>A 6 letter code for the species name for this individual. First three letters are the first three letter of the genus and the second three letters the first three letters of the species name. Variations to this rule are possible. See species list file LFDP_species. The species identifications include corrections made after census 2. Blank means no species identification was possible. Dead means tree was dead and no species identification was possible. ING? Means Inga species not determined.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>A 6 letter code for the species name for this individual. First three letters are the first three letter of the genus and the second three letters the first three letters of the species name. Variations to this rule are possible. See species list file LFDP_species. The species identifications include corrections made after census 2. Blank means no species identification was possible. Dead means tree was dead and no species identification was possible. ING? Means Inga species not determined.</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Fixed diameter of stems measured in Census 1 (survey 1; 2 and 3)</attributeName><attributeLabel>FDIAM</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>In file LFDP_treemapC1.txt these are actual diameter measurements on the indicated date. LFDP_treemapC1.txt these diameters were calculated to give the diameter that the stem would have had; if it had not been missed and had been measured in the correct survey for it's size class. Date for each stem in LFDP_treemapC1a.txt means the actual date a diameter was recorded although the diameter was calculated for an earlier time.Precision is0.1 cm; calculated diameters for stemsD10 cm may be given to 0.01 cm.Blank means no data recorded.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>X coordinate</attributeName><attributeLabel>Xm</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The location of the stem relative to the Southwest corner of the LFDP. Distance in meters East.Precision is+ or - 0.5 m in the field (digitizer gives .01 m).Blank means no data recorded.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>meter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.5</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Y coordinate</attributeName><attributeLabel>Ym</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The location of the stem relative to the Southwest corner of the LFDP. Distance in meters North.Precision is+ or - 0.5 m in the field (digitizer gives .01 m).Blank means no data recorded.u</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>meter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.5</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>LFDP_treemapC1a.txt</entityName><entityDescription>LFDP census 1 species, diameter and location</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>LFDP_treemapC1a.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb60/data/LFDP_treemapC1a.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReferenceLFDP_treemapC1a.txt" scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1990-08-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2008</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>During Census 1 survey 1, and Census 2, all stems &gt;=10 cm D130 were marked on a map of the 20 x 20 m quadrat in which they were located. We aimed for an accuracy of about 0.5 m. After the maps were complete the location of the stems relative to the Southwest corner of the LFDP was recorded using a map digitizer. This gave the X Y coordinates of each tree in meters from the origin at the Southwest corner of the LFDP. Unfortunately stems &gt;=10 cm D130 that were encountered in Census 1 surveys 2 and 3 were not located on a map so it wasn't until Census 2 that the XY coordinates could be determined. As a result some of the stems representing Census 1 have no X Y coordinates as they had died and disappeared before their location was established. In these cases we know only which quadrat and subquadrat the stem was located in.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReferenceLFDP_treemapC1a.txt</references></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>5 years</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Tag</attributeName><attributeLabel>TAG</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Unique number for each stem.These tags represent individual stems (including each stem on a multiple stemmed plant) not individual plants.Many numbers between-455 to 131126werenot used.No data is missing in this column.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Quadrat code number</attributeName><attributeLabel>QUAD</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Code represents the 20 x 20 m quadrat based upon its position in the rows and columns of the 16 ha grid. The first 2 digits form the column number counting quadrats from West to East and the second two digits form the row number counting quadrats South to North. Codes include 0101 first quadrat in southwest corner to 2525 last quadrat in North East corner. Leading zeros are not displayed so quadrats in columns 1-9 have only 3 digits. No data is missing in this column..</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Code represents the 20 x 20 m quadrat based upon its position in the rows and columns of the 16 ha grid. The first 2 digits form the column number counting quadrats from West to East and the second two digits form the row number counting quadrats South to North. Codes include 0101 first quadrat in southwest corner to 2525 last quadrat in North East corner. Leading zeros are not displayed so quadrats in columns 1-9 have only 3 digits. No data is missing in this column..</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Subquadrat number</attributeName><attributeLabel>SUBQUAD</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Code representing the position each of the 16-5m by 5 m subquadrat within each 20 m x 20 m quadrat. The code consists of 2 numbers. The first is the number of the plot counting from the southwest corner of the quadrat to the east. The second is the number of the subquadrat counting from the southwest corner to the north. See arrangement below:NW 14 24 34 44 NE13 23 33 3412 22 32 42SW 11 21 31 41 SENo data is missing in this column.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Code representing the position each of the 16-5m by 5 m subquadrat within each 20 m x 20 m quadrat. The code consists of 2 numbers. The first is the number of the plot counting from the southwest corner of the quadrat to the east. The second is the number of the subquadrat counting from the southwest corner to the north. See arrangement below:NW 14 24 34 44 NE13 23 33 3412 22 32 42SW 11 21 31 41 SENo data is missing in this column.</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>New species name</attributeName><attributeLabel>NEWSPP</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>A 6 letter code for the species name for this individual. First three letters are the first three letter of the genus and the second three letters the first three letters of the species name. Variations to this rule are possible. See species list file LFDP_species. The species identifications include corrections made after census 2. Blank means no species identification was possible. Dead means tree was dead and no species identification was possible. ING? Means Inga species not determined.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>A 6 letter code for the species name for this individual. First three letters are the first three letter of the genus and the second three letters the first three letters of the species name. Variations to this rule are possible. See species list file LFDP_species. The species identifications include corrections made after census 2. Blank means no species identification was possible. Dead means tree was dead and no species identification was possible. ING? Means Inga species not determined.</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Fixed diameter of stems measured in Census 1 (survey 1; 2 and 3)</attributeName><attributeLabel>FDIAM</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>In file LFDP_treemapC1.txt these are actual diameter measurements on the indicated date. LFDP_treemapC1.txt these diameters were calculated to give the diameter that the stem would have had; if it had not been missed and had been measured in the correct survey for it's size class. Date for each stem in LFDP_treemapC1a.txt means the actual date a diameter was recorded although the diameter was calculated for an earlier time.Precision is0.1 cm; calculated diameters for stemsD10 cm may be given to 0.01 cm.Blank means no data recorded.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>X coordinate</attributeName><attributeLabel>Xm</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The location of the stem relative to the Southwest corner of the LFDP. Distance in meters East.Precision is+ or - 0.5 m in the field (digitizer gives .01 m).Blank means no data recorded.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>meter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.5</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Y coordinate</attributeName><attributeLabel>Ym</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The location of the stem relative to the Southwest corner of the LFDP. Distance in meters North.Precision is+ or - 0.5 m in the field (digitizer gives .01 m).Blank means no data recorded.u</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>meter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.5</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset></ns0:eml>