<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-arc.1305.1" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><alternateIdentifier>96bomocb</alternateIdentifier><title>96bomocb.txt</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>William</givenName><surName>Bowden</surName></individualName></creator><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Dave</givenName><surName>Arscott</surName></individualName><role>additional investigator</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Jacques</givenName><surName>Finlay</surName></individualName><role>additional investigator</role></associatedParty><abstract><para>This file provides documentation for file 96BOMOCB.DAT, an ASCII file
that contains final data for cover biomass measurements used to estimate Hygrohypnum biomass in the Kuparuk River.
Hygrohypnum was the only bryophyte harvested for this measurement from the Kuparuk River's fertilized and recovery
reaches.  Harvests were done in June and August</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Kuparuk River</keyword><keyword>P-fertilized</keyword><keyword>P-recovery</keyword><keyword>Hygrohypnum</keyword><keyword>biomass</keyword><keyword>riffle</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>Acceptance and utilization of LTER data requires that:</para><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The Principal Investigator be sent a notice stating
reasons for acquiring any data and a description of the
publication intentions.</para></listitem><listitem><para>The Principal Investigator of the data set be sent a
copy of the report or manuscript prior to submission and be
adequately cited in any resultant publications</para></listitem><listitem><para>A copy of any resultant publications should be sent to:<literalLayout>Principal Investigator
Ecosystems Center
Marine Biological Laboratory
Woods Hole, MA 02543</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://ecosystems.mbl.edu/ARC/data/96bomocb.dat</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage id="GEO-1" scope="document"><geographicDescription>Kuparuk River:
Fertilized:	riffles at 1.7, 2.065, and 2.1 km
Recovery:	riffles at 1.025, 1.1, and 1.3 km</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-149.75</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-149.0433</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>68.8</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>68.5</southBoundingCoordinate><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>610</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>1360</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><singleDateTime><calendarDate>1996</calendarDate></singleDateTime></temporalCoverage></coverage><maintenance><description><para>Log of changes:</para><para>For Archival Use:
                
     DATE RECEIVED:  June 1997
     DATA FILE ENTERED BY:  Karie Slavik
     DATA FILE VALIDATION:
          NAME:
          DATE</para></description></maintenance><contact id="im" scope="document" system="knb"><positionName>Data Manager</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint><city>Woods Hole</city><administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea><postalCode>02543</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7496</phone><electronicMailAddress>arc_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://ecosystems.mbl.edu/ARC/</onlineUrl></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>ARC LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>The Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Marine Biological Lab</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>7 MBL St</deliveryPoint><city>Woods Hole</city><administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea><postalCode>02543</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(508) 289 7496</phone><electronicMailAddress>arc_im@mbl.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://ecosystems.mbl.edu/ARC/</onlineUrl></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>In 1990 we observed increased abundance's of several species of aquatic bryophytes 
in the fertilized zone of the Kuparuk River relative to the reference.  These bryophytes included, most notably, two species 
of Hygrohypnum, H. alpestre and H. ochraceum, Fontinalis neomexicana, and, to a lesser extent, Schistidium agassizii and 
the leafy liverwort Solenostoma.  To substantiate these data, we utilized point transects in 1992-96 to estimate bryophyte 
coverage in the P-enriched and reference reaches.  To estimate percent coverage, we normally completed 5 transects per 
riffle site.  In order to estimate the total biomass of Hygrohypnum and Schistidium in the Kuparuk River we performed a 
biomass harvest in 1995 which entailed harvesting these bryophytes from a known area at different coverage percentages.  
The result was a slide rule scale that could be used to determine the biomass of either species at differing percent covers.  
In 1996, we moved the point of phosphorus addition 0.75 km downstream to stream benchmark +1.4 km.  This created 3 
treatment reaches: a reference reach (upstream of +0.59 km), a P-recovery reach (+0.59 to +1.35 km), and a long-term P-
fertilized reach (1.35 to 10 km).  Further downstream (typically &amp;gt; 10 km) nutrient conditions return to background 
concentrations (Peterson et al. 1993, Bowden et al. 1994).  As part of monitoring the health of the extensive mats of 
Hygrohypnum in both the P-fertilized and P-recovery reaches we performed early and late season biomass harvests of 
Hygrohypnum.  Our efforts concentrated on monitoring any changes in cover and mat density of Hygrohypnum in the P-
recovery reach compared to the P-fertilized reach.  Data for benthic cover in P-fertilized , P-recovery, and reference 
reaches is reported in "96BOMOPT.DOC and .DAT".  Biomass harvests are reported in this file "96BOMOCB.DAT".  
Since Hygrohypnum is found predominantly in the P-fertilized reach (and now in the P-recovery reach) 1996 we harvested 
only Hygrohypnum from these 2 treatment reaches.
	Because the assessment of percent cover does not reveal thinning within a covered area of stream bottom a 
measure of mat density was used to determine whether Hygrohypnum spp. mats in the fertilized reach become more dense 
throughout the growing season and mats in the recovery reach become less dense or thin throughout the growing season.  
To determine mat density of Hygrohypnum spp. in recovery and fertilized reaches, biomass harvests were completed on 
19-June and 10-August, 1996.  Three riffles in the recovery reach and 3 riffles in the fertilized reach were sampled.  A 
1102.2 cm2 plot was placed on the stream bottom selected sites in an attempt to harvest plots that were as close to 100 % 
cover as possible.  This was done to minimize any differences due to a cover-density interaction.  For those plots not 100 % 
covered with Hygrohypnum spp. the percent cover within each plot was estimated prior to harvesting.  Three plots were 
harvested from each riffle yielding a total of 18 plots harvested in June and 18 harvested in August.
	All rocks with attached Hygrohypnum spp. within the plot were carefully removed.  Moss material was scraped 
from each of the rocks with a razor blade, rinsed repeatedly in a dip net (to remove sediment, detritus, and invertebrates), 
placed in labeled storage bags, and returned to the laboratory.  All material collected was dried at 65 oC until a consistent 
weight was established.  Dry mass was recorded for each plot.
	The mat density calculation is described in (12)CALCULATIONS and this is the value reported as MATDENS in 
the data file (mgdw/cm2).</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>Notes: These data should not be released to any party without the written permission of William 
B. Bowden. 
(11) VARIABLE DESCRIPTIONS:
						Precise				Coded
Variable		Variable description		Units				(Y/N)
SITE          	site of measurement                          				y
D/D           	distance from K or O dripper  	0.05 km        			n
DATE         	date                          		ddmmyy         			n
LOCATION   	location (REF, FERT)                         				n
SUBSITE       	typically POOL or RIFFLE                     				n
TYPE          	community description                        				n
PLOT#         	assigned harvest number                      				n
%COVER       	estimated coverage in plot       	%				n
RAWMASS    	biomass harvested from plot   	gdw/1102.2 cm2  		n
MATDENS    	calculated mat density        	mgdw/cm2       			n</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>Calculations: Mat Density
	              (Mp/1000)
       Md = ::::::::::::-                 Eq.1
            (%cover/100) * 1102.2cm2
			where:  Md = mat density (mgdw/cm2)
				   Mp = plot biomass (gdw/plot)
				   1102.2cm2= plot area</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>Reference Citations: Arscott, D. B. 1997.  Primary Production in an Arctic Stream Ecosystem.  Thesis, University of New Hampshire.
Manuscript submitted. 1997.  Arscott, Dave B., W. B. Bowden, and J. C. Finlay.  Epilithic algal and bryophyte metabolism 
in an arctic tundra stream, Alaska.
Manuscript submitted. 1997.  Arscott, Dave B., W. B. Bowden, J. C. Finlay, and J. Lee.  Ecophysiology of two arctic 
stream bryophytes.
Bowden, W. B., J. C. Finlay, and P. E. Maloney.  1994.  Long-term effects of PO4 fertilization on the distribution of 
bryophytes in an arctic river. Freshwater Biology 32:445-454.
Finlay, J. C. and W. B. Bowden.  1994.  Controls on production of bryophytes in an arctic tundra stream. Freshwater 
Biology 32:455-466.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>GEO-1</references></geographicCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>None</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=ARC,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access></dataset><additionalMetadata><sitetype>AQUATIC-STREAMS</sitetype></additionalMetadata></ns0:eml>