<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-cwt.4004.4" scope="system" system="cwt-lter" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 http://gce-lter.marsci.uga.edu/lter/files/schemas/eml-201/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Aboveground biomass and nitrogen allocation of ten deciduous southern Appalachian tree species.</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Brian D.</givenName><surName>Kloeppel</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Coweeta Hydrologic Laboratory</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>3160 Coweeta Lab Road</deliveryPoint><city>Otto</city><administrativeArea>North Carolina</administrativeArea><postalCode>28763</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(828) 524-2128 x127</phone><electronicMailAddress>kloeppel@sparc.ecology.uga.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://cwt33.ecology.uga.edu/piprofiles/pro_kloeppel.html</onlineUrl></creator><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Jonathan G.</givenName><surName>Martin</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>University of Minnesota</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Department of Forest Resources</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>115 Green Hall</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1530 North Cleveland Avenue</deliveryPoint><city>St. Paul</city><administrativeArea>Minnesota</administrativeArea><postalCode>55108</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(612) 626-1205</phone><electronicMailAddress>jmartin@forestry.umn.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://coweeta/ecology/uga.edu</onlineUrl></creator><abstract><para>Allometric equations were developed for mature trees of 10 deciduous species at the Coweeta Hydrologic Laboratory in western North Carolina, U.S.A. These equations included the following dependent variables: stem wood mass, stem bark mass, branch mass, total wood mass, foliage mass, total biomass, foliage area, stem surface area, sapwood volume, and total tree volume. High correlation coefficients (R2) were observed for all variables versus stem diameter, with the highest being for total tree biomass, which ranged from 0.981 for Oxdendrum arboreum to 0.999 for Quercus coccinea. Foliage area had the lowest R2 values, ranging from 0.555 for Quercus alba to 0.962 for Betula lenta. When all species were combined, correlation coefficients ranged from 0.822 for foliage area to 0.986 for total wood mass, total tree biomass, and total tree volume. Species with ring versus diffuse/semiring porous wood anatomy exhibited higher leaf area with a given cross-sectional sapwood area as well as lower total sapwood volume. Liriodendron tulipifera contained one of the highest foliar nitrogen concentrations and had consistently low branch, bark, sapwood, and heartwood nitrogen contents. For a tree diameter of 50 cm, Carya spp. exhibited the highest total nitrogen content whereas Liriodendron tulipifera exhibited the lowest.</para><para>Study Area  | Trees were sampled in the Southern Appalachian Mountains in western North Carolina at the Coweeta Hydrologic Laboratory (35 degrees N, 83 degrees W) as well as an area 4 km to the south; both areas are on the Nantahala National Forest. All trees were selected from mature stands (i.e. &gt; 80 years old) containing mixed oak [Quercus alba L., Quercus coccinea Muenchh., Quercus prinus L., Quercus rubra L. and Quercus velutina Lam.], hickory [Carya glabra (Mill.) Sweet, Carya ovata (Mill.) K. Kock. and Carya tomentosa (Poir.) Nutt.], red maple [Acru rubrum L.], sourwood [Oxydendrum arboreum (L.) DC.], sweet birch [Betula lenta L], flowering dogwood [Cornus florida L.], and tulip poplar [Liriodendron tulipifera L.]. The mean annual precipitation of the basin is 2035 mm, which comes from an average of 133 storm events per year (Swift et al. 1988). Steep topography at Coweeta Hydrologic Laboratory and in the surrounding area ranges in elevation from 675 to 1592 m. The soils are Inceptisols and Ultisols with A and B horizon depths ranging from trace covering to 70 cm (Velbel 1988). The younger Inceptisols occur at higher elevations and on rocky substrates and are typically Umbric Dystrochrepts and Typic Dystrochrepts (Thomas 1996). Inceptisols are also located in coves and are represented by Typic Haplumbrepts. The older Ultisols, found on mountain slopes, are depicted by Typic Hapludults and Humic Hapludults (Thomas 1996). || Field Measurements | Trees used in this study were selected by species, size, and location, and were harvested between June and August to reduce the effects of decreasing SLA (Kloeppel and Abrams 1993) and N translocation on nitrogen tissue concentrations (Day and Monk 1977). The range of species and sizes was selected to represent the distribution observed in over 400 permanent plots across the Coweeta Basin (Douglas and Hoover 1988). Trees were selected using a stratified random design (Avery and Burkhart 1994) so that sample trees would represent a wide diameter range (Table 1). After locating trees of a desired species, the individuals were examined for anomalies such as pathogen damage or atypical crown architecture due to proximity to gaps or roads; atypical trees were excluded from sampling. The study trees were chosen from numerous locations within the study area to encompass a range of sites for each species; no trees were taken from the treatment watersheds. Once suitable trees were identified and the diameter measured at breast height (DBH = 1.37 m), they were felled using a chain saw and the following variables were measured.Using a 25 m steel tape, we measured the height from the base of the tree to the base of the live crown (BLC), crown length, and total height to the nearest centimeter. The stem was divided into 1 or 2 m sections, depending on the size of the sample tree, and marked with spray paint; the crown, BLC to the top of the tree, was subsequently divided into thirds and marked. All limbs were removed and separated into crown position (e.g. lower, middle, and upper) based on the origin of the branch. This division accounts for the variation in the ratio of foliage mass to branch mass that occurs from the lower to the upper portion of the crown. A sub-sample branch, representative of the ratio of branch wood to foliage for a given section, was selected from each of the crown positions. This sub-sample was then weighed with a 125 plus/minus 0.05 kg digital scale (Intercomp, ST2000, Minneapolis, MN USA). We then weighed the remaining branches by crown position. The bare stem was cut into the 1 or 2 m sections and the individual log sections were weighed. We then cut a disk approximately 4 cm thick from the base of each log section to be used for determining water content and bark to wood ratios. Additional disks were cut from: the base of the tree, DBH, and BLC, and used to determine cross sectional sapwood area and sapwood volume. If a tree was too large to weigh (i.e. the 1 mm stem sections would exceed the capacity of the 125 kilogram scale), log volume from the base of the tree up to the point offeasible weighing was generated using Newtons log rule (Avery and Burkhart 1994). Disks were cut from the bottom, middle, and top of the log, and their circumferences as well as the total length of the log were recorded. || Laboratory Analysis | We separated the crown sub-samples into foliar and branch components which were then dried to a constant mass at 65 degrees C and weighed to determine moisture content. Prior to drying the

foliage, we selected ten representative leaves and separated the petiole from the leaf blade. The total area of the leaf blades was measured using a leaf area meter (LI-COR 3100, LI-COR, Inc., Lincoln, NE, USA); the blades and petioles were dried (65 degrees C) and weighed to determine specific leaf area (SLA) and the ratio of leaf blade mass to total leaf mass. The fresh weight and circumference (outside bark) were recorded for the disks sampled from the base of each log section; bark and wood were then separated. We dried

the disks (65 degrees C) and weighed the wood and bark separately to determine wood mass:total mass and bark mass:total mass ratios as well as moisture content of the total disk. The disks taken from the base of the tree, DBH, and BLC were stained with a potassium iodide solution to determine heartwood-sapwood boundaries (Kutscha and Sachs 1962). We traced the total disk area and the sapwood-heartwood delineation on acetate sheets and painted them to make them opaque. We then measured heartwood and sapwood area from these tracings on a leaf area meter. The disks from the large stem sections, where volumetric estimations were needed, had a 10degrees wedge cut from the center to the outside edge of the disk (including bark). Wedge volume was found by volumetric displacement (Heinrichs and Lassen 1970) and mass was determined after drying to a constant mass (65 degrees C ) to calculate specific gravity. The total log section mass is then calculated by multiplying the average specific gravity of the wedges for each species by the volume of the log section. || Scaling | The total dry weight of the foliage or branches for a given section was calculated by multiplying the ratio of dried foliage or dried branches to the total dried mass of the crown section sub-sample by the total crown section dry mass. The foliage mass of the crown section can then be multiplied by the specific leaf area (SLA) and by the leaf blade mass:total leaf mass ratio to determine total leaf area for a given crown section. The correction of the leaf blade mass:total leaf mass ratio is necessary because the petiole, which is not used in the leaf area calculations, accounted for 5 to 13% of the total leaf mass in this study for Quercus alba and Carya

spp., respectively. Similarly, we determined the log section dry mass by multiplying (1 - moisture content) by the field wet weight, and calculated total wood mass and bark mass for the section from the ratios of bark or wood to the total disk dry weight. Stem surface area was calculated by multiplying the log section length (e.g. 1 or 2 m) by the average of the circumferences from the disks at the base and top of the log, and summing over all sections. Similarly, we calculated stem volume by multiplying the surface area of the disks by the log section lengths and summing over all sections. The top log section was considered to be conical. The surface area of the volumetrically estimated logs was calculated using a modified version of Newtons log formula where disk circumference was substituted for disk surface area. Total sapwood volume for a tree is given by the sum of the sapwood volume of the branches and the sapwood volume of the stem, which is the difference between the total wood volume (inside bark) and the heartwood volume. For this study the branch volume was assumed to be entirely sapwood; the branch volume is then equal to the total branch dry mass divided by the branch density (see Clark and Schroeder 1986). The geometric solids of total wood volume aand heartwood volume were computed by summing the volumes for the "base to DBH" section (frustrum of a neiloid), the "DBH to the BLC" section (frustrum of a paraboloid), and from the "BLC to the top" section (paraboloid) (Husch et al.1972). || Nitrogen Analysis | Foliar tissue nitrogen concentration was determined from approximately 50 leaves from each dried, crown position sub-sample. Branch tissue nitrogen concentration was determined on arepresentative branch from each crown position sub-sample. The tree as a whole was the experimental unit so the mean of the three crown positions were used in all nitrogen analyses. For stem tissue nitrogen analysis, bark, sapwood from the last two years growth, and a 10 degrees wedge from the remaining wood were sampled from disks equally spaced within the stem. The last two years of sapwood and the remaining wood were used as separation points to correct for sapwood area variation between trees (Son and Gower 1991). We sampled three to five disks per tree depending on tree size. On the smaller trees (greater than 15 cm DBH) up to one half of the bark and sapwood from each disk

was used. All samples were ground with a Wiley mill to pass through a 0.5 mm2 screen (size 40) and analyzed with a combustion elemental analyzer (2400CHN, Perkin Elmer, Norwalk, CT, USA). Nitrogen content per component per tree was found by multiplying the nitrogen concentration for each tissue sample by the total dry mass of that component. Stem wood nitrogen content (excluding bark) was calculated following Son and Gower (1991). || Statistical Analysis | Simple linear regressions (PROC REG, SAS Institute Inc. 1985) were computed using log10 transformed data (to linearize) and took the form: [1] log10 Y = a + b*log10 X Where X is the stem diameter in cm at breast height, Y is the variable (e.g. stem wood, stem bark, sapwood volume, etc.), and a and b are the intercept and slope, respectively. Means were compared using the LSD mean separation test at the

a = 0.05 level for SLA and specific gravity (PROC MEANS, SAS Institute Inc. 1985). Pair-wise comparison of regression coefficients (PROC REG, SAS Institute Inc. 1985) were performed for the ring porous and diffuse porous models relating sapwood volume to DBH and foliage area to cross sectional sapwood area (Chatterjee and Price 1977). Regression analysis was also performed on tissue nitrogen content versus DBH to calculate values for predicted trees of diameters 10, 30, and 50 cm (PROC REG, SAS Institute Inc. 1985). **see Martin et al. (1998) citation below for complete citations of

all references mentioned above**</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Coweeta</keyword><keyword>LTER</keyword><keyword>Allometry</keyword><keyword>Biomass</keyword><keyword>Nitrogen concentration</keyword><keyword>Nitrogen content</keyword><keyword>Sapwood</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>Must adhere to the Coweeta LTER Data Policy (See http://coweeta.uga.edu/policies/data).</para></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://coweeta.uga.edu/summaries/Csummary4004_b.html</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Trees were sampled across the Coweeta Basin and surrounding areas (see online map information below).</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate /><eastBoundingCoordinate /><northBoundingCoordinate /><southBoundingCoordinate /></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1997-06-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>1997-08-01</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><positionName>Coweeta LTER Information Manager</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(828) 524-2128</phone></contact><project scope="document"><title>Coweeta Long Term Ecological Research</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Ted</givenName><surName>Gragson</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>tgragson@earthlink.net</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>James</givenName><surName>Vose</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>jvose@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Brian</givenName><surName>Kloeppel</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>kloeppel@sparc.ecology.uga.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><abstract><para>The Coweeta LTER Research Program has evolved since 1980 from a site-based to a site- and region-based project examining the effects of disturbance

and environmental gradients on biogeochemical cycling, and the underlying

watershed ecosystem processes that regulate and respond to those cycles. 

The objective for the 2002-2008 research is to advance scientific

understanding of the spatial, temporal, and decision-making components of

land use and land-use change in the southern Appalachian Mountains over the

last 200 years, and forecast patterns into the future 30 years.  This will

be accomplished by addressing ecological and socioeconomic aspects of

land-use change while continuing long-term studies of environmental

gradients and natural disturbance regimes.  The result will be a more

complete understanding of ecological dynamics in the southern Appalachian

Mountains that makes possible the development of reasonable forecasts of

its future ecological state. | The guiding hypothesis for the proposed research is that the frequency, intensity, and extent of land use represents human decision-making in

response to socioeconomic and bio-geophysical conditions with consequences

that cascade through ecosystems.  The research activities are organized

into three initiatives: (1) Characterization of the Socio-Natural Template,

(2) Ecosystem Responses to the Socio-Natural Template, and (3) Forecasting

Ecosystem Responses to Changes in the Socio-Natural Template.  The

integrated scientific research will provide both a description as well as

an explanation of the underlying causes of land use and the consequences of

land-use change for southern Appalachian ecosystems and society.  It thus

recognizes the complexity of land use as a process and the research needs

as defined in the LTER Program and the broader scientific community.</para></abstract><funding><para>National Science Foundation. Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed in the material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.</para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=cwt,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>4004.csv</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>4004.csv</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://cwt33.ecology.uga.edu/data/4004.csv</url></online></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>species</attributeName><attributeLabel>species</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Species codes</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>Acru</code><definition>Acer rubrum L.</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Bele</code><definition>Betula lenta L.</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Casp</code><definition>Carya species</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Cofl</code><definition>Cornus florida L.</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Litu</code><definition>Liriodendron tulipifera L.</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Oxar</code><definition>Oxydendrum arboreum (L. DC.</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Qual</code><definition>Quercus alba L.</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Quco</code><definition>Quercus coccinea Muenchh.</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Qupr</code><definition>Quercus prinus L.</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Quru</code><definition>Quercus rubra L.)</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>DBH</attributeName><attributeLabel>DBH</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Diameter at breast height (1.37m)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>site</attributeName><attributeLabel>site</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>site codes where samples were collected, mulb, ball, cold, dyke, shpe, drym, brkr</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>site codes where samples were collected, mulb, ball, cold, dyke, shpe, drym, brkr</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>elev</attributeName><attributeLabel>elev</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>elevation above sea level</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>meter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>aspect</attributeName><attributeLabel>aspect</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>location aspect</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>slope</attributeName><attributeLabel>slope</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>location slope</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>slopepos</attributeName><attributeLabel>slopepos</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>position on the slope</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>mid</code><definition>midslope</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>cov</code><definition>cove</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>rid</code><definition>ridge</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>canopycl</attributeName><attributeLabel>canopycl</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>canopy class</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>s</code><definition>supressed</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>i</code><definition>intermediate</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>c</code><definition>codominant</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>d</code><definition>dominant</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>age</attributeName><attributeLabel>age</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>tree age taken from basal disks</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>height</attributeName><attributeLabel>height</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>total tree height taken from ground to tip (m)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>meter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>tbrcmass</attributeName><attributeLabel>tbrcmass</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>dry branch mass of the top third of the crown (kg)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>kilogram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>tfolmass</attributeName><attributeLabel>tfolmass</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>dry foliage mass of the top third of the crown (kg)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>kilogram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>tSLA</attributeName><attributeLabel>tSLA</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>specific leaf area of the top third of the crown (cm2g-1)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>centimeterSquaredPerGram</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>tfolarea</attributeName><attributeLabel>tfolarea</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>foliage area of the top third of the crown (m2)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>squareMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>mbrcmass</attributeName><attributeLabel>mbrcmass</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>dry branch mass of the middle third of the crown (kg)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>kilogram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>mfolmass</attributeName><attributeLabel>mfolmass</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>dry foliage mass of the middle third of the crown (kg)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>kilogram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>mSLA</attributeName><attributeLabel>mSLA</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>specific leaf area of the middle third of the crown (cm2g-1)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>centimeterSquaredPerGram</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>mfolarea</attributeName><attributeLabel>mfolarea</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>foliage area of the middle third of the crown (m2)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>squareMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>bbrcmass</attributeName><attributeLabel>bbrcmass</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>dry branch mass of the bottom third of the crown (kg)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>kilogram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>bfolmass</attributeName><attributeLabel>bfolmass</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>dry foliage mass of the bottom third of the crown (kg)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>kilogram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>bSLA</attributeName><attributeLabel>bSLA</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>specific leaf area of the bottom third of the crown (cm2 g-1)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>centimeterSquaredPerGram</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>bfolarea</attributeName><attributeLabel>bfolarea</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>foliage area of the bottom third of the crown (m2)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>squareMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>brcmass</attributeName><attributeLabel>brcmass</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>total branch mass for the tree (kg)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>kilogram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>folmass</attributeName><attributeLabel>folmass</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>total foliage mass for the tree (kg)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>kilogram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>SLA</attributeName><attributeLabel>SLA</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>mean specific leaf area for the tree (cm2g-1)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>centimeterSquaredPerGram</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>folarea</attributeName><attributeLabel>folarea</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>total foliage area for the tree (m2)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>squareMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>stemmass</attributeName><attributeLabel>stemmass</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>stem mass [brach and stem wood] (kg)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>kilogram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>barkmass</attributeName><attributeLabel>barkmass</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>mass of bark only (kg)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>kilogram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>woodmass</attributeName><attributeLabel>woodmass</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>mass of wood only (kg)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>kilogram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>stemSA</attributeName><attributeLabel>stemSA</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>surface area of the stem (m2)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>squareMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>stemV</attributeName><attributeLabel>stemV</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>volume of the stem (m3)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>cubicMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>totV</attributeName><attributeLabel>totV</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>volume of the stem and branches (m3)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>cubicMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>biomass</attributeName><attributeLabel>biomass</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>stem mass, branch mass, and foliage mass (kg)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>kilogram</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>totsapwd</attributeName><attributeLabel>totsapwd</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>stem sapwood volume and branch volume (m3)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>cubicMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>saparea</attributeName><attributeLabel>saparea</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>cross sectional sapwood are a breast height (1.37m) (cm2)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>squareCentimeters</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>obsrvSG</attributeName><attributeLabel>obsrvSG</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>calculated wood specific gravity from the study</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>calculated wood specific gravity from the study</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>C_SSG</attributeName><attributeLabel>C_SSG</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>published wood specific gravity (Clark and Schroeder 1986)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>published wood specific gravity (Clark and Schroeder 1986)</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>C_SSGbrc</attributeName><attributeLabel>C_SSGbrc</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>published branch specific gravity (Clark and Schroeder 1986)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>published branch specific gravity (Clark and Schroeder 1986)</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>topfolN</attributeName><attributeLabel>topfolN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of the foliage from branches originating in top one third of crown</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>midfolN</attributeName><attributeLabel>midfolN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of the foliage from branches originating in middle one third of crown</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>bfolN</attributeName><attributeLabel>bfolN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of the foliage from branches originating in botton one third of crown</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>topbrcN</attributeName><attributeLabel>topbrcN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of the branches originating in top one third of crown</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>midbrcN</attributeName><attributeLabel>midbrcN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of the branches originating in top one third of crown</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>bbrcN</attributeName><attributeLabel>bbrcN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of the branches originating in top one third of crown</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>barkN</attributeName><attributeLabel>barkN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of the stem bark</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>sapwdN</attributeName><attributeLabel>sapwdN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of sapwood from the last two years of growth (1996-1997)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>hrtwdN</attributeName><attributeLabel>hrtwdN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of the heartwood from the remaining wood wedge</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><unitList><unit id="centimeterSquaredPerGram" /></unitList></additionalMetadata></ns0:eml>