<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-luq.75.3" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 C:/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><shortName>LUQMetadata75</shortName><title>Fern sporophyte growth observation at the Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF)</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Joanne</givenName><surName>Sharpe</surName></individualName><organizationName>Sharplex Services</organizationName><positionName>Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><city>Edgecomb</city><administrativeArea>ME</administrativeArea><postalCode>04556</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(207)882-5989</phone><phone phonetype="fax">voice</phone><electronicMailAddress>joannesharpe@email.com</electronicMailAddress></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Joanne</givenName><surName>Sharpe</surName></individualName><organizationName>Sharplex Services</organizationName><positionName>Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><city>Edgecomb</city><administrativeArea>ME</administrativeArea><postalCode>04556</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(207)882-5989</phone><phone phonetype="fax">voice</phone><electronicMailAddress>joannesharpe@email.com</electronicMailAddress></metadataProvider><language>english</language><abstract><para><literalLayout>Long-term (20-year) monitoring sites have been established in the Luquillo Experimental Forest. Individuals of approximately 20 species of ferns are being monitored on a regular basis to determine plant life history classes, leaf production rates, fertility characteristics and leaf damage levels. Effects of natural disturbance will be interpreted in light of these parameters. The study includes sites at El Verde, and Espiritu Santo and Bisley watersheds. A comparative study of ferns in the mangrove community at the Jobos Bay National Estuarine Research Reserve was started in January 1998 and completed in January 2001. Comparisons of similar species will also be made at temperate sites. Data for Thelypteris angustifolia from 1991 through 1995 were copied to a separate file (Fernthan.txt) when preliminary results on this species were analyzed and published (Sharpe, 1997).  Note: Data file 1(FERNTHAN) contains data, on a line-line basis, about individual leaves. Information in this file includes measurements and observations as well as leaf location and identification information. Leaves in these files were monitored three times a year from the time the plant was first included in the study until the plant died, dissappeared, or was dropped from the study. A selection of data from the long-term project data set FERNTHEANG was copied into the file FERNTHAN for public access after use for a preliminary publication (Sharpe, 1997).</literalLayout></para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>pr (comparative site)</keyword><keyword>life history</keyword><keyword>luquillo experimental forest (LEF)</keyword><keyword>phenology</keyword><keyword>rainforest</keyword><keyword>jobos bay national estuarine research</keyword><keyword>sonadora</keyword><keyword>spore production</keyword><keyword>disturbance</keyword><keyword>aguirre</keyword><keyword>bisley watersheds</keyword><keyword>demography</keyword><keyword>ferns</keyword><keyword>espiritu santo watershed</keyword><keywordThesaurus>Assigned by Principal Investigator</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>population dynamics</keyword><keyword>disturbance patterns</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LTER Core</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>lower montane wet</keyword><keyword>mangrove</keyword><keyword>plant lifehistory</keyword><keyword>primary production</keyword><keyword>rainfall</keyword><keyword>plant growth</keyword><keyword>seasonality</keyword><keyword>hurricane</keyword><keyword>disturbance</keyword><keyword>flood</keyword><keyword>bisley watersheds</keyword><keyword>ferns</keyword><keyword>el verde</keyword><keyword>LEF</keyword><keyword>drought</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LEF LTER Data Sets</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>Vegetation Dynamics</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LEF LTER Data Categories</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><title>ADEQUATE ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><para><literalLayout>The scientists, the LEF-LTER Program, and the USDA International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITF) must receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data by other scientists, and the LEF LTER program must receive two copies of any publication using that data. One copy will be placed at the IITF library and one copy will stay with the LEF LTER Data Manager. A suggested format for this acknowledgement will be distributed along with the requested data.</literalLayout></para><section><title>Acknowledgements for NSF Support.</title><para><literalLayout>The following paragraph should be included in the acknowledgements of all publications funded in any way by current and future LTER grants:</literalLayout><literalLayout>This research was performed under grant #DEB-0218039 from the National Science Foundation to the Institute of Tropical Ecosystem Studies (IEET), University of Puerto Rico, and the International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITFR) as part of the Long-Term Ecological Research Program in the Luquillo Experimental Forest. Additional support was provided by the Forest Service (U.S. Department of Agriculture) and the University of Puerto Rico.</literalLayout></para></section></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb75/metadata/lterdb75.htm#DATA</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage id="geoReference" scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF) covers 11,231 hectares and reaches 1079 m above sea level. It has a warm and wet climate and includes a variety of tropical habitats and forest types and streams, and a high diversity of plants and animals. A key feature of these ecosystems is disturbance. Hurricanes, landslides, and human disturbance have shaped the forest, and research by LUQ has stimulated a new appreciation of the significance of large-scale disturbances in tropical forested ecosystems and the key role of plants and animals in shaping the response to these events. Hurricanes occurring one and 10 years after LUQ began in 1988 provided landscape-scale natural experiments which are still followed closely.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-65.92</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-65.7</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>18.35</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>18.23</southBoundingCoordinate><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>20</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>1060</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Joanne</givenName><surName>Sharpe</surName></individualName><organizationName>Sharplex Services</organizationName><positionName>Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><city>Edgecomb</city><administrativeArea>ME</administrativeArea><postalCode>04556</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(207)882-5989</phone><phone phonetype="fax">voice</phone><electronicMailAddress>joannesharpe@email.com</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>Luquillo Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>University of Puerto Rico, Rio Piedras</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>P. O. Box 21910</deliveryPoint><city>San Juan</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931-1910</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787) 764 - 0000 (ext. 4940)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787) 772 -1481</phone><electronicMailAddress>nbrokaw@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://luq.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Individual sporophytes representing a range of life history classes (mainly spore-producing sporophytes) were selected for monitoring. Plants were chosen at one or more sites with relatively large concentrations of each species. Selected plants are mostly well off the main trails and accessible for measuring without damage to the surrounding areas. Initially, a representative sample (at least ten individuals, if possible) of plants at each site were selected. Additional individuals are added at later monitoring periods to fill gaps in life history class samples. At sites where it is possible to monitor all ferns present, new plants are added to the study when they are large enough to tag. Each plant is given a unique number and each of the leaves on the plant is measured and described. Each plant is identified with a white plastic tag attached one of the younger leaves and microhabitat data on substrate, slope and neighboring plants is recorded and maintained in a separate plant control file. Each leaf is identified with a small segment of colored plastic covered wire. Plants are monitored at intervals of 4 months during phase 1 (through January 30, 2001) and annually during phase 2 (through January 30, 2011). Data sheets were prepared prior to each visit to reflect the leaf additions, loss and changes to plants observed during the previous monitoring period. Both plant location and leaf identification information are included on the data sheets. For each plant in the study, the disappearance of previously monitored leaves is noted and new leaves are measured.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep></methods><project scope="document"><title>Fern Population Dynamics</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Joanne</givenName><surName>Sharpe</surName></individualName><role>Associate</role></personnel><abstract><para><literalLayout>Ferns are an important part of the understory of many tropic forests, yet nothing is known about their leaf turnover rates, hence their contribution to the litter layer and overall functioning of the forest ecosystem. This long-term project addresses that question by marking and monitoring each leaf produced by over a thousand individuals representing over 20 different species. Plants and their leaves were observed at four month intervals for ten years starting in September 1991 (Phase 1) and then at one year intervals for an additional ten years starting in January 2001. Seasonality in leaf and spore production, as well as effects of drought and hurricanes are noted. Defoliation experiments with several species are being conducted to determine the limits of disturbance effects.</literalLayout></para></abstract><funding><para><literalLayout>own</literalLayout></para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=LUQ,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>Fernthan.txt</entityName><entityDescription>Thelypteris angustifolia(selected records copied from FERNTHEANG for publication 1997)</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>Fernthan.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb75/data/Fernthan.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReferenceFernthan.txt" scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1991-09-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>1996-01-30</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Individual sporophytes representing a range of life history classes (mainly spore-producing sporophytes) were selected for monitoring. Plants were chosen at one or more sites with relatively large concentrations of each species. Selected plants are mostly well off the main trails and accessible for measuring without damage to the surrounding areas. Initially, a representative sample (at least ten individuals, if possible) of plants at each site were selected. Additional individuals are added at later monitoring periods to fill gaps in life history class samples. At sites where it is possible to monitor all ferns present, new plants are added to the study when they are large enough to tag. Each plant is given a unique number and each of the leaves on the plant is measured and described. Each plant is identified with a white plastic tag attached one of the younger leaves and microhabitat data on substrate, slope and neighboring plants is recorded and maintained in a separate plant control file. Each leaf is identified with a small segment of colored plastic covered wire. Plants are monitored at intervals of 4 months during phase 1 (through January 30, 2001) and annually during phase 2 (through January 30, 2011). Data sheets were prepared prior to each visit to reflect the leaf additions, loss and changes to plants observed during the previous monitoring period. Both plant location and leaf identification information are included on the data sheets. For each plant in the study, the disappearance of previously monitored leaves is noted and new leaves are measured.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReferenceFernthan.txt</references></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>Every four months (January, May, September)</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Species code, abbreviated</attributeName><attributeLabel>SPCODE</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Code for scientific name of the species of fern, abbreviated to two letters GS (usually genus and species initial) to save space in files. A value for this variable must be present in this file.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>AD = TA = Thelypteris angustifolia. Code for scientific name of the species of fern, abbreviated to two letters GS (usually genus and species initial) to save space in files. A value for this variable must be present in this file</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Profile code</attributeName><attributeLabel>PR</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Code indicating type of monitoring done on the leaf. A value for this variable must be present in this file.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>P</code><definition>profile record, one for each leaf node observed (generally signifies a mature leaf)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>S</code><definition>starter record  for leaves which are not mature (type C or I) when first encountered (changed to a P in the next monitoring period if the leaf is gone)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>D</code><definition>remeasurement of an immature leaf during the same monitoring period as a Starter measurement was taken.  Note (985): if a leaf has matured at the time of re-measurement this code becomes a P (A) though the day remonitored and differences remains</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Added record code</attributeName><attributeLabel>ADD</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>This code indicates whether the leaf was measured during the initial encounter with the plant; or during subsequent monitoring sessions.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>blank= If profile code is P, then the leaf was measured during the initial encounter with the plant--hence its actual age cannot be known. If profile code is S, D, or R, this code must be blank, A = Leaf added to plant during a monitoring period following the initial encounter with the plant. New plant to site where no leaves had been seen before.</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>ID number of plant</attributeName><attributeLabel>ID</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The sequentially assigned number on the tag that is affixed to the plant when it is old enough not to be damaged by a tag. For Phase 2; note that ID's greater than 2999and less than 9000 are temporary; do not involve tagging a specific plant and are assigned by year (ex 4000 = 2004). A value for this variable must be present in this file.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>The sequentially assigned number on the tag that is affixed to the plant when it is old enough not to be damaged by a tag. For Phase 2, note that ID's greater than 2999and less than 9000 are temporary, do not involve tagging a specific plant and are assigned by year (ex 4000 = 2004). A value for this variable must be present in this file. Ranges from 1 to 99999</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Sub-ID of plant</attributeName><attributeLabel>SI</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>A letter designation indicating either that 1) the plant is too young for a tag to be attached (A; B; C; D; etc.) or is a branch of the parent number; or 2) the plant was considered to be one plant at an earlier time; but is now considered to be two or more plants (S) or 3) the continuity of monitoring was broken for some reason and the plant was re-profiled (S) (Such records are archived; and the sub-id not used in continuation of monitoring).</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>A - J</code><definition>the plant is too young for a tag to be attached or is a branch of the parent number</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>S</code><definition>the plant was considered to be one plant at an earlier time but is now considered to be two or more plants</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Sequence of leaf</attributeName><attributeLabel>SEQ</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The oldest appearing leaf when the plant is first profiled is assigned the sequence number 1. Each youngerleaf;and each leaf that emerges during later monitoring periods is assigned the next number in sequence. A value for this variable must be present in this file. Note: Originally letters of the alphabet were used to indicate sequence of leaf emergence. As of January; 1994 all letter were converted to numbers: A was converted to1; B to 2; C to 3; D to 4; E to 5; F to 6; G to 7; H to 8; I to 9; J to 10 K to 11; L to 12; M to 13; N to 14; O to 15; P to 16; Q to 17; R to 18; S to 19; T to 20 U to 21; V to 22; W to 23; X to 24; Y to 25; Z to 26; AA to 27; AB to 28; AC to 29 AD to 30; ETC.)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>The oldest appearing leaf when the plant is first profiled is assigned the sequence number 1. Each youngerleaf;and each leaf that emerges during later monitoring periods is assigned the next number in sequence. A value for this variable must be present in this file. Note: Originally letters of the alphabet were used to indicate sequence of leaf emergence. As of January; 1994 all letter were converted to numbers: A was converted to1; B to 2; C to 3; D to 4; E to 5; F to 6; G to 7; H to 8; I to 9; J to 10 K to 11; L to 12; M to 13; N to 14; O to 15; P to 16; Q to 17; R to 18; S to 19; T to 20 U to 21; V to 22; W to 23; X to 24; Y to 25; Z to 26; AA to 27; AB to 28; AC to 29 AD to 30; ETC.)</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Wire color</attributeName><attributeLabel>WIRE</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Color of the 6-10 cm plastic insulated copper wire attached to leaf when first measured. Used only for leaf identification in the field when all individual leaves are measured.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>R</code><definition>Red</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Y</code><definition>Yellow</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>B</code><definition>Blue</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>G</code><definition>Green</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>O</code><definition>Orange</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>P</code><definition>Purple</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>K</code><definition>Black</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>N</code><definition>Brown</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>A</code><definition>Gray</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>W</code><definition>White</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>blank</code><definition>leaf too immature to attach wire without damage</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Tagged leaf code</attributeName><attributeLabel>TAG</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>A code to indicate that leaf has now or has had in the past a label affixed to it.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>L</code><definition>label attached at some point while leaf monitored</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Blank</code><definition>no label ever attached.</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Type of leaf</attributeName><attributeLabel>TYPELEAF(S1)</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Type of leaf in terms of reproductive status. Must be present. Note that for Profile code S or D (croziers), this code will be entered some time after the mature leaf has been observed.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>S</code><definition>Sterile (photosynthetic only; no spores)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>F</code><definition>Fertile (sporophyll, with sori present)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>U</code><definition>Unknown</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>C</code><definition>Crozier, therefore unknown</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>L</code><definition>Leaf base only</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Type of leaf modifier</attributeName><attributeLabel>TN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Additional information about the Type code</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Blank = no modifier needed</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Status of leaf</attributeName><attributeLabel>STAT</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Maturation status of leaf. A value for this variable must be present in this file.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>T</code><definition>Fully expanded leaf (was M in earlier field notes) mature leaf</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>I</code><definition>Immature.  not fully expanded (if no change in leaf length in subsequent monitoring period may be changed to T. If both I and B then enter I and put B in the gone code.)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>B</code><definition>Broken leaf (or cut if C follows In SN field. If both I (immature) and B then enter I and put B in the gone code)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>C</code><definition>crozier</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Status of leaf modifier</attributeName><attributeLabel>SN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Additional information about the maturation status of the leaf.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>n</code><definition>when describing Broken leaf (status B) it represents the number of pairs left.  when describing Crozier (status C) it indicates a pair of leaflets at top of coil observed counting from first (lowermost) pair unrolled</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>0</code><definition>when describing Broken leaf (status B) it indicates a broken tip. when describing Crozier (status C) it indicates that only tip still coiled</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>blank</code><definition>when describing Broken leaf (status B) it indicates that only petiole is left</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>99</code><definition>when describing Broken leaf (status B) it indicates that only petiole is left</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Leaf condition</attributeName><attributeLabel>LEAF</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Code indicates if all of the leaf is present in terms of expected number of leaflets for pinnate leaves and for simple leaves; if a portion of the lamina is missing. A value for this variable must be present in this file.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>A</code><definition>All there</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>N</code><definition>Some not there (was M in earlier field notes)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>n</code><definition>number of pairs of leaflets present (if minority)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>T</code><definition>terminal leaflet only left</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Leaf condition modifier</attributeName><attributeLabel>LN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Additional information about the development or damage status of the leaf. Present if Leaf condition code is present unless too many to count. An integer n indicates the number of missinig leaflets.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Additional information about the development or damage status of the leaf. Present if Leaf condition code is present unless too many to count. An integer n indicates the number of missinig leaflets.</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Condition of leaf surface</attributeName><attributeLabel>COND</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Describes various leaf surface characteristics.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>C</code><definition>Clean and mature green in color no unusual surface characteristics</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>D</code><definition>Damaged or dead</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>G</code><definition>Light green in color recently matured leaf I) Insect damage (herbivory)</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Petiole length</attributeName><attributeLabel>PET</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Petiole measured from rhizome to base of lamina or lowest pair of leaflets.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Lamina length</attributeName><attributeLabel>LAM</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Length of leaf from start of lamina or lowest pair of leaflets to tip. A Blank indicates simple leaf or crozier which has not reached the lowest set of leaflets in the unrolling process; or a leaf that broke off in the petiole</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Length of leaf from start of lamina or lowest pair of leaflets to tip. A Blank indicates simple leaf or crozier which has not reached the lowest set of leaflets in the unrolling process; or a leaf that broke off in the petiole</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Pairs of pinnae (leaflets)</attributeName><attributeLabel>PRS</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of pairs of leaflets with a clearly defined (though possible very short) petiolule on pinnate leaves. For simple leaves; this field may be either blank or 0. 1. Counted in field; usually on the right side with adaxial surface up. If pairs on both side are counted (occasionally done on smaller leaves) and are unequal in number; then .5 is used to average the number on both sides of rachis. 2. For leaves first encountered as croziers (Profile codes S and D); the number of pairs counted when the leaf is mature is inserted in this field later. A value for this variable must be present for pinnate leaves. Blank when first measured if crozier has not completely unrolled. Blank when data analyzed if leaf broken or gone before pairs could be counted.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>Blank</code><codeExplanation>Blank when first measured if crozier has not completely unrolled. Blank when data analyzed if leaf broken or gone before pairs could be counted.</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Length of leaf</attributeName><attributeLabel>LEN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Combined length of petiole and lamina. (Note that for Profile code D final length is noted in Orientation field.) (Calculated: Sum of petiole and lamina length). A value for this variable must be present in this file.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Difference in length</attributeName><attributeLabel>DIF</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Difference between: 1) PR code = R: leaf length and length on P record (if not first B record) or previous R record if there is one and Status of leaf is a B or blank if diff. is on a record with PR code P. 2) PR code = S: leaf length and length on P or R. Blank if not applicable.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Site Code</attributeName><attributeLabel>SITE</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Numerical code assigned to area of the forest where monitored ferns are located. A value for this variable must be present in this file.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Numerical code assigned to area of the forest where monitored ferns are located. A value for this variable must be present in this file.</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Orientation of leaf</attributeName><attributeLabel>OR</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Orientation of the leaf as it emerges from the apex with respect to some fixed background feature. Used in combination with wire color to identify a leaf when the plant is monitored. This field is used for the final length of the leaf (cm) and is blank if leaf is broken or gone before measured. When an integer in this field it represents the number of degrees around apex. Blank before degree system instituted; after that; should be present.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>UPS</code><definition>leaf is oriented up</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>DNS</code><definition>leaf is oriented down</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>0</code><definition>0 degrees around apex.orientation of leaf is up</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>180</code><definition>180 degrees around apex. orientation of leaf is down</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>90</code><definition>90 degrees around apex. orientation of leaf is left</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>270</code><definition>270 degrees around apex. orientation of leaf is right when looking at direction of the extension of a leaf.</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Monitor cycle month</attributeName><attributeLabel>MS</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of months since the beginning of the study with September; 1991 = 1.Records month in which monitoring took place and isused with GS to calculate leaf life span. A value for this variable must be present in this file.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Monitoring period year</attributeName><attributeLabel>MYRPHEN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Year that a plant was added to the study or a leaf was known to have emerged and/or matured or was remonitored. Indicates the year during which the recorded growth took place, not monitoring date year (ie: if monitored in January). A value for this variable must be present in this file.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>YYYY</formatString></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Leaf or plant monitoring season code</attributeName><attributeLabel>MPHEN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The year is divided into three "seasons" (between monitoring dates).: For a leaf with an ADD code, the monitoring season is the season in which the leaf is assumed to have emerged or matured as noted at the next monitoring date early in the month following the end of the season. If there is no ADD code, then MPHEN represents the first time a leaf is measured when a plant is added to ths tudy</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>1</code><definition>= January/April,</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>2</code><definition>May/August,</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>3</code><definition>September/December</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Gone cycle month</attributeName><attributeLabel>GS</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Number of months from beginning of study (September; 1991) to month of monitoring date when a previously monitored leaf or plant is no longer part of the study. On leaf monitoring records; used only on records with PR code of P. This field is left blank unless leaf is gone.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Gone year</attributeName><attributeLabel>GYRPHEN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Year in which a leaf or plant is observed or assumed to be dead at the next monitoring date.On leaf monitoring records, used only on records with PR code of P, and not on records with a Gone code (GC) of X, T, E, F, Q or B. This field is left blank if leaf is still present or if gone, then year of death not known.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>YYYY</formatString></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Leaf or plant gone season code</attributeName><attributeLabel>GPHEN</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The year is divided into three "seasons" (between monitoring dates). Leaf or plant gone season is the season in which the leaf or plant was assumed to have died as noted at the next monitoring date early in the month following the end of the season. If annual monitoring, then 0 indicates leaf or plant gone during the previous year. On leaf monitoring files, is found only the records with PR code of P. This field is left blank if year and/or season of deathisnot known.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>1</code><definition>= January/April,</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>2</code><definition>May/August,</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>3</code><definition>September/December</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Gone code</attributeName><attributeLabel>GC</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Code indicating the condition under which a leaf was no longer present in the study. This field is left blank if leaf is present.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>B</code><definition>crozier or immature leaf broken before full length known</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>G</code><definition>no sign of leaf after four months for Leaf phenology/life span codes</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>H</code><definition>wHip-petiole and rachis only present (no leaflets if that is typical of species) or Dead with leaflets still attached if that is typical of species (After four months) for Leaf phenology/life span codes</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>D</code><definition>Dead with leaflets still attached if losing leaflets is typical of species for Leaf phenology/life span codes,</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Z</code><definition>Leaf gone because its plant is assumed or known to be dead (may not be verified until next monitoring period) for Leaf phenology/life span codesT</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>W</code><definition>not found for temporarily and death date not known</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Day re-monitored</attributeName><attributeLabel>DAY</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Date of month that first and subsequent measurements were taken during the same monitoring month. A value for this field must be present when PR code is S; D and/or E if leaf remonitored during the same month.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>DD</formatString></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Day difference</attributeName><attributeLabel>DDIF</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Difference between date first observed and date next observed during a single monitoring period. A value for this field must be present when PR code is D or E.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Leaf Width</attributeName><attributeLabel>WIDTH</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Width of the leaf if measured.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset></ns0:eml>