<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-luq.115.1" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 C:/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><shortName>LUQMetadata115</shortName><title>Short-term disappearance of foliar litter of three tree species native to rain forest of Puerto Rico</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>William H.</givenName><surName>McDowell</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of New Hamshire</organizationName><positionName>Principal Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Natural Resources</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>215 James Hall</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>56 College Rd</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">787-749-4346(279)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">787-749-4462</phone><electronicMailAddress>bill.mcdowell@unh.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.unh.edu/natural-resources/fac-bmcdowell.html</onlineUrl></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Neal</givenName><surName>Sullivan</surName></individualName><organizationName>Miami University</organizationName><positionName>Visiting Assistant Professor</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Botany Department</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>346 Pearson Hall</deliveryPoint><city>Oxford</city><administrativeArea>OH</administrativeArea><postalCode>45056</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>neal.sullivan@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.nsforestry.com/</onlineUrl></metadataProvider><language>english</language><abstract><para><literalLayout>Litter disappearance was examined before (1989) and after (1990) Hurricane Hugo in the Luquillo Experimental Forest, Puerto Rico using mesh litterbags containing abscised Cyrilla racemiflora or Dacryodes excelsa leaves or fresh Prestoea montana leaves. Biomass and nitrogen dynamics were compared among: i) species; ii) mid- and high-elevation forest types; iii) riparian and upland sites; and iv) among pre- and post-hurricane disturbed environments. Biomass disappearance was compared using multiple regression and negative exponential models in which the slopes were estimates of the decomposition rates subsequent to apparent leaching losses and the y-intercepts were indices of initial mass losses (leaching). C. racemiflora leaves with low nitrogen (0.39 %) and high lignin (22.1 %) content decayed at a low rate and immobilized available nitrogen. D. excelsa leaves had moderate nitrogen (0.67 %) and lignin (16.6 %) content, decayed at moderate rates, and maintained the initial nitrogen mass. P. montana foliage had high nitrogen (1.76 %) and moderate lignin (16.7 %) content and rapidly lost both mass and nitrogen. There were not significant differences in litter disappearance and nitrogen dynamics among forest types and slope positions. Initial mass loss of C. racemiflora leaves was lower in 1990 but the subsequent decomposition rate did not change. Initial mass losses and the overall decomposition rates were lower in 1990 than in 1989 for D. excelsa. D. excelsa and C. racemiflora litter immobilized nitrogen in 1990 but released 10-15% of their initial N in 1989, whereas P. montana released nitrogen in both years (25-40 %). Observed differences in litter disappearance rates between years may have been due to differences in the timing of precipitation. Foliar litter inputs during post-hurricane recovery of vegetation in Puerto Rico may serve to immobilize and conserve site nitrogen.</literalLayout></para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Decomposition; leaf litter; Hurricane; Bisley; Icacos; Nitrogen; Cyrilla racemi</keyword><keyword>BISLEY WATERSHEDS</keyword><keyword>DECOMPOSITION</keyword><keyword>HURRICANE</keyword><keyword>ICACOS WATERSHED</keyword><keyword>LITTERFALL</keyword><keyword>NITROGEN</keyword><keyword>OTHER</keyword><keyword>PALMS</keyword><keyword>PALMS</keyword><keyword>PEER REVIEWED JOURNAL</keyword><keyword>RIPARIAN</keyword><keyword>TREES</keyword><keyword>Inorganic Inputs and Nutrient Movements</keyword><keyword>Litter breakdown</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><title>ADEQUATE ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><para><literalLayout>The scientists, the LEF-LTER Program, and the                                     USDA International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITF) must                                     receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data by other                                     scientists, and the LEF LTER program must receive two copies of                                     any publication using that data. One copy will be placed at the                                     IITF library and one copy will stay with the LEF LTER Data                                     Manager. A suggested format for this acknowledgement will be                                     distributed along with the requested data.</literalLayout></para><section><title>Acknowledgements for NSF Support.</title><para><literalLayout>The following paragraph should be                                         included in the acknowledgements of all publications funded                                         in any way by current and future LTER grants:</literalLayout><literalLayout>This research was performed under grant                                         #DEB-0218039 from the National Science Foundation to the                                         Institute of Tropical Ecosystem Studies (IEET), University                                         of Puerto Rico, and the International Institute of Tropical                                         Forestry (IITFR) as part of the Long-Term Ecological                                         Research Program in the Luquillo Experimental Forest.                                         Additional support was provided by the Forest Service (U.S.                                         Department of Agriculture) and the University of Puerto                                         Rico.</literalLayout></para></section></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb115/metadata/lterdb115.htm#DATA</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF) covers                                 11,231 hectares and reaches 1079 m above sea level. It has a warm                                 and wet climate and includes a variety of tropical habitats and                                 forest types and streams, and a high diversity of plants and                                 animals. A key feature of these ecosystems is disturbance.                                 Hurricanes, landslides, and human disturbance have shaped the                                 forest, and research by LUQ has stimulated a new appreciation of the                                 significance of large-scale disturbances in tropical forested                                 ecosystems and the key role of plants and animals in shaping the                                 response to these events. Hurricanes occurring one and 10 years                                 after LUQ began in 1988 provided landscape-scale natural experiments                                 which are still followed closely.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-65.92</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-65.7</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>18.35</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>18.23</southBoundingCoordinate><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>20</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>1060</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>William H.</givenName><surName>McDowell</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of New Hamshire</organizationName><positionName>Principal Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Natural Resources</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>215 James Hall</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>56 College Rd</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">787-749-4346(279)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">787-749-4462</phone><electronicMailAddress>bill.mcdowell@unh.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.unh.edu/natural-resources/fac-bmcdowell.html</onlineUrl></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>Luquillo Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>University of Puerto Rico, Rio Piedras</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>P. O. Box 21910</deliveryPoint><city>San Juan</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931-1910</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787) 764 - 0000 (ext. 4940)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787) 772 -1481</phone><electronicMailAddress>nbrokaw@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://luq.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Leaf Litter Samples: Recently abscised D. excelsa leaflets for each year were collected immediately prior to each study period from the forest floor near the El Verde field station (350 m elev.). Recently abscised C. racemiflora leaves were collected at or near the Icacos site for each year and also about 1.5 km south of the El Verde field station in 1990 (575 m elevation). Fresh (green) P. montana foliage was used due to the inconsistent and gradual way the species replaces fronds. Fronds were collected near the Icacos site, leaflets were stripped from the fronds and cut into 15-20 cm segments. The rhachi of the fronds were discarded. Foliage for the 1989 study was stored as collected for two days before being weighed. To improve our estimates of initial dry mass, the foliage collected for the 1990 study was air-dried for three days before being weighed. An unknown amount of moisture was lost from litter during storage in 1990. Foliage of a single species was weighed and placed in 20 cm by 30 cm litterbags (~1 mm fiberglass mesh). A sample of about one per six litterbags (randomly stratified across the processing interval) was retained and dried to later estimate the initial moisture, nitrogen, lignin, cellulose, and ash content of treatment samples. Between 8 and 14 g (oven-dry equivalent, Table 1) of foliage were placed in each litterbag, although the dry-mass per litterbag varied by less than one g for a given species and study year.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep></methods><project scope="document"><title>Litterfall and Decomposition</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>William H.</givenName><surName>McDowell</surName></individualName><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><abstract><para><literalLayout>Understanding the long-term impact of deforestation on ecosystem structure and function of tropical forests may aid in designing future conservation programs to preserve biodiversity and sustain ecosystem productivity. We examine forest structure, tree species composition, litterfall (fine and coarse) due to Hurricane Hugo and subsequent fine annual litterfall inputs, litterfall rate, and leaf litter decomposition.  Prestoea montana (R. Grah.) Nichols, Dacryodes excelsa (Vahl.), and Cyrilla racemiflora. Hurricane Hugo (August, 1989) provided a unique opportunity to study effects of this type of natural disturbance on decomposition. With some modifications study was repeated in 1990 with some changes in the design which allowed for comparisons of short -term foliar litter biomass and nitrogen dynamics: (1) among the three species, (between the colorado and tabonuco forest types, (3) between riparian and upland sites, and (4) between pre- and post-hurricane environments.  History of litterfall and decomposition studies (MRCE experiment) at the Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF)  1) forest fertilization (complete versus none); 2) transplant experiments using common gardens at high and low elevation, with and without wind protection at high elevation. In addition, phenology of leaves was studied in the dwarf forest to determine the longevity of leaves in the canopy. The occurrence of Hurricane Hugo in September 1989, just as the forest plot fertilization experiments were to begin, neccesitated the addition of a hurricane debris-removal treatment as a second type of control in the lower elevation tabonuco forest. The hurricane also changed the nature of the study into one of looking at changes in forest composition and the recovery of forest productivity in response to fertilization and hurricane debris-removal. Seedling, sapling, herbaceous plant, and fern responses, as well as measurements of light availability and canopy closure were added to the originally planned measurements of tree diameter growth, leaf litter production, and fine root production and turnover. Another hurricane in 1998 (Hurricane Georges) presented an opportunity to look at the effects of removing only the woody debris (in new plots) versus removing all hurricane debris.  Funding for continued studies of the MRCE plots ended in 1998, but they were of such great value as a long-term experiment that they were incorporated into the LTER program.</literalLayout></para></abstract><funding><para><literalLayout>LTER</literalLayout></para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=LUQ,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access></dataset></ns0:eml>