<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-luq.135.3" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 C:/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><shortName>LUQMetadata135</shortName><title>Recovery of a tropical stream after a harvest-related chlorine poisoning event</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Catherine</givenName><surName>Pringle</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of Georgia</organizationName><positionName>Principal Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology and Department of zoology</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>GA</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(706)542-4289</phone><electronicMailAddress>cpringle@uga.edu</electronicMailAddress></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Effie</givenName><surName>Greathouse</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of Georgia</organizationName><positionName>Graduate Student</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>308 Biological Sciences</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>GA</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(706)542-1120</phone><electronicMailAddress>effieg@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress></metadataProvider><language>english</language><abstract><para><literalLayout>1. Harvest-related poisoning events are common in tropical streams, yet research on stream recovery has largely been limited to temperate streams and generally does not include any measures of ecosystem function, such as leaf breakdown. 
2. We assessed recovery of a second-order, high-gradient stream draining the Luquillo Experimental Forest, Puerto Rico, three months after a chlorine-bleach poisoning event. The illegal poisoning of freshwater shrimps for harvest caused massive mortality of shrimps and dramatic changes in those ecosystem properties influenced by shrimps. We determined recovery potential using an established recovery index and assessed actual recovery by examining whether the poisoned reach returned to conditions resembling an undisturbed upstream reference reach.
3. Recovery potential was excellent (score=729 out of a possible 729) and can be attributed to nearby sources of organisms for colonization, the mobility of dominant organisms, unimpaired habitat, rapid flushing and processing of chlorine, and location within a national forest.
4. Actual recovery was substantial. Comparison of the reference reach with the formerly poisoned reach indicated: (1) complete recovery of xiphocaridid and palaemonid shrimp population abundances, shrimp size distributions, leaf breakdown rates, and abundances of oligochaetes and mayflies on leaves, and (2) only small differences in atyid shrimp abundance and community and ecosystem properties influenced by atyid shrimps (standing stocks of epilithic fine inorganic and organic matter, chlorophyll a, and abundances of chironomids and copepods on leaves). 
5. There was no detectable pattern between any measured variables and distance downstream from the poisoning. However, shrimp size-distributions indicated that the observed recovery may represent a source-sink dynamic, in which the poisoned reach acts as a sink which depletes adult shrimp populations from surrounding undisturbed habitats. Thus, the rapid recovery observed in this study is consistent with results from other field studies of pulse chlorine disturbances, harvest-related fish poisonings, and recovery of freshwater biotic interactions, but it is unlikely to be sustainable if multiple poisonings deplete adult populations to the extent that juvenile recruitment does not offset adult shrimp mortality.</literalLayout></para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>tropical stream</keyword><keyword>shrimps</keyword><keyword>recovery</keyword><keyword>puerto rico</keyword><keyword>decapoda</keyword><keyword>chlorine poisoning</keyword><keywordThesaurus>Assigned by Principal Investigator</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>quebrada sonadora</keyword><keyword>nutrient cycles/pools</keyword><keyword>human disturbance</keyword><keyword>aquatic insects</keyword><keyword>aquatic decapods</keyword><keyword>algae</keyword><keyword>headwater stream</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LEF LTER Data Sets</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>Disturbance</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LEF LTER Data Categories</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><title>ADEQUATE ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><para><literalLayout>The scientists, the LEF-LTER Program, and the USDA International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITF) must receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data by other scientists, and the LEF LTER program must receive two copies of any publication using that data. One copy will be placed at the IITF library and one copy will stay with the LEF LTER Data Manager. A suggested format for this acknowledgement will be distributed along with the requested data.</literalLayout></para><section><title>Acknowledgements for NSF Support.</title><para><literalLayout>The following paragraph should be included in the acknowledgements of all publications funded in any way by current and future LTER grants:</literalLayout><literalLayout>This research was performed under grant #DEB-0218039 from the National Science Foundation to the Institute of Tropical Ecosystem Studies (IEET), University of Puerto Rico, and the International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITFR) as part of the Long-Term Ecological Research Program in the Luquillo Experimental Forest. Additional support was provided by the Forest Service (U.S. Department of Agriculture) and the University of Puerto Rico.</literalLayout></para></section></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb135/metadata/lterdb135.htm#DATA</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage id="geoReference" scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF) covers 11,231 hectares and reaches 1079 m above sea level. It has a warm and wet climate and includes a variety of tropical habitats and forest types and streams, and a high diversity of plants and animals. A key feature of these ecosystems is disturbance. Hurricanes, landslides, and human disturbance have shaped the forest, and research by LUQ has stimulated a new appreciation of the significance of large-scale disturbances in tropical forested ecosystems and the key role of plants and animals in shaping the response to these events. Hurricanes occurring one and 10 years after LUQ began in 1988 provided landscape-scale natural experiments which are still followed closely.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-65.92</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-65.7</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>18.35</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>18.23</southBoundingCoordinate><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>20</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>1060</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Catherine</givenName><surName>Pringle</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of Georgia</organizationName><positionName>Principal Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology and Department of zoology</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>GA</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(706)542-4289</phone><electronicMailAddress>cpringle@uga.edu</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>Luquillo Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>University of Puerto Rico, Rio Piedras</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>P. O. Box 21910</deliveryPoint><city>San Juan</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931-1910</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787) 764 - 0000 (ext. 4940)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787) 772 -1481</phone><electronicMailAddress>nbrokaw@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://luq.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>From 15 June to 28 July, 1999, we assessed recovery of shrimp, fish and leaf pack invertebrate abundances, shrimp size distributions, algal colonization, accrual of fine particulate inorganic and organic matter, and leaf decomposition rates in pool habitats of the upper 315 meters of the 500-m reach affected by the March 1999 poisoning of the Sonadora. We used a 250-meter reach upstream from the poisoning as a reference reach for comparison to the formerly poisoned reach. Five reference pools and ten formerly poisoned pools were chosen for study.
In each pool, we haphazardly placed 6 unglazed ceramic tiles (7 x 15 cm) and 6 leaf packs, each tethered to cobble from the channel with cable ties and metal binder clips. Leaf packs were made from air-dried leaves of Cecropia schreberiana Miq. cut into smaller pieces, weighed to approximately 5 g, and held together with a binder clip. In the two most upstream study pools of the formerly poisoned reach, tiles and leaf packs were disturbed by swimmers (i.e. picked up and tossed). Tiles and leaf packs in the third study pool of the formerly poisoned reach suffered high washout during a storm 2 days after placement. The seven other study pools in the formerly poisoned reach were below the Road 186 bridge crossing of the Sonadora but similar to the pools of the upstream reference reach in physical parameters.
We randomly sampled, from each study pool, one tile on days 11, 16, 20, 25, and 34 and one leaf pack on days 6, 11, 14, 16 and 20. We also sampled 25 leaf packs on day 0 to obtain an air-dried to oven-dried ratio in order to convert the original air-dried weight of each leaf pack to an estimated oven-dried weight. We sampled tiles and leaf packs by cutting cable ties and raising the tile or leaf pack out of the water within a 363-&#181;m hand net. The tile or leaf pack and its associated hand net contents were placed into a ziplock bag and transported to the laboratory in a cooler.
Laboratory processing of tiles consisted of scraping the top surface of the tile with a razor blade and scrubbing the entire tile with a toothbrush. After removing insects from the resulting homogenate, two subsamples of known volumes were filtered onto combusted and pre-weighed glass fiber filters (Whatman GF/F, 0.7 &#181;m). Mass of organic (AFDM) and inorganic matter was determined for one filter, dried at 50 &#176;C for 24 h, weighed to the nearest 0.001 g, burned at 500 &#176;C for 3 h, and re-weighed. The second filter was frozen until analyzed for chlorophyll a using a Turner Designs fluorometer (model 10AU) and standard methods (APHA, 1985).
Laboratory processing of leaves consisted of rinsing off insects and sediments, oven-drying at 50 &#176;C for 24 h, weighing to the nearest 0.001 g, burning at 500 &#176;C for 3 h, and re-weighing. Insects and small benthic invertebrates were live-picked from sediments, preserved in 70% ethanol, and identified to family or order. We analyzed the abundances of the four most common invertebrate taxa (Ephemeroptera, Chironomidae, Oligochaeta and Copepoda).
Shrimp abundance in each study pool was assessed by trapping and by conducting standardized observations. Minnow traps, each baited with ~200 mL of dry cat food, were set overnight at an approximate density of 1 trap per m2 of pool surface area. On the following morning, trapped shrimps were identified to family, measured for carapace length ( 1 mm), and released. Daytime observations were conducted at each tile and leaf pack on days 8, 13, 20, 25 and 33 and were standardized within an observation date but were not standardized between observation dates. We recorded the number of shrimps in each family. Day 8 observations were conducted for one minute, recording shrimps occurring on the tile or leaf pack. On days 13, 20, and 25, observations were "spot checks," recording shrimps on the tile or leaf pack and in an estimated 5-inch radius around the tile or leaf pack. On day 33, observations were conducted for 10 minutes, again recorrding shrimps on the tile or leaf pack and in the 5-inch radius. 10-minute observations were not done on day 33 in one upstream reference reach pool. On day 42, density of the green stream goby (S. plumieri) in each pool was determined by snorkeling the entire pool and counting all individuals observed. Visibility was similar across pools.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep></methods><project scope="document"><title>Effects of and recovery from chlorine poisoning, Quebrada Sonadora (Fresh Water Shrimp Recovery from Poisoning)</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Catherine</givenName><surName>Pringle</surName></individualName><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><abstract><para><literalLayout>Quebrada Sonadora was poisoned with chlorine bleach 140 m upstream from the bridge of Road 186 in the LEF causing massive mortality of freshwater shrimps over a ~500 m reach (300 m a.s.l., Fig. 1). The poisoning was discovered on 12 March 1999 and was estimated to have occurred on 10 March, based on the state of decay of thousands of dead shrimps observed along the river. No carcasses of Sicydium plumieri were observed. While no bleach bottles were found at the site of this poisoning, bleach bottles have been found at other stream poisonings documented in the LEF, and locals report that swimming pool tablets are also sometimes used in illegal chlorine poisonings. Chlorine is known to display rapid volatilization, transformation, and flushing in lotic waters; thus, LEF chlorine poisonings are pulse disturbances. When the poisoning was discovered, the benthos in pools of the poisoned reach was visibly and dramatically different than the pool benthos upstream. In downstream pools, shrimps were not observed, and thick layers of sediment and fine particulate organic matter (FPOM) coated the rocks. In pools upstream from the poisoning, xiphocaridid and atyid shrimps were active, and no visible sediment/FPOM was observed on rocks. In contrast, there were no pronounced differences in sediment/FPOM accrual between riffles above and below the poisoning. These visual observations of immediate effects suggested that the poisoning event represented a unique opportunity to quantify large-scale effects of shrimp removal for comparison to previous small-scale manipulative experiments conducted in the Sonadora and tributaries (Prieta, Toronja). In the first component of this project, from March 26 to April 6, 1999, we quantified differences between the first 100 m of the poisoned reach and a 100-m reference reach immediately upstream from the poisoned reach, and we conducted a manipulative experiment, adding freshwater shrimps (Xiphocaris elongata, Atya lanipes, Macrobrachium spp.) to 3 poisoned pools for comparison to 3 poisoned pools in which no shrimps were added. In the second component of this project, from June 15 to July 28, 1999, we assessed recovery of the poisoned reach, comparing the upper 315 m of the poisoned reach to a 250-m reference reach immediately upstream from the poisoning.</literalLayout></para></abstract><funding><para><literalLayout>LTER, USDA Forest Service</literalLayout></para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=LUQ,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>recovphys_AND_shrimps.txt</entityName><entityDescription>Physical parameters and the number and mean lengths of trapped shrimps from 15 recovery study pools</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>recovphys_AND_shrimps.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb135/data/recovphys_AND_shrimps.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReferencerecovphys_AND_shrimps.txt" scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1999-06-08</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>1999-07-29</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>From 15 June to 28 July, 1999, we assessed recovery of shrimp, fish and leaf pack invertebrate abundances, shrimp size distributions, algal colonization, accrual of fine particulate inorganic and organic matter, and leaf decomposition rates in pool habitats of the upper 315 meters of the 500-m reach affected by the March 1999 poisoning of the Sonadora. We used a 250-meter reach upstream from the poisoning as a reference reach for comparison to the formerly poisoned reach. Five reference pools and ten formerly poisoned pools were chosen for study.
In each pool, we haphazardly placed 6 unglazed ceramic tiles (7 x 15 cm) and 6 leaf packs, each tethered to cobble from the channel with cable ties and metal binder clips. Leaf packs were made from air-dried leaves of Cecropia schreberiana Miq. cut into smaller pieces, weighed to approximately 5 g, and held together with a binder clip. In the two most upstream study pools of the formerly poisoned reach, tiles and leaf packs were disturbed by swimmers (i.e. picked up and tossed). Tiles and leaf packs in the third study pool of the formerly poisoned reach suffered high washout during a storm 2 days after placement. The seven other study pools in the formerly poisoned reach were below the Road 186 bridge crossing of the Sonadora but similar to the pools of the upstream reference reach in physical parameters.
We randomly sampled, from each study pool, one tile on days 11, 16, 20, 25, and 34 and one leaf pack on days 6, 11, 14, 16 and 20. We also sampled 25 leaf packs on day 0 to obtain an air-dried to oven-dried ratio in order to convert the original air-dried weight of each leaf pack to an estimated oven-dried weight. We sampled tiles and leaf packs by cutting cable ties and raising the tile or leaf pack out of the water within a 363-&#181;m hand net. The tile or leaf pack and its associated hand net contents were placed into a ziplock bag and transported to the laboratory in a cooler.
Laboratory processing of tiles consisted of scraping the top surface of the tile with a razor blade and scrubbing the entire tile with a toothbrush. After removing insects from the resulting homogenate, two subsamples of known volumes were filtered onto combusted and pre-weighed glass fiber filters (Whatman GF/F, 0.7 &#181;m). Mass of organic (AFDM) and inorganic matter was determined for one filter, dried at 50 &#176;C for 24 h, weighed to the nearest 0.001 g, burned at 500 &#176;C for 3 h, and re-weighed. The second filter was frozen until analyzed for chlorophyll a using a Turner Designs fluorometer (model 10AU) and standard methods (APHA, 1985).
Laboratory processing of leaves consisted of rinsing off insects and sediments, oven-drying at 50 &#176;C for 24 h, weighing to the nearest 0.001 g, burning at 500 &#176;C for 3 h, and re-weighing. Insects and small benthic invertebrates were live-picked from sediments, preserved in 70% ethanol, and identified to family or order. We analyzed the abundances of the four most common invertebrate taxa (Ephemeroptera, Chironomidae, Oligochaeta and Copepoda).
Shrimp abundance in each study pool was assessed by trapping and by conducting standardized observations. Minnow traps, each baited with ~200 mL of dry cat food, were set overnight at an approximate density of 1 trap per m2 of pool surface area. On the following morning, trapped shrimps were identified to family, measured for carapace length ( 1 mm), and released. Daytime observations were conducted at each tile and leaf pack on days 8, 13, 20, 25 and 33 and were standardized within an observation date but were not standardized between observation dates. We recorded the number of shrimps in each family. Day 8 observations were conducted for one minute, recording shrimps occurring on the tile or leaf pack. On days 13, 20, and 25, observations were "spot checks," recording shrimps on the tile or leaf pack and in an estimated 5-inch radius around the tile or leaf pack. On day 33, observations were conducted for 10 minutes, again recorrding shrimps on the tile or leaf pack and in the 5-inch radius. 10-minute observations were not done on day 33 in one upstream reference reach pool. On day 42, density of the green stream goby (S. plumieri) in each pool was determined by snorkeling the entire pool and counting all individuals observed. Visibility was similar across pools.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReferencerecovphys_AND_shrimps.txt</references></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>once</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Pool code</attributeName><attributeLabel>POOL</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The pool in which the data is from; letters A-E are codes for pools from the reference reach where A is the most downstream reference pool and E is the most upstream reference pool; numbers 1-10 are codes for pools from the formerly poisoned reach where 1 is the most upstream poisoned pool and 10 is the most downstream poisoned pool. A;B;C;C;C;1;2;3;4;5;6;7;8;9;10</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>The pool in which the data is from; letters A-E are codes for pools from the reference reach where A is the most downstream reference pool and E is the most upstream reference pool; numbers 1-10 are codes for pools from the formerly poisoned reach where 1 is the most upstream poisoned pool and 10 is the most downstream poisoned pool. A;B;C;C;C;1;2;3;4;5;6;7;8;9;10</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>depth</attributeName><attributeLabel>DEPTH</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The mean of depths measured at locations of tiles and leaf packs</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>molarity</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>Pools 1; 2  and  3</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>water velocity</attributeName><attributeLabel>FLOW</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The mean of water velocities measured at locations of tiles or leaf packs</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>metersPerSecond</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>Pools 1; 2  and  3</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>canopy cover</attributeName><attributeLabel>CANCOV</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The mean percent canopy cover measured with a spherical densiometer in the pool</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>surface area of pool</attributeName><attributeLabel>POOLAREA</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The surface area of the pool</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>squareMeter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>the number of traps</attributeName><attributeLabel>NO._TRAPS</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The number of traps set in the pool</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>The number of Xiphocaris trapped</attributeName><attributeLabel>X_NO._TRAPPED</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The number of Xiphocaris shrimps caught over all of the traps set in the pool</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>the number of Atya trapped</attributeName><attributeLabel>A_NO._TRAPPED</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The number of Atya shrimps caught over all of the traps set in the pool</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>the number of Macrobrachium trapped</attributeName><attributeLabel>M_NO._TRAPPED</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The number of Macrobrachium shrimps caught over all of the traps set in the pool</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Length of trapped Xiphocaris</attributeName><attributeLabel>X_CM</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The mean length of Xiphocaris shrimps trapped from the pool</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>pool 3</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Length of trapped Atya</attributeName><attributeLabel>A_CM</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The mean length of Atya shrimps trapped from the pool</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.0001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>pools 3  and  10</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Length of trapped Macrobrachium</attributeName><attributeLabel>M_CM</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The mean length of Macrobrachium shrimps trapped from the pool</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.0001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>pool 4</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>recovobs.txt</entityName><entityDescription>Observations on shrimps and gobies from 15 recovery study pools</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>recovobs.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb135/data/recovobs.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReferencerecovobs.txt" scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1999-06-23</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>1999-07-29</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>From 15 June to 28 July, 1999, we assessed recovery of shrimp, fish and leaf pack invertebrate abundances, shrimp size distributions, algal colonization, accrual of fine particulate inorganic and organic matter, and leaf decomposition rates in pool habitats of the upper 315 meters of the 500-m reach affected by the March 1999 poisoning of the Sonadora. We used a 250-meter reach upstream from the poisoning as a reference reach for comparison to the formerly poisoned reach. Five reference pools and ten formerly poisoned pools were chosen for study.
In each pool, we haphazardly placed 6 unglazed ceramic tiles (7 x 15 cm) and 6 leaf packs, each tethered to cobble from the channel with cable ties and metal binder clips. Leaf packs were made from air-dried leaves of Cecropia schreberiana Miq. cut into smaller pieces, weighed to approximately 5 g, and held together with a binder clip. In the two most upstream study pools of the formerly poisoned reach, tiles and leaf packs were disturbed by swimmers (i.e. picked up and tossed). Tiles and leaf packs in the third study pool of the formerly poisoned reach suffered high washout during a storm 2 days after placement. The seven other study pools in the formerly poisoned reach were below the Road 186 bridge crossing of the Sonadora but similar to the pools of the upstream reference reach in physical parameters.
We randomly sampled, from each study pool, one tile on days 11, 16, 20, 25, and 34 and one leaf pack on days 6, 11, 14, 16 and 20. We also sampled 25 leaf packs on day 0 to obtain an air-dried to oven-dried ratio in order to convert the original air-dried weight of each leaf pack to an estimated oven-dried weight. We sampled tiles and leaf packs by cutting cable ties and raising the tile or leaf pack out of the water within a 363-&#181;m hand net. The tile or leaf pack and its associated hand net contents were placed into a ziplock bag and transported to the laboratory in a cooler.
Laboratory processing of tiles consisted of scraping the top surface of the tile with a razor blade and scrubbing the entire tile with a toothbrush. After removing insects from the resulting homogenate, two subsamples of known volumes were filtered onto combusted and pre-weighed glass fiber filters (Whatman GF/F, 0.7 &#181;m). Mass of organic (AFDM) and inorganic matter was determined for one filter, dried at 50 &#176;C for 24 h, weighed to the nearest 0.001 g, burned at 500 &#176;C for 3 h, and re-weighed. The second filter was frozen until analyzed for chlorophyll a using a Turner Designs fluorometer (model 10AU) and standard methods (APHA, 1985).
Laboratory processing of leaves consisted of rinsing off insects and sediments, oven-drying at 50 &#176;C for 24 h, weighing to the nearest 0.001 g, burning at 500 &#176;C for 3 h, and re-weighing. Insects and small benthic invertebrates were live-picked from sediments, preserved in 70% ethanol, and identified to family or order. We analyzed the abundances of the four most common invertebrate taxa (Ephemeroptera, Chironomidae, Oligochaeta and Copepoda).
Shrimp abundance in each study pool was assessed by trapping and by conducting standardized observations. Minnow traps, each baited with ~200 mL of dry cat food, were set overnight at an approximate density of 1 trap per m2 of pool surface area. On the following morning, trapped shrimps were identified to family, measured for carapace length ( 1 mm), and released. Daytime observations were conducted at each tile and leaf pack on days 8, 13, 20, 25 and 33 and were standardized within an observation date but were not standardized between observation dates. We recorded the number of shrimps in each family. Day 8 observations were conducted for one minute, recording shrimps occurring on the tile or leaf pack. On days 13, 20, and 25, observations were "spot checks," recording shrimps on the tile or leaf pack and in an estimated 5-inch radius around the tile or leaf pack. On day 33, observations were conducted for 10 minutes, again recorrding shrimps on the tile or leaf pack and in the 5-inch radius. 10-minute observations were not done on day 33 in one upstream reference reach pool. On day 42, density of the green stream goby (S. plumieri) in each pool was determined by snorkeling the entire pool and counting all individuals observed. Visibility was similar across pools.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReferencerecovobs.txt</references></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>variable</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Pool code</attributeName><attributeLabel>POOL</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The pool in which the data is from; letters A-E are codes for pools from the reference reach where A is the most downstream reference pool and E is the most upstream reference pool; numbers 1-10 are codes for pools from the formerly poisoned reach where 1 is the most upstream poisoned pool and 10 is the most downstream poisoned pool. A;B;C;C;C;1;2;3;4;5;6;7;8;9;10</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>The pool in which the data is from; letters A-E are codes for pools from the reference reach where A is the most downstream reference pool and E is the most upstream reference pool; numbers 1-10 are codes for pools from the formerly poisoned reach where 1 is the most upstream poisoned pool and 10 is the most downstream poisoned pool. A;B;C;C;C;1;2;3;4;5;6;7;8;9;10</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Xiphocaris observed on June 23</attributeName><attributeLabel>X_6/23</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The mean number of Macrobrachium shrimps observed during spot checks of leaf packs and tiles in the pool on July 5</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.0001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Atya observed on June 23</attributeName><attributeLabel>A_6/23</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The mean number of Xiphocaris shrimps observed during spot checks of leaf packs and tiles in the pool on July 10</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.0001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Macrobrachium observed on June 23</attributeName><attributeLabel>M_6/23</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The mean number of Atya shrimps observed during spot checks of leaf packs and tiles in the pool on July 10</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.0001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Xiphocaris observed on June 28</attributeName><attributeLabel>X_6/28</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The mean number of Macrobrachium shrimps observed during spot checks of leaf packs and tiles in the pool on July 10</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.0001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Atya observed on June 28</attributeName><attributeLabel>A_6/28</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The mean number of Xiphocaris shrimps observed over ten minutes on leaf packs and tiles in the pool on July 18</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.0001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Macrobrachium observed on June 28</attributeName><attributeLabel>M_6/28</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The mean number of Atya shrimps observed over ten minutes on leaf packs and tiles in the pool on July 18</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.0001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Xiphocaris observed on July 5</attributeName><attributeLabel>X_7/5</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The mean number of Macrobrachium shrimps observed over ten minutes on leaf packs and tiles in the pool on July 18</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.0001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Atya observed on July 5</attributeName><attributeLabel>A_7/5</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Mean chlorophyll a on tiles in the pool sampled on day 11</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.0001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Macrobrachium observed on July 5</attributeName><attributeLabel>M_7/5</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Mean AFDM on tiles in the pool sampled on day 11</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Xiphocaris observed on July 10</attributeName><attributeLabel>X_7/10</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Mean AFDM on tiles in the pool sampled on day 16</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>pool 1</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Atya observed on July 10</attributeName><attributeLabel>A_7/10</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Mean AFDM on tiles in the pool sampled on day 20</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>pool 1</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Macrobrachium observed on July 10</attributeName><attributeLabel>M_7/10</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Mean AFDM on tiles in the pool sampled on day 25</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>pool 1</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Xiphocaris observed on July 18</attributeName><attributeLabel>X_7/18</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Mean AFDM on tiles in the pool sampled on day 34</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.0001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>pool E; pool 1; pool 2</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Atya observed on July 18</attributeName><attributeLabel>A_7/18</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Mean Inorganic dry mass on tiles in the pool sampled on day 11</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.0001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>pool E; pool 1; pool 2</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Macrobrachium observed on July 18</attributeName><attributeLabel>M_7/18</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Mean Inorganic dry mass on tiles in the pool sampled on day 16</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.0001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>pool E; pool 1; pool 2</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>recovtiles.txt</entityName><entityDescription>Chlorophyll a inorganic and organic matter accruing on tiles placed in 15 recovery study pools</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>recovtiles.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb135/data/recovtiles.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReferencerecovtiles.txt" scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1999-06-26</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>1999-07-18</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>From 15 June to 28 July, 1999, we assessed recovery of shrimp, fish and leaf pack invertebrate abundances, shrimp size distributions, algal colonization, accrual of fine particulate inorganic and organic matter, and leaf decomposition rates in pool habitats of the upper 315 meters of the 500-m reach affected by the March 1999 poisoning of the Sonadora. We used a 250-meter reach upstream from the poisoning as a reference reach for comparison to the formerly poisoned reach. Five reference pools and ten formerly poisoned pools were chosen for study.
In each pool, we haphazardly placed 6 unglazed ceramic tiles (7 x 15 cm) and 6 leaf packs, each tethered to cobble from the channel with cable ties and metal binder clips. Leaf packs were made from air-dried leaves of Cecropia schreberiana Miq. cut into smaller pieces, weighed to approximately 5 g, and held together with a binder clip. In the two most upstream study pools of the formerly poisoned reach, tiles and leaf packs were disturbed by swimmers (i.e. picked up and tossed). Tiles and leaf packs in the third study pool of the formerly poisoned reach suffered high washout during a storm 2 days after placement. The seven other study pools in the formerly poisoned reach were below the Road 186 bridge crossing of the Sonadora but similar to the pools of the upstream reference reach in physical parameters.
We randomly sampled, from each study pool, one tile on days 11, 16, 20, 25, and 34 and one leaf pack on days 6, 11, 14, 16 and 20. We also sampled 25 leaf packs on day 0 to obtain an air-dried to oven-dried ratio in order to convert the original air-dried weight of each leaf pack to an estimated oven-dried weight. We sampled tiles and leaf packs by cutting cable ties and raising the tile or leaf pack out of the water within a 363-&#181;m hand net. The tile or leaf pack and its associated hand net contents were placed into a ziplock bag and transported to the laboratory in a cooler.
Laboratory processing of tiles consisted of scraping the top surface of the tile with a razor blade and scrubbing the entire tile with a toothbrush. After removing insects from the resulting homogenate, two subsamples of known volumes were filtered onto combusted and pre-weighed glass fiber filters (Whatman GF/F, 0.7 &#181;m). Mass of organic (AFDM) and inorganic matter was determined for one filter, dried at 50 &#176;C for 24 h, weighed to the nearest 0.001 g, burned at 500 &#176;C for 3 h, and re-weighed. The second filter was frozen until analyzed for chlorophyll a using a Turner Designs fluorometer (model 10AU) and standard methods (APHA, 1985).
Laboratory processing of leaves consisted of rinsing off insects and sediments, oven-drying at 50 &#176;C for 24 h, weighing to the nearest 0.001 g, burning at 500 &#176;C for 3 h, and re-weighing. Insects and small benthic invertebrates were live-picked from sediments, preserved in 70% ethanol, and identified to family or order. We analyzed the abundances of the four most common invertebrate taxa (Ephemeroptera, Chironomidae, Oligochaeta and Copepoda).
Shrimp abundance in each study pool was assessed by trapping and by conducting standardized observations. Minnow traps, each baited with ~200 mL of dry cat food, were set overnight at an approximate density of 1 trap per m2 of pool surface area. On the following morning, trapped shrimps were identified to family, measured for carapace length ( 1 mm), and released. Daytime observations were conducted at each tile and leaf pack on days 8, 13, 20, 25 and 33 and were standardized within an observation date but were not standardized between observation dates. We recorded the number of shrimps in each family. Day 8 observations were conducted for one minute, recording shrimps occurring on the tile or leaf pack. On days 13, 20, and 25, observations were "spot checks," recording shrimps on the tile or leaf pack and in an estimated 5-inch radius around the tile or leaf pack. On day 33, observations were conducted for 10 minutes, again recorrding shrimps on the tile or leaf pack and in the 5-inch radius. 10-minute observations were not done on day 33 in one upstream reference reach pool. On day 42, density of the green stream goby (S. plumieri) in each pool was determined by snorkeling the entire pool and counting all individuals observed. Visibility was similar across pools.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReferencerecovtiles.txt</references></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>variable during a 24-days period</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Pool code</attributeName><attributeLabel>POOL</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The pool in which the data is from; letters A-E are codes for pools from the reference reach where A is the most downstream reference pool and E is the most upstream reference pool; numbers 1-10 are codes for pools from the formerly poisoned reach where 1 is the most upstream poisoned pool and 10 is the most downstream poisoned pool. A;B;C;C;C;1;2;3;4;5;6;7;8;9;10</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>The pool in which the data is from; letters A-E are codes for pools from the reference reach where A is the most downstream reference pool and E is the most upstream reference pool; numbers 1-10 are codes for pools from the formerly poisoned reach where 1 is the most upstream poisoned pool and 10 is the most downstream poisoned pool. A;B;C;C;C;1;2;3;4;5;6;7;8;9;10</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Chlorophyll a on day 11</attributeName><attributeLabel>CHL_11</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Mean Inorganic dry mass on tiles in the pool sampled on day 20</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>microGramPerSquareMeter</customUnit></unit><precision>0.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Chlorophyll a on day 16</attributeName><attributeLabel>CHL_16</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Mean Inorganic dry mass on tiles in the pool sampled on day 25</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>microGramPerSquareMeter</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Chlorophyll a on day 20</attributeName><attributeLabel>CHL_20</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Mean inorganic dry mass on tiles in the pool sampled on day 34</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>microGramPerSquareMeter</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Chlorophyll a on day 25</attributeName><attributeLabel>CHL_25</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The sampling day in terms of the number of days after June 15 (=day 0)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>microGramPerSquareMeter</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Chlorophyll a on day 34</attributeName><attributeLabel>CHL_34</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The air-dried weight of the leaf pack prior to placing it in the pool</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>microGramPerSquareMeter</customUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>pool E</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>AFDM on day 11</attributeName><attributeLabel>AFDM_11</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The estimate of the day 0 oven-dried weight of the leaf pack; estimated as the initial wet weight minus 0.382 g -an estimate of weight loss due to handing and oven-drying; based on day 0 leaf packs</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>AFDM on day 16</attributeName><attributeLabel>AFDM_16</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The estimate of the day 0 ash-free dry mass of the leaf pack; estimated as the estimated initial dry weight multiplied by the proportion AFDM on the sampling day propAFDM_onsampleday</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>AFDM on day 20</attributeName><attributeLabel>AFDM_20</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The measured oven-dried weight of the leaf pack after sampling it on the sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>AFDM on day 25</attributeName><attributeLabel>AFDM_25</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The measured weight of the leaf pack after ashing it for 3 hours at 500degrees C after obtaining the dry weight on sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>AFDM on day 34</attributeName><attributeLabel>AFDM_34</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The ash-free dry mass of the leaf pack after sampling it on the sampling day. the dry weight on the sampling day minus the ashed weight on the sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>pool E</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Inorganic dry mass on day 11</attributeName><attributeLabel>INORG_11</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>the AFDM on sampling day divided by the dry weight on sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Inorganic dry mass on day 16</attributeName><attributeLabel>INORG_16</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>100 times the AFDM on the sampling day divided by the estimated initial AFDM</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Inorganic dry mass on day 20</attributeName><attributeLabel>INORG_20</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The number of Ephemeroptera picked out of the leaf pack after sampling on the sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Inorganic dry mass on day 25</attributeName><attributeLabel>INORG_25</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The number of Chironomidae picked out of the leaf pack after sampling on the sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Inorganic dry mass on day 34</attributeName><attributeLabel>INORG_34</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The number of Oligochaeta picked out of the leaf pack after sampling on the sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>pool E</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>recovleaves.txt</entityName><entityDescription>Leaf mass remaining and invertebrates on leaf packs placed in 15 recovery study pools</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>recovleaves.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>\t</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb135/data/recovleaves.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage id="temporalReferencerecovleaves.txt" scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1999-06-15</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>1999-07-05</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>From 15 June to 28 July, 1999, we assessed recovery of shrimp, fish and leaf pack invertebrate abundances, shrimp size distributions, algal colonization, accrual of fine particulate inorganic and organic matter, and leaf decomposition rates in pool habitats of the upper 315 meters of the 500-m reach affected by the March 1999 poisoning of the Sonadora. We used a 250-meter reach upstream from the poisoning as a reference reach for comparison to the formerly poisoned reach. Five reference pools and ten formerly poisoned pools were chosen for study.
In each pool, we haphazardly placed 6 unglazed ceramic tiles (7 x 15 cm) and 6 leaf packs, each tethered to cobble from the channel with cable ties and metal binder clips. Leaf packs were made from air-dried leaves of Cecropia schreberiana Miq. cut into smaller pieces, weighed to approximately 5 g, and held together with a binder clip. In the two most upstream study pools of the formerly poisoned reach, tiles and leaf packs were disturbed by swimmers (i.e. picked up and tossed). Tiles and leaf packs in the third study pool of the formerly poisoned reach suffered high washout during a storm 2 days after placement. The seven other study pools in the formerly poisoned reach were below the Road 186 bridge crossing of the Sonadora but similar to the pools of the upstream reference reach in physical parameters.
We randomly sampled, from each study pool, one tile on days 11, 16, 20, 25, and 34 and one leaf pack on days 6, 11, 14, 16 and 20. We also sampled 25 leaf packs on day 0 to obtain an air-dried to oven-dried ratio in order to convert the original air-dried weight of each leaf pack to an estimated oven-dried weight. We sampled tiles and leaf packs by cutting cable ties and raising the tile or leaf pack out of the water within a 363-&#181;m hand net. The tile or leaf pack and its associated hand net contents were placed into a ziplock bag and transported to the laboratory in a cooler.
Laboratory processing of tiles consisted of scraping the top surface of the tile with a razor blade and scrubbing the entire tile with a toothbrush. After removing insects from the resulting homogenate, two subsamples of known volumes were filtered onto combusted and pre-weighed glass fiber filters (Whatman GF/F, 0.7 &#181;m). Mass of organic (AFDM) and inorganic matter was determined for one filter, dried at 50 &#176;C for 24 h, weighed to the nearest 0.001 g, burned at 500 &#176;C for 3 h, and re-weighed. The second filter was frozen until analyzed for chlorophyll a using a Turner Designs fluorometer (model 10AU) and standard methods (APHA, 1985).
Laboratory processing of leaves consisted of rinsing off insects and sediments, oven-drying at 50 &#176;C for 24 h, weighing to the nearest 0.001 g, burning at 500 &#176;C for 3 h, and re-weighing. Insects and small benthic invertebrates were live-picked from sediments, preserved in 70% ethanol, and identified to family or order. We analyzed the abundances of the four most common invertebrate taxa (Ephemeroptera, Chironomidae, Oligochaeta and Copepoda).
Shrimp abundance in each study pool was assessed by trapping and by conducting standardized observations. Minnow traps, each baited with ~200 mL of dry cat food, were set overnight at an approximate density of 1 trap per m2 of pool surface area. On the following morning, trapped shrimps were identified to family, measured for carapace length ( 1 mm), and released. Daytime observations were conducted at each tile and leaf pack on days 8, 13, 20, 25 and 33 and were standardized within an observation date but were not standardized between observation dates. We recorded the number of shrimps in each family. Day 8 observations were conducted for one minute, recording shrimps occurring on the tile or leaf pack. On days 13, 20, and 25, observations were "spot checks," recording shrimps on the tile or leaf pack and in an estimated 5-inch radius around the tile or leaf pack. On day 33, observations were conducted for 10 minutes, again recorrding shrimps on the tile or leaf pack and in the 5-inch radius. 10-minute observations were not done on day 33 in one upstream reference reach pool. Onday 42, density of the green stream goby (S. plumieri) in each pool was determined by snorkeling the entire pool and counting all individuals observed. Visibility was similar across pools.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><references>temporalReferencerecovleaves.txt</references></temporalCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>variable during a 15-days period</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>sampling day</attributeName><attributeLabel>Day</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The number of Copepoda picked out of the leaf pack after sampling on the sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>The number of Copepoda picked out of the leaf pack after sampling on the sampling day</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Pool code</attributeName><attributeLabel>Pool</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The pool in which the data is from; letters A-E are codes for pools from the reference reach where A is the most downstream reference pool and E is the most upstream reference pool; numbers 1-10 are codes for pools from the formerly poisoned reach where 1 is the most upstream poisoned pool and 10 is the most downstream poisoned pool. A;B;C;C;C;1;2;3;4;5;6;7;8;9;10</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>The pool in which the data is from; letters A-E are codes for pools from the reference reach where A is the most downstream reference pool and E is the most upstream reference pool; numbers 1-10 are codes for pools from the formerly poisoned reach where 1 is the most upstream poisoned pool and 10 is the most downstream poisoned pool. A;B;C;C;C;1;2;3;4;5;6;7;8;9;10</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Initial wet weight</attributeName><attributeLabel>initial_wet_wt</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The air-dried weight of the leaf pack prior to placing it in the pool</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Estimated initial dry weight</attributeName><attributeLabel>est_initial_dry_wt</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The estimate of the day 0 oven-dried weight of the leaf pack, estimated as the initial wet weight minus 0.382 g -an estimate of weight loss due to handing and oven-drying, based on day 0 leaf packs</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">4.528</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">4.709</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Estimated initial ash-free dry mass</attributeName><attributeLabel>est_initial_AFDM</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The estimate of the day 0 ash-free dry mass of the leaf pack, estimated as the estimated initial dry weight multiplied by the proportion AFDM on the sampling day propAFDM_onsampleday</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">3.988</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">4.356</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Dry weight on the sampling day</attributeName><attributeLabel>dry_wt_onsampleday</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The measured oven-dried weight of the leaf pack after sampling it on the sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0.295</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">3.708</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Ashed weight on the sampling day</attributeName><attributeLabel>ashed_wt_onsampleday</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The measured weight of the leaf pack after ashing it for 3 hours at 500degrees C after obtaining the dry weight on sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0.025</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">0.440</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Ash-free dry mass on sampling day</attributeName><attributeLabel>AFDM_onsampleday</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The ash-free dry mass of the leaf pack after sampling it on the sampling day. the dry weight on the sampling day minus the ashed weight on the sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0.270</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">3.294</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>The proportion of AFDM on the sampling day</attributeName><attributeLabel>propAFDM_onsampleday</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>the  proportion of AFDM on sampling day divided by the dry weight on sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0.866</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">0.945</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>percent times 100 of AFDM remaining</attributeName><attributeLabel>percentAFDMremaining</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>100 times the AFDM on the sampling day divided by the estimated initial AFDM</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">6.29</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">81.12</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Ephemeroptera</attributeName><attributeLabel>Ephemeroptera</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The number of Ephemeroptera picked out of the leaf pack after sampling on the sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">21</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Chironomidae</attributeName><attributeLabel>Chironomidae</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The number of Chironomidae  picked out of the leaf pack after sampling on the sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">28</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Oligochaeta</attributeName><attributeLabel>Oligochaeta</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The number of Oligochaeta  picked out of the leaf pack after sampling on the sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">46</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Copepoda</attributeName><attributeLabel>Copepoda</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The number of Copepoda  picked out of the leaf pack after sampling on the sampling day</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">13</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><unitList><unit id="microGramPerSquareMeter" /></unitList></additionalMetadata></ns0:eml>