<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-luq.121.1" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 C:/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><shortName>LUQMetadata121</shortName><title>Fern distribution in El Verde MRCE plots</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Leslie</givenName><surName>Finical</surName></individualName><organizationName>The Dirt Doctor's Dirt Magazine</organizationName><positionName>Editor</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>5629.5 Tremont St.</deliveryPoint><city>Dallas</city><administrativeArea>TX</administrativeArea><postalCode>75214</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>lesliehalleck@hotmail.com</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.growngreen.com/</onlineUrl></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Leslie Finical</givenName><surName>Halleck</surName></individualName><organizationName>The Dirt Doctor's Dirt Magazine</organizationName><positionName>Editor</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>5629.5 Tremont St.</deliveryPoint><city>Dallas</city><administrativeArea>TX</administrativeArea><postalCode>75214</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>lesliehalleck@hotmail.com</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.growngreen.com/</onlineUrl></metadataProvider><language>english</language><abstract><para><literalLayout>A fern survey was done of the plots established by under MRCE funding to assess controls on primary productivity along an elevational gradient. The control plots (CP), fertilized plots (FP) and plots where only leaf litter (ll) was removed at El Verde were survey and all ferns present in the plots listed, mapped and measured in Fall of 1995, several years after the initial fertilization and leaf litter treatment had been applied. The objective was to determine the extent to which the fern flora had been affected by the treatments.</literalLayout></para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>fern</keyword><keyword>growth</keyword><keyword>pteridophyte</keyword><keyword>EL VERDE</keyword><keyword>FERNS</keyword><keyword>LEF</keyword><keyword>MRCE</keyword><keyword>OTHER AGRICULTURAL USE</keyword><keyword>PLANT GROWTH</keyword><keyword>PRIMARY PRODUCTION</keyword><keyword>Primary Productivity</keyword><keyword>Nutrient enhancement effects</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><title>ADEQUATE ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><para><literalLayout>The scientists, the LEF-LTER Program, and the                                     USDA International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITF) must                                     receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data by other                                     scientists, and the LEF LTER program must receive two copies of                                     any publication using that data. One copy will be placed at the                                     IITF library and one copy will stay with the LEF LTER Data                                     Manager. A suggested format for this acknowledgement will be                                     distributed along with the requested data.</literalLayout></para><section><title>Acknowledgements for NSF Support.</title><para><literalLayout>The following paragraph should be                                         included in the acknowledgements of all publications funded                                         in any way by current and future LTER grants:</literalLayout><literalLayout>This research was performed under grant                                         #DEB-0218039 from the National Science Foundation to the                                         Institute of Tropical Ecosystem Studies (IEET), University                                         of Puerto Rico, and the International Institute of Tropical                                         Forestry (IITFR) as part of the Long-Term Ecological                                         Research Program in the Luquillo Experimental Forest.                                         Additional support was provided by the Forest Service (U.S.                                         Department of Agriculture) and the University of Puerto                                         Rico.</literalLayout></para></section></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb121/metadata/lterdb121.htm#DATA</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF) covers                                 11,231 hectares and reaches 1079 m above sea level. It has a warm                                 and wet climate and includes a variety of tropical habitats and                                 forest types and streams, and a high diversity of plants and                                 animals. A key feature of these ecosystems is disturbance.                                 Hurricanes, landslides, and human disturbance have shaped the                                 forest, and research by LUQ has stimulated a new appreciation of the                                 significance of large-scale disturbances in tropical forested                                 ecosystems and the key role of plants and animals in shaping the                                 response to these events. Hurricanes occurring one and 10 years                                 after LUQ began in 1988 provided landscape-scale natural experiments                                 which are still followed closely.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-65.92</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-65.7</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>18.35</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>18.23</southBoundingCoordinate><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>20</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>1060</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Joanne</givenName><surName>Sharpe</surName></individualName><organizationName>Sharplex Services</organizationName><positionName>Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>PO Box 499</deliveryPoint><city>Edgecomb</city><administrativeArea>ME</administrativeArea><postalCode>04556</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(207)882-5989</phone><electronicMailAddress>joannesharpe@email.com</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>Luquillo Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>University of Puerto Rico, Rio Piedras</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>P. O. Box 21910</deliveryPoint><city>San Juan</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931-1910</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787) 764 - 0000 (ext. 4940)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787) 772 -1481</phone><electronicMailAddress>nbrokaw@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://luq.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Each of the 11 MRCE 20 x 20 m plots at El Verde was surveyed for ferns. Each fern plant found was identified to species and located within one of the 16 subplots (5 x 5 m) within the plot. The substrate, leaf litter cover and height off the ground of each individual was noted. Leaves were counted and the petiole and length and width of the lamina of the longest mature sterile (fertile if no sterile leaves present) leaf was measured. The petiole and lamina lengths were summed to give the total length of the leaf. The number of fertile leaves present on the plant was noted as was any evidence of herbivory. The number of broken leaves on the plant was also noted. If the leaves were pinnate, then the number of pairs of leaflets was recorded.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep></methods><project scope="document"><title>Fern Population Dynamics</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Leslie</givenName><surName>Finical</surName></individualName><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><abstract><para><literalLayout>Ferns are an important part of the understory of many tropic forests, yet nothing is known about their leaf turnover rates, hence their contribution to the litter layer and overall functioning of the forest ecosystem. This long-term project addresses that question by marking and monitoring each leaf produced by over a thousand individuals representing over 20 different species. Plants and their leaves were observed at four month intervals for ten years starting in September 1991 (Phase 1) and then at one year intervals for an additional ten years starting in January 2001. Seasonality in leaf and spore production, as well as effects of drought and hurricanes are noted. Defoliation experiments with several species are being conducted to determine the limits of disturbance effects.</literalLayout></para></abstract><funding><para><literalLayout>none</literalLayout></para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=LUQ,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access></dataset></ns0:eml>