<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-luq.86.1" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 C:/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><shortName>LUQMetadata86</shortName><title>Fungi of the Greater Antilles</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Jean</givenName><surName>Lodge</surName></individualName><organizationName>USDA Forest Service</organizationName><positionName>Principal Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Forest Products Lab</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>PO Box 1377</deliveryPoint><city>Luquillo</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00773-1377</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787)889-7445</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787)889-7477</phone><electronicMailAddress>djlodge@caribe.net</electronicMailAddress></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Jean</givenName><surName>Lodge</surName></individualName><organizationName>USDA Forest Service</organizationName><positionName>Principal Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Forest Products Lab</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>PO Box 1377</deliveryPoint><city>Luquillo</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00773-1377</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787)889-7445</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787)889-7477</phone><electronicMailAddress>djlodge@caribe.net</electronicMailAddress></metadataProvider><language>english</language><abstract><para><literalLayout>Over 20 researchers and cooperators were enlisted to produce a survey of the basidiomycetes of Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Dominican Republic, and Jamaica. This included all basidiomycetes except rusts and smuts. These islands in the Greater Antilles were chosen for this survey for several reasons. There was previously very limited documentation on macrobasidiomycete diversity for these islands, although recent studies had shown that at least 15% of the species were undescribed. This project complemented previous and ongoing surveys in Mexico, Costa Rica, and Venezuela. The information gained from this project will ultimately help us to understand differences in colonization and rates of speciation among different groups of basidiomycetes in island chains. The investigators in this project discovered at least 75 new species and varieties so far, as well as several new genera (Pegler et al. 1998; Samuels &amp;amp; Lodge 1996) and one possible new family or order (see 'Aliens' under GENUS). Various cooperators have graciously provided identification of ascomycetes, myxomycetes, and mitosporic fungi, which are also included in the database.</literalLayout></para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Agaricales</keyword><keyword>Anguilla</keyword><keyword>Apyllophorales</keyword><keyword>Ascomycetes</keyword><keyword>Basidiomycetes</keyword><keyword>Dominican Republic</keyword><keyword>Fungi</keyword><keyword>Guana Island</keyword><keyword>Heterobasidiomycetes</keyword><keyword>Jamaica</keyword><keyword>Jelly Fungi</keyword><keyword>Mitosporic fungi</keyword><keyword>Mona Island</keyword><keyword>Puerto Rico</keyword><keyword>Slime Molds; Greater Antilles</keyword><keyword>Slime Molds; Greater Antilles</keyword><keyword>St. John</keyword><keyword>Tortola</keyword><keyword>Virgin Gorda</keyword><keyword>Virgin Islands</keyword><keyword>FUNGI</keyword><keyword>OTHER ECOSYSTEM</keyword><keyword>OTHER PLOTS</keyword><keyword>PEER REVIEWED JOURNAL</keyword><keyword>VAM</keyword><keyword>Population Dynamics</keyword><keyword>Biodiversity</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><title>ADEQUATE ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><para><literalLayout>The scientists, the LEF-LTER Program, and the                                     USDA International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITF) must                                     receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data by other                                     scientists, and the LEF LTER program must receive two copies of                                     any publication using that data. One copy will be placed at the                                     IITF library and one copy will stay with the LEF LTER Data                                     Manager. A suggested format for this acknowledgement will be                                     distributed along with the requested data.</literalLayout></para><section><title>Acknowledgements for NSF Support.</title><para><literalLayout>The following paragraph should be                                         included in the acknowledgements of all publications funded                                         in any way by current and future LTER grants:</literalLayout><literalLayout>This research was performed under grant                                         #DEB-0218039 from the National Science Foundation to the                                         Institute of Tropical Ecosystem Studies (IEET), University                                         of Puerto Rico, and the International Institute of Tropical                                         Forestry (IITFR) as part of the Long-Term Ecological                                         Research Program in the Luquillo Experimental Forest.                                         Additional support was provided by the Forest Service (U.S.                                         Department of Agriculture) and the University of Puerto                                         Rico.</literalLayout></para></section></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb86/metadata/lterdb86.htm#DATA</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF) covers                                 11,231 hectares and reaches 1079 m above sea level. It has a warm                                 and wet climate and includes a variety of tropical habitats and                                 forest types and streams, and a high diversity of plants and                                 animals. A key feature of these ecosystems is disturbance.                                 Hurricanes, landslides, and human disturbance have shaped the                                 forest, and research by LUQ has stimulated a new appreciation of the                                 significance of large-scale disturbances in tropical forested                                 ecosystems and the key role of plants and animals in shaping the                                 response to these events. Hurricanes occurring one and 10 years                                 after LUQ began in 1988 provided landscape-scale natural experiments                                 which are still followed closely.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-65.92</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-65.7</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>18.35</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>18.23</southBoundingCoordinate><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>20</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>1060</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Jean</givenName><surName>Lodge</surName></individualName><organizationName>USDA Forest Service</organizationName><positionName>Principal Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Forest Products Lab</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>PO Box 1377</deliveryPoint><city>Luquillo</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00773-1377</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787)889-7445</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787)889-7477</phone><electronicMailAddress>djlodge@caribe.net</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>Luquillo Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>University of Puerto Rico, Rio Piedras</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>P. O. Box 21910</deliveryPoint><city>San Juan</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931-1910</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787) 764 - 0000 (ext. 4940)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787) 772 -1481</phone><electronicMailAddress>nbrokaw@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://luq.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>The data contained here include all those in the database of the Center for Forest Mycology Research, USDA-Forest Service, Forest Products Laboratory, PO Box 1377, Luquillo, PR 00773, including basidiomycetes, ascomycetes, hyphomycetes, myxomycetes, and a few VA mycorrhizal fungi and water molds. The collections from October 1983-1993 were logged into the database with funds from a supplement grant to the LUQ-LTER site for herbarium improvement. A few of the records are from publications of our collaborators. This version was produced 1 March 2001. It is not completely free of errors. Some of the identifications are field determinations, and these are usually marked with "cf." after the name.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep></methods><project scope="document"><title>Basidiomycetes Inventory</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Jean</givenName><surName>Lodge</surName></individualName><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><abstract><para><literalLayout>The inventory of basidiomycetes of the Greater Antilles, with special emphasis on the Luquillo Long-Term Ecological Research Site, was a five year project initiated in 1996 with funding from the USA National Science Foundation&#226;&#128;&#153;s (NSF) Biotic Surveys and Inventories Program. The objective was to survey and inventory all basidiomycetes except rust fungi on the Caribbean islands of Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Hispaniola, and Jamaica.  Basidiomycetes of the Greater Antilles, with special emphasis on the Luquillo LTER site (DEB-9525902, March 1996 to March 2000). Research will concentrate on beneficial symbionts of pine roots, known as ectomycorrhizal fungi. Pine reaches its easternmost extent in the Caribbean on the island of Hispaniola, where it is the dominant ectomycorrhizal host. The rate of discovery of undescribed agaric fungi (mushrooms) in the Dominican Republic continued to rise throughout the previous study, especially among the ectomycorrhizal symbionts of the endemic pine (Pinus occidentalis). Further sampling will reveal many more species and varieties of agarics that remain to be discovered and described from that island.</literalLayout></para></abstract><funding><para><literalLayout>NSF</literalLayout></para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=LUQ,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access></dataset></ns0:eml>