<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-hbr.42.4" scope="system" system="knb-lter-hbr" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 http://www.hubbardbrook.org/eml/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Forest Inventory of a Northern Hardwood Forest: Bird Area 1981</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Tom</givenName><surName>Sherry</surName></individualName><organizationName>Department of Ecology, Evolution, and Organismal Biology, Tulane University</organizationName><address scope="document"><city>New Orleans</city><administrativeArea>LA</administrativeArea><postalCode>70118</postalCode><country>USA</country></address></creator><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Dick</givenName><surName>Holmes</surName></individualName><organizationName>Biology Department, Dartmouth College</organizationName><address scope="document"><city>Hanover</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03755</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice" /></creator><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Thomas G.</givenName><surName>Siccama</surName></individualName><organizationName>Yale School of Forestry and Environmental Studies</organizationName><address scope="document"><city>New Haven</city><administrativeArea>CT</administrativeArea><postalCode>06511</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice" /></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><organizationName>Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>U.S. Forest Service</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>271 Mast Rd.</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">603-868-7643</phone><phone phonetype="fax">603-868-7604</phone><onlineUrl>http://www.hubbardbrook.org</onlineUrl></metadataProvider><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Gene</givenName><surName>Likens</surName></individualName><organizationName>Institute of Ecosystem Studies</organizationName><address scope="document"><city>Millbrook</city><administrativeArea>NY</administrativeArea><postalCode>12545</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><role>associated researcher</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Tim</givenName><surName>Fahey</surName></individualName><organizationName>Department of Natural Resources, Cornell University</organizationName><address scope="document"><city>Ithaca</city><administrativeArea>NY</administrativeArea><postalCode>14853</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><role>associated researcher</role></associatedParty><intellectualRights><section><para><literalLayout>Publications using these data from the Hubbard Brook Ecosystem Study must include the following paragraph: Some data used in this publication were obtained by scientists of the Hubbard Brook Ecosystem Study; this publication has not been reviewed by those scientists. The Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest is operated and maintained by the Northeastern Research Station, U.S. Department of Agriculture, Newtown Square, Pennsylvania. Please note that data sharing and availability policy varies among the datasets available. Publishers of Hubbard Brook data are encouraged to contact the original data provider to obtain information for an acknowledgement of the original funding source of the research.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>LTER Network Data Access Requirements</title><para><literalLayout>The access to all LTER data is subject to requirements set forth by this policy document to enable data providers to track usage, evaluate its impact in the community, and confirm users' acceptance of the terms of acceptable use. These requirements are standardized across the LTER Network to provide contractual exchange of data between Site Data Providers, Network Data Providers, and Data Users that can be encoded into electronic form and exchanged between computers. This will allow direct access to data via a common portal once these requirements have been fulfilled. The following information may be required directly or by proxy prior to the transference of any data object:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Registration</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Name</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Affiliation</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Email address</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Full Contact Info</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptance of the General Public Use Agreement or Restricted Data Use Agreement, as applicable</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>A Statement of Intended Use that is compliant with the above agreements. Such statements may be made submitted explicitly or made implicitly via the data access portal interface.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section><section><title>Conditions of Data Use</title><para><literalLayout>The re-use of scientific data has the potential to greatly increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is fostered, supported and encouraged. Permission to use this dataset is granted to the Data User free of charge subject to the following terms:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptable Use. Use of the dataset will be restricted to academic, research, educational, government, recreational, or other not-for-profit professional purposes. The Data User is permitted to produce and distribute derived works from this dataset provided that they are released under the same license terms as those accompanying this Data Set. Any other uses for the Data Set or its derived products will require explicit permission from the dataset owner.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Redistribution. The data are provided for use by the Data User. The metadata and this license must accompany all copies made and be available to all users of this Data Set. The Data User will not redistribute the original Data Set beyond this collaboration sphere.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Citation. It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. Citation should take the following general form: Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset identifier.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acknowledgement. The Data User should acknowledge any institutional support or specific funding awards referenced in the metadata accompanying this dataset in any publications where the Data Set contributed significantly to its content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, the party that received the support, and any identifying information such as grant numbers.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Notification. The Data User will notify the Data Set Contact when any derivative work or publication based on or derived from the Data Set is distributed. The Data User will provide the data contact with two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the Data Set and will provide copies, or on-line access to, any derived digital products. Notification will include an explanation of how the Data Set was used to produce the derived work.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Collaboration. The Data Set has been released in the spirit of open scientific collaboration. Data Users are thus strongly encouraged to consider consultation, collaboration and/or co-authorship with the Data Set Creator.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist><literalLayout>By accepting this Data Set, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Data Owner shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement.</literalLayout><literalLayout>By viewing or downloading the data, I certify that I accept the conditions herein</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Disclaimer</title><para><literalLayout>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation contained in this Data Set, complete accuracy of data and metadata cannot be guaranteed. All data and metadata are made available "as is". The Data User holds all parties involved in the production or distribution of the Data Set harmless for damages resulting from its use or interpretation.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Definitions</title><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set</emphasis><literalLayout>Digital data and its metadata derived from any research activity such as field observations, collections, laboratory analysis, experiments, or the post-processing of existing data and identified by a unique identifier issued by a recognized cataloging authority such as a site, university, agency, or other organization.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data User</emphasis><literalLayout>ndividual to whom access has been granted to this Data Set, including his or her immediate collaboration sphere, defined here as the institutions, partners, students and staff with whom the Data User collaborates, and with whom access must be granted, in order to fulfill the Data User's intended use of the Data Set</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Creator</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution that produced the Data Set</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Owner</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution that holds intellectual property rights to the dataset. Note that this may or may not be defined as a legal copyright. If no other party is designated in the metadata as Data Set Owner, it may be presumed that these rights are held by the Data Set Creator.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Distributor</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution providing access to the Data Sets.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Contact</emphasis><literalLayout>party designated in the accompanying metadata of the Data Set as the primary contact for the Data Set.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/data/data_policy.php?firstname=metacat&amp;lastname=user&amp;affiliation=Other&amp;view=1&amp;accept=1&amp;comments=none&amp;phone=6035551212&amp;email=none@loopback.com&amp;target=ba81veg.txt</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Bird area studied here is a 2.5 km-squared area of mid elevation mature hardwood forest immediately below and to the west of the south-facing gauged watersheds at Hubbard Brook (elevation approximately 550 to 750 m).</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate /><eastBoundingCoordinate /><northBoundingCoordinate /><southBoundingCoordinate /><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>550</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>750</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><alternativeTimeScale><timeScaleName>Year</timeScaleName><timeScaleAgeEstimate>1981</timeScaleAgeEstimate></alternativeTimeScale></beginDate><endDate><alternativeTimeScale><timeScaleName>Ongoing</timeScaleName><timeScaleAgeEstimate>Ongoing</timeScaleAgeEstimate></alternativeTimeScale></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Thomas G.</givenName><surName>Siccama</surName></individualName><organizationName>Yale School of Forestry and Environmental Studies</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>205 Prospect St.</deliveryPoint><city>New Haven</city><administrativeArea>CT</administrativeArea><postalCode>06511</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(203)-432-5140</phone><electronicMailAddress>thomas.siccama@yale.edu</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>U.S Forest Service</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>U.S. Forest Service</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>271 Mast Rd.</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">603-868-7643</phone><phone phonetype="fax">603-868-7604</phone><onlineUrl>http://www.hubbardbrook.org</onlineUrl></publisher><pubPlace>Hubbard Brook LTER</pubPlace><methods><methodStep><description><section><title>SAMPLING BACKGROUND</title><para><literalLayout>The bird area has been used extensively for studies of bird populations since the 1970s.  The area is forested by typical northern hardwood species (sugar maple, beech and yellow birch) over about 85% of its area, and by patches of  red spruce and balsam fir over the remaining 15%.  Four semi permanent transects through this area, each 2 to 3 km long, were flagged  in 1981 and made permanent in 1991 with PVC stakes placed every 25 m. See the following webpage for more information: http://www.hubbardbrook.org/watersheds/maps/bird_area_location_map.htm.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>SAMPLING DESIGN</title><para><literalLayout>The inventory is representative of approximately 2.5 km2 of mid elevation northern hardwood forest. It consists of a total inventory of all trees &gt;=10 cm dbh, within each of four 10 m wide belt transects.  The parallel transects are placed approximately 200 m apart and run roughly in an east-west direction for 2200 to 2900 m.  Each transect is divided into between 88 and 116 continuous, contiguous plots, each 25 m long and 10 m wide, for a total of 397 plots.  The lengths of these plots are not always exactly 25 meters, due to drift or imprecise placement of the end stakes. The actual measured length of the plot is used to calculate the area of the plot.
In 1991, each live tree &gt;=10 cm dbh was tagged with a unique number.  This allowed us to track the fate of each tree and their progression from live to standing dead to snag to "down wood" at which point there were no longer followed.  The 1981 data included here, however, do not include tagged trees.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>DATA DESCRIPTION</title><para><literalLayout>The data consist of the diameters (dbh) of all the trees &gt;10 cm dbh, live and dead, along each of four belt transects (6229 individual stems).  An assessment of health or vigor was also recorded for each tree.  Live trees were noted "sick" if they had very sparse foliage or yellowing foliage in the mid summer sampling.  The presence and effect of beech bark disease was also noted.  Diseased beech showed signs of beech bark disease (cankers) but did not otherwise show evidence of crown decline.  Diseased beech with crown in decline had both cankers and were showing signs of physiological stress.  Dead trees were recorded as standing dead trees (trees dead but retaining most of their fine branches) or as snags (trees broken off above dbh or with only their major large branches still intact).
All stems that met the size criteria were measured individually, and in some years it was noted whether a stem was part of a group of stems from the same tree (i.e. multiple stems that split from a single trunk below breast height). For the Bird area, whether or not a stem was part of a group was not recorded until 1991.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>NOTES</title><para><literalLayout>It is not possible to compare the data from 1981 with the following years on a plot by plot basis. This is because trees were not individually tagged until 1991 and trees on the lines between plots could have "drifted" between plots from 1981 to 1991 depending on the observers line of sight or decision as to whether the center of the base of a tree is in one plot or the adjoining plot or outside of the transect.
For extensive notes about the details of these surveys and subsequent calculations, see the notes indicated at the bottom of the interactive calculation programs.</literalLayout></para></section></description><citation scope="document"><title>Population and biomass dynamics of a mature(ing) northern hardwood forest at Hubbard Brook</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><surName>(Siccama et al)</surName></individualName></creator><manuscript><institution scope="document"><organizationName>Hubbard Brook lter</organizationName></institution></manuscript></citation></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>CALCULATIONS</title><para><literalLayout>Phytosociology or biomass summaries can be obtained by using our interactive calculators. Phytosociology summaries include basal area, density and frequency of each species for the area as a whole or for smaller units as chosen by the user. Diameter distributions for a specific species can also be selected. Biomass summaries include biomass estimates by plant part for each species for the area as a whole or for smaller units as chosen by the user. Options to estimate productivity and total nutrient pools in the vegetation are also available.  For extensive details about how these calculations are made, see the notes indicated at the bottom of the calculator pages.</literalLayout></para></section></description></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=HBR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><otherEntity scope="document"><entityName>Quantifying the forest</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>stop-7.htm</objectName><dataFormat><externallyDefinedFormat><formatName>HTML</formatName></externallyDefinedFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/w6_tour/biomass-stop/stop-7.htm</url></online></distribution></physical><entityType>Webpage</entityType></otherEntity><otherEntity scope="document"><entityName>Bird area biomass calculator</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>biomassbird.htm</objectName><dataFormat><externallyDefinedFormat><formatName>HTML + Perl Script</formatName></externallyDefinedFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/w6_tour/biomass-stop/biomassbird.htm</url></online></distribution></physical><entityType>Webpage</entityType></otherEntity><otherEntity scope="document"><entityName>Bird area phytosociology calculator</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>phytobird.htm</objectName><dataFormat><externallyDefinedFormat><formatName>HTML + Perl Script</formatName></externallyDefinedFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/w6_tour/biomass-stop/phytobird.htm</url></online></distribution></physical><entityType>Webpage</entityType></otherEntity><otherEntity scope="document"><entityName>Bird area forest dynamics</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>dynambird.htm</objectName><dataFormat><externallyDefinedFormat><formatName>HTML</formatName></externallyDefinedFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/w6_tour/biomass-stop/dynambird.htm</url></online></distribution></physical><entityType>Webpage</entityType></otherEntity><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>ba81veg</entityName><entityDescription>Inventory data for Bird Area 1981</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>ba81veg.txt</objectName><characterEncoding>ASCII</characterEncoding><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n\r</recordDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/data/data_policy.php?firstname=metacat&amp;lastname=user&amp;affiliation=Other&amp;view=1&amp;accept=1&amp;comments=none&amp;phone=6035551212&amp;email=none@loopback.com&amp;target=ba81veg.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><additionalInfo><section><para><literalLayout>The data have not yet been published but a the manuscript listed in the methods section is under development.</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>The data is physically located at the Yale School of Forestry and Environmental Studies. Original field notes are in Greeley Lab, 370 Prospect Street, New Haven, CT. Data was last updated in October 2003 by Ellen Denny.</literalLayout></para></section></additionalInfo><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Plot</attributeName><attributeDefinition>plot number</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>An integer representing the plot</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Ln</attributeName><attributeDefinition>transect line number (using line numbers 5,9,13,17 of an existing grid)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>5</code><definition>Line number 5 of an existing grid</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>9</code><definition>Line number 9 of an existing grid</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>13</code><definition>Line number 13 of an existing grid</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>17</code><definition>Line number 17 of an existing grid</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Sp</attributeName><attributeDefinition>species acronym</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>ACSA</code><definition>Sugar maple (Acer saccharum)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>FAGR</code><definition>American beech (Fagus grandifolia)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>BEAL</code><definition>Yellow birch (Betula alleghaniensis)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>FRAM</code><definition>White ash (Fraxinus americana)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>ACSP</code><definition>Mountain maple (Acer spicatum)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>ACPE</code><definition>Striped maple or moose wood (Acer pensylvanicum)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>PRPE</code><definition>Pin or fire cherry (Prunus pensylvanica)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>PRVI</code><definition>Choke cherry (Prunus virginiana)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>ABBA</code><definition>Balsam fir (Abies balsamea)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>PIRU</code><definition>Red spruce (Picea rubens)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>BEPA</code><definition>White or paper birch (Betula papyrifera)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>SOAM</code><definition>Mountain ash (Sorbus americana)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>ACRU</code><definition>Red maple (Acer rubrum)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>TSCA</code><definition>Eastern hemlock (Tsuga canadensis)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>UNKN</code><definition>unknown, used for unidentifiable rotten snags</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>POTR</code><definition>Quaking aspen (Populus tremuloides)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>PRSE</code><definition>Black cherry (Prunus serotina)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>AMSP</code><definition>Shadbush (Amelanchier sp.)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>POGR</code><definition>Big-tooth aspen (Populus grandidentata)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>SASP</code><definition>Willow (Salix sp.)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>COAL</code><definition>Alternate-leaved dogwood (Cornus alternifolia)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>PRSP</code><definition>Cherry (unspecified) (Prunus sp.)</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Sp#</attributeName><attributeDefinition>species number</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>1</code><definition>Sugar maple (Acer saccharum)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>2</code><definition>American beech (Fagus grandifolia)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>3</code><definition>Yellow birch (Betula alleghaniensis)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>4</code><definition>White ash (Fraxinus americana)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>5</code><definition>Mountain maple (Acer spicatum)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>6</code><definition>Striped maple or moose wood (Acer pensylvanicum)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>7</code><definition>Pin or fire cherry (Prunus pensylvanica)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>8</code><definition>Choke cherry (Prunus virginiana)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>9</code><definition>Balsam fir (Abies balsamea)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>10</code><definition>Red spruce (Picea rubens)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>11</code><definition>White or paper birch (Betula papyrifera)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>12</code><definition>Mountain ash (Sorbus americana)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>13</code><definition>Red maple (Acer rubrum)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>14</code><definition>Eastern hemlock (Tsuga canadensis)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>15</code><definition>unknown, used for unidentifiable rotten snags</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>16</code><definition>Quaking aspen (Populus tremuloides)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>17</code><definition>Black cherry (Prunus serotina)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>18</code><definition>Shadbush (Amelanchier sp.)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>19</code><definition>Big-tooth aspen (Populus grandidentata)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>20</code><definition>Willow (Salix sp.)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>21</code><definition>Alternate-leaved dogwood (Cornus alternifolia)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>22</code><definition>Cherry (unspecified) (Prunus sp.)</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Seq#</attributeName><attributeDefinition>sequence number (unique number for each tree; multiple stems of same tree have same sequence)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>A positive integer representing the sequence number for the current sample</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Tag#</attributeName><attributeDefinition>tag number (not relevant until 1991 when Bird Area trees were tagged)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>A positive integer tag identifier</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-</code><codeExplanation>(Tag not relevant until 1991 when Bird Area trees were tagged)</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Dbh</attributeName><attributeDefinition>diameter at breast height, in cm</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit></unit><precision>.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Vig</attributeName><attributeDefinition>vigor code</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>0</code><definition>healthy</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>1</code><definition>diseased beech (with beech bark disease)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>2</code><definition>diseased beech with crown in decline</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>3</code><definition>sick (trees with crown in decline)</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>4</code><definition>standing dead tree</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>5</code><definition>standing dead snag (no limbs left)</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Lngt</attributeName><attributeDefinition>plot length in meters (see Sampling Design)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>meter</standardUnit></unit><precision>.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset></ns0:eml>