<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-hbr.49.3" scope="system" system="knb-lter-hbr" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 http://www.hubbardbrook.org/eml/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Fine Litterfall Data</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Timothy J.</givenName><surName>Fahey</surName></individualName><organizationName>Cornell University</organizationName></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><organizationName>Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>U.S. Forest Service</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>271 Mast Rd.</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">603-868-7643</phone><phone phonetype="fax">603-868-7604</phone><onlineUrl>http://www.hubbardbrook.org</onlineUrl></metadataProvider><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Jeffrey W.</givenName><surName>Hughes</surName></individualName><role>associated researcher</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Cindy</givenName><surName>Wood</surName></individualName><role>associated researcher</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Suzanne</givenName><surName>Wapner</surName></individualName><role>associated researcher</role></associatedParty><keywordSet><keyword>vegetation</keyword><keyword>litter</keyword><keyword>tree</keyword><keyword>leaf</keyword><keyword>foliage</keyword><keyword>seed</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><para><literalLayout>Publications using these data from the Hubbard Brook Ecosystem Study must include the following paragraph: Some data used in this publication were obtained by scientists of the Hubbard Brook Ecosystem Study; this publication has not been reviewed by those scientists. The Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest is operated and maintained by the Northeastern Research Station, U.S. Department of Agriculture, Newtown Square, Pennsylvania. Please note that data sharing and availability policy varies among the datasets available. Publishers of Hubbard Brook data are encouraged to contact the original data provider to obtain information for an acknowledgement of the original funding source of the research.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>LTER Network Data Access Requirements</title><para><literalLayout>The access to all LTER data is subject to requirements set forth by this policy document to enable data providers to track usage, evaluate its impact in the community, and confirm users' acceptance of the terms of acceptable use. These requirements are standardized across the LTER Network to provide contractual exchange of data between Site Data Providers, Network Data Providers, and Data Users that can be encoded into electronic form and exchanged between computers. This will allow direct access to data via a common portal once these requirements have been fulfilled. The following information may be required directly or by proxy prior to the transference of any data object:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Registration</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Name</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Affiliation</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Email address</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Full Contact Info</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptance of the General Public Use Agreement or Restricted Data Use Agreement, as applicable</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>A Statement of Intended Use that is compliant with the above agreements. Such statements may be made submitted explicitly or made implicitly via the data access portal interface.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section><section><title>Conditions of Data Use</title><para><literalLayout>The re-use of scientific data has the potential to greatly increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is fostered, supported and encouraged. Permission to use this dataset is granted to the Data User free of charge subject to the following terms:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptable Use. Use of the dataset will be restricted to academic, research, educational, government, recreational, or other not-for-profit professional purposes. The Data User is permitted to produce and distribute derived works from this dataset provided that they are released under the same license terms as those accompanying this Data Set. Any other uses for the Data Set or its derived products will require explicit permission from the dataset owner.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Redistribution. The data are provided for use by the Data User. The metadata and this license must accompany all copies made and be available to all users of this Data Set. The Data User will not redistribute the original Data Set beyond this collaboration sphere.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Citation. It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. Citation should take the following general form: Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset identifier.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acknowledgement. The Data User should acknowledge any institutional support or specific funding awards referenced in the metadata accompanying this dataset in any publications where the Data Set contributed significantly to its content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, the party that received the support, and any identifying information such as grant numbers.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Notification. The Data User will notify the Data Set Contact when any derivative work or publication based on or derived from the Data Set is distributed. The Data User will provide the data contact with two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the Data Set and will provide copies, or on-line access to, any derived digital products. Notification will include an explanation of how the Data Set was used to produce the derived work.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Collaboration. The Data Set has been released in the spirit of open scientific collaboration. Data Users are thus strongly encouraged to consider consultation, collaboration and/or co-authorship with the Data Set Creator.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist><literalLayout>By accepting this Data Set, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Data Owner shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement.</literalLayout><literalLayout>By viewing or downloading the data, I certify that I accept the conditions herein</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Disclaimer</title><para><literalLayout>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation contained in this Data Set, complete accuracy of data and metadata cannot be guaranteed. All data and metadata are made available "as is". The Data User holds all parties involved in the production or distribution of the Data Set harmless for damages resulting from its use or interpretation.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Definitions</title><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set</emphasis><literalLayout>Digital data and its metadata derived from any research activity such as field observations, collections, laboratory analysis, experiments, or the post-processing of existing data and identified by a unique identifier issued by a recognized cataloging authority such as a site, university, agency, or other organization.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data User</emphasis><literalLayout>ndividual to whom access has been granted to this Data Set, including his or her immediate collaboration sphere, defined here as the institutions, partners, students and staff with whom the Data User collaborates, and with whom access must be granted, in order to fulfill the Data User's intended use of the Data Set</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Creator</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution that produced the Data Set</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Owner</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution that holds intellectual property rights to the dataset. Note that this may or may not be defined as a legal copyright. If no other party is designated in the metadata as Data Set Owner, it may be presumed that these rights are held by the Data Set Creator.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Distributor</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution providing access to the Data Sets.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Contact</emphasis><literalLayout>party designated in the accompanying metadata of the Data Set as the primary contact for the Data Set.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/data/data_policy.php?firstname=metacat&amp;lastname=user&amp;affiliation=Other&amp;view=1&amp;accept=1&amp;comments=none&amp;phone=6035551212&amp;email=none@loopback.com&amp;target=fine_litter.txt</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Watershed 5 sites</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.739853</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.687683</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.957100</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.939945</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Bear Brook sites</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate /><eastBoundingCoordinate /><northBoundingCoordinate /><southBoundingCoordinate /><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>525</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>830</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Throughfall sites</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate /><eastBoundingCoordinate /><northBoundingCoordinate /><southBoundingCoordinate /><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>520</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>790</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><alternativeTimeScale><timeScaleName>Year</timeScaleName><timeScaleAgeEstimate>1992</timeScaleAgeEstimate></alternativeTimeScale></beginDate><endDate><alternativeTimeScale><timeScaleName>Year</timeScaleName><timeScaleAgeEstimate>2006</timeScaleAgeEstimate></alternativeTimeScale></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Tim</givenName><surName>Fahey</surName></individualName><organizationName>Dept. of Natural Resources, Cornell University</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Fernow Hall</deliveryPoint><city>Ithaca</city><administrativeArea>NY</administrativeArea><postalCode>14853</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(607)-255-5470</phone></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>U.S Forest Service</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>U.S. Forest Service</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>271 Mast Rd.</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">603-868-7643</phone><phone phonetype="fax">603-868-7604</phone><onlineUrl>http://www.hubbardbrook.org</onlineUrl></publisher><pubPlace>Hubbard Brook LTER</pubPlace><methods><methodStep><description><section><title>LOCATION DESCRIPTIONS</title><para><literalLayout>Watershed 5 sites:</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>Location and dimensions of collectors in WS5 were changed after May 1993. Before 1993 collectors (43 x 43 cm) were located in the twenty permanent vegetation plots. A map of these plots is filed in Durham, NH with the data manager.</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>After May 1993 new sites and collectors (0.097 m2) were initiated. Twenty traps are positioned randomly within four elevation zones, distributed with four collectors in each of five grid cells in WS5. Grid cell numbers refer to the WS5 grid; the watershed is gridded into 25 x 25 m cells, the corners of which are marked with orange poles, the pole in the northwest corner bearing the grid cell number. Contact the data manager for the grid cell map of WS5.</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout /></para><para><literalLayout>Bear Brook sites:</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>West of WS6: 0.097 m2 collectors are randomly situated along three -100 m long transects (325 degrees) which are approximately 25 m apart. Originally 20 collectors/elevation were set out; there are currently 12/elevation at all but high elevation where 15 remain.</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>lower - southwest of WS6 weir, west of tower platform - elevation @ 525 m;</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>mid - west of Throughfall Collector sites - elevation @ 585 m;</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>upper - west of tower site and seep - elevation @ 725 m;</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>high - west of rain gauge 9 - elevation @ 830 m.</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout /></para><para><literalLayout>Throughfall sites:</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>These sites are located along the WS6 trail except for the lower site which is located within the "wedge" area east of WS5: ten collections per/elevation (two - 0.097 m2 collectors randomly situated along five transects):</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>lower - elevation @ 520 m</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>mid - elevation @ 580 m</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>upper - elevation @ 730 m</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>spruce/fir - elevation @ 790 m</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>DATA DESCRIPTION</title><para><literalLayout>Fine litterfall (foliage, buds, seeds, fruits, bark and twigs/branches &lt; 2 cm diameter) is collected three times each year: soon after snowmelt (May), late summer before leaf fall (September), and late autumn after leaf fall (November). Note: Coarse litterfall is collected from cleared plots at a subset of the sites (see Hubbard Brook Coarse Litterfall Data).
						
	Spring and Summer collections are dried and weighed, Fall collections are sorted by species and tissue. Tree leaves are counted for each trap, seeds (except birch) are counted. A subsample of leaves of each species is taken for measurement of area per leaf. Leaf area index is estimated for each trap as the product of average area per leaf and leaf number. The whole sample is dried and weighed. All data except LAI are expressed per trap (0.097 m2) in the data set. Values found under species headings are leaf counts.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>SAMPLING DESIGN</title><para><literalLayout>The location of the 12 plots (four each in WS5, Bear Brook (west of WS6), and Throughfall Collection sites) have been chosen to stratify the sampling by elevation zones. These sites are co-located with sampling for soil CO2 flux, fine root biomass, throughfall, soil solutions, microbial biomass and microarthropods. Within sites, collectors are positioned randomly.</literalLayout></para></section></description></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=HBR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>fine_litter</entityName><entityDescription>Fine litter data at Hubbard Brook lter</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>fine_litter.txt</objectName><characterEncoding>ASCII</characterEncoding><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n\r</recordDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/data/data_policy.php?firstname=metacat&amp;lastname=user&amp;affiliation=Other&amp;view=1&amp;accept=1&amp;comments=none&amp;phone=6035551212&amp;email=none@loopback.com&amp;target=fine_litter.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><additionalInfo><section><title>NOTES</title><para><literalLayout>1. The collection for Fall 1992 was pooled into one sample for each site and represents the average per litter trap (for August - November 1992).</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>2. We realized recently that some leaf litter occasionally has blown into some collectors. Collectors were raised 1 m above ground surface in August 2001 to minimize this problem.</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>3. In November 1994 the samples were pooled for dry weight determination. The average dry weight for the site is entered for each trap.</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>4. In August 1998 a severe hailstorm removed substantial foliage (as well as twigs) in all locations. Leaves were counted in August 1998 collections only for BB High, BB Upper, TF High, TF Upper. LAI estimates for these sites include this correction. For other sites no correction for LAI lost to the hailstorm is included, but the extra litterfall mass appears in the August 1998 collection.</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>5. Collections on WS1 began in 1997.</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>The data is physically located at the USDA Forest Service, Durham, NH and was last updated in 2003.</literalLayout></para></section></additionalInfo><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>SITE</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Location where litterfall was collected</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>THROUGHFALL</code><definition>throughfall site</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>BEAR_BROOK</code><definition>Bear Brook site</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>W5</code><definition>Watershed 5 site</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>DATE</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Sample collection date (Month-Year)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>Mon-YY</formatString><dateTimePrecision>1 month</dateTimePrecision><dateTimeDomain><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">Jan-92</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">Nov-2000</maximum></bounds></dateTimeDomain></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>YEAR</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Sample collection year</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>YYYY</formatString><dateTimePrecision>1 year</dateTimePrecision><dateTimeDomain><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">1992</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">2000</maximum></bounds></dateTimeDomain></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>ELEV</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Elevation</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ordinal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>HIGH</code><definition>High elevation</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>LOW</code><definition>Low elevation</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>MID</code><definition>Mid elevation</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>UPPER</code><definition>Upper elevation</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></ordinal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>CELL</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Cell number</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>An integer number representing an existent cell number</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>na</code><codeExplanation>not applicable</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>TAG</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Tag number</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>An integer representing an existent tag number</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>POOLED</code><codeExplanation>Pooled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>DRY_MASS</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Oven dry weight of sample</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit></unit><precision>.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>M_COUNT</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Sugar maple leaf count</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>M_AREA</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Long-term average Sugar maple leaf area (per leaf)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>squareCentimeters</standardUnit></unit><precision>.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>f_COUNT</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Red maple leaf count</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>f_AREA</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Long-term average Red maple leaf area (per leaf)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>squareCentimeters</standardUnit></unit><precision>.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>t_COUNT</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Striped maple leaf count</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>t_AREA</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Long-term average Striped maple leaf area (per leaf)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>squareCentimeters</standardUnit></unit><precision>.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Q_COUNT</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Ash leaf count</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Q_AREA</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Long-term average Ash leaf area (per leaf)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>squareCentimeters</standardUnit></unit><precision>.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>B_COUNT</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Beech leaf count</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>B_AREA</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Long-term average Beech leaf area (per leaf)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>squareCentimeters</standardUnit></unit><precision>.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>W_COUNT</attributeName><attributeDefinition>White birch leaf count</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>W_AREA</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Long-term average White birch leaf area (per leaf)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>squareCentimeters</standardUnit></unit><precision>.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Y_COUNT</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Yellow birch leaf count</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Y_AREA</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Long-term average Yellow birch leaf area (per leaf)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>squareCentimeters</standardUnit></unit><precision>.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>P_COUNT</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Pin cherry leaf count</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>P_AREA</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Long-term average Pin cherry leaf area (per leaf)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>squareCentimeters</standardUnit></unit><precision>.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>a_COUNT</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Aspen leaf count</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>a_AREA</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Long-term average Aspen leaf area (per leaf)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>squareCentimeters</standardUnit></unit><precision>.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>LAI</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Leaf Area Index</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>metersSquaredPerMetersSquared</customUnit></unit><precision>.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.00</code><codeExplanation>missing data</codeExplanation></missingValueCode><missingValueCode><code>n/s</code><codeExplanation>not sampled</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>COMMENT</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Comments</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Comments (if none, no value present here) on the current datum</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>0x20</code><codeExplanation>No commens on this datum</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><unitList><unit abbreviation="m^2/m^2" id="metersSquaredPerMetersSquared" multiplierToSI="1" name="metersSquaredPerMetersSquared" parentSI="squareMeter"><description>A measure of area per area</description></unit></unitList></additionalMetadata></ns0:eml>