<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-hbr.60.5" scope="system" system="knb-lter-hbr" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 http://www.hubbardbrook.org/eml/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Daily Solar Radiation Data</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Campbell</givenName><surName>John</surName></individualName><organizationName>US Forest Service</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>271 Mast Rd.</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(603)-868-7643</phone></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><organizationName>Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>U.S. Forest Service</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>271 Mast Rd.</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">603-868-7643</phone><phone phonetype="fax">603-868-7604</phone><onlineUrl>http://www.hubbardbrook.org</onlineUrl></metadataProvider><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Amey</givenName><surName>Bailey</surName></individualName><role>associated researcher</role></associatedParty><keywordSet><keyword>weather</keyword><keyword>climate</keyword><keyword>solar radiation</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><para><literalLayout>Publications using these data from the Hubbard Brook Ecosystem Study must include the following paragraph: Some data used in this publication were obtained by scientists of the Hubbard Brook Ecosystem Study; this publication has not been reviewed by those scientists. The Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest is operated and maintained by the Northeastern Research Station, U.S. Department of Agriculture, Newtown Square, Pennsylvania. Please note that data sharing and availability policy varies among the datasets available. Publishers of Hubbard Brook data are encouraged to contact the original data provider to obtain information for an acknowledgement of the original funding source of the research.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>LTER Network Data Access Requirements</title><para><literalLayout>The access to all LTER data is subject to requirements set forth by this policy document to enable data providers to track usage, evaluate its impact in the community, and confirm users' acceptance of the terms of acceptable use. These requirements are standardized across the LTER Network to provide contractual exchange of data between Site Data Providers, Network Data Providers, and Data Users that can be encoded into electronic form and exchanged between computers. This will allow direct access to data via a common portal once these requirements have been fulfilled. The following information may be required directly or by proxy prior to the transference of any data object:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Registration</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Name</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Affiliation</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Email address</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Full Contact Info</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptance of the General Public Use Agreement or Restricted Data Use Agreement, as applicable</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>A Statement of Intended Use that is compliant with the above agreements. Such statements may be made submitted explicitly or made implicitly via the data access portal interface.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section><section><title>Conditions of Data Use</title><para><literalLayout>The re-use of scientific data has the potential to greatly increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is fostered, supported and encouraged. Permission to use this dataset is granted to the Data User free of charge subject to the following terms:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptable Use. Use of the dataset will be restricted to academic, research, educational, government, recreational, or other not-for-profit professional purposes. The Data User is permitted to produce and distribute derived works from this dataset provided that they are released under the same license terms as those accompanying this Data Set. Any other uses for the Data Set or its derived products will require explicit permission from the dataset owner.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Redistribution. The data are provided for use by the Data User. The metadata and this license must accompany all copies made and be available to all users of this Data Set. The Data User will not redistribute the original Data Set beyond this collaboration sphere.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Citation. It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. Citation should take the following general form: Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset identifier.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acknowledgement. The Data User should acknowledge any institutional support or specific funding awards referenced in the metadata accompanying this dataset in any publications where the Data Set contributed significantly to its content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, the party that received the support, and any identifying information such as grant numbers.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Notification. The Data User will notify the Data Set Contact when any derivative work or publication based on or derived from the Data Set is distributed. The Data User will provide the data contact with two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the Data Set and will provide copies, or on-line access to, any derived digital products. Notification will include an explanation of how the Data Set was used to produce the derived work.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Collaboration. The Data Set has been released in the spirit of open scientific collaboration. Data Users are thus strongly encouraged to consider consultation, collaboration and/or co-authorship with the Data Set Creator.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist><literalLayout>By accepting this Data Set, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Data Owner shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement.</literalLayout><literalLayout>By viewing or downloading the data, I certify that I accept the conditions herein</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Disclaimer</title><para><literalLayout>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation contained in this Data Set, complete accuracy of data and metadata cannot be guaranteed. All data and metadata are made available "as is". The Data User holds all parties involved in the production or distribution of the Data Set harmless for damages resulting from its use or interpretation.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Definitions</title><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set</emphasis><literalLayout>Digital data and its metadata derived from any research activity such as field observations, collections, laboratory analysis, experiments, or the post-processing of existing data and identified by a unique identifier issued by a recognized cataloging authority such as a site, university, agency, or other organization.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data User</emphasis><literalLayout>ndividual to whom access has been granted to this Data Set, including his or her immediate collaboration sphere, defined here as the institutions, partners, students and staff with whom the Data User collaborates, and with whom access must be granted, in order to fulfill the Data User's intended use of the Data Set</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Creator</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution that produced the Data Set</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Owner</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution that holds intellectual property rights to the dataset. Note that this may or may not be defined as a legal copyright. If no other party is designated in the metadata as Data Set Owner, it may be presumed that these rights are held by the Data Set Creator.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Distributor</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution providing access to the Data Sets.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Contact</emphasis><literalLayout>party designated in the accompanying metadata of the Data Set as the primary contact for the Data Set.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/data/data_policy.php?firstname=metacat&amp;lastname=user&amp;affiliation=Other&amp;view=1&amp;accept=1&amp;comments=none&amp;phone=6035551212&amp;email=none@loopback.com&amp;target=rad.txt</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>HBEF station headquarters</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.701859</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.701859</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.943943</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.943943</southBoundingCoordinate><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>830</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>830</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>foot</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><alternativeTimeScale><timeScaleName>Month Year</timeScaleName><timeScaleAgeEstimate>January 1956</timeScaleAgeEstimate></alternativeTimeScale></beginDate><endDate><alternativeTimeScale><timeScaleName>Ongoing</timeScaleName><timeScaleAgeEstimate>Ongoing</timeScaleAgeEstimate></alternativeTimeScale></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>John</givenName><surName>Campbell</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>PO Box 640</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(603)-868-7643</phone><electronicMailAddress>jlcampbell@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>U.S Forest Service</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>U.S. Forest Service</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>271 Mast Rd.</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">603-868-7643</phone><phone phonetype="fax">603-868-7604</phone><onlineUrl>http://www.hubbardbrook.org</onlineUrl></publisher><pubPlace>Hubbard Brook LTER</pubPlace><methods><methodStep><description><section><title>SAMPLING DESIGN</title><para><literalLayout>Daily solar radiation has been measured at HBEF Headquarters since 1960, using several different sensors. Solar radiation has been recorded continuously by a Belfort pyrano--graph and later by a Weather Measure pyranograph. The instrument has been at its current Headquarter location since 1960 and before that at weather station 1, near weir 1. Since the installation of the automatic weather station in 1981, its LiCor pyranometer has replaced the pyranograph as the primary radiation sensor. The pyranograph is still maintained as a backup. Solar radiation is now sampled by the LiCor sensor once minute and hourly means are calculated by a Campbell CR-21 Data logger. The data are dumped hourly to a data storage module, which is changed and downloaded monthly. Where LiCor data are not available, pyranograph data are used. The pyranograph chart is changed weekly. Because of rapid fluctuation, instantaneous readings cannot be obtained from the pyranograph on partly cloudy days. The pyranograph chart is digitized visually, using a digitizer, for each 2-hour increment throughout the day.</literalLayout></para></section></description><instrumentation>Belfort pyranograph</instrumentation><instrumentation>Weather measure pyranograph</instrumentation><instrumentation>LiCor pyranometer</instrumentation><instrumentation>LiCor sensor</instrumentation><instrumentation>Campbell CR-21 Data logger</instrumentation></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=HBR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>rad</entityName><entityDescription>Solar radiation data for Hubbard Brook LTER</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>rad.txt</objectName><characterEncoding>ASCII</characterEncoding><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n\r</recordDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/data/data_policy.php?firstname=metacat&amp;lastname=user&amp;affiliation=Other&amp;view=1&amp;accept=1&amp;comments=none&amp;phone=6035551212&amp;email=none@loopback.com&amp;target=rad.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><additionalInfo><section><title>NOTES</title><para><literalLayout>Although all sensors appear to have been within about +- 5% of the true value, users should be aware that bias may exist in the radiation data and may change over time.
Beginning in 1987, zeros are embedded in the date.</literalLayout></para><para><literalLayout>The data is physically located at the USDA Forest Service, Durham, NH and was last updated on March 26, 2003.</literalLayout></para></section></additionalInfo><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Date</attributeName><attributeLabel>Date</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Sample date</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>YYYYMMDD</formatString><dateTimePrecision>a day</dateTimePrecision><dateTimeDomain /></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>HQ</attributeName><attributeLabel>HQ</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Measured at Headquarters</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>megaJoulesPerSquareMeter</customUnit></unit><precision>.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-99.99</code><codeExplanation>Data missing or not taken at time</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><unitList><unit abbreviation="MJ/M^2" id="megaJoulesPerSquareMeter" name="megaJoulesPerSquareMeter" parentSi="joule"><description>A measure of solar radiation energy per unit area</description></unit></unitList></additionalMetadata></ns0:eml>