<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-hbr.113.2" scope="system" system="knb-lter-hbr" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 http://www.hubbardbrook.org/eml/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset id="113.1" scope="document" system="knb-lter-hbr"><shortName>nlcd_92</shortName><title>Hubbard Brook National Land Cover Dataset 1992</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>John</givenName><surName>Campbell</surName></individualName><organizationName>USDA Forest Service</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>PO Box 640</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(603) 868-7643</phone></creator><pubDate>2004-06-24</pubDate><language>English</language><abstract><para>The National Land Cover Dataset was compiled from Landsat satellite TM imagery
                (circa 1992) with a spatial resolution of 30 meters and supplemented by various
                ancillary data (where available). The analysis and interpretation of the satellite
                imagery was conducted using very large, sometimes multi-state image mosaics (i.e. up
                to 18 Landsat scenes). Using a relatively small number of aerial photographs for
                'ground truth', the thematic interpretations were necessarily conducted from a
                spatially-broad perspective. Furthermore, the accuracy assessments (see below)
                correspond to 'federal regions' which are groupings of contiguous states. Thus, the
                reliability of the data is greatest at the state or multi-State level. The
                statistical accuracy of the data is known only for the region. Important Caution
                Advisory With this in mind, users are cautioned to carefully scrutinize the data to
                see if they are of sufficient reliability before attempting to use the dataset for
                larger-scale or local analyses. This evaluation must be made remembering that the
                NLCD represents conditions in the early 1990s. The New Hampshire portion of the NLCD
                was created as part of land cover mapping activities for Federal Region I that
                includes the States of Connecticut, Maine, Vermont, Rhode Island, New Hampshire, and
                Massachusetts. The NLCD classification contains 21 different land cover categories
                with a spatial resolution of 30 meters. The NLCD was produced as a cooperative
                effort between the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and the U.S. Environmental
                Protection Agency (USEPA) to produce a consistent, land cover data layer for the
                conterminous U.S. using early 1990s Landsat thematic mapper (TM) data purchased by
                the Multi-resolution Land Characterization (MRLC) Consortium. The MRLC Consortium is
                a partnership of federal agencies that produce or use land cover data. Partners
                include the USGS (National Mapping, Biological Resources, and Water Resources
                Divisions), USEPA, the U.S. Forest Service, and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric
                Administration. The original NLCD grid was projected into UTM Zone 19 and was
                clipped to a box surrounding the USDA Forest Service, Hubbard Brook Experimental
                Forest.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">land use</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">land cover</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">US Forest Service</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">landsat</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">imagery</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">remote sensing</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">forest</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">vegetation</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">Hubbard Brook</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">New Hampshire</keyword><keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><additionalInfo><para>http://www.hubbardbrook.org/research/gis/coverages/nlcd_92.gif</para></additionalInfo><intellectualRights><para>The USDA Forest Service manages resource information and derived data as a service
                to USDA Forest Service users of digital geographic data. The USDA Forest Service is
                in no way condoning or endorsing the application of these data for any given
                purpose. It is the sole responsibility of the user to determine whether or not the
                data are suitable for the intended purpose. It is also the obligation of the user to
                apply the data in an appropriate and conscientious manner. The USDA Forest Service
                provides no warranty, nor accepts any liability occurring from any incorrect,
                incomplete, or misleading data, or from any incorrect, incomplete, or misleading use
                of these data. Much of the USDA Forest Service data are compiled, processed, and
                maintained with ARC/INFO software developed by the Environmental Systems Research
                Institute (ESRI). Much of the information presented uses conventions and terms
                popularized by ARC/INFO and its user community. The mention of commercial firms or
                products is for clarity and identification of procedures and methods only, and no
                endorsements are implied by the USDA Forest Service.</para><section><title>LTER Network Data Access Requirements</title><para><literalLayout>The access to all LTER data is subject to requirements set forth by this policy document to enable data providers to track usage, evaluate its impact in the community, and confirm users' acceptance of the terms of acceptable use. These requirements are standardized across the LTER Network to provide contractual exchange of data between Site Data Providers, Network Data Providers, and Data Users that can be encoded into electronic form and exchanged between computers. This will allow direct access to data via a common portal once these requirements have been fulfilled. The following information may be required directly or by proxy prior to the transference of any data object:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Registration</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Name</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Affiliation</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Email address</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Full Contact Info</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptance of the General Public Use Agreement or Restricted Data Use Agreement, as applicable</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>A Statement of Intended Use that is compliant with the above agreements. Such statements may be made submitted explicitly or made implicitly via the data access portal interface.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section><section><title>Conditions of Data Use</title><para><literalLayout>The re-use of scientific data has the potential to greatly increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is fostered, supported and encouraged. Permission to use this dataset is granted to the Data User free of charge subject to the following terms:</literalLayout><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acceptable Use. Use of the dataset will be restricted to academic, research, educational, government, recreational, or other not-for-profit professional purposes. The Data User is permitted to produce and distribute derived works from this dataset provided that they are released under the same license terms as those accompanying this Data Set. Any other uses for the Data Set or its derived products will require explicit permission from the dataset owner.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Redistribution. The data are provided for use by the Data User. The metadata and this license must accompany all copies made and be available to all users of this Data Set. The Data User will not redistribute the original Data Set beyond this collaboration sphere.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Citation. It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. Citation should take the following general form: Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset identifier.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Acknowledgement. The Data User should acknowledge any institutional support or specific funding awards referenced in the metadata accompanying this dataset in any publications where the Data Set contributed significantly to its content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, the party that received the support, and any identifying information such as grant numbers.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Notification. The Data User will notify the Data Set Contact when any derivative work or publication based on or derived from the Data Set is distributed. The Data User will provide the data contact with two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the Data Set and will provide copies, or on-line access to, any derived digital products. Notification will include an explanation of how the Data Set was used to produce the derived work.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><literalLayout>Collaboration. The Data Set has been released in the spirit of open scientific collaboration. Data Users are thus strongly encouraged to consider consultation, collaboration and/or co-authorship with the Data Set Creator.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist><literalLayout>By accepting this Data Set, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Data Owner shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement.</literalLayout><literalLayout>By viewing or downloading the data, I certify that I accept the conditions herein</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Disclaimer</title><para><literalLayout>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation contained in this Data Set, complete accuracy of data and metadata cannot be guaranteed. All data and metadata are made available "as is". The Data User holds all parties involved in the production or distribution of the Data Set harmless for damages resulting from its use or interpretation.</literalLayout></para></section><section><title>Definitions</title><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set</emphasis><literalLayout>Digital data and its metadata derived from any research activity such as field observations, collections, laboratory analysis, experiments, or the post-processing of existing data and identified by a unique identifier issued by a recognized cataloging authority such as a site, university, agency, or other organization.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data User</emphasis><literalLayout>ndividual to whom access has been granted to this Data Set, including his or her immediate collaboration sphere, defined here as the institutions, partners, students and staff with whom the Data User collaborates, and with whom access must be granted, in order to fulfill the Data User's intended use of the Data Set</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Creator</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution that produced the Data Set</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Owner</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution that holds intellectual property rights to the dataset. Note that this may or may not be defined as a legal copyright. If no other party is designated in the metadata as Data Set Owner, it may be presumed that these rights are held by the Data Set Creator.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Distributor</emphasis><literalLayout>individual or institution providing access to the Data Sets.</literalLayout></para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Data Set Contact</emphasis><literalLayout>party designated in the accompanying metadata of the Data Set as the primary contact for the Data Set.</literalLayout></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/research/gis/gisexe/nlcd_92.exe</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Hubbard Brook</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.829489</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.661710</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>43.977519</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>43.898077</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><purpose><para>To provide the public with spatial data from the Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest
                for use in research and educational activities.</para></purpose><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>John</givenName><surName>Campbell</surName></individualName><organizationName>USDA Forest Service</organizationName><positionName>Ecologist</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>USDA Forest Service</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Northeastern Research Station</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Attn: John Campbell</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>271 Mast Road</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03801</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(603) 868-7643</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(603) 868-7640</phone><electronicMailAddress>jlcampbell@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher id="HBR-LTER" scope="document"><organizationName>USDA Forest Service</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Northeastern Research Station</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>USDA Forest Service</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>PO Box 640</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03801</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(603) 868-7643</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(603) 868-7604</phone></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><para>Land Cover Characterization: The project is being carried out on the basis
                        of 10 Federal Regions that make up the conterminous United States; each
                        region is comprised of multiple states; each region is processed in
                        subregional units that are limited to the area covered by no more than 18
                        Landsat TM scenes. The general NLCD procedure is to: (1) mosaic subregional
                        TM scenes and classify them using an unsupervised clustering algorithm, (2)
                        interpret and label the clusters/classes using aerial photographs as
                        reference data, (3) resolve the labeling of confused clusters/classes using
                        the appropriate ancillary data source(s), and (4) incorporate land cover
                        information from other data sets and perform manual edits to augment and
                        refine the "basic" classification developed above. Two seasonally distinct
                        TM mosaics are produced, a leaves-on version (summer) and a leaves-off
                        (spring/fall) version. TM bands 3, 4, 5, and 7 are mosaicked for both the
                        leaves-on and leaves-off versions. For mosaick purposes, a base scene is
                        selected for each mosaic and the other scenes are adjusted to mimic spectral
                        properties of the base scene using histogram matching in regions of spatial
                        overlap. Following mosaicking, either the leaves-off version or leaves-on
                        version is selected to be the "base" for the land cover mapping process. The
                        4 TM bands of the "base" mosaic are clustered to produce a single 100- class
                        image using an unsupervised clustering algorithm. Each of the spectrally
                        distinct clusters/classes is then assigned to one or more Anderson level 1
                        and 2 land cover classes using National High Altitude Photography program
                        (NHAP) and National Aerial Photography program (NAPP) aerial photographs as
                        a reference. Almost invariably, individual spectral clusters/classes are
                        confused between two or more land cover classes. Separation of the confused
                        spectral clusters/classes into appropriate NLCD class is accomplished using
                        ancillary data layers. Standard ancillary data layers include: the
                        "non-base" mosaic TM bands and 100- class cluster image; derived TM
                        normalized vegetation index (NDVI), various TM band ratios, TM date bands;
                        3-arc second Digital Terrain Elevation Data (DTED) and derived slope, aspect
                        and shaded relief; population and housing density data; USGS land use and
                        land cover (LUDA); and National Wetlands Inventory(NWI) data if available.
                        Other ancillary data sources may include soils data, unique state or
                        regional land cover data sets, or data from other federal programs such as
                        the National Gap Analysis Program (GAP) of the USGS Biological Resources
                        Division (BRD). For a given confused spectral cluster/class, digital values
                        of the various ancillary data layers are compared to determine: (1) which
                        data layers are the most effective for splitting the confused cluster/class
                        into the appropriate NLCD class, and (2) the appropriate layer thresholds
                        for making the split(s). Models are then developed using one to several
                        ancillary data layers to split the confused cluster/class into the NLCD
                        class. For example, a population density threshold is used to separatehigh-intensity residential areas from commercial/industrial/transportation.
                        Or a cluster/class might be confused between row crop and grasslands. To
                        split this particular cluster/class, a TM NDVI threshold might be identified
                        and used with an elevation threshold in a class-splitting model to make the
                        appropriate NLCD class assignments. A purely spectral example is using the
                        temporally opposite TM layers to discriminate confused cluster/classes such
                        as hay pasture vs. row crops and deciduous forests vs. evergreen forests;
                        simple thresholds that contrast the seasonal differences in vegetation
                        between leaves-on vs. leaves-off. Not all cluster/class confusion can be
                        successfully modeled out. Certain classes such as urban/recreational grasses
                        or quarries/strip mines/gravel pits that are not spectrally unique require
                        manual editing. These class features are typically visually identified and
                        then reclassified using on-screen digitizing and recoding. Other classes
                        such as wetlands require the use of specific data sets such as NWI to
                        provide the most accurate classification. Areas lacking NWI data are
                        typically subset out and modeling is used to estimate wetlands in these
                        localized areas. The final NLCD product results from the classification
                        (interpretation and labeling) of the 100-class "base" cluster mosaic using
                        both automated and manual processes, incorporating both spectral and
                        conditional data layers. For a more detailed explanation please see
                        Vogelmann et al. 1998 and Vogelmann et al. 1998. Discussion: While we
                        believe that the approach taken has yielded a very good general land cover
                        classification product for the nation, it is important to indicate to the
                        user where there might be some potential problems. The biggest concerns are
                        listed below: 1) Some of the TM data sets are not temporally ideal.
                        Leaves-off data Sets are heavily relied upon for discriminating between
                        hay/pasture and row crop, and also for discriminating between forest
                        classes. The success of discriminating between these classes using
                        leaves-off data sets hinges on the time of data acquisition. When
                        hay/pasture areas are non-green, they are not easily distinguishable from
                        other agricultural areas using remotely sensed data. However, there is a
                        temporal window during which hay and pasture areas green up before most
                        other vegetation (excluding evergreens, which have different spectral
                        properties); during this window these areas are easily distinguishable from
                        other crop areas. The discrimination between hay/pasture and deciduous
                        forest is likewise optimized by selecting data in a temporal window where
                        deciduous vegetation has yet to leaf out. It is difficult to acquire a
                        single-date of imagery (leaves-on or leaves-off) that adequately
                        differentiates between both deciduous/hay and pasture and hay pasture /row
                        crop. 2) The data sets used cover a range of years (see data sources), and
                        Changes that have taken place across the landscape over the time period may
                        not have been captured. While this is not viewed as a major problem for mostclasses, it is possible that some land cover features change more rapidly
                        than might be expected (e.g. hay one year, row crop the next). 3) Wetlands
                        classes are extremely difficult to extract from Landsat TM spectral
                        information alone. The use of ancillary information such as National
                        Wetlands Inventory (NWI) data is highly desirable. We relied On GAP, LUDA,
                        or proximity to streams and rivers as well as spectral data to delineate
                        wetlands in areas without NWI data. 4) Separation of natural grass and shrub
                        is problematic. Areas observed on the ground to be shrub or grass are not
                        always distinguishable spectrally. Likewise, there was often disagreement
                        between LUDA and GAP on these classes. Acknowledgments This work was
                        performed under contract the U.S. Geological Survey(Contract
                        1434-CR-97-CN-40274). References More detailed information on the
                        methodologies and techniques employed In this work can be found in the
                        following: Kelly, P.M., and White, J.M., 1993. Preprocessing remotely sensed
                        data for efficient analysis and classification, Applications of Artificial
                        Intelligence 1993: Knowledge-Based Systems in Aerospace and Industry,
                        Proceeding of SPIE, 1993, 24-30. Cowardin, L.M., V. Carter, F.C. Golet, and
                        E.T. LaRoe, 1979. Classification of Wetlands and Deepwater Habitats of the
                        United States, Fish and Wildlife Service, U.S. Department of the Interior,
                        Washington, D.C. Vogelmann, J.E., Sohl, T., and Howard, S.M., 1998.
                        "Regional Characterization of Land Cover Using Multiple Sources of Data."
                        Photogrammetric Engineering &amp; Remote Sensing, Vol. 64, No. 1, pp.
                        45-47. Vogelmann, J.E., Sohl, T., Campbell, P.V., and Shaw, D.M., 1998.
                        "Regional Land Cover Characterization Using Landsat Thematic Mapper Data and
                        Ancillary Data Sources." Environmental Monitoring and Assessment, Vol. 51,
                        pp. 415-428. Zhu, Z., Yang, L., Stehman, S., and Czaplewski, R., 1999.
                        "Designing an Accuracy Assessment for USGS Regional Land Cover Mapping
                        Program." (In review) Photogrametric Engineering &amp; Remote
                    Sensing.</para></description><dataSource scope="document"><title>New Hampshire Land Cover Data Set</title><creator scope="document"><organizationName>US Geological Survey, EROS Data Center</organizationName></creator><pubDate>1995-05-25</pubDate><additionalInfo><para>raster digital data</para></additionalInfo><contact scope="document"><organizationName>US Geological Survey, EROS Data Center</organizationName></contact></dataSource></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=HBR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><spatialRaster id="nlcd_92" scope="document"><entityName>nlcd_92</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>Cover type</objectName><dataFormat><externallyDefinedFormat><formatName>Raster Dataset</formatName></externallyDefinedFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://www.hubbardbrook.org/research/gis/gisexe/nlcd_92.exe</url></online></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute id="Covertype" scope="document"><attributeName>Value</attributeName><attributeDefinition>National Land Cover Type classification</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">ESRI</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>11</code><definition>Open Water</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>21</code><definition>Low Intensity Residential</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>23</code><definition>Commercial/Industrial/Transportation</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>31</code><definition>Bare Rock/Sand/Clay</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>32</code><definition>Quarries/Strip Mines/Gravel Pits</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>33</code><definition>Transitional</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>41</code><definition>Deciduous Forest</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>42</code><definition>Evergreen Forest</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>43</code><definition>Mixed Forest</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>51</code><definition>Shrubland</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>81</code><definition>Pasture/Hay</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>82</code><definition>Row Crops</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>85</code><definition>Urban/Recreational Grasses</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>91</code><definition>Woody Wetlands</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>92</code><definition>Emergent Herbaceous Wetlands</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="Count" scope="document"><attributeName>Count</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Number of cells that have this value in the grid</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">ESRI</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><precision>0</precision><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType><bounds><maximum exclusive="false">65519</maximum></bounds><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">54</minimum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList><spatialReference scope="document"><horizCoordSysName>NAD_1927_UTM_Zone_19N</horizCoordSysName></spatialReference><horizontalAccuracy><accuracyReport>Each Landsat Thematic Mapper image used to create the NLCD was
                    precision terrain-corrected using 3-arc-second digital terrain elevation data
                    (DTED), and georegistered using ground control points. This resulted in a root
                    mean square registration error of less than 1 pixel (30
                meters).</accuracyReport></horizontalAccuracy><verticalAccuracy><accuracyReport /></verticalAccuracy><cellSizeXDirection>26.563664</cellSizeXDirection><cellSizeYDirection>26.563664</cellSizeYDirection><numberOfBands>1</numberOfBands><rasterOrigin>Upper Left</rasterOrigin><rows>316</rows><columns>497</columns><verticals>1</verticals><cellGeometry>matrix</cellGeometry></spatialRaster></dataset></ns0:eml>