<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-and.3115.4" scope="system" system="http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/data/mastercatalog.cfm?topnav=97" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd"><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=AND,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataset scope="document"><title>Influence of tree-fall gaps on soil characteristics in gaps of varying sizes in the Andrews Experimental Forest</title><creator scope="document"><organizationName>Andrews Forest LTER Site</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Forest Ecosystems and Society Department in Forestry</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>201K Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-8480</phone><electronicMailAddress>lterweb@fsl.orst.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/</onlineUrl></creator><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Robert</givenName><givenName>P.</givenName><surName>Griffiths</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Dept. of Forest Science;321 Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-6559</phone><electronicMailAddress>bbgriff@peak.org</electronicMailAddress><electronicMailAddress>griff@for.orst.edu</electronicMailAddress></creator><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Robert</givenName><givenName>P.</givenName><surName>Griffiths</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Dept. of Forest Science;321 Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-6559</phone><electronicMailAddress>bbgriff@peak.org</electronicMailAddress><electronicMailAddress>griff@for.orst.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Robert</givenName><givenName>P.</givenName><surName>Griffiths</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Dept. of Forest Science;321 Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-6559</phone><electronicMailAddress>bbgriff@peak.org</electronicMailAddress><electronicMailAddress>griff@for.orst.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>Abstractor</role></associatedParty><pubDate>2007-06-13</pubDate><abstract><section><para>Soil properties in 10, 20, 30, and 50 meter tree-fall gaps were compared with soils in the surrounding old-growth Douglas-fir forest by sampling at 1 meter intervals along transects running north and south through the gaps.  These transects extended one radius into the surrounding forest.  This study was designed to determine if carbon cycling within these gaps were different from those in the soils of surrounding undisturbed forests.  If there were differences, she wanted to determine what sized gap was required to show an effect.  These transects were divided into four zones.  Two zones were north of the E-W centerline; one in and one out of the gap.  The other two zones were south of the E-W centerline; one in and one out of the gap.

Soil moisture and temperature were both higher in the gap than in the surrounding forest but SOM, lab respiration and litter depth were both lower in the gap than in the forest.  These results suggest that either litter input is lower in the gap than in the surrounding forest and/or that the decomposition rates are lower in the gap.  

Except for the smallest gap, soil moisture was lower and temperature higher in the northern half of the gap.  In the 50 m gaps, laboratory respiration rates, litter depth, and SOM were higher in the southern portion of the gap as were total carbon values.</para></section></abstract><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER)</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Inorganic nutrients</keyword><keywordThesaurus>Andrews Experimental Forest site thesaurus</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><additionalInfo><para>The following are publications describing past work in these gaps: 
	
Gray, A.N., and T.A. Spies. 1995.  Water content measurement in decayed wood and forest soils using time domain reflectometry.  Canadian Journal of Forest Research 25: 376-385.

Gray, A.N., and T.A. Spies. 1996.  Gap size, within-gap position, and canopy structure effects on seedling establishment of conifer species in forest canopy gaps.  Journal of Ecology 84: 635-645.

Gray, A.N., and T.A. Spies. 1997.  Microsite controls on tree seedling establishment in conifer forest canopy gaps.  Ecology 78:2458-2473.
 
McCune, B. 1993.  Gradients in epiphyte biomass in three Pseudotsuga-Tsuga forests of different ages in western Oregon and Washington.  Bryologist 96: 405-411.

McCune, B. 1994.  Using epiphyte litter to estimate epiphyte biomass. Bryologist 97: 396-401.

Van Pelt, R., and M.P. North. 1996.  Analyzing canopy structure in Pacific Northwest old-growth forests with a stand-scale crown model.  Northwest Science 70(special issue): 15-30.

Van Pelt, Robert, and Jerry F. Franklin. 1999. Response of understory trees to experimental gaps in old-growth Douglas-fir forests. Ecological Applications 9: 504-512.

Van Pelt, Robert, and Jerry F. Franklin. 2000. Influence of canopy structure on the understory environment in tall, old-growth conifer forests. Canadian Journal of Forest Research 30: 1231-1245.

Vogt, K.A., D.A. Publicover, J. Bloomfield, J.M. Perez, D.J. Vogt and W.L. Silver. 1993. Belowground responses as indicators of environmental change. Environmental and Experimental Botany 33:189-205.

Vogt, K.A., D.J. Vogt, H. Asbjornsen, and R.A. Dahlgren. 1995.  Roots, nutrients and their relationship to spatial patterns. Plant and Soil 169: 113-123.

Vogt, K.A., D.J. Vogt, H. Asbjornsen, and R.A. Dahlgren. 1995.  Roots, nutrients and their relationship to spatial patterns. In: pp. 113-123 (L.O. Nilsson, R.F. Huttle and U.T. Johansson, eds.) Nutrient Uptake and Cycling in Forest Ecosystems. Developments in Plant and Soil Science Vol. 62. Kluwer Academic Publishers, Dordrecht, Boston.

Theses

Gitzen, R.A. 1999. The Effects of Experimental Canopy Gaps on Small Mammal Communities in the Southern Washington Cascades. M.S. Thesis. University of Washington, Seattle, WA.

Gray, A. N. 1995. Tree seedling establishment on heterogenous microsites in Douglas-fir forest canopy gaps.  Dissertation. Oregon State University, Corvallis, OR .

London, S.G. 1999. Spatial Distribution of Understory Vegetation in Tree Canopy Gaps of the Pacific Northwest. M.S. Thesis. Oregon State University, Corvallis, OR.

 St. Pierre, E.A. 2000. Effects of canopy gaps in Douglas-fir forests and resource gradients on fecundity and growth of understory herbs. Dissertation. Oregon State University, Corvallis, OR.

Van Pelt, R. 1995. Understory Tree Response to Canopy Gaps in Old-growth Douglas-fir Forests of the Pacific Northwest. Dissertation. University of Washington, Seattle, WA. These tree-fall gaps were established in 1990 by T.A. Spies and A.N. Gray.  A complete description of these sites are given in: Gray, A.N., and Spies, T.A. (1996). The general FSDB code for this study is TV025.  Shirley King, assisted by her husband Jon, conducted the measurements at the H.J. Andrews in the summer of 1995.</para></additionalInfo><intellectualRights><para>&lt;p&gt;Data Use Agreement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Any Andrews Experimental Forest data set and accompanying metadata available on these web pages can be downloaded for academic, research, recreational, and other professional purposes. Permission to download data sets is granted to the Data User without a fee subject to the following terms. The Data User will: &lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; notify the designated contact (e.g., Principle Investigator or Data Set Contact) when any derivative work based on or derived from the data and documentation is distributed;
		&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; notify users that such derivative work is a modified version and not the original data and documentation distributed by the Andrews LTER;
		&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; not redistribute original data and documentation; 
		&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; acknowledge the support of the Andrews LTER and appropriate NSF Grant numbers in any publications using these data and documentation. (See general acknowledgement below and see web page for specific data citation for each study data set); &lt;/para&gt;
		&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; send two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the data and documentation to the following address:  Andrews Experimental Forest LTER Program, c/o Don Henshaw, Forestry Sciences Lab, 3200 SW Jefferson Way, Corvallis, OR 97331
		&lt;/li&gt;		
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt; By using or copying these data and documentation, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Andrews Experimental Forest LTER Site shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement. Thank you for your cooperation. We hope your collaboration with our site is a productive one!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Disclaimer:  While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is". The Andrews Experimental Forest LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of data sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General acknowledgement:  Data were provided by the HJ Andrews Experimental Forest research program, funded by the National Science Foundation's Long-Term Ecological Research Program (DEB 08-23380), US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, and Oregon State University. &lt;/p&gt;</para><para>If data used in publication, Robert Griffiths and Shirley King will be listed as a coauthor.   Whenever these data are presented in whatever form, Griffiths and King will be acknowledged.</para></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="information">http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/lter/data/abstract.cfm?dbcode=SP017&amp;topnav=135</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Spies-Gray gap study site on the H.J. Andrews Experimental Forest.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>122.15000000</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>0.00000000</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>44.15000000</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>0.00000000</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1995-01-07</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>1995-01-08</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><purpose>Tree-fall gaps are known to play an important role in the formation and maintenance of old-growth forest structure and forest biodiversity.  Prior research has focused on above-ground vegetative succession and population dynamics and little is known about changes occurring below-ground as vegetation becomes reestablished.    

The interplay between gap microclimatic gradients and both vegetation and the below-ground component of the ecosystem is potentially complex.  Thus to understand how gaps influence forest floor carbon cycling, one must consider both above and below-ground components.  

This is the first of three tree-fall gap studies conducted at the HJA addressing the effects of tree-fall gaps on forest soil characteristics.   The second (Gap2) compared the effects of gaps on soil properties along both N-S and E-W transects to better differentiate between microclimate and vegetation effects within gaps.  The final study (Gap3) expanded the number of variables studied and sampling intensity.  By using the same grid system as Dr. Gray in his vegetation survey work, the Gap3 study provided the most definitive connection between above-ground vegetation and associated below-ground processes.</purpose><maintenance><description /><maintenanceUpdateFrequency>irregular</maintenanceUpdateFrequency><changeHistory><changeScope>Original metadata creation.</changeScope><oldValue>Version1</oldValue><changeDate>2001-05-02</changeDate></changeHistory><changeHistory><changeScope>Metadata restructured and moved into SQLServer metadata database LTERMETA. Data moved into SQLServer database FSDBDATA.</changeScope><oldValue>Version2</oldValue><changeDate>2002-02-08</changeDate></changeHistory><changeHistory><changeScope>Non-critical update to force reharvest of EML for this study database.  Addition of ACCESS code to EML and syntax updates</changeScope><oldValue>Version3</oldValue><changeDate>2005-07-25</changeDate></changeHistory><changeHistory><changeScope>Non-critical update to force reharvest of EML for this study database.  Correction for custom unit problem.</changeScope><oldValue>Version4</oldValue><changeDate>2007-06-13</changeDate></changeHistory></maintenance><contact scope="document"><positionName>Information Manager</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Andrews Forest LTER Program</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>3200 SW Jefferson Way</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331</postalCode></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 750-7335</phone><electronicMailAddress>hjaweb@fsl.orst.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/</onlineUrl></contact><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Robert</givenName><givenName>P.</givenName><surName>Griffiths</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Dept. of Forest Science;321 Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-6559</phone><electronicMailAddress>bbgriff@peak.org</electronicMailAddress><electronicMailAddress>griff@for.orst.edu</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>Andrews Forest LTER Site</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Forest Ecosystems and Society Department in Forestry</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>201K Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-8480</phone><electronicMailAddress>lterweb@fsl.orst.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/</onlineUrl></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Field Methods - SP017</title><para>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Litter depth and soil temperature measurements were made in the field. &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Litter depth was measured with a cm ruler and soil temperatures were made in the top 10 cm of soil using a dial thermometer calibrated with ice water. Cores (4.7 x 10 cm) were collected for bulk density measurements.  Grab samples were taken to a depth of 10 cm with a trowel for soil for the laboratory measurements of gravimetric soil moisture, laboratory respiration and total N and C.&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Laboratory Methods - SP017</title><para>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;In preparation for laboratory analyses, all soils were sieved through a 2-mm sieve.
Soil moisture was determined by drying duplicate 10 g field-moist sieved soils at 100 C for at least 8 h.  The percent soil moisture was calculated by dividing the difference between wet and dry samples and dividing that number by the dry wt., which was then multiplied by 100. Soil organic mater (SOM) was measured as weight loss after ignition at 550 &#186;C for 12 h on soils that had been dried at 100 &#186;C for 12 h.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laboratory respiration measurements were made in duplicate on 5 g of field-moist soil brought up to a moisture level of 75% with de-ionized water.   The soil sample was added to a 25-mL Erlenmeyer flask.  Once sealed with serum bottle stoppers, the flasks were incubated at 15&#730;C for 2 weeks.  Headspace CO2 concentration was measured using a gas chromatograph fitted a flame ionization detector and a methanizer in series.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten percent of the samples were analyzed for total carbon and nitrogen using a Carlo-Erba&#174; NA Series 2 CNS analyzer.  The soils were pulverized and passed through a 60 mesh screen in preparation for analysis.  Sample size varied from 8-15 mg.  &lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</para></section></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><description><para /></description></studyExtent><samplingDescription><para>&lt;p&gt;A general description of these gaps and the rational for this long-term study have been described by Gray and Spies (1996). The experimental design and site descriptions have been published (Gray and Spies, 1996, 1997) but are summarized below.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replicate 10, 20, 30 and 50 gaps as well as one 30 m control gap were used to determine how tree-fall gaps influence soil carbon cycling.  These gaps were created in the fall of 1990 at a site located 44&#162;&#170; 15&#161;&#175;N, 122 &#162;&#170; 15&#161;&#175;W at an elevation of 900 m at the H.J. Andrews Experimental Forest in the Central Oregon Cascade Mountains.  This study was conducted 5 years after gap formation.  North-south transects were established through the center of all gaps and sample nodes were located at 1 m intervals along those transects.  These transects ran one radius length into the surrounding forest.  These transects were divided into four zones.  Two zones were north of the E-W centerline; one in and one out of the gap.  The other two zones were south of the E-W centerline; one in and one out of the gap.&lt;/p&gt;</para><para>Citation: Gray, A.N., and T.A. Spies. 1996.  Gap size, within-gap position, and canopy structure effects on seedling establishment of conifer species in forest canopy gaps.  Journal of Ecology 84: 635-645.

Gray, A.N., and T.A. Spies. 1997.  Microsite controls on tree seedling establishment in conifer forest canopy gaps.  Ecology 78:2458-2473.</para></samplingDescription><spatialSamplingUnits><coverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Andrews Experimental Forest (HJA)</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-122.26172200</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.10084700</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>44.28196400</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>44.19770400</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></coverage></spatialSamplingUnits></sampling></methods><project scope="document"><title>Long-Term Ecological Research</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Barbara</givenName><givenName>J</givenName><surName>Bond</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Dept. of Forest Science;330 Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-6110</phone><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 908-2515</phone><electronicMailAddress>barbara.bond@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.fsl.orst.edu/~bond</onlineUrl><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Mark</givenName><givenName>E.</givenName><surName>Harmon</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Dept. of Forest Science;321 Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-8455</phone><phone phonetype="voice">(978) 724-0045 ext 223</phone><electronicMailAddress>mark.harmon@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Donald</givenName><givenName>L.</givenName><surName>Henshaw</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>USDA Forest Service Research;Pacific Northwest (PNW) Research Station;3200 SW Jefferson Way</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 750-7335</phone><electronicMailAddress>don.henshaw@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><electronicMailAddress>dhenshaw@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Sherri</givenName><givenName>L.</givenName><surName>Johnson</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>US Forest Service ;Pacific NW Research Station ;3200 SW Jefferson Way</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 758-7771</phone><electronicMailAddress>sherri.l.johnson@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><electronicMailAddress>sherrijohnson@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Julia</givenName><givenName>A.</givenName><surName>Jones</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Department of Geosciences; Wilkinson Hall 104</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331-5506</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-1224</phone><electronicMailAddress>geojulia@comcast.net</electronicMailAddress><electronicMailAddress>jonesj@geo.oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.geo.oregonstate.edu/people/faculty/jonesj.htm</onlineUrl><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Thomas</givenName><givenName>A.</givenName><surName>Spies</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>USDA Forest Service;Pacific NW Research Station;3200 SW Jefferson Way</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 750-7354</phone><electronicMailAddress>tom.spies@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><electronicMailAddress>tspies@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Denise</givenName><surName>Lach</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Sociology;Oregon State University</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">541-737-5471</phone><electronicMailAddress>denise.lach@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Mark</givenName><surName>Schulze</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>HJ Andrews Experimental Forest;PO Box 300</deliveryPoint><city>Blue River</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97413</postalCode></address><phone phonetype="voice">541-822-6336</phone><electronicMailAddress>mark.schulze@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><abstract><para>&lt;p&gt;The H.J. Andrews Experimental Forest is a living laboratory that provides unparalleled opportunities for the study of forest and stream ecosystems in the central Cascade Range of Oregon. Since 1980, as a part of the National Science Foundation Long Term Ecological Research (NSF-LTER) program, the Andrews Experimental Forest has become a leader in the analysis of forest and stream ecosystem dynamics.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;Long-term field experiments and measurement programs have focused on climate dynamics, streamflow, water quality, and vegetation succession. Currently researchers are working to develop concepts and tools needed to predict effects of natural disturbance, land use, and climate change on ecosystem structure, function, and species composition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Andrews Experimental Forest is administered cooperatively by the USDA Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, Oregon State University and the Willamette National Forest. Funding for the research program comes from the National Science Foundation (NSF), US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, Oregon State University, and other sources.&lt;/p&gt;</para></abstract><funding>National Science Foundation: DEB0823380</funding></project><dataTable scope="document"><alternateIdentifier>SP01701</alternateIdentifier><entityName>The influence of tree-fall gaps on soil characteristics in gaps of varying sizes</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>SP01701.csv</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter><quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-and.3115.4&amp;urlTail=SP01701_v1.csv</url></online></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>GAPNUMBR</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Site designator; gap 100 was a none-cut gap control</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(3,0)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">110</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">210</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>GAPSIZE</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Gap diameter in meters</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(2,0)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>meter</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">10</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">50</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>LOCATION</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Sampling location along transect</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(2,0)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">50</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>N_S</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Sample location north or south of gap center</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(1,0)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>ZONE</attributeName><attributeDefinition>1=Nout; 2=Nin; 3=Sout; 4=Sin;</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(1,0)</storageType><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">4</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>IN_OUT</attributeName><attributeDefinition>OUT = out of gap,  IN = in gap</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">char(3)</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>OUT = out of gap,  IN = in gap</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>MOIST</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Percent moisture</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(5,1)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">100</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>SOILTEMP</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Soil temperature</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(4,1)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">5</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">15</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>SOM</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Soil organic matter</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(4,1)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">5</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">40</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>LITTER</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Litter depth</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(4,1)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">20</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>BULKDENS</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Bulk density</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(4,2)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>TOTALN</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Total nitrogen</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(5,3)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>TOTALC</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Total carbon</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(5,3)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">20</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>C_NRATIO</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Total carbon/total nitrogn</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(2,0)</storageType><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">15</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">45</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>LABRESP</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Laboratory respiration rates (dry weight basis, as C)</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(3,0)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>micrograms per gram per hour</customUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">4</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList><numberOfRecords>510</numberOfRecords></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><metadata><ns2:unitList convention="CML"><ns2:unit constantToSI="0.0" id="grams per square centimeter" multiplierToSI="1" name="grams per square centimeter" parentSI="kilogramPerMeterSquared" unitType="arealMassDensity"><ns2:description>grams per square centimeter</ns2:description></ns2:unit><ns2:unit constantToSI="0.0" id="meters" multiplierToSI="1" name="meters" parentSI="meter" unitType="length"><ns2:description>meter; SI unit of length</ns2:description></ns2:unit><ns2:unit constantToSI="0.0" id="micrograms per gram per hour" multiplierToSI="1" name="micrograms per gram per hour" parentSI="unknown" unitType="massPerMassRate"><ns2:description>micrograms per gram per hour</ns2:description></ns2:unit><ns2:unit constantToSI="0.0" id="centimeters" multiplierToSI="0.01" name="centimeters" parentSI="meter" unitType="length"><ns2:description>centimeters; .01 meters</ns2:description></ns2:unit><ns2:unit constantToSI="0.0" id="degrees Celcius" multiplierToSI="273.18" name="degrees Celcius" parentSI="kelvin" unitType="temperature"><ns2:description>Degrees Celsius; a common unit of temperature; constantToSI=273.18</ns2:description></ns2:unit><ns2:unit constantToSI="0.0" id="percent" multiplierToSI="1" name="percent" parentSI="dimensionless" unitType="dimensionless"><ns2:description>percent; a number</ns2:description></ns2:unit><ns2:unit constantToSI="0.0" id="number" multiplierToSI="1" name="number" parentSI="dimensionless" unitType="dimensionless"><ns2:description>dimensionless number, i.e., ratio, count</ns2:description></ns2:unit></ns2:unitList></metadata></additionalMetadata></ns0:eml>