<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-luq.109.1" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 C:/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><shortName>LUQMetadata109</shortName><title>Rio Icacos hyporheic and riparian chemistry</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>William H.</givenName><surName>McDowell</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of New Hamshire</organizationName><positionName>Principal Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Natural Resources</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>215 James Hall</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>56 College Rd</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">787-749-4346(279)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">787-749-4462</phone><electronicMailAddress>bill.mcdowell@unh.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.unh.edu/natural-resources/fac-bmcdowell.html</onlineUrl></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Tamara</givenName><surName>Chestnut (Eklund)</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of New Hampshire</organizationName><positionName>Graduate Student</positionName><address scope="document"><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824-3589</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(505)272-7311</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(505)272-7080</phone><electronicMailAddress>tjeklund@christa.unh.edu</electronicMailAddress></metadataProvider><language>english</language><abstract><para><literalLayout>Same as project description</literalLayout></para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>DOC</keyword><keyword>hydrologic characteristics</keyword><keyword>hyporheic zone</keyword><keyword>nitrogen</keyword><keyword>nutrient cycling</keyword><keyword>riparian zone</keyword><keyword>tropical rainforest</keyword><keyword>COLORADO</keyword><keyword>PEER REVIEWED JOURNAL</keyword><keyword>Q ICACOS</keyword><keyword>RIPARIAN</keyword><keyword>RIVER</keyword><keyword>Inorganic Inputs and Nutrient Movements</keyword><keyword>Environmental monitoring</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><title>ADEQUATE ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><para><literalLayout>The scientists, the LEF-LTER Program, and the                                     USDA International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITF) must                                     receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data by other                                     scientists, and the LEF LTER program must receive two copies of                                     any publication using that data. One copy will be placed at the                                     IITF library and one copy will stay with the LEF LTER Data                                     Manager. A suggested format for this acknowledgement will be                                     distributed along with the requested data.</literalLayout></para><section><title>Acknowledgements for NSF Support.</title><para><literalLayout>The following paragraph should be                                         included in the acknowledgements of all publications funded                                         in any way by current and future LTER grants:</literalLayout><literalLayout>This research was performed under grant                                         #DEB-0218039 from the National Science Foundation to the                                         Institute of Tropical Ecosystem Studies (IEET), University                                         of Puerto Rico, and the International Institute of Tropical                                         Forestry (IITFR) as part of the Long-Term Ecological                                         Research Program in the Luquillo Experimental Forest.                                         Additional support was provided by the Forest Service (U.S.                                         Department of Agriculture) and the University of Puerto                                         Rico.</literalLayout></para></section></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb109/metadata/lterdb109.htm#DATA</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF) covers                                 11,231 hectares and reaches 1079 m above sea level. It has a warm                                 and wet climate and includes a variety of tropical habitats and                                 forest types and streams, and a high diversity of plants and                                 animals. A key feature of these ecosystems is disturbance.                                 Hurricanes, landslides, and human disturbance have shaped the                                 forest, and research by LUQ has stimulated a new appreciation of the                                 significance of large-scale disturbances in tropical forested                                 ecosystems and the key role of plants and animals in shaping the                                 response to these events. Hurricanes occurring one and 10 years                                 after LUQ began in 1988 provided landscape-scale natural experiments                                 which are still followed closely.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-65.92</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-65.7</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>18.35</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>18.23</southBoundingCoordinate><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>20</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>1060</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>William H.</givenName><surName>McDowell</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of New Hamshire</organizationName><positionName>Principal Investigator</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Natural Resources</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>215 James Hall</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>56 College Rd</deliveryPoint><city>Durham</city><administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea><postalCode>03824</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">787-749-4346(279)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">787-749-4462</phone><electronicMailAddress>bill.mcdowell@unh.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.unh.edu/natural-resources/fac-bmcdowell.html</onlineUrl></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>Luquillo Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>University of Puerto Rico, Rio Piedras</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>P. O. Box 21910</deliveryPoint><city>San Juan</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931-1910</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787) 764 - 0000 (ext. 4940)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787) 772 -1481</phone><electronicMailAddress>nbrokaw@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://luq.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Groundwater and hyporheic wells. Six well transects were installed along the 100-m stream reach. Floodplain wells were placed along transects on both sides of the stream at ~1 and 10 m from the stream. Floodplain wells were made of 5-cm PVC with 61 cm of slotted well screen that was covered with polyethylene geotextile fabric filter to reduce particle infiltration and clogging of screens. Well screens for riparian wells ranged from 1 to 3 m in depth depending on location. Hyporheic wells were installed at each transect as 3 sets of vertically nested wells located on the left, center, and right sides of the stream. Hyporheic wells were installed at depths of 10, 30, 50, and 80 cm below the ground surface with each nest oriented longitudinally along the stream. Hyporheic wells were made of 2.5-cm PVC pipe with 5-cm perforated well screens. Wells were capped on the bottom and were limited to 10 cm of pipe below the screen.</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep></methods><project scope="document"><title>Riparian Carbon and Nitrogen Dynamics</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>William H.</givenName><surName>McDowell</surName></individualName><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><abstract><para><literalLayout>Hydrologic and chemical characteristics were determined for both riparian and hyporheic subsurface flow along a 100-m reach of a sandy-bottom tributary of the Rio Icacos in the Luquillo Experimental Forest, Puerto Rico. Hydrologic data (vertical hydraulic gradient and hydraulic conductivity of streambed sediments) and the topographic and morphological features of the watershed indicated diffuse inputs of groundwater from the near-stream riparian zone along this site. Cumulative groundwater discharge, determined by tracer dilution techniques, was ~1.5 L/s or 10% of the total stream discharge. Spatial heterogeneity in hydrologic and chemical properties of riparian and hyporheic sediments was large. Hydraulic conductivity explained much of the variation in NH4-N and dissolved organic carbon (DOC) concentrations, with highest concentrations in sites having low conductivity. A mass-balance approach was used to examine the influence of the near-stream zone on nutrient transport and retention. Outwelling riparian groundwater had the potential to increase stream N concentrations by up to 84% and DOC concentrations by up to 38% along our 100-m reach. Because stream concentrations were constant downstream despite this input, we conclude that significant N and C retention or loss were occurring in the near-stream zone. Lotic ecosystems and their associated riparian groundwater can have a quantitatively significant impact on the nutrient budgets of tropical headwater catchments.</literalLayout></para></abstract><funding><para><literalLayout>LTER</literalLayout></para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=LUQ,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access></dataset></ns0:eml>