<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-and.4029.3" scope="system" system="http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/data/mastercatalog.cfm?topnav=97" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd"><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=AND,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataset scope="document"><title>Road-related erosion from the February 1996 flood in the Lookout Creek and Blue River watersheds, Oregon</title><creator scope="document"><organizationName>Andrews Forest LTER Site</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Forest Ecosystems and Society Department in Forestry</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>201K Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-8480</phone><electronicMailAddress>lterweb@fsl.orst.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/</onlineUrl></creator><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Julia</givenName><givenName>A.</givenName><surName>Jones</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Department of Geosciences; Wilkinson Hall 104</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331-5506</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-1224</phone><electronicMailAddress>geojulia@comcast.net</electronicMailAddress><electronicMailAddress>jonesj@geo.oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.geo.oregonstate.edu/people/faculty/jonesj.htm</onlineUrl></creator><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Julia</givenName><givenName>A.</givenName><surName>Jones</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Department of Geosciences; Wilkinson Hall 104</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331-5506</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-1224</phone><electronicMailAddress>geojulia@comcast.net</electronicMailAddress><electronicMailAddress>jonesj@geo.oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.geo.oregonstate.edu/people/faculty/jonesj.htm</onlineUrl><role>Principal Investigator</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Frederick</givenName><givenName>J.</givenName><surName>Swanson</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>USDA Forest Service;Pacific NW Research Station;3200 SW Jefferson Way</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 750-7355</phone><electronicMailAddress>fred.swanson@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><electronicMailAddress>fswanson@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress><role>Other Researcher</role></associatedParty><associatedParty scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Beverley</givenName><givenName>C.</givenName><surName>Wemple</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Geography;University of Vermont;</deliveryPoint><city>Burlington</city><administrativeArea>VT</administrativeArea><postalCode>05405</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice" /><electronicMailAddress>Beverley.Wemple@uvm.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>Abstractor</role></associatedParty><pubDate>2005-07-25</pubDate><abstract><section><para>Recent studies of the effects of forest roads on mountain watersheds (e.g. Jones and Grant, 1996; Wemple et al., 1996) led to asking how sedimentation processes were affected by roads during the flood. Of interest were how roads influenced erosional processes and how flood-induced erosion affected the transportation network.  By employing concepts of sediment budgeting and disturbance cascades, this study aims to create a landscape context for understanding the impact of an extensive road network on the geomorphic imprint left by this flood of record in February 1996.</para></section></abstract><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">Erosion</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Landslides/earthflows</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Road networks</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Roads</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Sedimentation</keyword><keywordThesaurus>Andrews Experimental Forest site thesaurus</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><additionalInfo><para>Funding for this research was provided by a grant from the U.S. Geological Survey, Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center (Task Order #H952-A1-0101-19). Additional funding was provided through the USDA Forest Service, Pacific Northwest Research Station for research at the H. J. Andrews Experimental Forest Long-Term Ecological Research site (National Science Foundation grant DEB96-32921).</para></additionalInfo><intellectualRights><para>&lt;p&gt;Data Use Agreement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Any Andrews Experimental Forest data set and accompanying metadata available on these web pages can be downloaded for academic, research, recreational, and other professional purposes. Permission to download data sets is granted to the Data User without a fee subject to the following terms. The Data User will: &lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; notify the designated contact (e.g., Principle Investigator or Data Set Contact) when any derivative work based on or derived from the data and documentation is distributed;
		&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; notify users that such derivative work is a modified version and not the original data and documentation distributed by the Andrews LTER;
		&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; not redistribute original data and documentation; 
		&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; acknowledge the support of the Andrews LTER and appropriate NSF Grant numbers in any publications using these data and documentation. (See general acknowledgement below and see web page for specific data citation for each study data set); &lt;/para&gt;
		&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; send two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the data and documentation to the following address:  Andrews Experimental Forest LTER Program, c/o Don Henshaw, Forestry Sciences Lab, 3200 SW Jefferson Way, Corvallis, OR 97331
		&lt;/li&gt;		
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt; By using or copying these data and documentation, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Andrews Experimental Forest LTER Site shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement. Thank you for your cooperation. We hope your collaboration with our site is a productive one!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Disclaimer:  While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is". The Andrews Experimental Forest LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of data sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General acknowledgement:  Data were provided by the HJ Andrews Experimental Forest research program, funded by the National Science Foundation's Long-Term Ecological Research Program (DEB 08-23380), US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, and Oregon State University. &lt;/p&gt;</para></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="information">http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/lter/data/abstract.cfm?dbcode=GE008&amp;topnav=135</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Lookout Creek and Blue River watersheds, western Oregon Cascades</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>0.00000000</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>0.00000000</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>0.00000000</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>0.00000000</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1999-05-02</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>1999-09-02</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><purpose>Recent studies of the effects of forest roads on mountain watersheds (e.g. Jones and Grant, 1996; Wemple et al., 1996) led to asking how sedimentation processes were affected by roads during the flood. Of interest were how roads influenced erosional processes and how flood-induced erosion affected the transportation network.  By employing concepts of sediment budgeting and disturbance cascades, this study aims to create a landscape context for understanding the impact of an extensive road network on the geomorphic imprint left by this flood of record in February 1996.</purpose><maintenance><description /><maintenanceUpdateFrequency>notPlanned</maintenanceUpdateFrequency><changeHistory><changeScope>Original metadata creation</changeScope><oldValue>Version1</oldValue><changeDate>1999-07-23</changeDate></changeHistory><changeHistory><changeScope>Moved database to SQL server</changeScope><oldValue>Version2</oldValue><changeDate>2005-04-15</changeDate></changeHistory><changeHistory><changeScope>Non-critical update to force reharvest of EML for this study database.  Addition of ACCESS code to EML and syntax updates</changeScope><oldValue>Version3</oldValue><changeDate>2005-07-25</changeDate></changeHistory></maintenance><contact scope="document"><positionName>Information Manager</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Andrews Forest LTER Program</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>3200 SW Jefferson Way</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331</postalCode></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 750-7335</phone><electronicMailAddress>hjaweb@fsl.orst.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/</onlineUrl></contact><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Beverley</givenName><givenName>C.</givenName><surName>Wemple</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Geography;University of Vermont;</deliveryPoint><city>Burlington</city><administrativeArea>VT</administrativeArea><postalCode>05405</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice" /><electronicMailAddress>Beverley.Wemple@uvm.edu</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>Andrews Forest LTER Site</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Forest Ecosystems and Society Department in Forestry</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>201K Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-8480</phone><electronicMailAddress>lterweb@fsl.orst.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/</onlineUrl></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Field Methods - GE008</title><para>&lt;![CDATA[A survey of the road network in the Lookout Creek and Blue River watersheds was conducted to inventory road-related sedimentation resulting from the February 1996 flood.   During the spring and summer of 1996, the entire road network in both basins was inventoried for erosional and depositional features associated with roads.  Each feature was field located on 7.5' topographic maps and later digitized into a geographic information system (GIS).  
&lt;p&gt;
To distinguish among forms of erosion and deposition associated with roads, a typology of features, based on the process type and the point of origin relative to the road zone (defined as the cutslope, road surface and ditch, and fillslope), was developed.  Two general process types were considered: mass wasting and fluvial.  Mass wasting involves en masse detachment and transport of sediment and organic debris on hillslopes (debris slides) and in channels (debris flows).  Mass wasting can also involve displacement of soil without evacuation from the site (e.g. slumps).  The features produced by these processes are referred to in this paper as mass movements.  Fluvial processes involve particle by particle transport of sediment by flowing water in channels (bedload transport) and on hillslopes or roads (incision and gullying), and produce what are generally refer to here as fluvial features.  Four points of origin were considered: above the road, the cutslope, the road surface and ditch, and the fillslope.  Three types of debris slides were distinguished for this study: those initiated on hillslopes above roads were termed hillslope slides, those originating on cutslopes were termed cutslope slides, and those from road fills were termed fillslope slides.  Other processes originating above roads included debris flows and bedload transport that plugged culverts.  Processes originating within the road zone included slumps, ditch incision, and gullying
The length, width and depth of erosional scars and deposits were measured as appropriate for each feature to determine sediment volumes.  Volumes are reported here to the nearest 5 m3.  The accuracy of volume estimates, however, varies by the size of the feature, and reported volumes are considered to be precise only to two significant figures.]]&gt;</para></section></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><description><para>The study was conducted in the Lookout Creek and Blue River watersheds, located approximately 70 km east of Eugene in the western Oregon Cascades.  Elevations in the basins range from 400 meters to over 1500 meters, with slopes ranging from 0 to 80 percent.  The basins are underlaid by Tertiary and early Quaternary volcanic rocks, primarily ash flows, mudflows and pyroclastic flows at the lower elevations (below 800 meters) and andesite and basalt lava flows in the higher elevations.  The geomorphic history of the basins is shaped by glacial, fluvial and mass wasting processes.  Glacial deposits are evident in the southeast portion of the Blue River drainage.  Lacustrine sediments and varve deposits are found along the banks of lower Blue River and Lookout Creek.  Geologic mapping (Swanson and James, 1975) and landslide inventories (Dyrness, 1967; Swanson and Dyrness, 1975) document the history of deep-seated earthflows and shallow landsliding in the area.
&lt;p&gt;
Mean annual precipitation ranges from 2300 to over 2500 mm at the upper elevations (Greenland, 1994).  Over 80% of the precipitation falls between November to April, typically as rain below 400 meters.  Elevations between 400 and 1200 meters have been termed the "transient snow zone" (Harr, 1981)  where precipitation falls alternately as rain and snow.  A permanent snow zone develops during most winters above 1200 meters.  Floods in the region often result from relatively warm rain events on an accumulated snowpack (Harr, 1981). 
&lt;p&gt;
  Summary of characteristics of study basins
  &lt;p&gt;
						Lookout Creek		Blue River
&lt;p&gt;		
Watershed area (km2)			 62				119
Harvested area (%)				 22				  25
Drainage density (km/km2)a		 3.0				 2.9
Road length (km)				118				230
Road density (km/km2)			 1.9			 	 1.9
Area of basin in roads (%)b		 3.1				 3.1
&lt;p&gt;
Notes:&lt;p&gt;
a Estimated winter baseflow drainage density (see Wemple et al., 1996).
b Computed using an average width of road cut, surface, and fill of 16 meters from Silen and Gratkowski, 1953.
 &lt;p&gt;
 Vegetation in the basins consists of Douglas fir (Pseudotsuga menziesii), western hemlock (Tsuga heterophylla) and western red cedar (Thuja plicata).  Stands of Pacific silver fir (Abies amabilis) occur above 800 m.  Forest harvesting and road construction have occurred in both basins since the late 1930's (Jones and Grant, 1996).  Harvesting and road construction in the Lookout Creek watershed occurred primarily in the 1950's and 1960's.  Most of the harvesting and road construction in the Blue River watershed occurred between 1960 and 1985.</para></description></studyExtent><samplingDescription><para>Following the February 1996 flood, a survey is conducted in two watersheds in the western Oregon Cascades to examine flood impacts associated with roads.  The approach to this study included four components: (1) an inventory of road-related sedimentation features, (2) an analysis of landscape position of these features, (3) an analysis of process complexity and disturbance cascades, and (4) a mass balance of sediment relative to the zone of road influence.</para></samplingDescription></sampling></methods><project scope="document"><title>Long-Term Ecological Research</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Barbara</givenName><givenName>J</givenName><surName>Bond</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Dept. of Forest Science;330 Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-6110</phone><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 908-2515</phone><electronicMailAddress>barbara.bond@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.fsl.orst.edu/~bond</onlineUrl><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Mark</givenName><givenName>E.</givenName><surName>Harmon</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Dept. of Forest Science;321 Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-8455</phone><phone phonetype="voice">(978) 724-0045 ext 223</phone><electronicMailAddress>mark.harmon@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Donald</givenName><givenName>L.</givenName><surName>Henshaw</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>USDA Forest Service Research;Pacific Northwest (PNW) Research Station;3200 SW Jefferson Way</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 750-7335</phone><electronicMailAddress>don.henshaw@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><electronicMailAddress>dhenshaw@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Sherri</givenName><givenName>L.</givenName><surName>Johnson</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>US Forest Service ;Pacific NW Research Station ;3200 SW Jefferson Way</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 758-7771</phone><electronicMailAddress>sherri.l.johnson@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><electronicMailAddress>sherrijohnson@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Julia</givenName><givenName>A.</givenName><surName>Jones</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Department of Geosciences; Wilkinson Hall 104</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331-5506</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-1224</phone><electronicMailAddress>geojulia@comcast.net</electronicMailAddress><electronicMailAddress>jonesj@geo.oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://www.geo.oregonstate.edu/people/faculty/jonesj.htm</onlineUrl><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Thomas</givenName><givenName>A.</givenName><surName>Spies</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>USDA Forest Service;Pacific NW Research Station;3200 SW Jefferson Way</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(541) 750-7354</phone><electronicMailAddress>tom.spies@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><electronicMailAddress>tspies@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Denise</givenName><surName>Lach</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Department of Sociology;Oregon State University</deliveryPoint><city>Corvallis</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97331</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">541-737-5471</phone><electronicMailAddress>denise.lach@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Mark</givenName><surName>Schulze</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>HJ Andrews Experimental Forest;PO Box 300</deliveryPoint><city>Blue River</city><administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea><postalCode>97413</postalCode></address><phone phonetype="voice">541-822-6336</phone><electronicMailAddress>mark.schulze@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></personnel><abstract><para>&lt;p&gt;The H.J. Andrews Experimental Forest is a living laboratory that provides unparalleled opportunities for the study of forest and stream ecosystems in the central Cascade Range of Oregon. Since 1980, as a part of the National Science Foundation Long Term Ecological Research (NSF-LTER) program, the Andrews Experimental Forest has become a leader in the analysis of forest and stream ecosystem dynamics.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;Long-term field experiments and measurement programs have focused on climate dynamics, streamflow, water quality, and vegetation succession. Currently researchers are working to develop concepts and tools needed to predict effects of natural disturbance, land use, and climate change on ecosystem structure, function, and species composition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Andrews Experimental Forest is administered cooperatively by the USDA Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, Oregon State University and the Willamette National Forest. Funding for the research program comes from the National Science Foundation (NSF), US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, Oregon State University, and other sources.&lt;/p&gt;</para></abstract><funding>National Science Foundation: DEB0823380</funding></project><dataTable scope="document"><alternateIdentifier>GE00801</alternateIdentifier><entityName>Erosion/Depositional Features with Sediment Volumes</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>GE00801.csv</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter><quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-and.4029.3&amp;urlTail=GE00801_v1.csv</url></online></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>STCODE</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Study code</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">char(4)</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Study code</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>FORMAT</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Format number</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(1,0)</storageType><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>F_NUMBER</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Feature number (erosional or depositional features)</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(3,0)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">103</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>F_TYPE</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Type of feature (based on the point of origin relative to road network)</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">char(2)</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>hs</code><definition>Hillslope slides</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>ff</code><definition>Fillslope slides</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>cf</code><definition>Cutslope slides</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>df</code><definition>Debris flows</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>s</code><definition>Slumps</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>pc</code><definition>Plugged culverts</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>id</code><definition>Incised ditches</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>g</code><definition>Gullies</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>LANDSLIDE</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Refers to identification number in Swanson/Wallenstein inventory of landslides - see GE007</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">char(8)</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Refers to identification number in Swanson/Wallenstein inventory of landslides - see GE007</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>VOL_H</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Volume of hillslope material</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(6,0)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">6000</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>VOL_S</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Volume stored on the road</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(6,0)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">4750</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>VOL_T</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Volume transported through the road</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(6,0)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">5000</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>VOL_R</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Volume of road material</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(6,0)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">6255</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>VOL_OUT</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Volume yielded below the road</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">numeric(6,0)</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">6255</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>BASIN</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Refers to basin where feature was mapped</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">char(2)</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>lo</code><definition>Lookout creek</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>br</code><definition>Upper blue river</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>DECADE</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Refers to decade of construction for road on which feature was mapped</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">char(2)</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>50</code><definition>Before 1950</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>60</code><definition>Before 1960</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>70</code><definition>1961-1970</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>80</code><definition>1971-1980</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>90</code><definition>1981-1990</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>ELEV</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Refers to elevation zone in which feature was mapped</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">char(1)</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>1</code><definition>400-800 meter elevation</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>2</code><definition>801-1200 meter elevation</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>3</code><definition>&gt;1200 meter elevation</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>POSITION</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Landscape position of inventoried feature</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">char(1)</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>m</code><definition>Midslopes: everything not defined as valley floor or ridge/upslope</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>v</code><definition>Valley floors: delineated with a 200 meter buffer around fifth-order streams and delineated with a 100 meter buffer around fourth-order streams</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>r</code><definition>Riddges/upperslopes defined with a 100 meter buffer on a linear network of ridges digitized from 7.5' topographic maps</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>ASSOC</attributeName><attributeDefinition>Refers to number of associated feature</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="Microsoft SQL Server 2008">char(6)</storageType><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Refers to number of associated feature</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><metadata><ns2:unitList convention="CML"><ns2:unit constantToSI="0.0" id="number" multiplierToSI="1" name="number" parentSI="dimensionless" unitType="dimensionless"><ns2:description>dimensionless number, i.e., ratio, count</ns2:description></ns2:unit><ns2:unit constantToSI="0.0" id="cubic meter" multiplierToSI="1" name="cubic meter" parentSI="meterCubed" unitType="volume"><ns2:description>cubic meters</ns2:description></ns2:unit></ns2:unitList></metadata></additionalMetadata></ns0:eml>