<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-cwt.1075.4" scope="system" system="cwt-lter" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 http://gce-lter.marsci.uga.edu/lter/files/schemas/eml-201/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Salamander Plethodon Population/Diversity survey along an Elevation Gradient.</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Jacqueline M.</givenName><surName>Doyle</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>The College of Wooster</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>C-1427</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>1189 Beall Ave.</deliveryPoint><city>Wooster</city><administrativeArea>Ohio</administrativeArea><postalCode>44691</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(330) 287-3000 ext. 7046</phone><electronicMailAddress>jdoyle@acs.wooster.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://coweeta.ecology.uga.edu</onlineUrl></creator><abstract><para>Altitudinal gradients are specifically correlated with climate, precipitation, and numerous other variables; variables which must be taken into consideration when designing effective conservation studies in the Southern Appalachians. Furthermore, community relationships along elevation gradients can specifically be used to predict effects of global and local climate change. Salamanders and other amphibians are extremely good indicators of the overall health of an ecosystem, but many species of salamanders have begun to die out within the Southern Appalachians. Therefore, it is necessary to survey salamander populations along an elevation gradient in order to study the effects of disturbance in the Southern Appalachians, predict the results of global climate change upon salamander populations, and design ways of combating present disturbance within salamander populations. This study will consider the relationship between the number and diversity of salamanders at each elevation with altitude, climate and precipitation.</para><para>Adjacent to each gradient site, 25 plots will be partitioned off within a grid quadrat. Plots will be at least 6 meters from each other. Within each plot will be two 1X1 ft cover boards made from pine shelving wood, which is not chemically treated. Coverboards with each plot will be placed 1 inch apart from each other. Identical grid quadrats will be created at altitudes of 782 m, 795 m, 865 m 1001 m, and 1347 m on the opposite side of the mountain. Coverboards will be allowed to sit, undisturbed, for one month. Surveying will begin the first week of July and will occur bi-weekly until August 17th. Surveying will then occur at least twice more between September and November. Surveying will entail determining number of salamanders beneath each cover board, species and length of each salamander. Length of salamander will be used to determine whether individual salamanders are being caught multiple times under the same coverboard. Temperature and precipitation at each elevation will be obtained using microclimate stations. Data analysis will include the following: | Average number of salamanders at each elevation | Average number of salamanders per species at each elevation | Average temperature and precipitation for each elevation | Chi square for elevation gradients and # of salamanders, species of salamanders | ANOVA for Y= # of salamanders per sampling, X= species, elevation | ANOVA for Y= # of salamanders, X= climate per elevation, precipitation per elevation</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Coweeta</keyword><keyword>LTER</keyword><keyword>Salamander population survey</keyword><keyword>elevational gradient</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>Must adhere to the Coweeta LTER Data Policy (See http://coweeta.uga.edu/policies/data).</para></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://coweeta.uga.edu/summaries/Csummary1075_b.html</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Directly adjacent to elevation gradient sites BUT not within gradient sites, at altitudes of 782 m, 795 m, 865 m 1001 m, and 1347 m.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate /><eastBoundingCoordinate /><northBoundingCoordinate /><southBoundingCoordinate /></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2002-05-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2002-11-01</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><positionName>Coweeta LTER Information Manager</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(828) 524-2128</phone></contact><project scope="document"><title>Coweeta Long Term Ecological Research</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Ted</givenName><surName>Gragson</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>tgragson@earthlink.net</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>James</givenName><surName>Vose</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>jvose@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Brian</givenName><surName>Kloeppel</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>kloeppel@sparc.ecology.uga.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><abstract><para>The Coweeta LTER Research Program has evolved since 1980 from a site-based to a site- and region-based project examining the effects of disturbance

and environmental gradients on biogeochemical cycling, and the underlying

watershed ecosystem processes that regulate and respond to those cycles. 

The objective for the 2002-2008 research is to advance scientific

understanding of the spatial, temporal, and decision-making components of

land use and land-use change in the southern Appalachian Mountains over the

last 200 years, and forecast patterns into the future 30 years.  This will

be accomplished by addressing ecological and socioeconomic aspects of

land-use change while continuing long-term studies of environmental

gradients and natural disturbance regimes.  The result will be a more

complete understanding of ecological dynamics in the southern Appalachian

Mountains that makes possible the development of reasonable forecasts of

its future ecological state. | The guiding hypothesis for the proposed research is that the frequency, intensity, and extent of land use represents human decision-making in

response to socioeconomic and bio-geophysical conditions with consequences

that cascade through ecosystems.  The research activities are organized

into three initiatives: (1) Characterization of the Socio-Natural Template,

(2) Ecosystem Responses to the Socio-Natural Template, and (3) Forecasting

Ecosystem Responses to Changes in the Socio-Natural Template.  The

integrated scientific research will provide both a description as well as

an explanation of the underlying causes of land use and the consequences of

land-use change for southern Appalachian ecosystems and society.  It thus

recognizes the complexity of land use as a process and the research needs

as defined in the LTER Program and the broader scientific community.</para></abstract><funding><para>National Science Foundation. Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed in the material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.</para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=cwt,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access></dataset></ns0:eml>