<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-ntl.223.7" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
	<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
		<allow>
			<principal>uid=NTL, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
			<permission>all</permission>
		</allow>
		<allow>
			<principal>public</principal>
			<permission>read</permission>
		</allow>
	</access>
	<dataset>
		<alternateIdentifier system="NTL-DEIMS">5625</alternateIdentifier>
		<shortName>DODSON2</shortName>
		<title>Crustacean Zooplankton Species Richness in 66 North American Lakes</title>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Stanley</givenName>
				<surName>Dodson</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
    </address>
		</creator>
		<metadataProvider>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</metadataProvider>
		<pubDate>2000</pubDate>
		<language>english</language>
		<abstract>
			<para>Data from 66 North American lakes were collected to construct a model for predicting the
				number of crustacean zooplankton species expected in a lake. The chosen lakes have a range
				from 4 sq m to 80 x 10**9 sq m surface area, range from ultra-oligotrophic to
				hypereutrophic, and have zooplankton species lists based of several years of observation The
				number of crustacean zooplankton species in a lake is significantly correlated with lake
				size, average rate of photosynthesis (parabolic function) and the number of lakes within 20
				km. A multiple linear regression model, using these three independent variables, explains
				approximately 75% of the variation in log species richness. Prediction of species richness
				is not enhanced by the knowledge of lake depth, salinity, elevation, latitude, longitude, or
				distance to nearest lake. The North American species area curve is statistically different
				from and steeper than the corresponding European curve. Number of sites: 69 </para>
		</abstract>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>conductance</keyword>
			<keyword>conductivity</keyword>
			<keyword>populations</keyword>
			<keyword>species richness</keyword>
			<keyword>zooplankton</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>LTER Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>North Temperate Lakes - LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>lake density</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>NTL Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<intellectualRights>
			<section>
				<title>Data Policies</title>
				<para>Copyright Board of Regents, University of Wisconsin, Madison. This information is
					released to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes
					subject to the following restrictions: The Data User must realize that these data sets are
					being actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary
					to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the NTL lead Principal
					Investigator, leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu, to check on other uses of the data. Where
					appropriate, the Data User may be encouraged to consider collaboration and/or
					co-authorship with original investigators.</para>
				<para>The Data User must realize that the data may be misinterpreted if taken out of
					context. We request that you provide the NTL lead Principal Investigator, ATTN: Data
					Access, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 680 North Park St.,
					Madison, WI 53706 with a copy of any manuscript using the data so that it may be reviewed
					and comments provided on the presentation of our data.</para>
				<para>The Data User must acknowledge use of the data by an appropriate citation (see
					Citation) of the NTL-LTER database. A generic citation for our databases is: name of data
					set, North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research program, NSF, contact person for
					data set, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison. The data set name and
					contact person for each data set can be found in the metadata header of the online data
					sets.</para>
				<para>The Data User must send two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the
					data to the address above. We would like to include such manuscripts in our LTER
					publications list.</para>
				<para>The Data User must not redistribute original data and documentation without permission
					from Emily Stanley, lead Principal Investigator, (ehstanley@wisc.edu).</para>
				<para>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation,
					complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is".
					The North Temperate Lakes LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or
					misinterpretation of data sets. Data users should be aware that we periodically update
					data sets.</para>
				<para>Our goal is to release all long term data associated with core research areas within 2
					years of collection. These data and accompanying metadata will be available for download
					from the NTL-LTER web site.</para>
				<para>By using these data, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement.
					Thank you for your cooperation. </para>
			</section>
		</intellectualRights>
		<distribution>
			<online>
				<url function="information">http://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/node/5625</url>
			</online>
		</distribution>
		<coverage>
			<geographicCoverage>
				<geographicDescription>Imikpuk Lake, AK, USA, NARL IBP A and B, AK, USA, NARL IBP C, AK, USA, NARL IBP D, AK, USA, Toolik Lake, AK, USA, Clear Lake, CA, USA, Miramar 1 Lake, CA, USA, Reissen Lake, CA, USA, Tu-Vu Lake, CA, USA, Lake Tahoe, CA NV, USA, Leechmere Lake, CO, USA, Long Lake Lake, CO, USA, Mexican Cut L1, CO, USA, Mexican Cut L12, CO, USA, Mexican Cut L8, CO, USA, Linsley Lake, CT, USA, Thonotosassa Lake, FL, USA, Oglethorp Lake, GA, USA, Dynamite Lake, IL, USA, Miller Wds. Lake, IL, USA, Frains Lake, MI, USA, Gull Lake, MI, USA, Lawrence Lake, MI, USA, Peter Lake, MI, USA, Pond II Lake, MI, USA, Tuesday Bog Lake, MI, USA, Wintergreen Lake, MI, USA, Mirror Lake, NH, USA, Cornell 209 Lake, NY, USA, Cornell 246 Lake, NY, USA, Oneida Lake, NY, USA, Texoma Lake, OK TX, USA, Crater Lake, OR, USA, Hellertown Lake, PA, USA, Lacawac Lake, PA, USA, Bullhead Lake, RI, USA, Little Bullhead Lake, RI, USA, Dubinkey Lake, UT, USA, Utah Rock Pool AA1, UT, USA, Utah Rock Pool G5A, UT, USA, Utah Stock Pond C9, UT, USA, Lake Washington, WA, USA, Bavarian Sauage Pond, WI, USA, Crystal Lake, WI, USA, Dead Dog Pond, WI, USA, Lake Mendota, WI, USA, Lake Wingra, WI, USA, Little Rock Lake, WI, USA, Martin Lake, WI, USA, Plagge Lake, WI, USA, Sparkling Lake, WI, USA, Tower Lake, WI, USA, Trout Lake, WI, USA, Lake Michigan, WI MI, USA, Lake Erie, MI OH PA NY ON, USA Canada, Lake Superior, MN WI ON, USA Canada, Memphremagog Lake, VT QC, USA Canada, Eunice Lake, BC, Canada, Gwendoline Lake, BC, Canada, Marion Lake, BC, Canada, Lake Winnipeg, MB, Canada, Manitoba 885 Lake, MB, Canada, Great Slave Lake, NT, Canada, Char Lake, NU, Canada, ELA Lake 223 Lake, ON, Canada, Kendal II Lake, ON, Canada, Lake St. George, ON, Canada, La Caldera, SPAIN, Tjeukemeer Lake, The Netherlands
</geographicDescription>
				<boundingCoordinates>
					<westBoundingCoordinate>-156.700</westBoundingCoordinate>
					<eastBoundingCoordinate>5.800</eastBoundingCoordinate>
					<northBoundingCoordinate>74.800</northBoundingCoordinate>
					<southBoundingCoordinate>28.000</southBoundingCoordinate>
				</boundingCoordinates>
			</geographicCoverage>
			<temporalCoverage>
				<rangeOfDates>
					<beginDate>
						<calendarDate>1992-01-01</calendarDate>
					</beginDate>
					<endDate>
						<calendarDate>1993-01-01</calendarDate>
					</endDate>
				</rangeOfDates>
			</temporalCoverage>
		</coverage>
		<maintenance>
			<description>
				<para>completed </para>
			</description>
		</maintenance>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Information Manager</positionName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
			<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<publisher>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</publisher>
		<pubPlace>North Temperate Lakes</pubPlace>
		<methods>
			<methodStep>
				<description>
					<section>
						<para>Dodson, S. 1992. Predicting Crustacean Zooplankton Species Richness. Limnology and
							Oceanography 37:848-856. Dodson, S. 1991. Species richness of crustacean zoo- plankton
							in European lakes of different sizes. Int. Ver. Theor. Angew. Limnol. Verh.
							24:1223-1229. </para>
					</section>
				</description>
			</methodStep>
		</methods>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>dodson_richness_92</entityName>
			<entityDescription>Crustacean Zooplankton Species Richness</entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>dodsonrichness92</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-ntl.223&amp;urlTail=ntl/data/5625_v1.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<coverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Crystal Lake is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County.
It is a seepage lake with predominantly sand substrate. It has a surface area of 36.7 hectare, 2.3 kilometers of highly developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 20.4 meters.
Crystal Lake represents one extreme in the groundwater input gradient, with a marked predominance of precipitation inputs. Groundwater accounts for only 5% of input water, yet, because groundwater is more concentrated chemically than precipitation, groundwater accounts for substantial amounts of incoming solutes. For example, about 50% of the silica budget comes into the lake via groundwater, exerting a major influence on primary production.
The lake is an oligotrophic, dimictic lake high in the landscape with minimal groundwater input, a light attenuation coefficient of 0.24 per meter (average ice-free Secchi depth of 8 m), a mean depth of 11.4 m, and a maximum depth of 20.4 m. Crystal Lake is circular with a shoreline development factor very close to 1.0. The littoral zone is fairly homogenous and is dominated by sandy substrate with low macrophyte and coarse woody habitat densities. The fish community has been historically dominated by pelagic yellow perch. However, yellow perch drastically declined after the detection of rainbow smelt in 1985.

</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.612233</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.612233</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.00275</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.00275</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Trout Lake is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County.
It is a drainage lake with predominantly gravel and sand substrate. It has a surface area of 1607.9 hectare, 25.9 kilometers of mostly undeveloped shoreline and a maximum depth of 35.7 meters.
</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.665017</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.665017</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.029267</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.029267</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Lake Mendota is located in the Yahara River watershed within Dane County.
It is a drainage lake with predominantly muck substrate. It has a surface area of 3937.7 hectare, 33.8 kilometers of highly developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 25.3 meters.
</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>43.098333</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>43.098333</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>-89.405278</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>-89.405278</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Lake Wingra is located in the Yahara River watershed within Dane County.
It is a drainage lake with predominantly muck substrate. It has a surface area of 139.6 hectare, 5.9 kilometers of highly developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 6.7 meters.
</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.42499</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.42499</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>43.05258</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>43.05258</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
			</coverage>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>lakename</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>lake name</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>lake name</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>lake name</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>country</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>country</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>country</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>country</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>state</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>state</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>state</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>state</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>latitude</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>latitude</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>latitude</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>longitude</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>longitude</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>longitude</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>elevation</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>elevation</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>elevation</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>area</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>area of lake</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>surface area of lake</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>hectare</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>max_depth</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>maximum depth</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>maximum depth</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>mean_depth</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>mean depth</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>mean depth</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>conductivity</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>conductivity</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>conductivity</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>microSiemenPerCentimeter</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>distance_to_lake</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>distance to nearest lake</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>distance to nearest lake</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>kilometer</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>lakes_within_20km</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>lakes within 20 kilometers</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>number of lakes within 20 kilometers</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>primaryprod</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>primary production</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>primary production - C production per square meter per day</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>milligramPerMeterSquaredPerDay</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>zooplankton_species</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>species - crust zooplankton</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>number of species - crustacean zooplankton</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
	</dataset>
	<additionalMetadata>
		<metadata>
			<ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1     http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="uS/cm" constantToSI="0" id="microSiemenPerCentimeter" multiplierToSI="0.0001" name="microSiemenPerCentimeter" parentSI="siemenPerMeter" unitType="conductivityPerLength">
					<ns2:description>conductivity unit</ns2:description>
				</ns2:unit>
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="mg/m&#178;/day" constantToSI="0" id="milligramPerMeterSquaredPerDay" multiplierToSI="86400000000" name="milligramPerMeterSquaredPerDay" parentSI="kilogramsPerMeterSquaredPerSecond" unitType="arealMassDensityRate">
					<ns2:description>areal primary production rate</ns2:description>
				</ns2:unit>
			</ns2:unitList>
		</metadata>
	</additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>