<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-ntl.222.8" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
	<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
		<allow>
			<principal>uid=NTL,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
			<permission>all</permission>
		</allow>
		<allow>
			<principal>public</principal>
			<permission>read</permission>
		</allow>
	</access>
	<dataset>
		<alternateIdentifier system="NTL-DEIMS">5624</alternateIdentifier>
		<shortName>DODSON1</shortName>
		<title>Primary Production and Species Richness in Lake Communities 1997 - 2000</title>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Stanley</givenName>
				<surName>Dodson</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
    </address>
		</creator>
		<metadataProvider>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</metadataProvider>
		<pubDate>2001</pubDate>
		<language>english</language>
		<abstract>
			<para>An understanding of the relationship between species richness and productivity is
				crucial to understanding biodiversity in lakes. We investigated the relationship between the
				primary productivity of lake ecosystems and the number of species for lacustrine
				phytoplankton, rotifers, cladocerans, copepods, macrophytes, and fish. Our study includes
				two parts: (1) a survey of 33 well-studied lakes for which data on six major taxonomic
				groups were available; and (2) a comparison of the effects of short- and long-term
				whole-lake nutrient addition on primary productivity and planktonic species richness Dodson,
				Stanley I., Shelley E. Arnott, and Kathryn L. Cottingham. 2000. The relationship in lake
				communities between primary productivity and species richness. Ecology 81:2662-79. Number of
				sites: 33 </para>
		</abstract>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>crustaceans</keyword>
			<keyword>fishes</keyword>
			<keyword>phytoplankton</keyword>
			<keyword>populations</keyword>
			<keyword>primary production</keyword>
			<keyword>rotifers</keyword>
			<keyword>species richness</keyword>
			<keyword>zooplankton</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>LTER Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>NTL LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>North Temperate Lakes - LTER</keyword>
			<keyword>cladoceran species richness</keyword>
			<keyword>copepod species richness</keyword>
			<keyword>crustacean zooplankton species richness</keyword>
			<keyword>fish species richness</keyword>
			<keyword>macrophyte species richness</keyword>
			<keyword>macrophytes</keyword>
			<keyword>phytoplankton species richness</keyword>
			<keyword>rotifer species richness</keyword>
			<keyword>zooplankton species richness</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>NTL Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<intellectualRights>
			<section>
				<title>Data Policies</title>
				<para>Copyright Board of Regents, University of Wisconsin, Madison. This information is
					released to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes
					subject to the following restrictions: The Data User must realize that these data sets are
					being actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary
					to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the NTL lead Principal
					Investigator, leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu, to check on other uses of the data. Where
					appropriate, the Data User may be encouraged to consider collaboration and/or
					co-authorship with original investigators.</para>
				<para>The Data User must realize that the data may be misinterpreted if taken out of
					context. We request that you provide the NTL lead Principal Investigator, ATTN: Data
					Access, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 680 North Park St.,
					Madison, WI 53706 with a copy of any manuscript using the data so that it may be reviewed
					and comments provided on the presentation of our data.</para>
				<para>The Data User must acknowledge use of the data by an appropriate citation (see
					Citation) of the NTL-LTER database. A generic citation for our databases is: name of data
					set, North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research program, NSF, contact person for
					data set, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison. The data set name and
					contact person for each data set can be found in the metadata header of the online data
					sets.</para>
				<para>The Data User must send two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the
					data to the address above. We would like to include such manuscripts in our LTER
					publications list.</para>
				<para>The Data User must not redistribute original data and documentation without permission
					from Emily Stanley, lead Principal Investigator, (ehstanley@wisc.edu).</para>
				<para>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation,
					complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is".
					The North Temperate Lakes LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or
					misinterpretation of data sets. Data users should be aware that we periodically update
					data sets.</para>
				<para>Our goal is to release all long term data associated with core research areas within 2
					years of collection. These data and accompanying metadata will be available for download
					from the NTL-LTER web site.</para>
				<para>By using these data, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement.
					Thank you for your cooperation. </para>
			</section>
		</intellectualRights>
		<distribution>
			<online>
				<url function="information">http://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/node/5624</url>
			</online>
		</distribution>
		<coverage>
			<geographicCoverage>
				<geographicDescription>Imipuk Lake,AK,USA,Toolik Lake,AK,USA,Long Lake,CO,USA,Mexican Cut Nature Preserve Lake L1,CO,USA,Lake Thonotosassa,FL,USA,Gull Lake,MI,USA,Lawerence Lake,MI,USA,Paul Lake,MI,USA,Wintergreen Lake,MI,USA,Mirror Lake,NH,USA,Acton Lake,OH,USA,Lake Washington,WA,USA,Crystal Lake,WI,USA,Fish Lake,WI,USA,Lake Mendota,WI,USA,Lake Monona,WI,USA,Lake Wingra,WI,USA,Little Rock Lake,WI,USA,Madison Metro Sewage Facility Pond 2B,WI,USA,Sparkling Lake,WI,USA,Trout Lake,WI,USA,Char Lake,NU,Canada,ELA Lake 239,ON,Canada,St. George Lake,ON,Canada,Lake Plusssee,Germany,Lake Kinneret,Israel,Lake Biwa,Japan,Lake Kasumigaura,Japan,Lake Suwa,Japan,Lake Lanao,Phillipines,La Caldera,Spain,Lake Latnjajaure,Sweden,Lake Valencia,Venezuela
</geographicDescription>
				<boundingCoordinates>
					<westBoundingCoordinate>-156.700</westBoundingCoordinate>
					<eastBoundingCoordinate>140.400</eastBoundingCoordinate>
					<northBoundingCoordinate>74.800</northBoundingCoordinate>
					<southBoundingCoordinate>7.800</southBoundingCoordinate>
				</boundingCoordinates>
			</geographicCoverage>
			<temporalCoverage>
				<rangeOfDates>
					<beginDate>
						<calendarDate>1997-01-01</calendarDate>
					</beginDate>
					<endDate>
						<calendarDate>2000-01-01</calendarDate>
					</endDate>
				</rangeOfDates>
			</temporalCoverage>
		</coverage>
		<maintenance>
			<description>
				<para>completed </para>
			</description>
		</maintenance>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Information Manager</positionName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
			<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<publisher>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</publisher>
		<pubPlace>North Temperate Lakes</pubPlace>
		<methods>
			<methodStep>
				<description>
					<section>
						<para>Our first goal was to understand the relationship between primary productivity and
							species richness for several groups of freshwater organisms. By species richness, we
							mean the number of species observed in a lake over a number of years. It is useful to
							have several years of observations because the number of species observed varies from
							year to year. We chose the total list of species (the asymptote of the collectors
							curve) as our index of species richness. The lakes studied as part of the U.S.
							Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) Program are particularly valuable because they
							have been studied for two decades, and complete species lists exist for many kinds of
							organisms in these systems. LTER lake sites occur in northern and southern Wisconsin
							and northern Alaska (Toolik Lake). However, because there are fewer than 15 LTER lakes
							(and only seven with measured rates of primary productivity), we increased sample size
							by including data from additional well-studied lakes of similar size, but which span a
							greater range of primary productivity (see Table 1). These lakes have been studied for
							several years, and estimates of annual primary productivity exist for each lake. Some
							well-studied lakes were not included, such as those which lacked much of the crucial
							data, or lakes that were unusually turbid or saline. For example, Lake Okeechobee
							(Florida, USA) is turbid and exhibits a wide range of productivity levels, depending
							on the part of the lake sampled, while Marion Lake (British Columbia, Canada) has a
							flushing rate of only a few days (W. E. Neill, personal communication). Sampling
							design and protocol are not standardized among studies of lakes. For example, species
							identifications were done by different people, sampling period was quite variable, and
							the number of samples per lake was variable. Such heterogeneity reduces the accuracy
							and precision of relationships between productivity and species richness. Primary
							productivity.&#226;&#128;&#148;Pelagic primary productivity (PPR) can be measured by the 14C method
							(Vollenweider 1974). This method gives a close approximation to gross primary
							productivity (GPP), but because some of the fixed carbon is respired quickly, the
							value obtained is less than GPP (Fee et al.1982). Point values of PPR are then
							integrated by depth and area to produce estimates of whole-lake annual primary
							productivity per cubic meter or square meter. Lake primary productivity is
							fundamentally different than productivity measured in other biomes (e.g., grasslands,
							forests). The 14C method measures available (gross) primary productivity more than
							utilized (net) production, which is what is normally measured in terrestrial systems.
							The 14C method is also a fairly direct measure of productivity, compared to the proxy
							methods (e.g., nutrient loading, biomass, climate, soil fertility) used in many
							studies. Sampling protocols for aquatic organisms.&#226;&#128;&#148;Sampling protocols differed among
							taxonomic groups and lakes (e.g., Downing and Rigler 1984). For example, phytoplankton
							samples are taken by capturing (at most) a few liters of lake water, either from a
							specific depth or with a sampler that integrates water across a range of depths.
							Zooplankton are usually sampled by vertical tows (i.e., raising a net through the
							water column). Both zooplankton and phytoplankton samples are typically taken from the
							center of the lake, although replicate samples at different locations may be taken
							from larger lakes. Planktonic organisms are much smaller than the sampling device, and
							hundreds to hundreds of thousands of organisms are typically captured in a single
							sample. In contrast, aquatic macrophytes are sampled using quadrats and rake samples,
							or simply based on a walk around the lake, while fish are sampled using a variety of
							nets andoror electroshocking equipment. Criteria for species lists.&#226;&#128;&#148;Species lists for
							fish, macrophytes, and pelagic phytoplankton, rotifers, cladocerans, and copepods were
							obtained from the literature and from unpublished data. We avoided lists restricted to
							only dominant or common species, and thus included only lists that were exhaustive.
							Few lakes had species lists for all six groups of organisms. However, we included any
							lake that had an estimate of the average annual primary productivity and had lists for
							at least three taxa. We standardized this database by developing criteria for
							inclusion of species in analyses. Phytoplankton lists included all prokaryotic and
							eukaryotic photosynthetic phytoplankton for which there were abundances of more than
							one organism per milliliter (a criterion also used by Lewis 1979). We included all
							nonsessile species caught in open water as pelagic rotifers. For the crustacean
							zooplankton (cladocerans and copepods), we followed the criteria of Dodson (1992).
							Species lists of macrophytes included all submerged, floating, or emergent species of
							flowering plants, including Typha, sedges, grasses, and duck weed. We did not include
							Isoetes or macroalgae such as Chara and Nitella as macrophytes. The fish list included
							all species reported from the lake, including introduced taxa. Fish species reported
							to occur in the watershed, but not in the lake (as in Pearse1920) were not considered
							part of the lakes biota. </para>
					</section>
				</description>
			</methodStep>
		</methods>
		<project>
			<title>North Temperate Lakes LTER</title>
			<personnel>
				<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
				<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
				<address>
        <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
				<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<abstract>
				<para>North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research studies the ecology of lakes as
					one of a network of sites established by the National Science Foundation. We are
					interested in how biophysical setting, climate, and changing land use and cover interact
					to shape lake characteristics and dynamics over time (past, present, future). Our primary
					study sites include a set of seven northern Wisconsin and four southern Wisconsin lakes
					and their surrounding landscapes. The project, which started in 1981, is administered by
					the Center for Limnology at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. Perception of Long-Term
					Change: How and why have the lake districts changed, and how will they change in the
					future? Climatic Forcing of Change: What are the major ecological and social responses of
					lake districts to climate change? Interacting Drivers, Scales of Space and Time, and
					Regional Change: How do multiple interacting drivers affect regional change in lake
					districts at multiple scales? Ecosystem Services: Past, Present and Future: What are the
					magnitudes, interactions and potential future flows of ecosystem services in lake
					districts? </para>
			</abstract>
		</project>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>dodson_lake_comm</entityName>
			<entityDescription>Primary Production and Species Richness in Lake Communities</entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>dodsonlakecomm</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-ntl.222&amp;urlTail=ntl/data/5624_v1.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<coverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Crystal Lake is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County.
It is a seepage lake with predominantly sand substrate. It has a surface area of 36.7 hectare, 2.3 kilometers of mostly undeveloped (campground) developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 20.4 meters.
Crystal Lake represents one extreme in the groundwater input gradient, with a marked predominance of precipitation inputs. Groundwater accounts for only 5% of input water, yet, because groundwater is more concentrated chemically than precipitation, groundwater accounts for substantial amounts of incoming solutes. For example, about 50% of the silica budget comes into the lake via groundwater, exerting a major influence on primary production.
The lake is an oligotrophic, dimictic lake high in the landscape with minimal groundwater input, a light attenuation coefficient of 0.24 per meter (average ice-free Secchi depth of 8 m), a mean depth of 11.4 m, and a maximum depth of 20.4 m. Crystal Lake is circular with a shoreline development factor very close to 1.0. The littoral zone is fairly homogenous and is dominated by sandy substrate with low macrophyte and coarse woody habitat densities. The fish community has been historically dominated by pelagic yellow perch. However, yellow perch drastically declined after the detection of rainbow smelt in 1985.
</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.612233</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.612233</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.00275</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.00275</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Sparkling Lake is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County.
It is a seepage lake with predominantly sand and gravel substrate. It has a surface area of 64 hectare, 4.3 kilometers of moderately developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 20 meters.
</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.701183</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.701183</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.007733</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.007733</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Trout Lake is located within the Northern Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County.
It is a drainage lake with predominantly gravel and sand substrate. It has a surface area of 1607.9 hectare, 25.9 kilometers of mostly undeveloped shoreline and a maximum depth of 35.7 meters.
</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.665017</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.665017</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>46.029267</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>46.029267</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Fish Lake is located in the Yahara River watershed within Dane County.
It is a seepage lake with predominantly sand and muck substrate. It has a surface area of 87.4 hectare, 4.3 kilometers of highly developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 18.9 meters.
</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.65112</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.65112</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>43.287083</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>43.287083</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Lake Mendota is located in the Yahara River watershed within Dane County.
It is a drainage lake with predominantly muck substrate. It has a surface area of 3937.7 hectare, 33.8 kilometers of highly developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 25.3 meters.
</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>43.098333</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>43.098333</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>-89.405278</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>-89.405278</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Lake Wingra is located in the Yahara River watershed within Dane County.
It is a drainage lake with predominantly muck substrate. It has a surface area of 139.6 hectare, 5.9 kilometers of highly developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 6.7 meters.
</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.42499</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.42499</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>43.05258</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>43.05258</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
				<geographicCoverage>
					<geographicDescription>Location: Lake Monona is located in the Yahara River watershed within Dane County.
It is a drainage lake with muck, sand and gravel substrate. It has a surface area of 1324 hectare, 20.9 kilometers of highly developed shoreline and a maximum depth of 22.5 meters.
</geographicDescription>
					<boundingCoordinates>
						<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.361</westBoundingCoordinate>
						<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.361</eastBoundingCoordinate>
						<northBoundingCoordinate>43.063</northBoundingCoordinate>
						<southBoundingCoordinate>43.063</southBoundingCoordinate>
					</boundingCoordinates>
				</geographicCoverage>
			</coverage>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>lakename</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>lake name</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>lake name</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>lake name</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>state</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>state</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>state</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>state</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>country</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>country</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>country</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>country</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>latitude</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>latitude</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>latitude</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>longitude</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>longitude</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>longitude</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>elevation</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>elevation</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>elevation</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>area</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>area of lake</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>surface area of lake</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>hectare</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>primaryprod</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>primary production</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>primary production - C production per square meter per year</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<customUnit>gramPerMeterSquaredPerYear</customUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>phytoplankton</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>species - phytoplankton</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>number of species - phytoplankton</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>rotifers</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>species - rotifers</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>number of species - rotifers</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>crust_zooplankton</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>species - crust zooplankton</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>number of species - crustacean zooplankton</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>cladocerans</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>species - cladocerans</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>number of species - cladocerans</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>copepods</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>species - copepods</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>number of species - copepods</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>macrophytes</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>species - macrophytes</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>number of species - macrophytes</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>fish</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>species - fish</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>number of species - fish</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
	</dataset>
	<additionalMetadata>
		<metadata>
			<ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1     http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
				<ns2:unit abbreviation="g/m&#178;/yr" constantToSI="0" id="gramPerMeterSquaredPerYear" multiplierToSI="0.0000000000317098" name="gramPerMeterSquaredPerYear" parentSI="kilogramsPerMeterSquaredPerSecond" unitType="arealMassDensityRate">
					<ns2:description>grams Per Meter Squared Per Year</ns2:description>
				</ns2:unit>
			</ns2:unitList>
		</metadata>
	</additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>