<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-vcr.179.16" system="VCR" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
   <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst">
      <allow>
         <principal>public</principal>
         <permission>read</permission>
      </allow>
      <allow>
         <principal>uid=VCR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
         <permission>all</permission>
      </allow>
   </access>

<dataset id="179" system="VCR">
   <alternateIdentifier>VCR10171</alternateIdentifier>
   <title>Network analysis of nitrogen cycling in Hog Island Bay, VA and Sacca   di Goro, IT</title>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
         <givenName>Robert</givenName>
         <surName>Christian</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>East Carolina University, Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Greenville</city>
         <administrativeArea>NC</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>27858-4353</postalCode>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(252) 328-1835</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(252) 328-4178</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>christianr@ecu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/cgi-bin/w3e/msql/personnel/msql2/person.html?QID=">rchristian</userId>
   </creator>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <givenName>Christine</givenName>
         <surName>Voss</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>102 Adams Blvd.</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Greenville</city>
         <administrativeArea>NC</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>27858</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">252.752.6690</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>chrisscross60@yahoo.com</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/cgi-bin/w3e/msql/personnel/msql2/person.html?QID=">cvoss</userId>
   </creator>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <givenName>C.</givenName>
         <surName>Bondavalli</surName>
      </individualName>
   </creator>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <givenName>P.</givenName>
         <surName>Viaroli</surName>
      </individualName>
   </creator>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <givenName>M.</givenName>
         <surName>Naldi</surName>
      </individualName>
   </creator>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <salutation>Ms.</salutation>
         <givenName>A.</givenName>
         <surName>Tyler</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Dept. of Environmental Sciences, University of Virginia</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22903</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">434-924-6846</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>act9q@virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/cgi-bin/w3e/msql/personnel/msql2/person.html?QID=">atyler</userId>
   </creator>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <givenName>Iris</givenName>
         <surName>Anderson</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>College of William and Mary, Virginia Institute of Marine Science, School of Marine Science</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Gloucester Point</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>23062</postalCode>
         <country>225</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(804) 684-7242</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(804) 684-7179</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>iris@vims.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/cgi-bin/w3e/msql/personnel/msql2/person.html?QID=">ianderson</userId>
   </creator>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
         <givenName>Karen</givenName>
         <surName>McGlathery</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Department of Environmental Sciences, Clark Hall, University of Virginia</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22903</postalCode>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">434-924-0558</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">434-982-2137</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>kjm4k@virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/cgi-bin/w3e/msql/personnel/msql2/person.html?QID=">kmcglathery</userId>
   </creator>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <givenName>R.E.</givenName>
         <surName>Ulanowicz</surName>
      </individualName>
   </creator>
   <creator>
      <individualName>
         <givenName>V.</givenName>
         <surName>Camacho-Ibar</surName>
      </individualName>
   </creator>
   <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>Virginia Coast Reserve Long-Term Ecological Research Project</organizationName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Department of Environmental Sciences, University of Virginia, 291 McCormick Road, PO Box 400123</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22904-4123</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">434-924-7761</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">434-982-2137</phone>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu</onlineUrl>
   </metadataProvider>
   <pubDate>2010-02-22</pubDate>
   <abstract>
  <para> This data was used in a Network Analysis of Nitrogen Cycling in two shallow coastal lagoons: Hog Island Bay in Virginia, USA and Sacca di Goro in Italy. </para>
  <para>This dataset consists of data in the Excel spreadsheet formatted for use with the WAND software package (http://www.dsa.unipr.it/netanalysis/?Software).</para>
   </abstract>
   <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Inorganic Nutrients</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTERCoreAreas</keywordThesaurus>
   </keywordSet>
   <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">nitrogen</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Network Analysis</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Lagoons</keyword>
   </keywordSet>
   <additionalInfo>
<section>
<title>Relevant URLs</title>
<para><orderedlist>
<listitem><para>
WAND software package) 
URL=http://www.dsa.unipr.it/netanalysis/?Software
</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>
</section>
<section> 
 <title>Related Documents</title>
  <para> Christian, R.R., C.M. Voss, C. Bondavalli, P. Viaroli, M. Naldi, A.C. Tyler, I.C. Anderson, K.J. McGlathery, R.E. Ulanowicz, and V. Camacho-Ibar. 2010. Ecosystem Health Indexed through Networks of Nitrogen Cycling. Pp. 73-91. In M.J. Kennish and H.W. Paerl (eds.), Coastal Lagoons: Critical Habitats of Environmental Change. Taylor &amp; Francis Group LLC. Boca Raton, FL. </para>
</section>

   </additionalInfo>
   <intellectualRights>
            <section>
                <title>Data License</title>
                <para>Data and documentation is copyrighted by The Virginia Coast Reserve LTER
                    project of the University of Virginia (UVA), and ownership remains with the UVA.</para>
                <para>The UVA grants you (hereafter, Licensee) a license to use the data and
                    documentation for academic, and research purposes only, without a fee.</para>
                <para>Licensee may make derivative works. However, if Licensee distributes any
                    derivative work based on or derived from the data and documentation, then
                    Licensee will</para>
                <para>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>notify the VCR/LTER designated contact (typically the investigator
                                who collected the data) regarding its distribution of the derivative
                                work, and</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>clearly notify users that such derivative work is a modified
                                version and not the original data and documentation distributed by
                                the UVA.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>acknowledge the support of NSF Grants BSR-8702333-06, DEB-9211772,
                                DEB-9411974, DEB-0080381 and DEB-0621014 in any publications using the data and documentation.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>send to the address, above, two reprints of any publications
                                resulting from use of the data and documentation. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </para>
                <para>Any Licensee wishing to make commercial use of the data and documentation
                    should contact the UVA, c/o VCR/LTER, to negotiate an appropriate license for
                    such commercial use. Commercial use includes</para>
                <para>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>integration of all or part of the data and documentation into a
                                product for sale or license by or on behalf of Licensee to third
                                parties, or</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> distribution of the data or documentation to third parties that
                                need it to utilize a commercial product sold or licensed by or on
                                behalf of Licensee.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </para>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>UVA MAKES NO REPRESENTATIONS ABOUT THE SUITABILITY OF THIS DATA AND
                        DOCUMENTATION FOR ANY PURPOSE. IT IS PROVIDED "AS IS" WITHOUT EXPRESS OR
                        IMPLIED WARRANTY. THE UVA SHALL NOT BE LIABLE FOR ANY DAMAGES SUFFERED BY
                        THE USERS OF THIS DATA AND DOCUMENTATION.</emphasis>
                </para>
                <para>By using or copying this data and documentation, Licensee agrees to abide by
                    the copyright law and all other applicable laws of the U.S. including, but not
                    limited to, export control laws, and the terms of this license. UVA shall have
                    the right to terminate this license immediately by written notice upon
                    Licensee's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. Licensee may be
                    held legally responsible for any copyright infringement that is caused or
                    encouraged by Licensee's failure to abide by the terms of this license. </para>
            </section>
   </intellectualRights>
   <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
         <geographicDescription>HOGBAY - Hog Island Bay</geographicDescription>
         <boundingCoordinates>
            <westBoundingCoordinate>-75.700000</westBoundingCoordinate>
            <eastBoundingCoordinate>-75.810000</eastBoundingCoordinate>
            <northBoundingCoordinate>37.500000</northBoundingCoordinate>
            <southBoundingCoordinate>37.360000</southBoundingCoordinate>
         </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
         <geographicDescription>SACCAGORO - Sacca di Goro, Italy</geographicDescription>
         <boundingCoordinates>
            <westBoundingCoordinate>-76</westBoundingCoordinate>
            <eastBoundingCoordinate>-75.3</eastBoundingCoordinate>
            <northBoundingCoordinate>38</northBoundingCoordinate>
            <southBoundingCoordinate>37</southBoundingCoordinate>
            <boundingAltitudes>
               <altitudeMinimum>-2</altitudeMinimum>
               <altitudeMaximum>10</altitudeMaximum>
               <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
            </boundingAltitudes>
         </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
         <singleDateTime>
            <calendarDate>2010-02-22</calendarDate>
         </singleDateTime>
      </temporalCoverage>
   </coverage>
   <maintenance>
      <description>
<para>Data are updated as needed</para>
      </description>
      <maintenanceUpdateFrequency>asNeeded</maintenanceUpdateFrequency>
   </maintenance>
   <contact>
      <individualName>
         <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
         <givenName>Robert</givenName>
         <surName>Christian</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>East Carolina University, Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Greenville</city>
         <administrativeArea>NC</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>27858-4353</postalCode>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(252) 328-1835</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">(252) 328-4178</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>christianr@ecu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/cgi-bin/w3e/msql/personnel/msql2/person.html?QID=">rchristian</userId>
   </contact>
   <contact id="im">
      <positionName>Information manager - Virginia Coast Reserve Long-Term Ecological Research Project</positionName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Department of Environmental Sciences, University of Virginia, 291 McCormick Road, PO Box 400123</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22904-4123</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">434-924-8999</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">434-982-2137</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>jporter@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu/jhp7e.html</onlineUrl>
   </contact>
   <publisher>
      <organizationName>Virginia Coast Reserve Long-Term Ecological Research Project</organizationName>
      <address>
         <deliveryPoint>Department of Environmental Sciences, University of Virginia, 291 McCormick Road, PO Box 400123</deliveryPoint>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
         <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
         <postalCode>22904-4123</postalCode>
         <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">434-924-7761</phone>
      <phone phonetype="facsimile">434-982-2137</phone>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.vcrlter.virginia.edu</onlineUrl>
   </publisher>
   <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
   <methods>
      <methodStep>
         <description>
  <para> We constructed our networks of nitrogen cycling during two periods at each habitat (3 in HIB and 2 in GOR). A generally more productive period in spring and early summer (Sp)(March to June) was compared to a generally less productive period in late summer and early autumn (Su)(August to October). </para>
  <para>Units of standing stock were mmol N x m-2 and flows were mmol N x m-2 x d-1. Three compartments were used for primary producers: phytoplankton (PHY), macroalgae (MAC) and microphytobenthos (MPB). None of the habitats had rooted phanerogams. Dissolved nitrogen was divided into separate inorganic (DIN) and organic (DON) compartments. The trypton (TRP) compartment contained non-phytoplankton N in seston. This included any consumer organisms. Estimates of the importance of size of aquatic consumers to nitrogen cycling indicate that planktonic sized consumers, included in seston, dominate fluxes. The sediment (SED) compartment contained all forms of N within sediments, including N within and outside of organisms, except MPB. Standing stocks and flows were derived from a number of sources.</para>
  <para>We quantified both flows between compartments as well as flows connecting internal components to the outside of the system. The latter consisted of imports and two forms of outputs: exports and dissipations. Compartments PHY, TRP, SED, DIN and DON can receive nitrogen from outside the location, whereas all the state variables, but MPB, have been assumed to export it. Growth of MAC is represented as either export (HIB) or dissipation (GOR). This removal of MC nitrogen has been added to the network in order to have MAC compartment balanced (networks are assumed to balance over each season), and it stands for standing stock increase. Dissipation for both locations involves the loss of N due to denitrification from the sediment. Compartments are connected to one another via feeding, biogeochemical and detrital pathways. When a flow is considered possible but not measurable, it is given a minimal value of 0.001 mmol N x m-2 x d-1.</para>
  <para>Network analysis is more easily interpreted when flows of matter entering and leaving a given compartment, and the ecosystem as a whole, are in steady-state so that there is no increase or decrease in mass with time. Once the flow networks were constructed with initial values, flows for each compartment were balanced.</para>
  <para>In this study, balancing was achieved by a three step process. The first step is based on expert judgment, whereby change of flows is made in such a way that: (a) makes ecological sense, (b) goes in the direction of balancing, (c) tries to minimize the change in flows perceived to be most reliable, and (d) promotes final closure on imports or exports. In this step and based on the degree of uncertainty in the measurements, the original flows were categorized as highly reliable (e.g., standing stocks of all compartments but trypton, denitrification, all flows from sediments), intermediately reliable (e.g., trypton standing stocks, DIN and DON consumption by macroalgae and phytoplankton) and least reliable (e.g., imports of all primary producers, DIN and DON consumption by trypton). In each case, the maximum adjustment to the flow was allowed to increase with decreased reliability. Expert balancing proceeded until the balance between imports and exports was within 10%, or when further flow modifications were not ecologically meaningful. In step two we applied the output-input (OI) and/or the average algorithms for balancing ecosystem networks using the WAND Balance package (http://www.dsa.unipr.it/netanalysis/?Software).</para>
  <para>In the case of HIB, the average balance resulted in a substantial distortion of the most dominant flows (i.e. from microphytobenthos to sediments and vice versa) than with the OI-balance. As flow distortion between these compartments was high even after balancing with the OI-algorithm, a third-step in the balancing procedure was included for HIB. In this step, the values of the MPB to sediment and the sediment to MPB flows in the matrix obtained from the OI balance were substituted by their original values and an average balance was performed on the modified matrix. ENA was applied on 10 balanced matrices using the WAND software package (http://www.dsa.unipr.it/netanalysis/?Software).</para>
         </description>
      </methodStep>
   </methods>
   <otherEntity>
      <entityName>VCR10171</entityName>
      <entityDescription>
Excel spreadsheets containing the data are stored in a .ZIP file. To accommodate different versions of Microsoft Excel the .ZIP file contains  subdirectories. The original data files used in the analysis used EXCEL 2003 formats.

Note that each spreadsheet file contains two intertwined worksheets.  


      </entityDescription>
      <physical>
         <objectName>N_Cycling_Network_Analysis_Data_VCR10171.zip</objectName>
         <characterEncoding>Binary</characterEncoding>
         <dataFormat>
            <externallyDefinedFormat>
               <formatName>Esoteric</formatName>
            </externallyDefinedFormat>
         </dataFormat>
         <distribution>
            <online>
               <url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-vcr.179.16&amp;urlHeadID=2&amp;urlTail=1/VCR10171/VCR10171/N_Cycling_Network_Analysis_Data_VCR10171.zip</url>
            </online>
            <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst">
               <allow>
                  <principal>public</principal>
                  <permission>read</permission>
               </allow>
               <allow>
                  <principal>uid=VCR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
                  <permission>all</permission>
               </allow>
            </access>
         </distribution>
      </physical>
      <entityType>file      </entityType>
   </otherEntity>

</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
   <metadata>
      <localtags>
         <system>VCRLTER</system>
         <weight>-7</weight>
         <researchTheme>Fluxes Watershed&#8211;Bay&#8211;Ocean</researchTheme>
      </localtags>
   </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>

</ns0:eml>