<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="evilanova.3.1" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataset scope="document"><title>Tropical Forests Monitoring and carbon balance</title><creator id="1279914629125" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Emilio</givenName><surName>Vilanova</surName></individualName><organizationName>Universidad de Los Andes - Instituto de Investigaciones para el Desarrollo Forestal (INDEFOR)</organizationName><positionName>Assistant researcher and professor</positionName></creator><abstract><para>Carbon emissions from deforestation and forest degradation, especially in the tropics, account for at least 20% of global CO2 release. Accurate estimations of forest carbon are needed to improve our knowledge of carbon cycle in tropical forests and how these ecosystems may be affected by human activities. In this project, we are providing with accurate estimations of aboveground biomass and carbon  based on long-term data from permanent plots in remnant forests of Caparo Forest Reserve, located in the western plains of Venezuela. Monitoring initiated in 1990 and consist of systematic evaluations of forests with special emphasis on tree species. Diameter, height and several pther dasonomic features of decidous forests are being monitored and data incorporated into allometric models to estimate temporal dynamics of forest biomass and carbon balance. Caparo includes on the last samples of tropical seasonal forests of western Venezuela and remaind as an opportunity to promote new strategues for sustainable management includin ecosystem services such as carbon (REDD initiatives) and biodiversity.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Aboveground biomass</keyword><keyword>Caparo</keyword><keyword>Carbon</keyword><keyword>Monitoring</keyword><keyword>Tropical Forests</keyword></keywordSet><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Caparo - El Cant&#243;n</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-71.25</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-69.875</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>7.875</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>6.75</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><contact id="1279914747515" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Armando</givenName><surName>Torres Lezama</surName></individualName><organizationName>Universidad de Los Andes</organizationName><positionName>Full Professor</positionName></contact></dataset></ns0:eml>