<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-bes.93.570" system="BES" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0   http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
    <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="BES">
      <allow>
        <principal>uid=BES,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
        <permission>all</permission>
      </allow>
      <allow>
        <principal>public</principal>
        <permission>read</permission>
      </allow>
    </access>
    <dataset scope="document">
      <title>TIGER Road Network</title>
      <creator id="BES-LTER-Org">
      <organizationName>Cary Institute Of Ecosystem Studies</organizationName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>Baltimore Ecosystem Study</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>1280 Sharon Turnpike</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>PO Box AB</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Millbrook</city>
          <administrativeArea>NY</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>12545</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <onlineUrl>http://caryinstitute.org</onlineUrl>
      </creator>
      <creator id="BES-LTER-Person">
      <organizationName>Cary Institute Of Ecosystem Studies</organizationName>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Jarlath</givenName>
          <surName>O'Neil-Dunne</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>University of Vermont  Spatial Analysis Laboratory</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>Rubenstein School of Environment and Natural Resources</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>220 George D. Aiken Center</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Burlington</city>
          <administrativeArea>VT</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>05405-0088</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <electronicMailAddress>Jarlath.ONeil-Dunne@uvm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      </creator>
        <pubDate>2009-12-31</pubDate>
        <abstract>
          <para>
          TIGER road data for the MSA.  When compared to high-resolution imagery and other transportation datasets positional inaccuracies were observed.  As a result caution should be taken when using this dataset. TIGER, TIGER/Line, and Census TIGER are registered trademarks of the U.S. Census Bureau.  ZCTA is a trademark of the U.S. Census Bureau. The Census 2000 TIGER/Line files are an extract of selected geographic and cartographic information from the Census TIGER data base.  The geographic coverage for a single TIGER/Line file is a county or statistical equivalent entity, with the coverage area based on January 1, 2000 legal boundaries.  A complete set of census 2000 TIGER/Line files includes all counties and statistically equivalent entities in the United States, Puerto Rico, and the Island Areas.  The Census TIGER data base represents a seamless national file with no overlaps or gaps between parts.  However, each county-based TIGER/Line file is designed to stand alone as an independent data set or the files can be combined to cover the whole Nation.  The Census 2000 TIGER/Line files consist of line segments representing physical features and governmental and statistical boundaries.  The boundary information in the TIGER/Line files are for statistical data collection and tabulation purposes only; their depiction and designation for statistical purposes does not constitute a determination of jurisdictional authority or rights of ownership or entitlement.  The Census 2000 TIGER/Line files do NOT contain the Census 2000 urban areas which have not yet been delineated.  The files contain information distributed over a series of record types for the spatial objects of a county.  There are 17 record types, including the basic data record, the shape coordinate points, and geographic codes that can be used with appropriate software to prepare maps.  Other geographic information contained in the files includes attributes such as feature identifiers/census feature class codes (CFCC) used to differentiate feature types, address ranges and ZIP Codes, codes for legal and statistical entities, latitude/longitude coordinates of linear and point features, landmark point features, area landmarks, key geographic features, and area boundaries.  The Census 2000 TIGER/Line data dictionary contains a complete list of all the fields in the 17 record types.</para><para>
          </para><para>
          This is part of a collection of 221 Baltimore Ecosystem Study metadata records that point to a geodatabase.</para><para>
          </para><para>
          The geodatabase is available online and is considerably large.  Upon request, and under certain arrangements, it can be shipped on media, such as a usb hard drive.</para><para>
          </para><para>
          The geodatabase is roughly 51.4 Gb in size, consisting of 4,914 files in 160 folders.</para><para>
          </para><para>
          Although this metadata record and the others like it are not rich with attributes, it is nonetheless made available because the data that it represents could be indeed useful.
          </para>
        </abstract>
        <keywordSet>
        <keyword keywordType="theme">Not Available</keyword>
        </keywordSet>
        <keywordSet>
        <keyword keywordType="theme">Not Available</keyword>
        </keywordSet>
        <intellectualRights>
        <para>Publisher: Jarlath O'Neil-Dunne The scientists the BES-LTER Program and the Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies must receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data.  Please inform the BES Project Facilitator and use a statement such as the following to give credit on any document using the data: 'Data was supported by the Baltimore Ecosystem Study'</para>
        </intellectualRights>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url function="information">http://beslter.org</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
        <coverage>
          <geographicCoverage>
            <geographicDescription>Bounding coordinates describing the area covered by the entire BES study</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
            <westBoundingCoordinate>-77.314183</westBoundingCoordinate>
            <eastBoundingCoordinate>-76.012008</eastBoundingCoordinate>
            <northBoundingCoordinate>39.724847</northBoundingCoordinate>
            <southBoundingCoordinate>38.708367</southBoundingCoordinate>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </geographicCoverage>
          <temporalCoverage>
            <rangeOfDates>
              <beginDate>
                <calendarDate>2004-01-01</calendarDate>
              </beginDate>
              <endDate>
                <calendarDate>2011-11-17</calendarDate>
              </endDate>
            </rangeOfDates>
          </temporalCoverage>
        </coverage>
        <contact><positionName>Baltimore Ecosystem Study Information Manager</positionName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>Cary Institute Of Ecosystem Studies</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>2801 Sharon Turnpike</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Millbrook</city>
          <administrativeArea>New York</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>12545</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <electronicMailAddress>walshj@caryinstitute.org</electronicMailAddress>
        </contact>
        <otherEntity id="BES Datatype OtherEntity" system="BES system name for other entity">
          <entityName>TIGER Road Network</entityName>
          <entityDescription>This GIS dataset only available by contacting BES Directly. Title: TIGER Road Network</entityDescription>
          <physical>
            <objectName>Transportation.mdb</objectName>
            <size unit="kilobyte">53999756</size>
            <dataFormat>
            <externallyDefinedFormat>
              <formatName>.dbf</formatName>
            </externallyDefinedFormat>
            </dataFormat>
            <distribution>
            <online>
              <onlineDescription>This GIS dataset only available by contacting BES Directly. Title: TIGER Road Network</onlineDescription>
              <url function="download">http://beslter.org/geodatabase_SAL/Transportation/Transportation.mdb</url>
            </online>
            </distribution>
          </physical>
          <entityType>ESRI GIS</entityType>
          </otherEntity>
    </dataset>
    <additionalMetadata>
      <metadata>
        <unitList>
          <unit abbreviation="mg/l" id="milligramsPerLiter" multiplerToSI=".001" name="MilligramsPerLiter" parentSI="grams per cubic centimeter" unitType="massDensity">
            <description>per meter, describes optical properties</description>
          </unit>
          <unit abbreviation="ug/l" id="microgramsPerLiter" multiplerToSI=".0001" name="MilligramsPerLiter" parentSI="grams per cubic centimeter" unitType="massDensity">
            <description>per meter, describes optical properties</description>
          </unit>
          <unit abbreviation="ft" id="foot" multiplerToSI="2.54" name="ft" parentSI="meter" unitType="length">
            <description>how long is something, describes physical properties</description>
          </unit>
          <unit abbreviation="mph" id="milesperhour" multiplerToSI=".44704" name="milesperhour" parentSI="meterspersecond" unitType="speed">
            <description>how fast is something going, describes physical properties</description>
          </unit>
        </unitList>
      </metadata>
    </additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>