<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-mcm.67.8" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
   <allow>
    <principal>uid=MCM,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
   </allow>
   <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
   </allow>
  </access>
<dataset>
<shortName>icethickness</shortName>
<title>Ice Thickness for Taylor Valley Lakes, Antarctica</title>
<creator>
   <individualName>
    <givenName>John</givenName>
    <surName>Priscu</surName>
   </individualName>
   <address>
    <deliveryPoint> Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
    <deliveryPoint>309 Lewis Hall</deliveryPoint>
    <deliveryPoint>   Montana State University </deliveryPoint>
    <city>Bozeman</city>
    <administrativeArea>MT</administrativeArea>
    <postalCode> 59717</postalCode>
    <country>USA</country>
   </address>
   <phone phonetype="voice">(406)994-3250</phone>
   <electronicMailAddress>jpriscu@montana.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
<metadataProvider>
<organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
  <address>
 <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Albuquerque</city>
   <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">505-277-3418</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">505-277-0304</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>mcmdata@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </metadataProvider>
<associatedParty>
   <individualName>
    <givenName>Chiuchiolo</givenName>
    <surName>Amy</surName>
   </individualName>
   <address>
    <deliveryPoint> Department of Land Resources and Environmental Sciences</deliveryPoint>
    <deliveryPoint>Montana State University </deliveryPoint>
    <city>Bozeman</city>
    <administrativeArea>MT</administrativeArea>
    <postalCode> 59717 </postalCode>
    <country>USA</country>
   </address>
   <phone phonetype="voice">406-994-2360 </phone>
   <electronicMailAddress>achiuchiolo@montana.edu</electronicMailAddress>
   <role>Associated Researcher</role>
  </associatedParty>
<abstract>
   <section>
    <para>
      Ice thickness was measured from the bottom of the ice cover to the piezometric
      water level and to the top of the ice cover. Because most limnological sampling 
      holes are drilled in low-lying areas, it was thought that ice thickness measurements 
      were biased. Therefore, random ice thickness measurements were performed in a 1000 m2 
      sampling grid on each lake in past years. Statistical analyses by Dr. Priscu have 
      shown that measurements from three ice holes are representative of the ice thickness 
      measured by this grid system.
    </para>
   </section>
  </abstract>
<keywordSet>
   <keyword keywordType="theme"> lake</keyword>
   <keyword keywordType="theme"> ice thickness</keyword>
<keyword keywordType="place">McMurdo Dry Valleys</keyword>
<keyword keywordType="theme">MCM</keyword>
  </keywordSet>
<additionalInfo>
   <section>
    <title>Comments</title>
    <para>
     <literalLayout> Problems with the Kovacs drill prevented the limnological sampling team from
      attaining more than one "unbiased" measurement at Lake Fryxell during the 1996-97
     season.</literalLayout>
    </para>
   </section>
   <section>
    <title>Citations</title>
    <para>
     <literalLayout> </literalLayout>
    </para>
   </section>
   <section>
    <title>Notes about 04-05 season</title>
    <para>
     <literalLayout> Because sampling at Lake Vanda was done as a day trip, the Aqua-Vu system 
      was not brought to this sampling location, and the ice thickness measurement was done using 
      the method employed in previous years.  A 30 cm brass rod, with nylon cord attached to one end, 
      was fastened to a 10 m tape measure and lowered through the newly drilled ice hole. Once 
      through the ice, the tape measure was slowly pulled upward allowing the brass rod to catch on 
      the bottom of the ice cover.  The distances from the bottom of the ice cover to the piezometric
      water level (z-water), and to the top of the ice cover (z-ice), were recorded.  </literalLayout>
    </para>
   </section>
   <section>
    <title>Notes</title>
    <para>
     <literalLayout> Data contained in these files has been subjected to quality control standards
      imposed by the investigator. The user of this data should be aware that, while efforts have
      been taken to ensure that these data are of the highest quality, there is no guarantee of
      perfection for the data contained herein and the possibility of errors exists. If you
      encounter questionable data, please contact the MCM LTER data manager corrected or qualified.
      Thus, these data may be modified and future data will be appended.</literalLayout>
    </para>
   </section>
  </additionalInfo>
<intellectualRights>
   <section>
    <title>MCM LTER data may be used freely with the following restrictions:</title>
    <para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literalLayout>The Principal Investigator be sent a notice stating reasons for acquiring any
         data and a description of the publication intentions. </literalLayout>
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literalLayout>The Principal Investigator of the data set be sent a copy of the report or
         manuscript prior to submission and be adequately cited in any resultant
        publications.</literalLayout>
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literalLayout>A copy of any resultant publications should be sent to the McMurdo data
         manager and principal investigator.</literalLayout>
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literalLayout>The end-user follow the guidelines set forth in the LTER Network Data Access
         Policy, Data Access Requirements, and General Data Use Agreement found at
         http://www.mcmlter.org/data_guidelines.htm</literalLayout>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </para>
   </section>
  </intellectualRights>
<distribution>
   <online>
    <url>http://www.mcmlter.org/queries/limno_results.jsp?begDate=01/01/0001&amp;endDate=01/01/3000&amp;dataType=ICE_THICKNESS</url>
   </online>
  </distribution>
<coverage>
   <geographicCoverage>
    <geographicDescription> Measurements were taken from East Lake Bonney, West Lake Bonney, Lake
     Hoare, Lake Fryxell, Lake Joyce, and Lake Miers in the McMurdo Dry Valleys of Antarctica. </geographicDescription>
    
    <boundingCoordinates>
     <westBoundingCoordinate>162</westBoundingCoordinate>
     <eastBoundingCoordinate>163.6</eastBoundingCoordinate>
     <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.2</northBoundingCoordinate>
     <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.8</southBoundingCoordinate>
     
     <boundingAltitudes>
      <altitudeMinimum>0</altitudeMinimum>
      <altitudeMaximum>1000</altitudeMaximum>
      <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
     </boundingAltitudes>
    </boundingCoordinates>
   </geographicCoverage>
   <temporalCoverage>
    <rangeOfDates>
     <beginDate>
      <calendarDate>1995</calendarDate>
     </beginDate>
     <endDate>
      <calendarDate>2011</calendarDate>
     </endDate>
    </rangeOfDates>
   </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
<maintenance>
   <description>
    <section>
     <para>
      <literalLayout> The 1995/96 data from this table was submitted to INSTAAR by Ray Kepner at the
       Desert Research Institute. It was included in several e-mail messages sent in August 1997.
       Denise Steigerwald, the data manager used the information in these messages to create a file
       called thckness.dat.
       
       The 1996/97 and 1997/98 data was submitted to INSTAAR by John Priscu's
       team at Montana State University. The former is a Microsoft Excel version 6.0 file
       (icethk.xls), and the latter is an ascii text file. 
       
       Upon arrival at INSTAAR, the data manager  fine-tuned the files to allow them to be merged for use on the MCM LTER web site. Adjustments
       included the following: 
       
       Lake Descriptions" file. added to the "Limno Holes, Dive Holes, Lake
       Level Measurement Locations" file. 
       
       The icethk.xls file did not contain variables for latitude
       and longitude, but records for each "location" represented in this dataset were added to the
       "Limno Holes, Dive Holes, Lake Level Measurement Locations" file (leaving the latitude and
       longitude fields blank). The links made possible by doing this will allow users to call up
       further information about a given lake (thru the link with the "McMurdo Dry Valley Lake
       Descriptions" file), and/or about a given sampling location on the lake (thru the link with
       the "Limno Holes, Dive Holes, Lake Level Measurement Locations" file). 
       
       icethk.xls file had  variables for z-water, z-ice, and z-diff. After consulting with Craig Wolf (at Montana State
       University), the ice thickness variable was renamed to z-ice. project (S025) which is still
       taking place. John Priscu requested to have these records removed from the MCM LTER web site
       in an August, 1998 e-mail message. Any location codes containing a "C" followed by a number
       (eg. C01) were removed from this file.
       
       Each of these adjustments allowed the all of the ice
       thickness measurements to be represented in one data file on the MCM LTER web site. The file
       was imported into Microsoft Access on INSTAAR's Unix system, and can currently be found
       there. The file was then exported in ascii, comma delimited text and MS-DOS text (table
       layout) to present on the MCM LTER web site. Both of these files are linked to this web page
       above. 
       
       Information for the metadata was obtained from the icethick.metadata.txt and
       Metaicethick9697.rtf files. The".rtf" file was called up using Microsoft Word version 6.0,
       and a simple text editor was used for the icethick.metadata.txt file. Text from these files
       was used to create this page in html format.
      
      In 2006, Chris Gardner added Latitude and Longitude columns to the Ice Thickness table.  He also deleted and reloaded
       seasons 2001-2002 through 2003-2004 as some errors were found.  Lat/Longs were added to these dates as well.
      </literalLayout>
     </para>
    </section>
   </description>
  </maintenance>
<contact>
<organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
  <address>
 <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Albuquerque</city>
   <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">505-277-3418</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">505-277-0304</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>mcmdata@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
<publisher>
<organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
  <address>
 <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Albuquerque</city>
   <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">505-277-3418</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">505-277-0304</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>mcmdata@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </publisher>
<methods>
   <methodStep>
    <description>
     <para>
      <literalLayout> A 30 cm brass rod, with nylon string attached to one end, was fastened to a 10
       m tape measure and lowered through a newly drilled ice hole. Once through the ice, the tape
       measure was slowly pulled upward allowing the brass rod to catch on the bottom of the ice
       cover. The distances from the bottom of the ice cover to the piezometric water level
       (z-water), and to the top of the ice cover (z-ice) were then recorded. The difference between
       these two measurements (z-difference) or "freebore" provides some insight into the
       topographical features of the ice cover as well as density of the ice. Ice thickness
       measurements are typically performed on each hole drilled through the ice cover. Because most
       limnological sampling holes are drilled in low-lying areas, ice thickness measurements have
       been biased. Therefore, random ice thickness measurements were performed in a 1000 m2
       sampling grid on each lake. At Lakes Fryxell, Hoare, East and West Bonney the sampling grids
       are located along a 100 m baseline due south of the blue instrument boxes. Prior to sampling,
       two sets of random numbers between 0 and 100 were generated as south and east coordinates in
       this 100x100m grid. For example, if the sampling coordinates were (56S, 72E), the hole would
       be located 56 m due south along the baseline, then similarly, 72 m due east of that
      baseline.</literalLayout>
     </para>
    </description>
   </methodStep>
   <methodStep>
    <description>
     <para>
      <literalLayout>
A new method for measuring ice thickness was employed in the 2004-2005 season using the Aqua-Vu underwater viewing system, which allows us to see the exact point where the bottom of the ice cover is located. The Aqua-Vu underwater camera is lowered through a newly drilled (and usually at least partially melted) ice hole, and the camera lowered until the bottom of the ice cover is viewed through the above-water viewing system. The distance from the bottom of the ice cover to the piezometric water level (z-water) is marked on the viewing system cord and measured with a tape measure once the viewing system is brought out of the ice hole. The distance from the piezometric water level to the top of the ice cover (z-difference) is measured using a tape measure. If more than one replicate measurement is taken for z-water or z-difference, the replicates are averaged. Z-difference, or 'freebore,' provides some insight into the topographical features of the ice cover as well as density of the ice. The addition of z-water and z-difference gives the total ice thickness (z-ice). Ice thickness measurements are typically performed on each hole drilled through the ice cover. Because most limnological sampling holes are drilled in low-lying areas, it was thought that ice thickness measurements were biased. Therefore, random ice thickness measurements were performed in a 1000 m2 sampling grid on each lake in past years. However, statistical analyses by Dr. Priscu have shown that measurements from three ice holes are representative of the ice thickness measured by this grid system. Starting during the 2004-2005 season, ice thickness measurements were done on the two holes drilled for limnological sampling, plus one additional hole. In addition, notes were taken to describe the topography of the ice surrounding the ice hole (see comments section of data file). Generally ice thickness measurements are done on the two holes drilled for limnological sampling (1 hole inside the polarhaven, designated as "Inside Hole," and 1 hole outside) plus one additional outside hole. If there is an opportunity to take measurements in other holes that have been drilled, measurements are taken. Holes that are maintained open throughout the season are measured for ice thickness throughout the season. Note that ablation occurs around the sampling polarhaven, so take note of this when reviewing the Z-difference values for the "inside" holes throughout the season. Notes are taken to describe the topography of the ice surrounding the ice hole and are detailed in the comments section of the data file.
     </literalLayout></para>
    </description>
   </methodStep>
  </methods>
<dataTable>
   <entityName>ICETHICKNESS_Units_And_Column_Descriptions</entityName>
   <physical>
    <objectName>ICETHICKNESS_Units_And_Column_Descriptions</objectName>
    <dataFormat>
     <textFormat>
      <numHeaderLines>27</numHeaderLines>
      <numFooterLines>1</numFooterLines>
<recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
      <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
      <simpleDelimited>
       <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
       <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
      </simpleDelimited>
     </textFormat>
    </dataFormat>
<distribution>
<online>
<url function="download">http://www.mcmlter.org/queries/limno_results.jsp?begDate=01/01/0001&amp;endDate=01/01/3000&amp;dataType=ICE_THICKNESS</url>
</online>
</distribution>
   </physical>
   <attributeList>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>DATASET_CODE</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>Code that designates the name of the data table in the database</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
     <measurementScale>
      <nominal>
       <nonNumericDomain>
        <textDomain>
         <definition>code that identifies the name of the table in the database</definition>
        </textDomain>
       </nonNumericDomain>
      </nominal>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Required entry</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>Lake</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>Name of lake where measurement was made</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
     <measurementScale>
      <nominal>
       <nonNumericDomain>
        <textDomain>
         <definition>Name of lake where measurement was made</definition>
        </textDomain>
       </nonNumericDomain>
      </nominal>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Required entry</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>LOCATION NAME</attributeName>
     <attributeLabel>Location Name</attributeLabel>
     <attributeDefinition>Specifics of ice hole site upon lake. Locations designated by numbers are
      distances in meters, south and east,respectively, from the blue box</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
     <measurementScale>
      <nominal>
       <nonNumericDomain>
        <textDomain>
         <definition>Specifics of ice hole site upon lake. Locations designated by numbers are
          distances in meters, south and east,respectively, from the blue box</definition>
        </textDomain>
       </nonNumericDomain>
      </nominal>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Required entry</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>DATE_TIME</attributeName>
     <attributeLabel>Date Time</attributeLabel>
     <attributeDefinition>Date on which sample was gathered</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Date" />
     <measurementScale>
      <dateTime>
<formatString>mm/dd/yy</formatString>
</dateTime>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Required entry</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>Z-water (m)</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>Distance from piezometric water level to bottom of ice (negative value)</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
       </unit>
       <precision>0.01</precision>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">-10</minimum>
         <maximum exclusive="false">0</maximum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Required entry</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>Z-ice (m)</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>Distance from bottom of ice to top of ice (total ice thickness)</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
       </unit>
       <precision>0.01</precision>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
         <maximum exclusive="false">10</maximum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>Z-diff (m)</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>Distance from piezometric water level to top of ice (positive value)</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
       </unit>
       <precision>0.01</precision>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
         <maximum exclusive="false">5</maximum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>Density</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>Density of ice</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
       </unit>
       <precision>0.0001</precision>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
         <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName> Tool</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>Tool used to gather sample</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
     <measurementScale>
      <nominal>
       <nonNumericDomain>
        <textDomain>
         <definition>Tool used to gather sample</definition>
        </textDomain>
       </nonNumericDomain>
      </nominal>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName> Comments</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>Helpful hints about the ice thickness measurement</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
     <measurementScale>
      <nominal>
       <nonNumericDomain>
        <textDomain>
         <definition>Helpful hints about the ice thickness measurement</definition>
        </textDomain>
       </nonNumericDomain>
      </nominal>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>File Name</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>Name of file in which data was submitted</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
     <measurementScale>
      <nominal>
       <nonNumericDomain>
        <textDomain>
         <definition>Name of file in which data was submitted</definition>
        </textDomain>
       </nonNumericDomain>
      </nominal>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>LAT</attributeName>
     <attributeLabel>Latitude</attributeLabel>
     <attributeDefinition>Point Latitude of the whole where measurement was made</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
       <ratio>
       <unit>
        <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
       </unit>
       <precision>0.0001</precision>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
         <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>         
       </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>LON</attributeName>
     <attributeLabel>Longitude</attributeLabel>
     <attributeDefinition>Point Longitude of the whole where measurement was taken</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
       <ratio>
       <unit>
        <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
       </unit>
       <precision>0.0001</precision>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
         <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>         
       </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
   </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
</ns0:eml>