<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-mcm.4002.6" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
   <allow>
    <principal>uid=MCM,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
   </allow>
   <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
   </allow>
  </access>
<dataset>
<shortName>LTM</shortName>
<title>Algae Addition Long Term Manipulation Experiment</title>
<creator>
   <individualName>
    <givenName>Diana</givenName>
    <surName>Wall</surName>
   </individualName>
   <address>
   <deliveryPoint>NREL</deliveryPoint>
   <deliveryPoint>Colorado State University</deliveryPoint>
   <city>Fort Collins</city>
   <administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea>
   <postalCode>80523</postalCode>
   <country>USA</country>
  </address>
   <phone phonetype="voice">970-491-2504</phone>
   <electronicMailAddress>diana@nrel.colostate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
<creator>
   <individualName>
    <givenName>Ross</givenName>
    <surName>Virginia</surName>
   </individualName>
   <address>
   <deliveryPoint>Environmental Studies Program</deliveryPoint>
   <deliveryPoint>Dartmouth College</deliveryPoint>
   <city>Hanover</city>
   <administrativeArea>NH</administrativeArea>
   <postalCode>03755</postalCode>
   <country>USA</country>
  </address>
   <phone phonetype="voice">603-646-0192</phone>
   <electronicMailAddress>Ross.A.Virginia@Dartmouth.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
<metadataProvider>
<organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
  <address>
 <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Albuquerque</city>
   <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">505-277-3418</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">505-277-0304</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>mcmdata@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </metadataProvider>
<abstract>
   <section>
    <para>
     <literalLayout>A long-term soil manipulation experiment has been conducted 
	 as part of the McMurdo Dry Valleys Long Term Ecological Research (LTER) project. 
	 The response of soil organisms (nematodes, rotifers and tardigrades) to the 
	 treatments is monitored by sampling soil on an annual basis.</literalLayout>
    </para>
   </section>
  </abstract>
<keywordSet>
   <keyword keywordType="theme">soil organic C</keyword>
   <keyword keywordType="theme">nematodes</keyword>
   <keyword keywordType="theme">rotifers</keyword>
   <keyword keywordType="theme">tartigrades</keyword>
   <keyword keywordType="theme">McMurdo</keyword>
   <keyword keywordType="theme">Antarctica</keyword>
   <keyword keywordType="theme">LTER</keyword>
<keyword keywordType="place">McMurdo Dry Valleys</keyword>
<keyword keywordType="theme">MCM</keyword>
  </keywordSet>
<additionalInfo>
   <section>
    <title>Notes about the attribute table</title>
    <para>
     <literalLayout> Since the attribute table for this dataset is very large, the user must construct the actual column
      name.  The FIRST letter represents the species, and the following letters represent the life stage/sex/sum type.  The nermatode
      species codes are:
      
      S: Scottnema lindsayae 
      E: Eudorylaimus spp. 
      P: Plectus spp.  
      
      For example, in the attribute table,  "(code)ML" has the description "The total number of living male (species) adult nematodes extracted
      from the soil sample in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent. In this case, a column name 
      called "SML" would be  "The total number of living male Scottnema lindsayae adult nematodes..."</literalLayout>
    </para>
   </section>
   <section>
    <title>Preserved Samples</title>
    <para>
     <literalLayout>Preserved samples are stored in the NREL Preserved Nematode Collection in
      room 226, College of Natural Resources, Colorado State University. Original data are stored 
      in Room A208, Natural and Environmental Sciences Building, Colorado State University.</literalLayout>
    </para>
   </section>
   <section>
    <title>Notes</title>
    <para>
     <literalLayout> Data contained in these files has been subjected to quality control standards
      imposed by the investigator. The user of this data should be aware that, while efforts have
      been taken to ensure that these data are of the highest quality, there is no guarantee of
      perfection for the data contained herein and the possibility of errors exists. If you
      encounter questionable data, please contact the MCM LTER data manager corrected or qualified.
      Thus, these data may be modified and future data will be appended.</literalLayout>
    </para>
   </section>
  </additionalInfo>
<intellectualRights>
   <section>
    <title>MCM LTER data may be used freely with the following restrictions:</title>
    <para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literalLayout>The Principal Investigator be sent a notice stating reasons for acquiring any
         data and a description of the publication intentions. </literalLayout>
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literalLayout>The Principal Investigator of the data set be sent a copy of the report or
         manuscript prior to submission and be adequately cited in any resultant
        publications.</literalLayout>
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literalLayout>A copy of any resultant publications should be sent to the McMurdo data
         manager and principal investigator.</literalLayout>
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literalLayout>The end-user follow the guidelines set forth in the LTER Network Data Access
         Policy, Data Access Requirements, and General Data Use Agreement found at
         http://www.mcmlter.org/data_guidelines.htm</literalLayout>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </para>
   </section>
  </intellectualRights>
<coverage>
   <geographicCoverage>
    <geographicDescription>Study site is on the south side of Lake Hoare, Taylor Valley, Antarctica (77deg38'02" S, 162deg52'23" E).  </geographicDescription>
    <boundingCoordinates>
     <westBoundingCoordinate>162.87305556</westBoundingCoordinate>
     <eastBoundingCoordinate>162.87305556</eastBoundingCoordinate>
     <northBoundingCoordinate>-77.63388889</northBoundingCoordinate>
     <southBoundingCoordinate>-77.63388889</southBoundingCoordinate>
     <boundingAltitudes>
      <altitudeMinimum>0</altitudeMinimum>
      <altitudeMaximum>1000</altitudeMaximum>
      <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
     </boundingAltitudes>
    </boundingCoordinates>
   </geographicCoverage>
   <temporalCoverage>
    <rangeOfDates>
     <beginDate>
      <calendarDate>1994</calendarDate>
     </beginDate>
     <endDate>
      <calendarDate>2008</calendarDate>
     </endDate>
    </rangeOfDates>
   </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
<maintenance>
   <description> 
   <section>
     <para>
      <literalLayout>This file contains archived data pulled from Nemadisk and the field season directories by Jeb Barrett. 
       The data page contains the raw data for nematode abundance in # of animals per kg oven dry weight equivalent. </literalLayout>
     </para>
    </section>
     <section>
      <para>
       <literalLayout>The time-zero samples were taken on 26 December 1994 at the algae experiment on the South side of 
        Lake Hoare. The only organisms that were found in these samples, were nematodes (Scottnema). [EPB, 8 April 1997].</literalLayout>
      </para>
     </section>
   </description>
  </maintenance>
<contact>
<organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
  <address>
 <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Albuquerque</city>
   <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">505-277-3418</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">505-277-0304</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>mcmdata@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
<publisher>
<organizationName>McMurdo Dry Valleys LTER</organizationName>
  <address>
 <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Albuquerque</city>
   <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">505-277-3418</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">505-277-0304</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>mcmdata@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </publisher>
<methods>
   <methodStep>
    <description>
     <para>
      <literalLayout>The experimental design is a randomized block, with 8 replicates per treatment. Within each block are 2 plots measuring approximately 1m x 1m, with a central circular area of 85 cm diameter (approx. 0.57 m2) used for treatments and sampling. The treatments are as follows:
       (C) control plots (no manipulations),
       (A) algae amendment (25 g per plot per year, one application).
       The algae was previously collected from Lake Hoare, dried, lypholized and finely ground.
       
       Soil samples were taken for organism enumeration and moisture content analysis as follows: Sampling bags were prepared with one sterile 'Whirlpak' bag and clean plastic scoop per sample. Samples were taken from within the 85 cm diameter circular area of each plot. The location of the sampling was recorded each year so that areas were not re-sampled. Using the plastic scoop, soil was collected to 10 cm depth. Very large rocks (&gt;20 mm diameter) were excluded from the sample. The soil was shoveled into the 'Whirlpak' bag until three quarters full (about 1.5 kg soil). The soil was mixed well in the bag, then the bag was closed tightly, expelling as much air as possible. The soil samples were stored in a cooler for transportation.
       
       On return to the laboratory (within 8 hours of sampling), the soils were stored at +5C until further processing. In the laboratory, soil samples were handled in a laminar flow hood to prevent contamination. The Whirlpak bags of soil were mixed thoroughly prior to opening. A sub-sample of approximately 50g was removed and placed in a pre-weighed aluminum soil can, and weighed on a balance accurate to 0.01g. This sample was dried at 105C for 24 hours. The sample was removed, placed in a desiccator to cool down, and re-weighed. These data were used to calculate water content of the soil.
       
       The remaining soil in the plastic beaker was weighed. Cold tap water was added up to 650 mL. The soil suspension was stirred carefully (star stir or figure of 8) for 30 seconds, using a spatula. Immediately the liquid was poured into wet screens - a stack of 40 mesh on top of a 400 mesh. The screens were rinsed gently with ice cold tap water (from a wash bottle) through the top of the stack, keeping the screens at an angle as the water filtered through. The water was kept on ice at all times. The top screen was removed, and the lower screen rinsed top down, never directly on top of the soil, but at the top of the screen and from behind. The wate r was allowed to cascade down and carry the particles into the bottom wedge of the angled screen. The side of the screen was tapped gently to filter all the water through. The suspension was rinsed from the front and the back, keeping the screen at an angle and not allowing the water to overflow the edge of the screen. The soil particles were backwashed into a 50mL plastic centrifuge tube, tipping the screen into the funnel above the tube and rinsing the funnel gently. The suspension was centrifuged for five minutes at 1744 RPM. The liquid was decanted, leaving a few mL on top of the soil particles. The tube was filled with sucrose solution (454g sucrose per liter of tap water, kept refrigerated) up to 45mL. This was stirred gently with a spatula until the pellet was broken up and suspended. The suspension was centrifuged for one minute at 1744 RPM, decanted into a wet 500 mesh screen, rinsed well with ice cold tap water and backwashed into a centrifuge tube. Samples were refrigerated at 5C until counted.
       
       Samples were washed in to a counting dish and examined under a microscope at x10 or x20 magnification. Rotifers and tardigrades were identified and counted. Nematodes were identified to species and sex, and counted. Total numbers in each sample were recorded on data sheets. All species of nematode, and all rotifers and tardigrades found in the sample were recorded. Data were entered in to Excel files, printed, and checked for errors.
       
       Extraction of chlorophyll from the soil. All procedures were carried out in the dark or very low irradiance to avoid degradation of the chlorophyll. The soil samples were mixed thoroughly in the vials, and a sample of approximately 5 g was weighed out in to a 50 mL plastic centrifuge tube with a screw-top cap. 10 mL of a 50:50 DMSO/90% acetone solution was added to each sample and they were mixed thoroughly on a bench-top Vortex mixer for about 5 seconds. The vials were placed in a -4C constant temperature room, in the dark, and left for 12-18 hours.
       Determination of chlorophyll a concentration. This was determined fluorometrically using a Turner model 111 fluorometer. A calibration using a known concentration of chlorophyll was carried out prior to sample analysis. The machine was blanked using a 50:50 DMSO/90% acetone solution. Each vial was mixed thoroughly, then centrifuged for 5 minutes at about 1800 RPM. A sample of approximately 4mL of the DMSO/acetone solution was taken from the top of the sample with a pipette, being careful not to get any soil particles in the solution. The sample was placed in a cuvette, in to the fluorometer and the fluorescence was recorded. This was done fairly quickly in order to prevent light from breaking down the chlorophyll. This measurement is called Fo, the initial fluorescence. After taking this reading, 0.1 mL of 1N HCl was added directly to the cuvette and the cuvette was gently agitated. After 20 seconds, the fluorescence was re-measured.
       (During this step, the acid converts the chlorophyll to phaeophytin by releasing a magnesium ion in an acidic environment). This measurement is called Fa, the fluorescence after acidification. The solution was discarded in to a waste container, and the cuvette rinsed 3 times with DMSO/90% acetone solution before proceeding with the next sample. Data were entered in to Excel files, printed, and checked for errors.
       For measurements of pH, 40 of DI water was added to 20g of soil in a clean, DI- rinsed glass beaker (coarse fragments &gt;2 mm were removed). The samples were stirred until thoroughly mixed (about 5-10 sec). After sitting to equilibrate for 10 minutes the samples were stirred again and a reading was taken with a Beckman 0265 pH meter. For measurements of electrical conductivity, an additional 60 ml of DI water was then added (totaling 100 ml water). The samples were stirred until thoroughly mixed (about 5-10 sec). After sitting to equilibrate for 10 minutes the samples were stirred again and a reading was taken with a YSI 30 conductivity meter.
      </literalLayout>
     </para>
    </description>
   </methodStep>
  </methods>
<dataTable>
   <entityName>Units_and_Column_Descriptions</entityName>
   <physical>
    <objectName>Units_and_Column_Descriptions</objectName>
    <dataFormat>
     <textFormat>
      <numHeaderLines>27</numHeaderLines>
      <numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
<recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
      <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
      <simpleDelimited>
       <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
       <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
      </simpleDelimited>
     </textFormat>
    </dataFormat>
<distribution>
<online>
<url function="download">http://mcmlter.org/queries/soils/soils_core.jsp?dataset=LTM_ALGAE&amp;begDate=10/01/1994&amp;endDate=04/01/2009</url>
</online>
</distribution>
   </physical>
   <attributeList>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>DATASET_CODE</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>Unique identifier for the table in the MCM LTER database</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
     <measurementScale>
      <nominal>
       <nonNumericDomain>
        <textDomain>
         <definition>Unique identifier for the table in the MCM LTER database</definition>
        </textDomain>
       </nonNumericDomain>
      </nominal>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Required entry</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>SAMPLE_ID</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The block and treatment combination of the sample.</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
     <measurementScale>
      <nominal>
       <nonNumericDomain>
        <textDomain>
         <definition>The block and treatment combination of the sample.</definition>
        </textDomain>
       </nonNumericDomain>
      </nominal>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Required entry</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>Plot</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The plot number that the soil sample was collected from.</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
     <measurementScale>
      <nominal>
       <nonNumericDomain>
        <textDomain>
         <definition>The plot number that the soil sample was collected from.</definition>
        </textDomain>
       </nonNumericDomain>
      </nominal>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Required entry</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>Treatment</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The manipulation for a give plot from where the soil was collected. The treatments are: A: + algae, C: control</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
     <measurementScale>
      <nominal>
       <nonNumericDomain>
        <textDomain>
         <definition>The manipulation for a give plot from where the soil was collected. The treatments are: A: + algae, C: control</definition>
        </textDomain>
       </nonNumericDomain>
      </nominal>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Required entry</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>DATE_TIME</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The date the soil sample was collected from the field</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Date" />
     <measurementScale>
      <dateTime>
<formatString>mm/dd/yyyy</formatString>
</dateTime>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Required entry</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>Soil water content</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The gravimetric soil water content </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit>percent g/g</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
         <maximum exclusive="false">100</maximum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>Chlorophyll a (ug chl-a/g soil)</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The chlorophyll a content of the sample expressed per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit>ug chl-a/g soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>(code)ML</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The total number of living male (species) adult nematodes extracted from the soil sample in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>(code)MD</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The total number of dead male (species) adult nematodes extracted from the soil sample in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>(code)FL</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The total number of living female (species) adult nematodes extracted from the soil sample in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>(code)FD</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The total number of dead female (species) adult nematodes extracted from the soil sample in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>(code)JL</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The total number of living juvenile (species) adult nematodes extracted from the soil sample in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>(code)JD</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The total number of dead juvenile (species) adult nematodes extracted from the soil sample in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>(code)A</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The total number of living and dead (species) adult nematodes  extracted from the soil sample in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>(code)J</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The total number of living and dead (species) juvenile nematodes extracted from the soil sample in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>(code)TL</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>total number of living (species) (juvenile and adults) nematodes extracted from the soil sample in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>(code)TD</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The total number of dead (species) (juvenile and adults) nematodes extracted from the soil sample in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>(code)TLD</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The total number of live + dead (species) (juvenile and adults) nematodes extracted from the soil sample in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>total rotifers</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>total number of rotifers per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent present in a sample </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>total tardigrades</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>total number of tardigrades per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent present in a sample </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>unclassified (nematode species)</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The total number of nematodes from the respective genera (Scottnema, Eudorylaimus, Plectus and unknown) for which sex and life stage was not determined.</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>unknown</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>Unkown nematode species</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>total_live</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The total number of living nematodes extracted from the soil sample in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>total_dead</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The total number of dead nematodes extracted from the soil sample in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent  </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>total_unclassified</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The total number of nematodes extracted from the soil sample for which sex and life stage and/or species was not determined in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>total</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The total number of living and dead nematodes extracted from the soil sample in number of organisms per kg soil oven dry weight equivalent </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit># kg/soil</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>COMMENTS</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>Generic comments about the sample</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Text" />
     <measurementScale>
      <nominal>
       <nonNumericDomain>
        <textDomain>
         <definition>Generic comments about the sample</definition>
        </textDomain>
       </nonNumericDomain>
      </nominal>
     </measurementScale>
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>pH</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The opposite log of the hydrogen ion concentration of a 1:2 soil-water paste</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit>pH</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
        <bounds>
         <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </bounds>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute> 
    <attribute>
     <attributeName>CONDUCTIVITY</attributeName>
     <attributeDefinition>The electrical conductivity in microSiemens/cm of a 1:5 soil:deionized water solution. </attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="Number" />
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <customUnit>microSiemens/cm</customUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
     <missingValueCode>
      <code>Null</code>
      <codeExplanation>None given</codeExplanation>
     </missingValueCode>
    </attribute>
   </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
<metadata>
<unitList>
   <unit id="percent g/g" />
   <unit id="ug chl-a/g soil" />
   <unit id="# kg/soil" />
   <unit id="microSiemens/cm" />
   <unit id="pH" />
  </unitList>
</metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>