<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-cwt.1099.4" scope="system" system="cwt-lter" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 http://gce-lter.marsci.uga.edu/lter/files/schemas/eml-201/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Development of Bloodroot (Sanguinaria canadensis) as an Identity-Preserved Phyto-Pharmaceutical Crop for Western North Carolina.</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>David A.</givenName><surName>Danehower</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>North Carolina State University</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Department of Crop Science</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Box 7620</deliveryPoint><city>Raleigh</city><administrativeArea>North Carolina</administrativeArea><postalCode>27695</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">919.515.3567</phone><electronicMailAddress>david_danehower@ncsu.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://coweeta.ecology.uga.edu</onlineUrl></creator><abstract><para>The mountains of western North Carolina are one of the most botanically diverse regions in the world. Many  plants native to the region are recognized to have significant medicinal properties. Recent growth in the medicinal plants industry provides an opportunity for western NC to utilize its unique biodiversity and environment to develop alternative agricultural and industrial enterprises for its citizens. The key to a successful and sustainable medicinal herb industry is the development of &#65533;identity-preserved&#65533; domesticated medicinal plant varieties and systems for their propagation and agronomic production. Identity-preservation is a system of agricultural and industrial supply and production that ensures a controlled source of high quality plant products containing reproducible active ingredient level. Such a system will be critical to the development of successful markets. This proposal focuses on the identification of native plant resources, genetic, phyto-chemical, and agronomic evaluation of those resources, and subsequent development of systems for their propagation and agronomic production. Initial studies will focus on bloodroot (Sanguinaria canadensis), a native plant with recognized market demand. Bloodroot germplasm will be collected from the wild within the Natahala, Pisgah, and Cherokee National Forests of western NC and additional sites along the spine of the Appalachian Mountains. The collected materials will be transferred to an &#65533;ex situ&#65533; accession collection for genetic &#65533;fingerprinting&#65533; using AFLP analysis. Collected accessions will also be evaluated for alkaloids and agronomically desirable traits including yield and pest resistance. High yielding accessions selected will be used for development of identity-preserved varieties, seed and rhizome-based propagation methods, and small and medium scale agronomic production systems. Additional experiments will be focused on development of seed and rhizome-based propagation and agronomic production systems for bloodroot. Working relationships will be developed between researchers and possible grower groups as well as those companies currently purchasing bloodroot. The ultimate goal of the project is to bring the results of our research to growers and purchasers in order to create a new niche crop for small farmers in western NC.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Coweeta</keyword><keyword>LTER</keyword><keyword>bloodroot</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>Must adhere to the Coweeta LTER Data Policy (See http://coweeta.uga.edu/policies/data).</para></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://coweeta.uga.edu/summaries/Csummary1099_b.html</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>We have currently identified two sites within the Coweeta Hydrologic Station that contain bloodroot. Both sites are along Ball Creek Rd at 2.5 and 3.9mi from the USFS gate. These sites are designated as DAD 79 and DAD79A.

					DAD79 - 35.02.294N 83.27.146W DAD79A - 35.01.976N 83.27.080W Accuracy of these readings is within 20 ft of actual site.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate /><eastBoundingCoordinate /><northBoundingCoordinate /><southBoundingCoordinate /></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2004-08-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2007-12-01</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><positionName>Coweeta LTER Information Manager</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(828) 524-2128</phone></contact><project scope="document"><title>Coweeta Long Term Ecological Research</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Ted</givenName><surName>Gragson</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>tgragson@earthlink.net</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>James</givenName><surName>Vose</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>jvose@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Brian</givenName><surName>Kloeppel</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>kloeppel@uga.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><abstract><para>The Coweeta LTER Research Program has evolved since 1980 from a site-based to a site- and region-based project examining the effects of disturbance

and environmental gradients on biogeochemical cycling, and the underlying

watershed ecosystem processes that regulate and respond to those cycles. 

The objective for the 2002-2008 research is to advance scientific

understanding of the spatial, temporal, and decision-making components of

land use and land-use change in the southern Appalachian Mountains over the

last 200 years, and forecast patterns into the future 30 years.  This will

be accomplished by addressing ecological and socioeconomic aspects of

land-use change while continuing long-term studies of environmental

gradients and natural disturbance regimes.  The result will be a more

complete understanding of ecological dynamics in the southern Appalachian

Mountains that makes possible the development of reasonable forecasts of

its future ecological state. | The guiding hypothesis for the proposed research is that the frequency, intensity, and extent of land use represents human decision-making in

response to socioeconomic and bio-geophysical conditions with consequences

that cascade through ecosystems.  The research activities are organized

into three initiatives: (1) Characterization of the Socio-Natural Template,

(2) Ecosystem Responses to the Socio-Natural Template, and (3) Forecasting

Ecosystem Responses to Changes in the Socio-Natural Template.  The

integrated scientific research will provide both a description as well as

an explanation of the underlying causes of land use and the consequences of

land-use change for southern Appalachian ecosystems and society.  It thus

recognizes the complexity of land use as a process and the research needs

as defined in the LTER Program and the broader scientific community.</para></abstract><funding><para>National Science Foundation. Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed in the material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.</para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=cwt,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access></dataset></ns0:eml>