<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-luq.138.3" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 C:/eml-2.0.1/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><shortName>LUQMetadata138</shortName><title>Conservation and management of migratory fauna and dams in tropical streams of Puerto Rico</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Effie A.</givenName><surName>Greathouse</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of Georgia</organizationName><positionName>Graduate Student</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>GA</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">916-332-5771</phone><phone phonetype="fax">facsimile</phone><electronicMailAddress>effieg@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress></creator><metadataProvider scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Effie A.</givenName><surName>Greathouse</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of Georgia</organizationName><positionName>Graduate Student</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>GA</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">916-332-5771</phone><phone phonetype="fax">facsimile</phone><electronicMailAddress>effieg@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress></metadataProvider><language>english</language><abstract><para><literalLayout>1. Compared to most other tropical regions, Puerto Rico appears to have dammed its running waters decades earlier and to a greater degree. The island has more large dams per unit area than many countries in both tropical and temperate regions (e.g., 3x that of the U.S.), and the peak rate of large dam construction occurred two and three decades prior to reported peak rates in Latin America, Asia and Africa.
2. Puerto Rico is a potential window into the future of freshwater migratory fauna in tropical regions, given the island's extent and magnitude of dam development and the available scientific information on ecology and management of the island's migratory fauna.
3. We review ecology, management and conservation of migratory fauna in relation to dams in Puerto Rico. Our review includes a synthesis of recent and unpublished observations on upstream effects of large dams on migratory fauna and an analysis of patterns in free crest spillway discharge across Puerto Rican reservoirs. Analyses suggest that large dams with rare spillway discharge cause near, not complete, extirpation of upstream populations of migratory fauna. They also suggest several management and conservation issues in need of further research and consideration. These include research on the costs, benefits and effectiveness of simple fish/shrimp passage designs involving simulating spillway discharge and the appropriateness of establishing predatory fishes in reservoirs of historically fishless drainages.</literalLayout></para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>migratory fauna</keyword><keyword>freshwater shrimps</keyword><keyword>dams</keyword><keyword>experimental scale</keyword><keyword>diadromy</keyword><keywordThesaurus>Assigned by Principal Investigator</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>population dynamics</keyword><keyword>disturbance patterns</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LTER Core</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>headwater stream</keyword><keyword>insects</keyword><keyword>water abstraction</keyword><keyword>other plots</keyword><keyword>decapods</keyword><keyword>peer reviewed journal</keyword><keyword>river</keyword><keyword>fish</keyword><keyword>dissertation</keyword><keyword>algae</keyword><keyword>aquatic</keyword><keyword>disturbance</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LEF LTER Data Sets</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>LUQ</keyword><keyword>Luquillo</keyword><keyword>Disturbance</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LEF LTER Data Categories</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><intellectualRights><section><title>ADEQUATE ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><para><literalLayout>The scientists, the LEF-LTER Program, and the USDA International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITF) must receive adequate acknowledgement for the use of data by other scientists, and the LEF LTER program must receive two copies of any publication using that data. One copy will be placed at the IITF library and one copy will stay with the LEF LTER Data Manager. A suggested format for this acknowledgement will be distributed along with the requested data.</literalLayout></para><section><title>Acknowledgements for NSF Support.</title><para><literalLayout>The following paragraph should be included in the acknowledgements of all publications funded in any way by current and future LTER grants:</literalLayout><literalLayout>This research was performed under grant #DEB-0218039 from the National Science Foundation to the Institute of Tropical Ecosystem Studies (IEET), University of Puerto Rico, and the International Institute of Tropical Forestry (IITFR) as part of the Long-Term Ecological Research Program in the Luquillo Experimental Forest. Additional support was provided by the Forest Service (U.S. Department of Agriculture) and the University of Puerto Rico.</literalLayout></para></section></section></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb138/metadata/lterdb138.htm#DATA</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage id="geoReference" scope="document"><geographicDescription>The Luquillo Experimental Forest (LEF) covers 11,231 hectares and reaches 1079 m above sea level. It has a warm and wet climate and includes a variety of tropical habitats and forest types and streams, and a high diversity of plants and animals. A key feature of these ecosystems is disturbance. Hurricanes, landslides, and human disturbance have shaped the forest, and research by LUQ has stimulated a new appreciation of the significance of large-scale disturbances in tropical forested ecosystems and the key role of plants and animals in shaping the response to these events. Hurricanes occurring one and 10 years after LUQ began in 1988 provided landscape-scale natural experiments which are still followed closely.</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-65.92</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-65.7</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>18.35</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>18.23</southBoundingCoordinate><boundingAltitudes><altitudeMinimum>20</altitudeMinimum><altitudeMaximum>1060</altitudeMaximum><altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits></boundingAltitudes></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Effie A.</givenName><surName>Greathouse</surName></individualName><organizationName>University of Georgia</organizationName><positionName>Graduate Student</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>GA</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">916-332-5771</phone><phone phonetype="fax">facsimile</phone><electronicMailAddress>effieg@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress></contact><publisher scope="document"><organizationName>Luquillo Experimental Forest LTER</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>University of Puerto Rico, Rio Piedras</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>P. O. Box 21910</deliveryPoint><city>San Juan</city><administrativeArea>PR</administrativeArea><postalCode>00931-1910</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(787) 764 - 0000 (ext. 4940)</phone><phone phonetype="fax">(787) 772 -1481</phone><electronicMailAddress>nbrokaw@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://luq.lternet.edu</onlineUrl></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Spillway discharge analysis: For each large dam downstream from our high-gradient, high-elevation sampling sites from Greathouse et al. (in press) (dams were: Dos Bocas, Caonillas, Matrullas, Carite, Toa Vaca, Luchetti, Garzas), we obtained the entire USGS daily-lake-elevation record prior to the last date of our field research on 30 June 2003 (records ranged from 4-15 years long). For other dams, we analyzed water years 1999 and 2000 (for dams: Guayabal, Patillas, Guajataca, Cidra, Loco, Lo&#237;za, Guayo, La Plata, Cerrillos) or records from recently-installed lake elevation gages (installations in November 2004: Comerio; installations in February 2005: Coamo, Adjuntas, V&#237;v&#237;, Prieto, Yahuecas). For each record, we then determined the percentage of days with spillway discharge (100 times the number of days with lake elevations exceeding the spillway crest elevation divided by the total number of days for which a lake elevation was reported). Previously unpublished observations of native shrimps and fishes occurring upstream from large dams were made by various methods ranging from simple visual observation to non-quantitative sampling to quantitative sampling by electroshocking. Descriptions of the methods, when available, are included in the data set file (aquaticconservation.txt).</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep></methods><project scope="document"><title>Ecological studies of dams and migratory fauna, Puerto Rico</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Effie A.</givenName><surName>Greathouse</surName></individualName><role>Associate</role></personnel><abstract><para><literalLayout>The ecological roles of diadromous fauna (freshwater shrimps, fishes, and snails) in Puerto Rico were studied in the context of examining consequences of their loss from streams above large (height &gt;15 m) dams. Four sub-projects were conducted:
(a) Indirect upstream effects of dams: consequences of migratory consumer extirpation in Puerto Rico. This sub-project examined the effects of decimation of migratory fauna populations on stream ecosystem structure above large dams. We compared streams above large dams to streams without large dams, in terms of relative abundances of migratory fauna and ecosystem components affected by migratory fauna in previous in situ experiments. Previous research indicated that: (1) all native fishes and shrimps in Puerto Rico are extirpated from habitats upstream of large dams without regular spillway discharge because they are diadromous, whereas streams above large dams with regular spillway discharge have greatly reduced abundances of diadromous fauna, and streams without large dams have relatively natural fish and shrimp assemblages (Holmquist et al. 1998); and (2) small-scale experimental exclusion of native shrimps and fishes decreases leaf decay rates and increases epilithic organic and inorganic matter, chlorophyll a, carbon, nitrogen, carbon-to-nitrogen ratio (C:N), and chironomid biomass (Pringle et al. 1999, Crowl et al. 2001, March et al. 2001, March et al. 2002). We examined whether sites above large dams had higher levels of epilithic coarse organic matter, algae, fine organic and inorganic matter, carbon, nitrogen, C:N, and non-decapod invertebrates, consistent with previous findings of small-scale experimental shrimp and fish exclusions.
(b) Do small-scale exclosure/enclosure experiments have relevance for large-scale extirpation of migratory fauna? This sub-project took advantage of large dams to examine effects of experimental scale. Alteration of migratory stream populations due to large dams represents a large-scale (i.e. whole-catchment), long-term (i.e. decades) "extirpation experiment." We compared this large-scale perturbation to four small-scale experiments (two exclusion experiments in sites with no large dams and two shrimp addition experiments in dammed sites) that we conducted in a subset of the sites sampled in sub-project (a). We examined whether small-scale experiments predicted effects at the large-scale in terms of direction and magnitude.
(c) Conservation and management of migratory fauna and dams in tropical streams of Puerto Rico. This sub-project was a review, in which we: (1) examined Puerto Rico's potential to serve as a window into the future of freshwater migratory fauna in tropical regions, given the island's extent and magnitude of dam development and the available scientific information on ecology and management of the island's migratory fauna, and (2) reviewed ecology, management and conservation of migratory fauna in relation to dams in Puerto Rico. Our review included a synthesis of recent and unpublished observations on upstream effects of large dams on migratory fauna and an analysis of patterns in free crest spillway discharge across Puerto Rican reservoirs.
(d) Ecological effects of non-migratory native and non-native fauna above large dams in tropical streams, Puerto Rico. This sub-project consisted of a set of electric exclusion experiments conducted above two of the dammed sites in sub-project a. Previous research demonstrated higher abundances of exotic fishes above large dams (Holmquist et al. 1998). Thus, these experiments examined whether exotic fishes affect stream ecosystem patterns and confound any interpretations in sub-project a regarding roles of migratory macroconsumers.</literalLayout></para></abstract></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=LUQ,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable scope="document"><entityName>aquaticconservation.txt</entityName><entityDescription>Supplemental information on an analysis of spillway crest discharge and detailed unpublished observations of native migratory fauna occurring upstream from large dams across Puerto Rico</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>aquaticconservation.txt</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter><physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://luq.lternet.edu/data/lterdb138/data/aquaticconservation.txt</url></online></distribution></physical><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage></coverage><method><methodStep><description><para><literalLayout>Spillway discharge analysis: For each large dam downstream from our high-gradient, high-elevation sampling sites from Greathouse et al. (in press) (dams were: Dos Bocas, Caonillas, Matrullas, Carite, Toa Vaca, Luchetti, Garzas), we obtained the entire USGS daily-lake-elevation record prior to the last date of our field research on 30 June 2003 (records ranged from 4-15 years long). For other dams, we analyzed water years 1999 and 2000 (for dams: Guayabal, Patillas, Guajataca, Cidra, Loco, Lo&#237;za, Guayo, La Plata, Cerrillos) or records from recently-installed lake elevation gages (installations in November 2004: Comerio; installations in February 2005: Coamo, Adjuntas, V&#237;v&#237;, Prieto, Yahuecas). For each record, we then determined the percentage of days with spillway discharge (100 times the number of days with lake elevations exceeding the spillway crest elevation divided by the total number of days for which a lake elevation was reported). Previously unpublished observations of native shrimps and fishes occurring upstream from large dams were made by various methods ranging from simple visual observation to non-quantitative sampling to quantitative sampling by electroshocking. Descriptions of the methods, when available, are included in the data set file (aquaticconservation.txt).</literalLayout></para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><references>geoReference</references></geographicCoverage></coverage></studyExtent><samplingDescription><section><para><literalLayout>once</literalLayout></para></section></samplingDescription></sampling></method><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Dam name</attributeName><attributeLabel>Dam</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The name of the large dam</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>The name of the large dam</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>none</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Spillway crest elevation</attributeName><attributeLabel>Elevation</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The elevation of the crest of the dam's free crest spillway (if the dam has a free crest spillway instead of a morning glory spillway)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>meter</standardUnit></unit><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>USGS gage number</attributeName><attributeLabel>Gage #</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>The last 6 digits of the United States Geological Survey lake elevation gage used in the spillway discharge analysis.  The first two digits for all gages are 50.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>The last 6 digits of the United States Geological Survey lake elevation gage used in the spillway discharge analysis.  The first two digits for all gages are 50.</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>Descriptions of observations of migratory fauna</attributeName><attributeLabel>Observations</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Detailed descriptions of previously unpublished observations of native migratory shrimps and fishes occurring upstream from large dams across Puerto Rico.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Detailed descriptions of previously unpublished observations of native migratory shrimps and fishes occurring upstream from large dams across Puerto Rico.</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>non</code><codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset></ns0:eml>