<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.253.170195" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Biome Transition Along Elevational Gradients  in New Mexico (SEON) Study: Flux Tower Net Primary Productivity (NPP) Quadrat Study at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Marcy</givenName>
      <surName>Litvak</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>mlitvak@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">14590</userId>
  </creator>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Marcy</givenName>
      <surName>Litvak</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>mlitvak@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">14590</userId>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>The varied topography and large elevation gradients that characterize the arid and semi-arid Southwest create a wide range of climatic conditions - and associated biomes - within relatively short distances. This creates an ideal experimental system in which to study the effects of climate on ecosystems. Such studies are critical givien that the Southwestern U.S. has already experienced changes in climate that have altered precipitation patterns (Mote et al. 2005), and stands to experience dramatic climate change in the coming decades (Seager et al. 2007; Ting et al. 2007). Climate models currently predict an imminent transition to a warmer, more arid climate in the Southwest (Seager et al. 2007; Ting et al. 2007). Thus, high elevation ecosystems, which currently experience relatively cool and mesic climates, will likely resemble their lower elevation counterparts, which experience a hotter and drier climate. In order to predict regional changes in carbon storage, hydrologic partitioning and water resources in response to these potential shifts, it is critical to understand how both temperature and soil moisture affect processes such as evaportranspiration (ET), total carbon uptake through gross primary production (GPP), ecosystem respiration (Reco), and net ecosystem exchange of carbon, water and energy across elevational gradients.We are using a sequence of six widespread biomes along an elevational gradient in New Mexico -- ranging from hot, arid ecosystems at low elevations to cool, mesic ecosystems at high elevation to test specific hypotheses related to how climatic controls over ecosystem processes change across this gradient. We have an eddy covariance tower and associated meteorological instruments in each biome which we are using to directly measure the exchange of carbon, water and energy between the ecosystem and the atmosphere. This gradient offers us a unique opportunity to test the interactive effects of temperature and soil moisture on ecosystem processes, as temperature decreases and soil moisture increases markedly along the gradient and varies through time within sites.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>primary production</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>measurements</keyword>
    <keyword>climate</keyword>
    <keyword>elevation</keyword>
    <keyword>plants</keyword>
    <keyword>foliage</keyword>
    <keyword>grasses</keyword>
    <keyword>forbs</keyword>
    <keyword>vegetation</keyword>
    <keyword>stems</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/6336</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: Deep Well is located on McKenzie Flats and is site of the longest running SEV LTER met station, number 40, which has been active since 1988.&#160; In addition to studies of meteorological variables, core line-intercept vegetation transects and line-intercept transects from the 1995 and 2001 Deep Well fires are sampled here.&#160; The mini-rhizotron study, blue and black grama compositional comparison, blue and black grama patch dynamics investigation, and kangaroo rat population assessement are all ongoing here.&#160; Deep Well Blue/Black Grama Mixed is also the location of the warming and monsoon experiments, as well as portions of the line-intercept and vegetation removal studies.
On August 4, 2009, a lightning-initiated fire began on the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge. By August 5, 2009, the fire had reached the area of Deep Well Blue/Black Grama Mixed.&#160; While portions of this site were burned, the entirety was not.&#160; See individual projects for further information on the effects of the fire.Vegetation: The vegetation of Deep Well Blue/Black Grama Mixed is Chihuahuan Desert Grassland, dominated by black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda) and blue grama (B. gracilis).  Other grasses found at the site include dropseeds (Sporobolus spp.) and threeawns (Aristida spp.).  Shrubs are uncommon but those that occur include Yucca glauca, Ephedra torreyi, and four-wing saltbush (Atriplex canescens). Herbaceous plants include Plantago purshii, Hymenopappus filifolius, and globe mallows (Sphaeralcea spp.).

 , </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1600</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1600</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Five Points area emcompasses both the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote study sites.&#160; Five Points falls along the transition between the Chihuahuan Desert Scrub and Desert Grassland habitats.&#160; Both core sites are subject to intensive research activities, including NPP measurements, phenology observations, pollinator diversity studies, and ground dwelling arthropod and rodent population assessments.&#160; There are rain-out shelters for drought studies in both the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote sites.Vegetation: The Five Points Creosote site is characterized as Chihuahuan Desert Scrub, dominated by a creosote overstory, with broom snakeweed, purple pricklypear (Opuntia macrocentra), and soapweed yucca as co-occurring shrubs. The site is also characterized by numerous, dense, grass-dominated patches, reflecting proximity to the Five Points Black Grama Site.  Dominant grasses are black grama, fluffgrass (Dasyochloa pulchellum), burrograss (Scleropogon brevifolia), bushmuhly (Muhlenbergia porteri), and galleta (Pleuraphis jamesii).  Notable forbs include field bahia (Bahia absinthifolia), baby aster (Chaetopappa ericoides), plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala), Indian rushpea (Hoffmannseggia glauca), Fendlers bladderpod (Lesquerella fendleri), and globemallows (Sphaeralcea spp.)., siteid: 3</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <singleDateTime>
        <calendarDate>2012-01-06</calendarDate>
      </singleDateTime>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Sevilleta</givenName>
      <surName>Information Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Marcy</givenName>
      <surName>Litvak</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>mlitvak@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">14590</userId>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Above-Ground Net Primary Productivity (ANPP) measurements:Above-ground net primary production data is collected three times each year, winter, spring, and fall, for all burn sites. Spring measurements are taken in April or May when shrubs and spring annuals have reached peak biomass. Fall measurements are taken in either September or October when summer annuals have reached peak biomass but prior to killing frosts. Winter measurements are taken in February before the onset of spring growth and only creosote is measured.Vegetation data is collected on a palm top computer. A 1-m2 PVC-frame is placed over the fiberglass stakes that mark the diagonal corners of each quadrat. When measuring cover it is important to stay centered over the vegetation in the quadrat to prevent errors caused by angle of view (parallax). Each PVC-frame is divided into 100 squares with nylon string. The dimensions of each square are 10cm x 10cm and represent 1 percent of the total area.The cover (area) and height of each individual live (green) vegetative unit that falls within the one square meter quadrat is measured. A vegetative unit consists of an individual size class (as defined by a unique cover and height) of a particular species within a quadrat. Cover is quantified by counting the number of 10cm x 10cm squares filled by each vegetative unit. It is possible to obtain a total percent cover greater than 100% for a given quadrat because vegetative units for different species often overlap.Niners and plexidecs are additional tools that can help accurately determine the cover a vegetative unit. A niner is a small, hand-held PVC frame that can be used to measure canopies. Like the larger PVC frame it is divided into 10cm x 10cm squares, each square representing 1% of the total cover. However, there are only nine squares within the frame, hence the name &#8220;niner.&#8221; A plexidec can help determine the cover of vegetative units with covers less than 1%. Plexidecs are clear plastic squares that are held above vegetation. Each plexidec represents a cover of 0.5% and has smaller dimensions etched onto the surface that correspond to 0.01%, 0.05%, 0.1%, and 0.25% cover.It is extremely important that cover and height measurements remain consistent over time to ensure that regressions based on this data remain valid. Field crew members should calibrate with each other to ensure that observer bias does not influence data collectionCover Measurements:Grasses-To determine the cover of a grass clump, envision a perimeter around the central mass or densest portion of the plant, excluding individual long leaves, wispy ends, or more open upper regions of the plant. Live foliage is frequently mixed with dead foliage in grass clumps and this must be kept in mind during measurement as our goal is to measure only plant biomass for the current season. In general, recently dead foliage is yellow and dead foliage is gray. Within reason, try to include only yellow or green portions of the plant in cover measurement while excluding portions of the plant that are gray. This is particularly important for measurements made in the winter when there is little or no green foliage present. In winter, sometimes measurements will be based mainly on yellow foliage. Stoloniferous stems of grasses that are not rooted should be ignored. If a stem is rooted it should be recorded as a separate observation from the parent plant.Forbs-The cover of forbs is measured as the perimeter of the densest portion of the plant. If the forb is an annual it is acceptable to include the inflorescence in this measurement. If the forb is a perennial, do not include the inflorescence as part of the cover measurement. Measure all foliage that was produced during the current season, including any recently dead (yellow) foliage. Avoid measuring gray foliage that died in a previous season.Cacti-For cacti that consist of a series of pads or jointed stems (Opuntia phaecantha, Opuntia imbricata) measure the length and width of each pad to the nearest cm instead of cover and height. Cacti that occur as a dense ball/clump of stems (Opuntia leptocaulis) are measured using the same protocol as shrubs. Pincushion or hedgehog cacti (Escobaria vivipara, Schlerocactus intertextus, Echinocereus fendleri) that occur as single (or clustered) cylindrical stems are measured as a single cover.Yuccas-Make separate observations for the leaves and caudex (thick basal stem). Break the observations into sections of leaves that are approximately the same height and record the cover as the perimeter around this group of leaf blades. The caudex is measured as a single cover. The thick leaves of yuccas make it difficult to make a cover measurement by centering yourself over the caudex of the plant. The cover of the caudex may be estimated by holding a niner next to it or using a tape measure to measure to approximate the area.Height Measurements:Height is recorded as a whole number in centimeters. All heights are vertical heights but they are not necessarily perpendicular to the ground if the ground is sloping.Annual grasses and all forbs-Measure the height from the base of the plant to the top of the inflorescence (if present). Otherwise, measure to the top of the green foliage.Perennial grasses-Measure the height from the base of the plant to the top of the live green foliage. Do not include the inflorescence in the height measurement. The presence of live green foliage may be difficult to see in the winter. Check carefully at the base of the plant for the presence of green foliage. If none is found it may be necessary to pull the leaf sheaths off of several plants outside the quadrat. From this you may be able to make some observations about where green foliage is likely to occur.Perennial shrub and sub-shrubs-Measure the height from the base of the green foliage to the top of the green foliage, ignoring all bare stems. Do not measure to the ground unless the foliage reaches the ground. Plants rooted outside but hanging into a quadrat-Do not measure the height from the ground. Measure only the height of the portion of the plant that is within the quadrat.Recording the Data:Excel spreadsheets are used for data entry and file names should begin with the overall study (npp), followed by the date (mm.dd.yy) and the initials of the recorder (.abc). Finally, the site abbreviation should be added (i.e., c, g, b, p). The final format should be as follows: npp_flux.mm.dd.yy.abc.xls. File names should be in lowercase.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
  </methods>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>sev253_nppfluxquadrat_12092013.txt</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data for sev253, biome transition along elevational gradients NPP study. </entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>sev253_nppfluxquadrat_12092013.txt</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url>http://sev.lternet.edu/sites/default/files/data/sev-253/sev253_nppfluxquadrat_12092013.txt</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2011-05-04</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2013-10-24</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>year</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>year</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The year in which data was collected.  </attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>season</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>season</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The season in which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1 </code>
                  <definition> winter</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>2 </code>
                  <definition> spring</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3 </code>
                  <definition> fall</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>date</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>date</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The date on which data or a sample was collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>MM/DD/YY</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>site</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>site</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The site at which data was collected for sev 253, the Biome Transition Along Elevational Gradients in New Mexico Net Primary Productivity (NPP) Study.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>Burn03</code>
                  <definition>This site was burned in 2003 and is designated "control."</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>Burn09</code>
                  <definition>This site was burned in 2009 and is designated "burned."</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>treatment</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>treatment</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The treatment applied to a site.
</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>B </code>
                  <definition> burned </definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C </code>
                  <definition> control</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>quad</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>quad</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The quadrat at which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The quadrat at which data was collected.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>species</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>species</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The Kartez code for a plant species as designated by the USDA Plants Database. </attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The Kartez code for a plant species as designated by the USDA Plants Database. </definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>obs</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>obs</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The sequential number given to a specific vegetative unit within a quadrat.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The sequential number given to a specific vegetative unit within a quadrat.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>cover</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>cover</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The percent cover of an observation (or vegetative unit) for a given species.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0.01</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">100</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>height</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>height</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The height of an observation (or vegetative unit) for a given species.  For grasses, this is the average height of green foliage.  For herbs, it includes the inflorescence, if applicable.  </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>count</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>count</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The number of records within a vegetative unit for a given species.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The number of records within a vegetative unit for a given species.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>comments</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>comments</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>A special statement related to an observation.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>na </code>
                  <definition> not applicable</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit abbreviation="" id="percentage" name="percentage" unitType=""><ns2:description /></ns2:unit>

    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>