<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.255.36797" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Comparative Hydraulic Performance of Pi&#241;on and Juniper in a Rainfall Manipulation Experiment at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>William</givenName>
      <surName>Pockman</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, MSC03 2020, 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>pockman@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">12857</userId>
  </creator>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Patrick</givenName>
      <surName>Hudson</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>husdon.patrick.j@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <metadataProvider>
    <positionName>, </positionName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuqeurque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
  </metadataProvider>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para> From 2000-2003, extreme drought&#160; across the Southwestern US resulted in widespread tree mortality: pi&#241;on pine (Pinus edulis) experienced up to 95% mortality while juniper (Juniperus monosperma) mortality was 25% or less at surveyed sites.&#160; Field data have shown repeatedly that pi&#241;on typically exhibits isohydric regulation of leaf water potential, maintaining relatively constant leaf water potentials even as soil water potentials fluctuate, while juniper is anisohydric, allowing leaf water potential to decline during drought.&#160; The goal of this study was to elucidate functional consequences of these two contrasting hydraulic strategies.&#160; The study was conducted in the context of a rainfall manipulation experiment in pi&#241;on-juniper woodland at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge and LTER in central New Mexico, USA, sampling trees in irrigation (~150% ambient rainfall), drought (50% ambient), cover control (ambient rainfall with similar drought infrastructure) and ambient control plots.&#160; To quantify tissue and shoot level hydraulic performances we measured sapwood area-specific (KS, kg&#8226;m-1&#8226;s-1&#8226;MPa-1) and leaf area-specific (KL, g&#8226;m-1&#8226;s-1&#8226;MPa-1) hydraulic conductivity in similar sized distal branches, and we calculated AS:AL (sapwood area to leaf area ratio) to compare shoot level allocation. Samples collected at predawn and midday both exhibited significant trends between species and across treatments.&#160; Between species, juniper possessed significantly higher KS compared to pi&#241;on in all plots except irrigation, and higher KL than pi&#241;on in all plots.&#160; Across treatments, irrigated juniper exhibited higher KS and KL relative to ambient and droughted plants, while irrigated pi&#241;on exhibited higher KS relative to ambient, drought and cover control plants, and irrigated and ambient pi&#241;on had higher KL than droughted and cover control plants.&#160; Junipers did not modify AS:AL across treatments, while irrigated pi&#241;on had significantly lower AS:AL compared to all other plots.&#160; Thus, under current climatic conditions in the Sevilleta, pi&#241;on and juniper achieve similar shoot hydraulic performances, but through different strategies: juniper maximizes xylem conductivity, while pi&#241;on maximizes xylem supply to leaves.&#160; If climate change in the Southwest results in increased aridity, pi&#241;on could be vulnerable to extirpation from its current distribution in lower elevation PJ woodlands, as juniper demonstrates superior hydraulic capability at both the tissue and shoot level under drought conditions. &#160;</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>primary production</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>droughts</keyword>
    <keyword>measurements</keyword>
    <keyword>leaf area</keyword>
    <keyword>rain</keyword>
    <keyword>hydraulic conductance</keyword>
    <keyword>conductivity</keyword>
    <keyword>irrigation</keyword>
    <keyword>water</keyword>
    <keyword>leaves</keyword>
    <keyword>trees</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/6389</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Cerro Montosa Pinyon-Juniper site has been the location of major Sevilleta LTER research since 1989. Meteorological trends, net primary productivity, rodent and ground-dwelling arthropod populations, mycorrhizal responses to fertilizer, pinyon-juniper fruit and nut production, and pinyon mortality are all being investigated at this site. Previous studies have included analyses of pinyon tree rings for regional climate reconstruction.Vegetation: The vegetation is New Mexico Pinyon-Juniper Woodland, dominated by Colorado pinyon (Pinus edulis) and one-seed juniper (Juniperus monosperma), and accompanied by gray oak (Quercus grisea).  There is a diverse shrub component, including scrub live oak (Q. turbinella), mountain mahogany (Cercocarpus montanus), broom snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae), sacahuista (Nolina microcarpa), red barberry (Mahonia haematocarpa), Apache plume (Fallugia paradoxa), tree cholla (Opuntia imbricata), skunkbush (Rhus trilobata), and banana yucca (Yucca baccata).  Grass diversity is also high, and open spaces between trees are dominated by blue grama (Bouteloua gracilis), with hairy and sideoats grama (B. hirsuta and B. curtipendula) and black grama (B. eriopoda) also being significant. Other common grasses include purple threeawn (Aristida purpurea), wolftail (Lycurus phleoides), mountain and ring muhly (M. montanus and M. torreyi), and New Mexican porcupinegrass (Heterostipa neomexicana). Common forbs include small-flowered milkvetch (Astragalus nuttallianus), white sagebrush (Artemesia ludoviciana), Fendler&#8217;s arabis (Arabis fendleri), Fendler&#8217;s sandmat (Chamaesyce fendleri), New Mexico thistle (Cirsium neomexicanum), false pennyroyal (Hedeoma oblongifolia), bastard sage (Eriogonum wrightii), ping&#252;e rubberweed (Hymenoxys richardsonii), large four o&#8217;clock (Mirabilis multiflora), Fendler's penstemon (Penstemon fendleri), and globemallows (Sphaeralcea hastulata and S. wrightii). , </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.368</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.368</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1976</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1976</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2010-07-01</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2010-10-01</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <contact>
    <positionName>, </positionName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuqeurque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
  </contact>
  <publisher>
    <positionName>, </positionName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque, NM  </city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
  </publisher>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout> Shoot &#936;WOne shoot from each target tree was harvested between 0430-0545h and between 1200-1400h, to get predawn and midday water potential (referred to hereafter as &#936;PD and &#936;MD, respectively). Samples were placed in plastic bags containing a small segment of moist paper towel to prevent further dessication, which were placed in coolers out of direct sunlight in the interim time between collection and processing (between 15-60 minutes). Water potential (&#936;W) [u1]was measured using a pressure chamber (PMS, Corvallis, OR). Stem Hydraulics After &#936;W was measured, shoots were placed in humid plastic bags and allowed to equilibrate for 24 hours in a refrigerator.&#160; Shoots were then trimmed underwater to remove peripheral embolized tissue and inserted into a steady state flow meter to measure hydraulic conductivity, Kh, kg&#8226;m-1&#8226;s-1&#8226;MPa-1 (see Hudson et al. 2010 for a full explanation of method).&#160; In brief, the steady state flowmeter operates on the Ohm&#8217;s Law analogy of hydraulic transport (Tyree 1997), and solves for Kh by knowing the pressure gradient and the flow rate of sap surrogate (20 mM KCl, Zwieniecki et al. 2001) through the flowmeter, and measuring the pressure drop across the sample stem segment.&#160; Hydraulic conductivity was calculated as flow through the sample segment divided by the pressure gradient across the sample segment. Sapwood cross-sections and distal leaf areas were measured for each sample to normalize Kh at tissue level (KS, sapwood area specific hydraulic conductivity, kg&#8226;m-1&#8226;s-1&#8226;MPa-1) and shoot level (KL, leaf area specific hydraulic conductivity, g&#8226;m-1&#8226;s-1&#8226;MPa-1). AS:AL was calculated for each species by dividing each sample&#8217;s sapwood area by distal leaf area. </literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
      <instrumentation> Instrument Name: Pressure Chamber&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; Manufacturer: PMS Instrument Company&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; Model Number: 1505D&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160; Instrument Name: &#160;Gage model pressure transducer (0-15 psig range)&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; Manufacturer: &#160;Omega&#160;Engineering, INC. Model number: PX26-015GV</instrumentation>
    </methodStep>
  </methods>
</dataset>
</ns0:eml>