<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-ntl.86.4" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
	<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
		<allow>
			<principal>uid=NTL, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
			<permission>all</permission>
		</allow>
		<allow>
			<principal>public</principal>
			<permission>read</permission>
		</allow>
	</access>
	<dataset>
		<alternateIdentifier system="NTL-DEIMS">5619</alternateIdentifier>
		<shortName>CPISC1</shortName>
		<title>Cascade Project at North Temperate Lakes LTER: Piscivore Fish 1984 - 2003</title>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Stephen</givenName>
				<surName>Carpenter</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">(608) 262-3014</phone>
			<phone phonetype="fax">(608) 265-2340</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>srcarpen@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Jim</givenName>
				<surName>Kitchell</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
    </address>
			<phone phonetype="voice">(608) 262-3014</phone>
			<phone phonetype="fax">(608) 265-3014</phone>
			<electronicMailAddress>kitchell@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Jon</givenName>
				<surName>Cole</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>colej@caryinstitute.org</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Mike</givenName>
				<surName>Pace</surName>
			</individualName>
			<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>pacem@virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</creator>
		<metadataProvider>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</metadataProvider>
		<pubDate>2009</pubDate>
		<language>english</language>
		<abstract>
			<para>Fish collected for the Casade Project. Sampling Frequency: varies Number of sites: 9
			</para>
		</abstract>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>populations</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>LTER Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>fish</keyword>
			<keyword>fish abundance</keyword>
			<keyword>fish diet</keyword>
			<keyword>fish prey</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>NTL Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<intellectualRights>
			<section>
				<title>Data Policies</title>
				<para>Copyright Board of Regents, University of Wisconsin, Madison. This information is
					released to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes
					subject to the following restrictions: The Data User must realize that these data sets are
					being actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary
					to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the NTL lead Principal
					Investigator, leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu, to check on other uses of the data. Where
					appropriate, the Data User may be encouraged to consider collaboration and/or
					co-authorship with original investigators.</para>
				<para>The Data User must realize that the data may be misinterpreted if taken out of
					context. We request that you provide the NTL lead Principal Investigator, ATTN: Data
					Access, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 680 North Park St.,
					Madison, WI 53706 with a copy of any manuscript using the data so that it may be reviewed
					and comments provided on the presentation of our data.</para>
				<para>The Data User must acknowledge use of the data by an appropriate citation (see
					Citation) of the NTL-LTER database. A generic citation for our databases is: name of data
					set, North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research program, NSF, contact person for
					data set, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison. The data set name and
					contact person for each data set can be found in the metadata header of the online data
					sets.</para>
				<para>The Data User must send two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the
					data to the address above. We would like to include such manuscripts in our LTER
					publications list.</para>
				<para>The Data User must not redistribute original data and documentation without permission
					from Emily Stanley, lead Principal Investigator, (ehstanley@wisc.edu).</para>
				<para>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation,
					complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is".
					The North Temperate Lakes LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or
					misinterpretation of data sets. Data users should be aware that we periodically update
					data sets.</para>
				<para>Our goal is to release all long term data associated with core research areas within 2
					years of collection. These data and accompanying metadata will be available for download
					from the NTL-LTER web site.</para>
				<para>By using these data, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement.
					Thank you for your cooperation. </para>
			</section>
		</intellectualRights>
		<distribution>
			<online>
				<url function="information">http://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/node/5619</url>
			</online>
		</distribution>
		<coverage>
			<geographicCoverage>
				<geographicDescription>Cascade lakes: Peter, Paul, Tuesday, East Long, West Long, Central Long, Hummingbird, Crampton, UNDERC (University of Notre Dame Environmental Research Center) Vilas County, WI and Gogebic County, MI, USA
</geographicDescription>
				<boundingCoordinates>
					<westBoundingCoordinate>-89.506</westBoundingCoordinate>
					<eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.468</eastBoundingCoordinate>
					<northBoundingCoordinate>46.254</northBoundingCoordinate>
					<southBoundingCoordinate>46.206</southBoundingCoordinate>
				</boundingCoordinates>
			</geographicCoverage>
			<temporalCoverage>
				<rangeOfDates>
					<beginDate>
						<calendarDate>1984-05-01</calendarDate>
					</beginDate>
					<endDate>
						<calendarDate>2003-08-19</calendarDate>
					</endDate>
				</rangeOfDates>
			</temporalCoverage>
		</coverage>
		<maintenance>
			<description>
				<para>completed </para>
			</description>
		</maintenance>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Information Manager</positionName>
			<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<contact>
			<positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
			<organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</contact>
		<publisher>
			<organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
			<address>
      <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Madison</city>
      <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
			<electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
		</publisher>
		<pubPlace>North Temperate Lakes</pubPlace>
		<methods>
			<methodStep>
				<description>
					<section>
						<para>FISH SAMPLING TECHNIQUES The techniques used to sample the fish and estimate the
							population density in the cascade lakes, vary according to the species and life-stage
							of interest. The following techniques for the different fish populations have been
							used from 1984 to present, except when noted. 1. Minnows (Dace, Mudminnows,
							Sticklebacks and assorted small cyprinids) and Bass (young-of-year): The gear most
							used to sample these small-bodied species is the minnow trap. The traps are
							commercially available under the name Gee s Minnow Trap. They are made of 1or4"
							galvanized hardware cloth with approximately 1" openings in either end. The only
							modification made to the commercial trap, is treatment with acid prior to use to
							remove the shine of the new trap. Shiny traps have been found to be less effective.
							Twenty-four minnow traps are set in the littoral zone and 18 in the pelagic zone of
							each lake. The littoral traps are set from stakes approximately uniformly spaced
							around the lake at depths of .5 m and on the bottom alternately. The pelagic traps are
							set at 1 and 3 m across the deepest portion of the lake on a single transect with 9
							stations (one 1 m and one 3 m trap at each station). The traps are set bi-weekly for
							24 hr. All fish are counted and identified to species. The traps are normally set
							unbaited. Bait (bread) is used when large numbers of minnows must be caught, such as
							for a Delury estimate (Ricker, 1975). A subsample of approximately 400 individuals is
							measured. These 400 fish are anesthetized in small batches with MS-222. The
							anesthetized fish are placed on a clipboard covered with a sheet of transparency
							plastic. The nose of the minnow is placed against a retaining board and a hole is
							punched in the plastic at the end of the minnow s tail. The distance from the edge of
							the plastic to hole is measured back at the lab to obtain total length in millimeters.
							Both mark-recapture and Delury population estimation are used to estimate the
							abundance of minnows. With mark-recapture, a large subsample, greater than1000
							individuals, from a minnow-trap capture are finclipped and released. Minnow traps are
							then reset after waiting at least 1 but not more than 7 days. The population is then
							estimated using the ratio of marked to unmarked fish caught in the second set. The
							Delury estimate is done by depleting the population using repeated minnow trapping and
							recording the catch and cumulative catch. The minnows are held in floating net boxes
							at densities of 1000-2000 per cubic meter until at least four trap sets have been
							made. The population is estimated by the intercept of the regression between catch and
							cumulative catch (the level of cumulative catch where catch equals zero). The Delury
							and mark-recapture estimates provides an independent population estimate to correlate
							the catch-per132 unit-effort (CPUE) of the regular minnow-trapping with known
							population densities. 133 2) Bass and perch (age 1plus and older): The larger fishes
							are sampled for population estimation twice each year, once in mid-May and once in
							mid-August. The primary technique used is night electrofishing with mark-recapture
							population estimation. A 16 foot Cofelt electrofishing boat, with dual booms (3 4-ft
							electrodes per boom), is used. Electroshocking is done largely perpendicular to shore,
							shocking from approximately 3 meters water depth to the shore. DC current is used to
							minimize damage to the fish. 600 volts provides adequate current, 2-6 amps, to stun
							the fish. All fish are placed in a live-well on board the shock boat and are taken to
							a shore station for processing. On shore, the first 25 fish of each species are
							stomach pumped for gut analysis. Scales are also taken from a subsample of the fish
							for age analysis. All fish are identified to species, counted, measured (total length
							in millimeters), and weighed with either a Pesola spring-scale or an Ohaus electronic
							pan balance. If the spring-scale is used then the fish is simply held by the lip with
							the clip on the scale; if the electronic scale is used the fish is wrapped in a wet
							cloth to restrain the fish and the fish and cloth are weighed together. The weight of
							the cloth is removed by taring the scale with the cloth prior to weighing the fish. If
							a markorrecapture estimation of the population is to be done, all fish sampled on the
							first night of electrofishing are marked. The fish are tagged with individually
							numbered anchor tags (Wydoski and Emery, 1983) if the fish is greater than 150mm total
							length and has not been previously tagged. If the fish is smaller than 150mm, the
							dorsal lobe of the caudal fin is clipped. The marked fish are then placed in a holding
							net until the first sampling is complete. The fish are released at the end of the
							first night of electrofishing. To increase the power of the mark-recapture technique,
							the number of marked fish is increased by angling and marking fish on the day prior to
							electroshocking at night for recapture. The population is sampled again the following
							night to estimate the ratio of marked to unmarked fish. For the Delury estimation,
							fish are removed from the lake using several days of sampling effort using both
							angling and electroshocking. 3) Scale Samples: Scale samples are taken at least once a
							year, from at least 50 randomly selected fish of each species. Large fish are usually
							sampled for scales when they are caught. At least 5 scales are taken from each fish
							from the area below the origin of the dorsal fin and above the lateral line. Scales
							are permanently mounted on a plastic slide later for aging and individual growth
							determination (Summerfelt and Hall, 1987). 134 4) Larval Perch (and other pelagic
							larvae), 1989-present: Two techniques are used to sample pelagic fish larvae: purse
							seining, and sonar. a. Purse seining is a method of enclosing a volume of water in the
							pelagic zone with a net and filtering that water to obtain the larval fish. The net
							design and technique are described in Evans and Johannes (1988). The net used in the
							Cascade project is 33 meters long and 6 meters deep, made of polyester net material
							with 1.6mm openings and dyed green. b. Sonar is used in conjunction with purse seining
							to obtain the sizefrequency, species composition, and spatial distribution of
							icthyoplankton. The Cascade project uses both 70 and 200 khz sonar. The transducer is
							towed approximately 20cm under the surface. The technique is outlined in Thorne
							(1983). The HADAS acoustics processing hardware and software is used to analyze the
							recorded signal (see Rudstam, 1988, for a description of the analysis). STATISTICAL
							POPULATION ESTIMATION The two techniques used in the Cascade project to estimate
							population density are the modified Peterson mark-recapture and Delury estimations
							(Ricker 1975). a. Mark-recapture is used for populations that are not being
							intentionally depleted in a lake such as the bass population in Paul Lake. b. Delury
							estimates are used when a population is being removed from a lake such as for the bass
							in Peter Lake in the fall of 1989 or for minnows which are easily handled. 135
							REFERENCES: Evans, D.O. and P.R. Johannes. 1988. A bridle-less trawl and fine-mesh
							purse seine for sampling pelagic coregonine larvae with observations of the spatial
							distribution and abundance. Ontario Fish. Tech. Rep. no 27:1-19. Ricker, W.E. 1975.
							Computation and interpretation of biological statistics of fish populations.
							Department of the Environment, Fisheries and Marine Service, Fisheries Research Board
							of Canada Bulletin 191, Ottawa, Canada. Rudstam, Lars G. 1988. Patterns of
							zooplanktivory in a coastal area of the northern Baltic proper. Doctoral thesis at the
							University of Stockholm. Summerfelt, R.C. and G.E. Hall. 1987. Age and Growth of Fish.
							Iowa State University Press, Ames. Iowa. Thorne, R.E. 1983. Hydroacoustics. pp.
							239-260. In: L.A. Nielsen and D.L. Johnson ed. Fisheries Techniques. American
							Fisheries Society, Bethesda, Maryland. Wydoski, R. and L. Emery. 1983. Tagging and
							Marking. pp. 215-237. In: L.A. Nielsen and D.L. Johnson ed. Fisheries Techniques.
							American Fisheries Society, Bethesda, Maryland. 136 </para>
					</section>
					<section>
						<para>FISH DIET ANALYSIS PROCEDURES Fish that are 1plus and older are sampled biweekly
							from mid-May to late August for diet analysis, using angling as the capture method
							(Hodgson and Cochran, 1988). Fish are processed in less than an hour (usually much
							less) after capture in the following manner: 1. Between capture and release, specimens
							are contained in a live-well, except for rainbow trout, which are processed at the
							time of capture to reduce thermal related mortality. All fish are processed on shore
							and released at that point. 2. All gut samples are obtained from live fish using a
							stomach flushing technique (for the basic design of the stomach probe see Seaburg,
							1957). The diameter of the afferent probe varies with the species andoror age: small
							for rainbow trout; 6 - 15 mm for largemouth and smallmouth bass. Water flow and
							pressure is maintained with a modified backpack, pesticide sprayer (Jetpak Knapsack
							sprayer, Ben Meadows Co., Atlanta, Georgia). 3. The gut samples are concentrated into
							a zooplankton cup strainer. The mesh size can be adjusted to accommodate different
							prey sizes (small Daphnia and Polyphemus are the smallest prey species sampled). 4.
							The samples are transferred to small glass vials, labeled and preserved in 95percent
							ethanol. All gut samples are identified to nearest functional taxa (i.e. cladocerans
							to species; dipterans to the family - Chironomidae or to the genus - Chaoborus; other
							invertebrates to order; and fish to species). 5. For each of the diet items, the
							following is determined: a. Percent number of the total sample (percent number of diet
							item "a" in gut sample "A", where sample A = all individuals of the sample period). b.
							Percent weight of the total (same as percent number). c. Frequency of occurrence (the
							number of individuals in sample "A" that contain prey item "a"). These estimates are
							then used in the calculation of an Index of Relative Importance. See Hodgson and
							Kitchell (1987) for details, as well as for the prey category weight determinations.
							137 6. All diet data are stored on mainframe files at St. Norbert College, DePere,
							Wisconsin. Raw data are stored under a coding for sample period (there are 287
							recorded sample periods between 1980 and 1989 - there are none for 1982). In addition,
							diet records of specific prey, along with other information (length, weight, catching
							methods and aging) for over 5,000 individual fish are found in the Cascade piscivory
							data files (see Appendix V for the input variables). The files can be found in ASCII
							andoror dBase IIIplus for the IBM, and Panorama andoror "text" formats for the MAC.
							REFERENCES: Hodgson, J.R. and P.A. Cochran. 1988. The effect of sampling methodology
							on diet analysis in largemouth bass (Micropterus salmoides). Verh. int. Ver. Limnol.
							23:1670-1675. Hodgson, J.R. and J.F. Kitchell. 1987. Opportunistic foraging by
							largemouth bass (Micropterus salmoides). Am. Mid. Natl 118:323-335. Seaburg, K.G.
							1957. A stomach sampler for live fish. Progressive Fish-Culturist. 19:137-139. </para>
					</section>
				</description>
			</methodStep>
		</methods>
		<project>
			<title>Cascade Project at North Temperate Lakes LTER</title>
			<personnel>
				<individualName>
					<givenName>Stephen</givenName>
					<surName>Carpenter</surName>
				</individualName>
				<organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
				<address>
        <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
				<phone phonetype="voice">(608) 262-3014</phone>
				<phone phonetype="fax">(608) 265-2340</phone>
				<electronicMailAddress>srcarpen@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<personnel>
				<individualName>
					<givenName>Jim</givenName>
					<surName>Kitchell</surName>
				</individualName>
				<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
				<address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
      </address>
				<phone phonetype="voice">(608) 262-3014</phone>
				<phone phonetype="fax">(608) 265-3014</phone>
				<electronicMailAddress>kitchell@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<personnel>
				<individualName>
					<givenName>Jon</givenName>
					<surName>Cole</surName>
				</individualName>
				<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
				<address>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
				<electronicMailAddress>colej@caryinstitute.org</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<personnel>
				<individualName>
					<givenName>Mike</givenName>
					<surName>Pace</surName>
				</individualName>
				<organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
				<address>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
				<electronicMailAddress>pacem@virginia.edu</electronicMailAddress>
				<role>project personnel</role>
			</personnel>
			<abstract>
				<para>The Cascade project is a whole-ecosystem experimental test of the theory that: 1)
					increased variance 2) red-shift of variance 3) critical slowing down of recovery rate
					across components of a food web are leading indicators of a common type of regime shift in
					lake ecosystems caused by changes in the structure of the fish community. Variability will
					be assessed at all trophic levels for three years in both a manipulated lake and a
					non-manipulated reference lake using high-frequency data acquisition methods including
					automated in situ instrumentation for analysis of alagal biomass and primary production,
					zooplankton abundance and size structure, acoustical measure of fish migration, and daily
					measures of fish growth from otoliths. Modern signal processing methods of time series,
					spectral and wavelet analysis will evaluate changes in variance, variance sprectra and
					return rate. </para>
			</abstract>
		</project>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>cascade_fish_pisc_ind</entityName>
			<entityDescription>Cascade Project: Piscovore Fish Individuals</entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>cascadefishpiscind</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-ntl.86&amp;urlTail=ntl/data/5619_1_v1.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>lakename</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>lake name</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>lake name</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>lake name</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>year4</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>year</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>year</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<precision>1</precision>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>sampledate</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>sample date</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>sample date</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>date</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<dateTime>
							<formatString>yyyy-MM-dd</formatString>
						</dateTime>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>daynum</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>day of year</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>day of year</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>nominalDay</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<precision>1</precision>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
								<bounds>
									<minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum>
									<maximum exclusive="false">366</maximum>
								</bounds>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>species</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>fish species</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>fish species</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<enumeratedDomain>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>1</code>
										<definition>yellow perch</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>2</code>
										<definition>rock bass</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>3</code>
										<definition>rainbow smelt</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>4</code>
										<definition>smallmouth bass</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>5</code>
										<definition>walleye</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>6</code>
										<definition>muskellunge</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>7</code>
										<definition>cisco</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
								</enumeratedDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
		<dataTable>
			<entityName>cascade_fish_pisc_diet</entityName>
			<entityDescription>Cascade Project: Piscovore Fish Diet</entityDescription>
			<physical>
				<objectName>cascadefishpiscdiet</objectName>
				<dataFormat>
					<textFormat>
						<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
						<recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
						<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
						<simpleDelimited>
							<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
							<quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
						</simpleDelimited>
					</textFormat>
				</dataFormat>
				<distribution>
					<online>
						<url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-ntl.86&amp;urlTail=ntl/data/5619_2_v1.csv</url>
					</online>
				</distribution>
			</physical>
			<attributeList>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>fish_id</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>Fish identification code</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>Alphanumeric fish identification code</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<textDomain>
									<definition>Alphanumeric fish identification code</definition>
								</textDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>food_item</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>Food Item</attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>Food Item</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>string</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<nominal>
							<nonNumericDomain>
								<enumeratedDomain>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>AMPHI</code>
										<definition>Amphipods</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>BASSF</code>
										<definition>Bass Fry</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>BASSY</code>
										<definition>Bass Yearling</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>CHAOB</code>
										<definition>Chaoborus</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>CHIRO</code>
										<definition>Chironomid</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>COLEO</code>
										<definition>Coleoptera</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>CRATF</code>
										<definition>Crayfish</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>DACES</code>
										<definition>Daces</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>DAPHN</code>
										<definition>Daphnia</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>EPHEM</code>
										<definition>Ephemeroptera</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>LEECH</code>
										<definition>Leech</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>MEGAL</code>
										<definition>Megaloptera</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>MITES</code>
										<definition>Mites</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>MOLLU</code>
										<definition>Mollusca</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>NOTON</code>
										<definition>Notonectid</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>ODONA</code>
										<definition>Odonate Adult</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>ODONN</code>
										<definition>Odonate Nymph</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>OFISH</code>
										<definition>Other Fish</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>OTHER</code>
										<definition>Other</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>POLYP</code>
										<definition>Polyphemous</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
									<codeDefinition>
										<code>TRICH</code>
										<definition>Trichoptera</definition>
									</codeDefinition>
								</enumeratedDomain>
							</nonNumericDomain>
						</nominal>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
				<attribute>
					<attributeName>number_indiv</attributeName>
					<attributeLabel>Number of individuals </attributeLabel>
					<attributeDefinition>Number of individuals of food item</attributeDefinition>
					<storageType>float</storageType>
					<measurementScale>
						<ratio>
							<unit>
								<standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
							</unit>
							<numericDomain>
								<numberType>real</numberType>
							</numericDomain>
						</ratio>
					</measurementScale>
				</attribute>
			</attributeList>
		</dataTable>
	</dataset>
</ns0:eml>