<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.280.76005" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>The Contribution of Biological Soil Crust Carbon and Nitrogen Exchange to the Net Ecosystem Exchange Along an Elevation Gradient at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Marcy</givenName>
      <surName>Litvak</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>mlitvak@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">14590</userId>
  </creator>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Eva</givenName>
      <surName>Dettweiler-Robinson</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>erobinson@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Sevilleta</givenName>
      <surName>Information Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <pubDate>2012</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>The purpose of this project is to: 1.) determine how biological soil crust (BSC) cover changes along an elevation gradient and across seasons, 2.) determine how carbon and nitrogen exchanges of BSC communities vary with temperature along an elevation gradient in arid and semi-arid environments and, 3.) use photosynthetic and respiration rates of BSC communities to determine how the contribution of the BSC communities to whole ecosystem carbon exchange varies across the same gradient and over seasons.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>inorganic nutrients</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>fluxes</keyword>
    <keyword>carbon fluxes</keyword>
    <keyword>eddy covariance</keyword>
    <keyword>processes</keyword>
    <keyword>biogeochemical processes</keyword>
    <keyword>nutrient cycling</keyword>
    <keyword>nitrogen cycling</keyword>
    <keyword>biological processes</keyword>
    <keyword>carbon cycling</keyword>
    <keyword>elements and compounds</keyword>
    <keyword>carbon</keyword>
    <keyword>carbon dioxide</keyword>
    <keyword>nitrogen</keyword>
    <keyword>oxygen</keyword>
    <keyword>soil</keyword>
    <keyword>organisms</keyword>
    <keyword>algae</keyword>
    <keyword>microbes</keyword>
    <keyword>bacteria</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>  Study sites included: Flux tower sites, desert grassland, desert shrubland, juniper savanna, pi&#241;on-juniper woodland, ponderosa pine forest, and mixed conifer forest.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/6904</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Cerro Montosa Pinyon-Juniper site has been the location of major Sevilleta LTER research since 1989. Meteorological trends, net primary productivity, rodent and ground-dwelling arthropod populations, mycorrhizal responses to fertilizer, pinyon-juniper fruit and nut production, and pinyon mortality are all being investigated at this site. Previous studies have included analyses of pinyon tree rings for regional climate reconstruction.Vegetation: The vegetation is New Mexico Pinyon-Juniper Woodland, dominated by Colorado pinyon (Pinus edulis) and one-seed juniper (Juniperus monosperma), and accompanied by gray oak (Quercus grisea).  There is a diverse shrub component, including scrub live oak (Q. turbinella), mountain mahogany (Cercocarpus montanus), broom snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae), sacahuista (Nolina microcarpa), red barberry (Mahonia haematocarpa), Apache plume (Fallugia paradoxa), tree cholla (Opuntia imbricata), skunkbush (Rhus trilobata), and banana yucca (Yucca baccata).  Grass diversity is also high, and open spaces between trees are dominated by blue grama (Bouteloua gracilis), with hairy and sideoats grama (B. hirsuta and B. curtipendula) and black grama (B. eriopoda) also being significant. Other common grasses include purple threeawn (Aristida purpurea), wolftail (Lycurus phleoides), mountain and ring muhly (M. montanus and M. torreyi), and New Mexican porcupinegrass (Heterostipa neomexicana). Common forbs include small-flowered milkvetch (Astragalus nuttallianus), white sagebrush (Artemesia ludoviciana), Fendler&#8217;s arabis (Arabis fendleri), Fendler&#8217;s sandmat (Chamaesyce fendleri), New Mexico thistle (Cirsium neomexicanum), false pennyroyal (Hedeoma oblongifolia), bastard sage (Eriogonum wrightii), ping&#252;e rubberweed (Hymenoxys richardsonii), large four o&#8217;clock (Mirabilis multiflora), Fendler's penstemon (Penstemon fendleri), and globemallows (Sphaeralcea hastulata and S. wrightii). , </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.368</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.368</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1976</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1976</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: Deep Well is located on McKenzie Flats and is site of the longest running SEV LTER met station, number 40, which has been active since 1988.&#160; In addition to studies of meteorological variables, core line-intercept vegetation transects and line-intercept transects from the 1995 and 2001 Deep Well fires are sampled here.&#160; The mini-rhizotron study, blue and black grama compositional comparison, blue and black grama patch dynamics investigation, and kangaroo rat population assessement are all ongoing here.&#160; Deep Well Blue/Black Grama Mixed is also the location of the warming and monsoon experiments, as well as portions of the line-intercept and vegetation removal studies.
On August 4, 2009, a lightning-initiated fire began on the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge. By August 5, 2009, the fire had reached the area of Deep Well Blue/Black Grama Mixed.&#160; While portions of this site were burned, the entirety was not.&#160; See individual projects for further information on the effects of the fire.Vegetation: The vegetation of Deep Well Blue/Black Grama Mixed is Chihuahuan Desert Grassland, dominated by black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda) and blue grama (B. gracilis).  Other grasses found at the site include dropseeds (Sporobolus spp.) and threeawns (Aristida spp.).  Shrubs are uncommon but those that occur include Yucca glauca, Ephedra torreyi, and four-wing saltbush (Atriplex canescens). Herbaceous plants include Plantago purshii, Hymenopappus filifolius, and globe mallows (Sphaeralcea spp.).

 , </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1600</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1600</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Five Points area emcompasses both the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote study sites.&#160; Five Points falls along the transition between the Chihuahuan Desert Scrub and Desert Grassland habitats.&#160; Both core sites are subject to intensive research activities, including NPP measurements, phenology observations, pollinator diversity studies, and ground dwelling arthropod and rodent population assessments.&#160; There are rain-out shelters for drought studies in both the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote sites.Vegetation: The Five Points Creosote site is characterized as Chihuahuan Desert Scrub, dominated by a creosote overstory, with broom snakeweed, purple pricklypear (Opuntia macrocentra), and soapweed yucca as co-occurring shrubs. The site is also characterized by numerous, dense, grass-dominated patches, reflecting proximity to the Five Points Black Grama Site.  Dominant grasses are black grama, fluffgrass (Dasyochloa pulchellum), burrograss (Scleropogon brevifolia), bushmuhly (Muhlenbergia porteri), and galleta (Pleuraphis jamesii).  Notable forbs include field bahia (Bahia absinthifolia), baby aster (Chaetopappa ericoides), plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala), Indian rushpea (Hoffmannseggia glauca), Fendlers bladderpod (Lesquerella fendleri), and globemallows (Sphaeralcea spp.)., siteid: 3</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Goat Draw Juniper Savanna Core Site was established in 1998 in order to provide data at the lower end of the transition from the Pinon-Juniper Woodland habitat at the Cerro Montoso site to Juniper Savanna.Vegetation: While the site is positioned between two ridgelines, the vegetation is best characterized as Juniper Savanna, dominated by one-seed juniper (Juniperus monosperma), scrub liveoak (Quercus turbinella), and grama grasses (Bouteloua curtipendula, B. gracilis, B. eriopoda, and B. hirsuta), with scattered Colorado pinyon pine trees (Pinus edulis) in the upper reaches. There is also a significant influence of Arroyo Riparian vegetation in the main arroyo, Goat Draw, and its tributaries., siteid: 39</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.5228246</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.5228246</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.41464054</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.41464054</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1790</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1790</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2012-06-01</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2013-05-31</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Sevilleta</givenName>
      <surName>Information Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout> At each sampling site and sampling period a small amount of surface crust (approx. one teaspoonful per sample) was taken from each of 10 locations at approximately 1 meter intervals over a transect.&#160; Samples were transported back to the laboratory in plastic bags. On rare occasions we removed a larger sample, 0.5 liter volume or less, at one or two sampling stations.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
  </methods>
</dataset>
</ns0:eml>