<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.248.30297" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Pi&#241;on Pine (Pinus edulis) Responses of Annual Growth to Water Availability in a Pinyon-Juniper Forest at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Amanda</givenName>
      <surName>Boutz</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>aboutz@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">15592</userId>
  </creator>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>William</givenName>
      <surName>Pockman</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, MSC03 2020, 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>pockman@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">12857</userId>
  </creator>
  <metadataProvider>
    <positionName>, </positionName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuqeurque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
  </metadataProvider>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Amanda</givenName>
      <surName>Boutz</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>aboutz@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">15592</userId>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Amanda</givenName>
      <surName>Boutz</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>aboutz@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">15592</userId>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Amanda</givenName>
      <surName>Boutz</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>aboutz@unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">15592</userId>
    <role>labcrew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>Increased incidence of large-scale forest die-off attributed to drought has been observed globally over the past decade, raising concern about the future stability of forests as carbon sinks. &#160;To understand the mechanistic basis of semi-arid woodland responses to drought, we measured annual increment growth from branches of Pinus edulis in a rainfall manipulation experiment at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge and LTER site in central New Mexico, USA. We collected 4 branches from each of five trees growing in drought, irrigation, cover control, and ambient control plots at a site in the Los Pinos Mountains. &#160;We measured annual branch elongation, stem diameter, sapwood area, and leaf area. &#160;We compared these structural data to fluctuations in annual precipitation across treatments to understand how such variation in available water influence branch growth. &#160;Rainfall manipulation produced clear differences among treatment groups, with drought trees exhibiting shorter stem lengths, decreased stem and sapwood diameters, and decreased leaf area production than control treatments. &#160;Irrigated trees displayed increased stem length, stem diameter, sapwood diameter, and leaf area production relative to ambient controls. &#160;The net effect of these responses is a likely shift in the allometric relationships, such as hydroactive xylem and absorbing root area.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>primary production</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>biology</keyword>
    <keyword>droughts</keyword>
    <keyword>leaf area</keyword>
    <keyword>productivity</keyword>
    <keyword>growth</keyword>
    <keyword>tree growth</keyword>
    <keyword>irrigation</keyword>
    <keyword>water</keyword>
    <keyword>leaves</keyword>
    <keyword>trees</keyword>
    <keyword>vegetation</keyword>
    <keyword>stems</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/6331</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Cerro Montosa Pinyon-Juniper site has been the location of major Sevilleta LTER research since 1989. Meteorological trends, net primary productivity, rodent and ground-dwelling arthropod populations, mycorrhizal responses to fertilizer, pinyon-juniper fruit and nut production, and pinyon mortality are all being investigated at this site. Previous studies have included analyses of pinyon tree rings for regional climate reconstruction.Vegetation: The vegetation is New Mexico Pinyon-Juniper Woodland, dominated by Colorado pinyon (Pinus edulis) and one-seed juniper (Juniperus monosperma), and accompanied by gray oak (Quercus grisea).  There is a diverse shrub component, including scrub live oak (Q. turbinella), mountain mahogany (Cercocarpus montanus), broom snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae), sacahuista (Nolina microcarpa), red barberry (Mahonia haematocarpa), Apache plume (Fallugia paradoxa), tree cholla (Opuntia imbricata), skunkbush (Rhus trilobata), and banana yucca (Yucca baccata).  Grass diversity is also high, and open spaces between trees are dominated by blue grama (Bouteloua gracilis), with hairy and sideoats grama (B. hirsuta and B. curtipendula) and black grama (B. eriopoda) also being significant. Other common grasses include purple threeawn (Aristida purpurea), wolftail (Lycurus phleoides), mountain and ring muhly (M. montanus and M. torreyi), and New Mexican porcupinegrass (Heterostipa neomexicana). Common forbs include small-flowered milkvetch (Astragalus nuttallianus), white sagebrush (Artemesia ludoviciana), Fendler&#8217;s arabis (Arabis fendleri), Fendler&#8217;s sandmat (Chamaesyce fendleri), New Mexico thistle (Cirsium neomexicanum), false pennyroyal (Hedeoma oblongifolia), bastard sage (Eriogonum wrightii), ping&#252;e rubberweed (Hymenoxys richardsonii), large four o&#8217;clock (Mirabilis multiflora), Fendler's penstemon (Penstemon fendleri), and globemallows (Sphaeralcea hastulata and S. wrightii). , </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.368</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.368</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1976</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1976</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <singleDateTime>
        <calendarDate>2012-01-04</calendarDate>
      </singleDateTime>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Sevilleta</givenName>
      <surName>Information Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <publisher>
    <positionName>, </positionName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque, NM  </city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
  </publisher>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Branch sampling, four small branches were removed from each of five target trees per plot according to aspect (North, South, East, West).&#160;Experimental design: &#160;Single block from complete block design.Plots: &#160;Four plots of varying treatments (Irrigation, Drought, Cover control, Ambient control) were used from preexisting study, each 40m X 40m.Sampling: &#160;Samples taken according to aspect (North, South, East, West) on all pinon target trees within one replicate block.Measurements: &#160;Stem length, two perpendicular midpoint diameter, and two perpendicular sapwood diameters were taken for each growth increment for each sample using digital callipers. Needles from each age cohort were scanned and leaf area was estimated using ImageJ software.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
  </methods>
</dataset>
</ns0:eml>