<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sbc.56.3" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.1/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=SBC,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset id="56">
    <alternateIdentifier>knb-lter-sbc.56</alternateIdentifier>
    <shortName>Byrnes kelp forest foodweb</shortName>
    <title>SBC LTER: Reef: Feeding relationships for kelp forest species</title>
    <creator id="sbclter">
      <organizationName>Santa Barbara Coastal LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Science Institute</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>University of California</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Santa Barbara</city>
        <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>93106</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>sbclter@msi.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator id="jbyrnes">
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Jarrett</givenName>
        <givenName>Edward</givenName>
        <surName>Byrnes</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>University of California</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Santa Barbara</city>
        <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>93101</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">805-892-2512</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>byrnes@nceas.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator id="dreed">
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Daniel</givenName>
        <givenName>C</givenName>
        <surName>Reed</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Science Institute</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>University of California</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Santa Barbara</city>
        <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>93106-6150</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">805-893-8363</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">805-893-8062</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>dan.reed@lifesci.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator id="bcardinale">
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Bradley</givenName>
        <givenName>Joseph</givenName>
        <surName>Cardinale</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Department of Ecology, Evolution and Marine Biology</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>University of California</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Santa Barbara</city>
        <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>93106-9620</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">805-893-4157</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>cardinale@lifesci.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator id="kcavanaugh">
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Kyle</givenName>
        <givenName>C</givenName>
        <surName>Cavanaugh</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UCSB</deliveryPoint>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>kyle@eri.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator id="sholbrook">
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Sally</givenName>
        <givenName>J</givenName>
        <surName>Holbrook</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Department of Ecology, Evolution and Marine Biology</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>University of California</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Santa Barbara</city>
        <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>93106-9620</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">805-893-3956</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">805-893-3777</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>sally.holbrook@lifesci.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator id="rschmitt">
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Russell</givenName>
        <givenName>J</givenName>
        <surName>Schmitt</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Department of Ecology, Evolution and Marine Biology</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>University of California</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Santa Barbara</city>
        <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>93106-9620</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">805-893-2051</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">805-893-3777</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>russ.schmitt@lifesci.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <associatedParty id="sharrer">
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Shannon</givenName>
        <surName>Harrer</surName>
      </individualName>
      <positionName>Lead field technician, analyst</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Science Institute</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>University of California</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Santa Barbara</city>
        <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>93106-6150</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">805-893-7295</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>harrer@msi.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Lead field technician, analyst</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2012-02-27</pubDate>
    <language>english</language>
    <abstract>
      <para>These data are an assembled food web for all species sampled in the SBC LTER annual kelp
    forest community surveys. Relationships are taken from literature review on diets and
    consumption habits of target species, plus searches of theses, grey literature, and student
    report databases at major west coast libraries. Only feeding observations from studies that
    showed direct consumption or provided strong evidence of a direct feeding relationship between
    two taxa were used. Our final food web was revised and verified after consultation with several
    experts in the field of kelp forest community ecology. See Methods section for complete
    information on cited literature and contributing experts.</para>
      <para>These data represent Table S1 for Appendix S1 for a published paper: <ulink url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2486.2011.02409.x">Byrnes, J. E., D. C. Reed, B. J.
      Cardinale, K. C. Cavanaugh, S. J. Holbrook and R. J. Schmitt. 2011. Climate-driven increases
      in storm frequency simplify kelp forest food webs. Global Change Biology, 17: 2513&#226;24. doi:
      10.1111/j.1365-2486.2011.02409.x</ulink>.</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">climate change</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">disturbance</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">food web</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">kelp forest</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">kelp forest food web</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">LTER</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">network theory</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">ongoing</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Santa Barbara Coastal</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">structural equation modeling</keyword>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Kelp Forest</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Reef</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Santa Barbara Coastal LTER Habitats</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Community Structure</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Santa Barbara Coastal LTER Measurement Types</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="place">Arroyo Burro Reef</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="place">Arroyo Hondo Reef</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="place">Arroyo Quemado Reef</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="place">Bullito Reef</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="place">Carpinteria Reef</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="place">Goleta Bay</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="place">Isla Vista</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="place">Mohawk Reef</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="place">Naples Reef</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Santa Barbara Coastal LTER Places</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">abundance</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">biomass</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">forests</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">long term ecological research</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">marine</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">organism</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">species</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">transects</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary v1</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Disturbance Patterns</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Population Studies</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary v1: Core Research Areas</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Cover</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Density</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Estimation</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Kelps</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Reefs</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Species</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>NBII Biocomplexity</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The user of SBC LTER data agrees to contact the data owner (i.e., the SBC  investigator responsible for data) prior to publishing. Where appropriate, users whose projects are integrally dependent on SBC LTER 
data are encouraged to consider   collaboration and/or co-authorship with the data owner.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The user agrees to cite SBC LTER in all publications that use SBC LTER data by   including the following statement in the Acknowledgments: "Data were provided by the  Santa Barbara Coastal LTER, funded by the US National Science Foundation (OCE-1232779)".</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The user agrees to send the full citation of any publication using SBC LTER data   to sbclter@msi.ucsb.edu</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Users are prohibited from selling or redistributing any data provided by SBC  LTER.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Extensive efforts are made to ensure that online data are accurate and up to date,  but SBC LTER will not take responsibility for any errors that may exist.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The user agrees also to adhere to the Data Use Agreement of the Long Term   Ecological Research Network.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Any violation of the terms of this agreement will result in immediate forfeiture   of the data and loss of access privileges to other SBC LTER data sets.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>SBC LTER is committed to protecting the privacy and accuracy of your confidential  information. See our Privacy Policy for more information.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">http://sbc.lternet.edu/</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage id="sbc-boilerplate-geoCov_SBC">
        <geographicDescription>Santa Barbara Coastal LTER bounding box: The Santa Barbara Coastal LTER research area extends from Point Conception (W) to the mouth of the Santa Clara River (E) and from the Santa Ynez Mountains (N) to the north shores of the Channel Islands (S), California, USA</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-120.475</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-119.255</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>34.531</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>34</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager, Santa Barbara Coastal LTER</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Science Institute</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>University of California</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Santa Barbara</city>
        <administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>93106-6150</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">805 893 2071</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>sbclter@msi.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://sbc.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <organizationName>Santa Barbara Coastal LTER</organizationName>
    </publisher>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Kelp Forest Food Web Assembly</title>
            <para>In order to assemble a food web for all species sampled in the SBC LTERs summer
              kelp forest community surveys, we conducted a literature review on diets and
              consumptive habits of target species. After obtaining information from several general
              reviews of the natural history of kelp forest fish and invertebrates (Limbaugh,
              1955; Quast, 1968; Foster &amp; Schiel, 12 1985; Hobson &amp; Chess, 1986, 2001) we
              performed a search for each species using ISI Web of Science, Google Scholar, Avano,
              and Aquatic Commons. Each species name was searched with the additional keywords of
              'diet', 'predator', 'prey', 'gut content', and 'feeding' (asterisks used to expand
              search terms). In addition, we searched these five keywords in theses, grey
              literature, and student report databases at the Cadet Hand Library at the Bodega
              Marine Laboratory, the Moss Landing Marine Laboratory Library, the Miller Library at
              the Hopkins Marine Station, and the Scripps Institute of Oceanography Library. Only
              feeding observations from studies that showed direct consumption (e.g., either a
              feeding observation in the field, gut contents, or lab preference study) or provided
              strong evidence of a direct feeding relationship between two taxa were used. Our final
              food web was revised and verified after consultation with several experts in the field
              of kelp forest community ecology.</para>
            <para>Studies had to meet different criteria depending on their origin in order to be
              used. Information on feeding habits was obtained from papers in the peer reviewed
              literature, unpublished dissertations, government reports, observations from
              undergraduate field classes, or from consultation with experts. This information could
              be from field observations, gut contents analyses, laboratory experiments (i.e., it
              was assumed that researchers were creating treatments from a priori knowledge of the
              natural history of organisms), or summaries of natural history information. Only field
              and laboratory observations with quantitative data were used from PhD dissertations,
              Masters theses, and agency reports. Only direct field observations or gut contents
              information was used from undergraduate theses and student reports. All references are
              reported in the feeding list. When completed, we solicited expert opinions from the
              scientists (below)</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Notes</title>
            <para>The quality of data varied greatly by taxon and author. In many cases, diet
              information was taxonomically vague (e.g., "Gastropods"). We therefore categorized the
              information by the level of taxonomic resolution provided. If information was provided
              at the genus or family level, all prey items in that genus or family are listed.
              Additionally, SBC LTER associates individual species with a 'group' categorization
              that blends Class and Phyla in many cases (e.g., Gastropods versus Bryozoans). This
              matched how data were often reported in the literature, and as such, Group has
              therefore been included as the coarsest level of categorization. The level of
              taxonomic specificity for each prey item is listed in a separate data column. Analyses
              were carried out using each level of taxonomic uncertainty (e.g. both with a stringent
              'species only' analysis as well as a 'group and below' analysis). As results did not
              qualitatively differ, we here only report results of the species only analysis. We
              report the higher-level information in order to provide a broader picture of
              kelp-forest food webs, and we hope that it will be refined by future efforts.</para>
            <para>Note that some consumer and prey species are not listed because they are not
              sampled by SBC LTER. See the supplemental list of all species sampled in SBC LTER
              monitoring.</para>
            <para>In addition, we applied the following criteria to clarify feeding links where
              ambiguous:</para>
            <para>1) If a species was a filter feeder or alga, no prey were listed.</para>
            <para>2) Only predators and prey for which the SBC LTER collects data for are listed.
              For example, while nudibranchs are consumed by several species listed here, the SBC
              LTER collects no information on nudibranchs, and hence they are not listed as prey.
              Similarly, only one type of amphipod - Amphipod Tube Mat - is listed, and many species
              consumed amphipods. It is therefore found in the diets of a wide variety of
              species.</para>
            <para>3) SBC LTER samples several categories of fish that are not identified to the
              species level. They were dealt with as follows:</para>
            <para> Embiotocid spp. and Sebastes spp.- these typically referred to juvenile
              Embiotocids or Rockfish respectively. As their diets are obviously not the same as
              adults, they are only listed as eating amphipods.</para>
            <para> Bothid spp. - This category was for unidentified flatfishes. We therefore used
              the diets of several flounder species native to the area.</para>
            <para> Gibbonsia spp. and Cottid spp. - These two fish groupings had species represented
              in the data with detailed diets. We therefore combined diets of these other
              represented species (which were typically quite similar) to create a diet for these
              taxonomically broader groups. This was a conservative approach, as individuals sampled
              within these two groups could have been one of the already listed species, but eluded
              identification due to age or poor visibility.</para>
            <para>4) In cases where information on prey was general, but a size range of prey was
              provided, (Quast 1968), all prey of that taxon whose maximum size was less than the
              maximum size given were listed as prey at the group level. Similarly, many species
              consumed smaller individuals of a given prey species than are commonly observed in the
              survey. We therefore assumed that if a large individual of a prey species was observed
              in the survey, small individuals likely existed at the site as well. See additional
              notes in table S1.</para>
            <para>5) For two species no diet information was found - the sarcastic fringehead
              Neoclinus blanchardi and the threaded abalone Haliotis kamtschatkana. Neoclinus was
              excluded from the analysis as a predator, as it did not have sufficiently similar or
              congeneric species in the data set. However, for Haliotis kamtschatkana, we have
              listed all kelp species as potential prey. Because all other species of abalone
              consumed kelp, this appeared to be a reasonable assumption. These species were also
              rare within the dataset.</para>
            <para>6) There is a surprising lack of detail on the diets of sea urchins in the
              literature. This is largely due to their ability to rapidly grind and macerate their
              prey. However, they are well known to completely denude vast areas of algae. The work
              of Watanabe and Harrold was particularly helpful here, as it provides an example of
              species that are eliminated after urchins move in as a front. As such, we have
              generally assumed urchins will eat any algae. In our own work, we have observed purple
              urchins Strongylocentrotus purpuratus removing all types of ascidians, sponges, and
              bryozoans (Byrnes and Stachowicz 2009). There was also very little information on the
              diet of the white sea urchin Lytechinus anamesus other than observations of it eating
              other urchins (Coyer et al. 1987). We have therefore assumed that their diet is
              similar to S. purpuratus.</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Expert scientists:</title>
            <para>Paul Dayton - Professor, Scripps Institution of Oceanography, University of
              California San Diego, kelp forest community ecologist</para>
            <para>Jim Watanabe - Lecturer, Hopkins Marine Station, Stanford, kelp forest
              invertebrate community ecologist</para>
            <para>Jack Engle - Research Biologist, Marine Science Institute, University of
              California Santa Barbara, kelp forest community ecologist</para>
            <para>Shane Anderson - Marine Collector, Marine Science Institute, University of
              California Santa Barbara</para>
            <para>Milton Love - Research Biologist, Marine Science Institute, University of
              California Santa Barbara, ichthyologist</para>
            <para>Larry Allen - Professor of Biology, California State University Northridge, fish
              ecologist</para>
            <para>Mark Steele - Assistant Professor of Biology, California State University
              Northridge, fish ecologist</para>
            <para>Based on these opinions, several feeding links were added, deleted, or refined to
              a lower taxonomic level, and are marked as such in Supplementary Table 1.</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Literature references for food web relationships</title>
            <para>Ackerman, L. T. 1971. Contributions to the biology of the leopard shark, Triakis
              semifasciata (Girard) in Elkhorn Slough, Monterey Bay, CA. M. S. Thesis. Sacramento
              State College.</para>
            <para>Alguilar Rosas, R. l. 1990. Qualitative analysis of the macroalgal diet of the
              snail Astrea undosa Wood 1828 in Punta Banda, Maja California, Mexico. Ciencia Marina
              16:111-120.</para>
            <para>Allen, L. G. and T. E. Howey. 2001. Kelp Bass. California's Marine Living
              Resources: A Status Report. California Department of Fish and Game.</para>
            <para>Ambrose, R. F. 1984. Food preferences, prey availability, and the diet of Octopus
              bimaculatus Verrill. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology
              77:29-44.</para>
            <para>Anderson, T. W. 2001. Predator responses, prey refuges, and density-dependent
              mortality of a marine fish. Ecology 82:245-257.</para>
            <para>Annett, C. and R. Pierotti. 1984. Foraging behavior and prey selection of the
              leather seastar Dermasterias imbricata. Marine Ecology Progress Series
              14:197-206.</para>
            <para>Barry, J. and M. Ehret. 1993. Diet, food preference, and algal availability for
              fishes and crabs on intertidal reef communities in southern California. Environmental
              Biology of Fishes 37:75-95.</para>
            <para>Barry, J. P., M. M. Yoklavich, G. M. Cailliet, D. A. Ambrose, and B. S. Antrim.
              1996. Trophic ecology of the dominant fishes in Elkhorn Slough, California, 1974-1980.
              Estuaries 19:115-138.</para>
            <para>Beaudreau, A. H. and T. E. Essington. 2007. Spatial, temporal, and ontogenetic
              patterns of predation on rockfishes by lingcod. Transactions of the American Fisheries
              Society 136:1438-1452.</para>
            <para>Bellquist, L. F., C. G. Lowe, and J. E. Caselle. 2008. Fine-scale movement
              patterns, site fidelity, and habitat selection of ocean whitefish (Caulolatilus
              princeps). Fisheries Research 91:325-335.</para>
            <para>Bingham, B. L. and L. F. Braithwaite. 1986. Defense adaptations of the
              dendrochirote holothurian Psolus chitonoides Clark. Journal of Experimental Marine
              Biology and Ecology 98:311-322.</para>
            <para>Bray, R. N., A. C. Miller, S. Johnson, P. R. Krause, D. L. Robertson, and A. M.
              Westcott. 1988. Ammonium excretion by macroinvertebrates and fishes on a subtidal
              rocky reef in southern California. Marine Biology 100:21-30.</para>
            <para>Breitburg, D. L. 1984. Residual effects of grazing: Inhibition of competitor
              recruitment by encrusting coralline algae. Ecology 65:1136-1143.</para>
            <para>Bryant, M. 1978. Ecological studies of the striped perch Embiotoca lateralis and
              the kelp greenling Hexagrammus decagrammus in Carmel Bay, California. M. S. Thesis.
              California State University Fresno.</para>
            <para>Byrnes, J. E. and J. J. Stachowicz. 2009. The consequences of consumer diversity
              loss: different answers from different experimental designs. Ecology
              90:2879-2888.</para>
            <para>Byrnes, J. E., J. J. Stachowicz, K. M. Hultgren, A. R. Hughes, S. V. Olyarnik, and
              C. S. Thornber. 2006. Predator diversity strengthens trophic cascades in kelp forests
              by modifying herbivore behavior. Ecology Letters 9:61-71.</para>
            <para>Cowen, R. 1986. Site-specific differences in the feeding ecology of the California
              sheephead, Semicossyphus pulcher (Labridae). Environmental Biology of Fishes
              16:193-203.</para>
            <para>Cowen, R. K. 1979. Trophic interactions within a central California kelp forest.
              M. S. Thesis. California State University Hayward.</para>
            <para>Cox, T. and S. Murray. 2006. Feeding preferences and the relationships between
              food choice and assimilation efficiency in the herbivorous marine snail Lithopoma
              undosum (Turbinidae). Marine Biology 148:1295-1306.</para>
            <para>Coyer, J. A., J. M. Engle, R. F. Ambrose, and B. V. Nelson. 1987. Utilization of
              purple and red sea urchins (Strongylocentrotus purpuratus Simpson and S. franciscanus
              Agassiz) as food by the white sea urchin (Lytechinus anamesus Clark) in the field and
              laboratory. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology 105:21-38.</para>
            <para>Curtner, W. W. 1917. Observations on the growth and habits of the red and black
              abalones. M. S. Thesis. Stanford University.</para>
            <para>Day, R. W. and R. W. Osman. 1981. Predation by Patiria miniata (Asteroidea) on
              bryozoans: Prey diversity may depend on the mechanism of succession. Oecologia
              51:300-309.</para>
            <para>Dean, T. A., F. R. Jacobsen, K. Thies, and S. L. Lagos. 1988. Differential effects
              of grazing by white sea urchins on recruitment of brown algae. Marine Ecology Progress
              Series 48:99-102.</para>
            <para>Domier, M. L. 2001. Giant sea bass. Pages 209-211 in W. S. Leet, C. M. Dewes, R.
              Klingbeil, and E. J. Larson, editors. California's Living Marine Resources: A Status
              Report. California Department of Fish and Game, Sacramento.</para>
            <para>Duggins, D. O. 1981. Sea urchins and kelp: The effects of short-term changes in
              urchin diet. Limnology and Oceanography 26:391-394.</para>
            <para>Ebert, D. A. and T. B. Ebert. 2005. Reproduction, diet and habitat use of leopard
              sharks, Triakis semifasciata (Girard), in Humboldt Bay, California, USA. Marine and
              Freshwater Research 56:1089-1098.</para>
            <para>Elliott, J. 1992. The role of sea anemones as refuges and feeding habitats for the
              temperate fish Oxylebius pictus. Environmental Biology of Fishes 35:381-400.</para>
            <para>Ellison, J. P., C. Terry, and J. S. Stephens. 1979. Food resource utilization
              among five species of embiotocids at King Harbor, California, with preliminary
              estimates of caloric intake. Marine Biology 52:161-169.</para>
            <para>Elorduy-Garay, J. and J. Caraveo-Pati&#241;o. 1994. Feeding habits of the ocean
              whitefish Caulolatilus princeps Jenyns 1842 (Pices: Branchiostegidae), in La Paz Bay,
              B.C.S., Mexico. Ciencia Marina 20:199-218.</para>
            <para>Engle, J. M. 1979. Ecology and growth of juvenile California spiny lobster,
              Panulirus interruptus (Randall). Ph. D. Thesis. University of California San
              Diego.</para>
            <para>Fitzgerald, S. A. 1979. Dietary habits and food preferences of Pugettia producta
              from the U.S. Coast Guard wharf and south jetty of the Bodega Harbor, Bodega Bay, CA.
              Problems in Marine Biology. Unpublished manuscript at Bodega Marine Laboratory.
              University of California Berkeley.</para>
            <para>Foster, M. S. and D. R. Schiel. 1985. The Ecology of Giant Kelp Forests In
              California: A Community Profile. Fish and Wildlife Service, U.S. Department of the
              Interior.</para>
            <para>Froese, R. and D. Pauly. 2009. FishBase. http://www.fishbase.org. Last accessed
              October 10, 2009.</para>
            <para>Gerard, V. A. 1976. Some aspects of material dynamics and energy flow in a kelp
              forest in Monterey Bay, California. Ph. D. Thesis. University of California Santa
              Cruz, Santa Cruz, CA.</para>
            <para>Graham, M. H., B. S. Halpern, and M. H. Carr. 2008. Diversity and dynamics of
              Californian subtidal kelp forests. Pages 103-134 in T. R. McClanahan and G. R. Branch,
              editors. Food Webs and the Dynamics of Marine Benthic Ecosystems. Oxford University
              Press.</para>
            <para>Grossman, G. D. 1986. Food resource partitioning in a rocky intertidal fish
              assemblage. Journal of Zoology (London) 1:317-355.</para>
            <para>Halliday, E. B. B. 1991. The natural history and ecology of Astraea undosa in a
              southern California kelp forest. M. S. Thesis. University of California Santa
              Cruz.</para>
            <para>Harris, L. G. 1991. Comparative ecology of subtidal actiniarians from the coasts
              of California and the Gulf of Maine, USA. Hydrobiologia 216-217:271-278.</para>
            <para>Harrold, C. 1981. Feeding ecology of the asteroid Pisaster giganteus in a kelp
              forest system: Prey selection, predator-prey interactions, and energetics. Ph. D.
              Thesis. University of California Santa Cruz.</para>
            <para>Hart, J. L. 1973. Pacific Fishes of Canada. Fisheries Research Board of Canada,
              Ottowa, Canada.</para>
            <para>Hartman, H. 1983. The Importance of body size in the subtidal ecology of Norrisia
              norrisii (Sowerby) (Gastropoda, Prosobranchia). Journal of Natural History
              17:247-255.</para>
            <para>Hartney, K. 1989. The foraging ecology of two sympatric gobiid fishes: importance
              of behavior in prey type selection. Environmental Biology of Fishes 26:105-118.</para>
            <para>Hilaski, R. 1972. Stomach contents of flatfish. M. A. Thesis. California State
              University Fresno, Moss Landing Marine Labs.</para>
            <para>Hines, A. H. 1982. Coexistence in a kelp forest: Size, population dynamics, and
              resource partitioning in a guild of spider crabs (Brachyura, Majidae). Ecological
              Monographs 52:179-198.</para>
            <para>Hobday, A. J. and S. M. Rumsey. 1999. Population dynamics of the sheep crab
              Loxorhynchus grandis (Majidae) Stimpson 1857 at La Jolla California. UC San Diego:
              Scripps Institution of Oceanography.</para>
            <para>Hobson, E. S. and J. R. Chess. 2001. Influence of trophic relations on form and
              behavior among fishes and benthic invertebrates in some California marine communities.
              Environmental Biology of Fishes 60:411-457.</para>
            <para>Holbrook, S. J., R. J. Schmitt, and J. A. Coyer. 1985. Age-related dietary
              patterns of sympatric adult surfperch. Copeia 1985:986-994.</para>
            <para>Howard, D. K. and K. R. Silerberg. 2001. Kelp Greenling.in W. S. Leet, C. M.
              Dewes, R. Klingbeil, and E. J. Larson, editors. California's Marine Living Resources:
              A Status Report. California Department of Fish and Game.</para>
            <para>Iampietro, P. J. 1999. Distribution, diet, and pigmentation of the northern kep
              crab, Pugettia producta (Randall) in central California kelp forests. M. S. Thesis.
              California State University Stanislaus.</para>
            <para>Johnson, D. W. 2006. Predation, habitat complexity, and variation in
              density-dependent mortality of temperate reef fishes. Ecology 87:1179-1188.</para>
            <para>Johnson, K. 2005. Pugettia can be a cannibal on itself. Unpublished work on file
              at the Bodega Marine Laboratory. Bodega Marine Lab.</para>
            <para>Johnson, M. E. and H. J. Snook. 1935. Seashore Animals of the Pacific Coast.
              Macmillan, New York.</para>
            <para>Kohn, A. J. 1966. Food specialization in Conus in Hawaii and California. Ecology
              47:1041-1043.</para>
            <para>Korb, R. 2003. Lack of dietary specialization in adult Aplysia californica:
              evidence from stable carbon isotope composition. Journal of the Marine Biological
              Association of the UK 83:501-505.</para>
            <para>Kosman, E. T., M. A. Colton, and R. J. Larson. 2007. Feeding preferences and
              size-related dietary shifts of treefish (Scorpaenidae: Sebastes serriceps) off
              southern California. California Fish and Game 93:40-48.</para>
            <para>Krekorian, C. O., D. C. Sommerville, and R. F. Ford. 1974. Laboratory study of
              behavioral interactions between the American lobster, Homarus americanus and the
              California spiny lobster, Panulirus interruptus with comparative observations on the
              rock crab. Fisheries Bulletin 72:1146-1159.</para>
            <para>Kupfermann, I. and T. J. Carew. 1974. Behavior patterns of Aplysia californica in
              its natural environment. Behavioral Biology 12:317-337.</para>
            <para>Landenberger, D. E. 1968. Studies on selective feeding in the Pacific starfish
              Pisaster in Southern California. Ecology 49:1062-1075.</para>
            <para>Larson, R. J. 1972. The food habits of four kelp-bed rockfishes (Scorpaenidae,
              Sebastes) off Santa Barbara, California. M. A. Thesis. University of California Santa
              Barbara.</para>
            <para>Leighton, D. and R. A. Boolootian. 1963. Diet and growth in the black abalone,
              Haliotis cracerodii. Ecology 44:228-238.</para>
            <para>Leighton, D. L. 1959. Diet and its relation to growth in the black abalone,
              Haliotis cracherodii Leach. M. S. Thesis. University of California Los Angeles.</para>
            <para>Leighton, D. L. 1966. Studies of food preference in algivorous invertebrates of
              Southern California kelp beds. Pacific Science 20:104-113.</para>
            <para>Limbaugh, C. 1955. Fish life in the kelp beds and the effects of kelp harvesting.
              University of California San Diego.</para>
            <para>Lindberg, R. G. 1955. Growth, population dynamics, and field behavior in the spiny
              lobster, Panulirus interruptus (Randall). University of California Publications in
              Zoology 59:157-248.</para>
            <para>Lonhart, S. I. 2001. An invasive whelk as predator and prey: The ecology of
              Kelletia kelletii in Monterey Bay, California. Ph. D. Thesis. University of California
              Santa Cruz.</para>
            <para>Love, M. 1996. Probably More Than You Want to Know About the Fishes of the Pacific
              Coast. Really Big Press, Santa Barbara, CA.</para>
            <para>Love, M. S., M. M. Yoklavich, and L. Thorsteinson. 2006. The Rockfishes of the
              Northeast Pacific. University of California Press.</para>
            <para>MacGinitie, G. E. 1937. Notes on the natural history of several marine Crustacea.
              American Midland Naturalist 18:1031-1037.</para>
            <para>Mauzey, K. P., C. Birkeland, and P. K. Dayton. 1968. Feeding behavior of asteroids
              and escape responses of their prey in the Puget Sound region. Ecology
              49:603-619.</para>
            <para>Morris, R. H., D. R. Abbott, and E. C. Haderlie. 1980. Intertidal Invertebrates of
              California. Stanford University Press.</para>
            <para>Murie, D. J. 1995. Comparative feeding ecology of two sympatric rockfish
              congeners, Sebastes caurinus (copper rockfish) and S. maliger (quillback rockfish).
              Marine Biology 124:341-353.</para>
            <para>Nakashima, R. 1974. Asteroid predation in Monterey Bay. B. S. Thesis. University
              of California Santa Barbara.</para>
            <para>Nichols, A. W. 1979. Predation by tidepool and nearshore fishes and its impact on
              the rocky intertidal zone community. Unpublished manuscript on file at Hopkins Marine
              Station Laboratory. Hopkins Marine Stations.</para>
            <para>O'Connell, C. P. 1953. The life history of the cabezon Scorpaenichthys marmoratus
              (Ayres). M. A. Thesis. Stanford.</para>
            <para>Page, H. M., J. E. Dugan, D. M. Schroeder, M. M. Nishimoto, M. S. Love, and J. C.
              Hoesterey. 2007. Trophic links and condition of a temperate reef fish: comparisons
              among offshore oil platform and natural reef habitats. Marine Ecology Progress Series
              344:245-256.</para>
            <para>Paul, A. J. and J. M. Feder. 1975. The food of the seastar Pycnopodia
              helioanthoides (Brandt) in Prince William Sound, Alaska. Ophelia 14:15-22.</para>
            <para>Pennings, S. C. 1962. The ecology of Aplysia californica at Santa Catalina Island,
              CA: recruitment, specialization, and predation risk. Ph. D Thesis. University of
              California Santa Barbara, Santa Barbara, CA.</para>
            <para>Pennings, S. C. 1990. Size-related shifts in herbivory: specialization in the sea
              hare Aplysia californica Cooper. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology
              142:43-61.</para>
            <para>Pennings, S. C. 1991. Spatial and temporal variation in recruitment of Aplysia
              californica Cooper: Patterns, mechanisms and consequences. Journal of Experimental
              Marine Biology and Ecology 146:253-274.</para>
            <para>Perez, M. M. 1981. The possible relationship between the feeding guilds of
              selected species of rockfish (Scorpaenidae) and surfperch (Embiotocidae) and their
              diet related parasites. B. A. Thesis. University of California Santa Cruz.</para>
            <para>Quast, J. 1968. Observations on the food of the kelp-bed fishes. Pages 109-142 in
              W. J. N. a. C. L. Hubbs, editor. Utilization of kelp-bed resources in southern
              California. California Department of Fish and Game, Fish Bulletin.</para>
            <para>Raith, M. R. 2007. Feeding preferenes of the marine gastropod Aplysia vaccaria.
              B.S. Thesis. California State University Fullerton.</para>
            <para>Robbins, E. A. 2006. Essential fish habitat in Santa Monica bay, San Pedro Bay,
              and San Diego Bay: A reference guide for managers. M. S. Thesis. Duke
              University.</para>
            <para>Roberts, D. A. 1979. Food habits as an ecological partitioning mechanism in the
              nearshore rockfishes (Sebastes) of Carmel Bay, CA. M. S. Thesis. San Francisco State
              University.</para>
            <para>Roberts, D. A., E. E. DeMartini, and K. M. Plummer. 1984. The feeding habits of
              juvenile-small adult barred sand bass (Paralabrax nebulifer) in nearshore waters off
              northern San Diego county. CalCOFI Reports 25:105-111.</para>
            <para>Robles, C. and J. Robb. 1993. Varied carnivore effects and the prevalence of
              intertidal algal turfs. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology
              166:65-91.</para>
            <para>Robles, C., D. A. Sweetnam, and D. Dittman. 1989. Diel variation of intertidal
              foraging by Cancer productus in British Columbia. Journal of Natural History
              23:1041-1049.</para>
            <para>Rohwer, S. 1978. Parent cannibalism of offspring and egg raiding as a courtship
              strategy. The American Naturalist 112:429-440.</para>
            <para>Rosenthal, R. J. and J. R. Chess. 1972. A predator-prey relationship between the
              leather star, Dermasterias imbricata, and the purple urchin, Strongylocentrotus
              purpuratus. Fishery Bulletin (Seattle) 70:205-216.</para>
            <para>Rosenthal, R. J., W. D. Clarke, and P. K. Dayton. 1974. Ecology and natural
              history of a stand of giant kelp, Macrocystis pyrifera, off Del Mar, California.
              Fishery Bulletin 72:670-684.</para>
            <para>Scanland, T. B. 1971. Effects of predation on epifaunal assemblages in a submarine
              canyon. Ph. D. Thesis. University of California San Diego.</para>
            <para>Schiel, D. R. and B. C. Welden. 1987. Responses to predators of cultured and wild
              red abalone, Haliotis rufescens, in laboratory experiments. Aquaculture
              60:173-188.</para>
            <para>Schmitt, R. J. 1982. Consequences of dissimilar defenses against predation in a
              subtidal marine community. Ecology 63:1588-1601.</para>
            <para>Schmitt, R. J. 1987. Indirect interactions between prey: Apparent competition,
              predator aggregation, and habitat segregation. Ecology 68:1887-1897.</para>
            <para>Shiviji, M., D. Parker, B. Hartwick, M. J. Smith, and N. A. Sloan. 1983. Feeding
              and distribution study of the sunflower sea star Pycnopodia helianthoides (Brandt,
              1835). Pacific Science 37:133-140.</para>
            <para>Steele, M. A. 1997. The relative importance of processes affecting recruitment of
              two temperate fishes. Ecology 78:129-145.</para>
            <para>Stewart, J. and W. F. Gilly. 2005. Piscivorous behavior of a temperate cone snail,
              Conus californicus. Biology Bulletin 209:146-153.</para>
            <para>Taylor, P. B. and L.-C. Chen. 1969. The predator-prey relationship between the
              octopus (Octopus bimaculatus) and the California scorpionfish (Scorpaena guttata).
              Pacific Science 23.</para>
            <para>Tullis, R. E., J. L. Carter, and G. W. Lanlois. 1981. Salton Sea Sampling Program:
              Baseline Studies. Lawrence Livermore Laboratory.</para>
            <para>Tutschulte, T. C. and J. J. Connell. 1988. Feeding behavior and algal food of
              three species of abalones (Haliotis) in southern California. Marine Ecology Progress
              Series 49:57-64.</para>
            <para>Vadas, R. L. 1977. Preferential feeding: An optimization strategy in sea urchins.
              Ecological Monographs 47:337-371.</para>
            <para>Van Dykhuizen, G. S. 1983. Activity patterns and feeding chronology of the kelp
              rockfish, Sebastes atrovirens, in a central California kelp forest. M. S. Thesis. San
              Jose State University.</para>
            <para>Van Veldhuizen, H. D. 1978. Feeding biology of subtidal Pisaster brevispinus on
              soft substrate in Bodega Harbor, California. Ph. D. Thesis. University of California
              Davis.</para>
            <para>Van Veldhuizen, H. D. and D. W. Phillips. 1978. Prey capture by Pisaster
              brevispinus (Asteriodea: Echinodermata) on Soft Substrate. Marine Biology
              48:89-97.</para>
            <para>Wiley, J. W. 1973. Life history of the western North American goby, Coryphopterus
              nicholsii (Bean). Transactions of the San Diego Society of Natural History
              17:187-208.</para>
            <para>Winget, R. R. 1968. Trophic relationships and metabolic energy budget of the
              California spiny lobster, Panulirus interruptus (Randall). M. S. Thesis. San Diego
              State College.</para>
            <para>Winkler, L. R. and E. Y. Dawson. 1963. Observations and experiments on the food
              habits of California Sea Hares of the genus Aplysia. Pacific Science
              17:102-105.</para>
            <para>Yang, M. S. and P. A. Livingston. 1986. Food habits and diet overlap of two
              congeneric species, Atherestes stomias and Atherestes evermanni, in the Eastern Bering
              Sea. Fishery Bulletin (Seattle) 82:615-623.</para>
            <para>Zimmer-Faust, R. K. 1982. The influence of odors on food search: studies with
              marine decapod Crustacea. Ph. D. Thesis. University of California Santa
              Barbara.</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>Santa Barbara Coastal Long Term Ecological Research Project</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
          <givenName>Daniel</givenName>
          <surName>Reed</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>Marine Science Institute</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>University of California</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Santa Barbara</city>
          <administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>93106-6150</postalCode>
          <country>United States</country>
        </address>
        <phone phonetype="voice">805 893 8363</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>reed@lifesci.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
          <givenName>John</givenName>
          <surName>Melack</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>Bren School of Environmental Science and Management</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>University of California</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Santa Barbara</city>
          <administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>93106-5131</postalCode>
          <country>United States</country>
        </address>
        <phone phonetype="voice">805 893 3879</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>melack@lifesci.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Co-principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
          <givenName>Sally</givenName>
          <surName>Holbrook</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>Ecology, Evolution and Marine Biology</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>University of California</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Santa Barbara</city>
          <administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>93106-9620</postalCode>
          <country>United States</country>
        </address>
        <phone phonetype="voice">805 893 3777</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>holbrook@lifesci.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Co-principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
          <givenName>David</givenName>
          <surName>Siegel</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>Institute for Computational Earth System Science</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>University of California</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Santa Barbara</city>
          <administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>93106-3060</postalCode>
          <country>United States</country>
        </address>
        <phone phonetype="voice">805 893 4547</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>davey@icess.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Co-principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <abstract>
        <section>
          <para>The primary research objective of the Santa Barbara Coastal LTER is to investigate
            the importance of land and ocean processes in structuring giant kelp
            (<emphasis>Macrocystis pyrifera</emphasis>) forest ecosystems. As in many temperate
            regions, the shallow rocky reefs in the Santa Barbara Channel, California, are dominated
            by giant kelp forests. Because of their close proximity to shore, kelp forests are
            influenced by physical and biological processes occurring on land as well as in the open
            ocean. SBC LTER research focuses on measuring and modeling the patterns, transport, and
            processing of material constituents (e.g., nutrients, carbon, sediment, organisms, and
            pollutants) from terrestrial watersheds and the coastal ocean to these reefs.
            Specifically, we are examining the effects of these material inputs on the primary
            production of kelp, and the population dynamics, community structure, and trophic
            interactions of kelp forest ecosystems.</para>
        </section>
      </abstract>
      <funding>
        <section>
          <para>NSF Awards OCE-9982105, OCE-0620276, OCE-1232779</para>
        </section>
      </funding>
    </project>
    <dataTable id="ent01">
      <entityName>Byrnes, foodweb table_1</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Feeding relationships for kelp forest species</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>byrnes_foodweb_table1.csv</objectName>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <collapseDelimiters>no</collapseDelimiters>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url function="download">http://sbc.lternet.edu/external/Reef/Data/Kelp_Forest_Foodweb/byrnes_foodweb_table1.csv</url>
          </online>
          <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst">
            <allow>
              <principal>uid=SBC,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
              <permission>all</permission>
            </allow>
            <allow>
              <principal>public</principal>
              <permission>read</permission>
            </allow>
          </access>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute id="Predator">
          <attributeName>Predator</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Predator</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Predator name or code</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>any text</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="Prey">
          <attributeName>Prey</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Prey</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Prey name or code</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>any text</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="Pred_taxon">
          <attributeName>Pred_taxon</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Pred_taxon</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Predator's species binomial</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>any text</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="Prey_taxon">
          <attributeName>Prey_taxon</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Prey_taxon</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Prey's species binomial</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>any text</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="Feeding_link">
          <attributeName>Feeding_link</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Feeding Link</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Boolean value indicating whether a predator is documented to feed on the prey</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">integer</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain enforced="yes">
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>0</code>
                    <definition>false</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>1</code>
                    <definition>true</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="Specificity">
          <attributeName>Specificity</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Specificity</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>lowest level of taxonomic certainty for the feeding relationship. Groups refers to an aggregated taxonomic listing in the SBC LTER (see methods)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain enforced="yes">
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Family</code>
                    <definition>Taxanomic Family</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Genus</code>
                    <definition>Taxanomic Genus</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Group</code>
                    <definition>Taxanomic Group</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Species</code>
                    <definition>Taxanomic Species</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>-99999</code>
            <codeExplanation>value not recorded or not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="Reference">
          <attributeName>Reference</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Reference</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Literature references for this relationship</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>any text</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>-99999</code>
            <codeExplanation>value not recorded or not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute id="Notes">
          <attributeName>Notes</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Notes</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Text annotations to data observations</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>any text</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>-99999</code>
            <codeExplanation>value not recorded or not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>1820</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <ns2:unitList>
            </ns2:unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>