<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-cap.378.8" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0      http://data.gios.asu.edu/eml2_1_0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=CAP,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset id="378.378_1" system="gios_dataset">
    <alternateIdentifier system="gios_dataset">378</alternateIdentifier>
    <shortName>19apr2000_24cls_18cls_final.img</shortName>
    <title>Spectrally unmixed percent of impervious surface, soil, and vegetation cover in central Arizona-Phoenix, year 2000</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Soe</givenName>
        <surName>Myint</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Global Institute of Sustainability</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Arizona State University</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>PO Box 875401</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Tempe</city>
        <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>85287-5402</postalCode>
      </address>
    </creator>
    <pubDate>2008</pubDate>
    <language>en</language>
    <abstract>
      <para>Urban land covers (e.g., cement parking lots, asphalt roads, shingle rooftops, grass, tress, exposed soil) can only be recorded as either present or absent in each pixel when using traditional per-pixel classifiers. Sub-pixel analysis approaches that can provide the relative fraction of surface covers within a pixel may be a potential solution to effectively identifying urban impervious areas. Spectral mixture analysis approach is probably the most commonly used approach that models image spectra as spatial average of spectral signatures from two or more surface features. However, spectral mixture analysis does not account for the absence of one of the surface features or spectral variation within pure materials since it utilizes an invariable set of surface features. Multiple endmember spectral mixture analysis (MESMA) approach addresses these issues by allowing endmembers to vary on a per pixel basis. The MESMA technique was employed in this study to model Landsat ETM+ reflectance in the Phoenix metropolitan area. Field spectra of vegetation, soil, and impervious surface areas collected with the use of a fine resolution Quickbird image and pixel purity index tool in ENVI software were modeled as reference endmembers in addition to photometric shade that was incorporated in every model. This study employs thirty endmembers and six hundred and sixty spectral models to identify soil, impervious, vegetation, and shade in the Phoenix metropolitan area. The mean RMS error for the selected land use land cover classes range from 0.003 to 0.018. The Pearson correlation between the fraction outputs from MESMA and reference data from Quickbird 60 cm resolution data for soil, impervious, and vegetation were 0.7052, 0.7249, and 0.8184 respectively.</para>
    </abstract><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">Land-Use, Land-Cover and Land Architecture</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">disturbance patterns</keyword><keywordThesaurus>IPA and Core Area CAP Data Portal Controler</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="place">sonoran desert</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">phoenix</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">urban</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">metropolitan area</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">land architecture</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">land use changes</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">gis</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">database remote sensing gis applications</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">remote sensing</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">human environment feedback</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">landsat</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Climate, Ecosystems and People</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">impervious</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">vegetation cover</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">spectral unmixing</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">spectral mixture modeling</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">multiple endmember spectral mixture analysis</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">Land-Use, Land-Cover and Land Architecture</keyword><keywordThesaurus>Creator Defined Keyword Set</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">urban</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">land use</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">land cover</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">vegetation</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">abundance</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">methods</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">remote sensing</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">modeling</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">soil</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">reflectance</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary Keyword Set</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">caplter</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">central arizona phoenix longterm ecological research</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">arizona</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">caplter created</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">az</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">cap</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">arid land</keyword><keywordThesaurus>CAPLTER Keyword Set List</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet>
    
    
    
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <para>Copyright Board of Regents, Arizona State University. This dataset is released to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes subject to the following restrictions:</para>
        <para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>While CAP LTER will make every effort possible to control and document the quality of the data it publishes, the data are made available "as is".</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>CAP LTER cannot assume responsibility for damages resulting from mis-use or mis-interpretation of datasets or from errors or omissions that may exist in the data.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists that has resulted in data used in subsequent research.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>CAP LTER expects that any use of data from this server will be accompanied with the appropriate citations and acknowledgments.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>CAP LTER encourages users to contact the original investigator responsible for the data that they are accessing. Where appropriate, researchers whose projects are integrally dependent on CAP LTER data are encouraged to consider collaboration and/or co-authorship with original investigators.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>CAP LTER requests that users submit to the Global Institute of Sustainability, ASU, one copy of any publication resulting from the use of data obtained from this site.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>CAP LTER requests that users not redistribute data obtained from this site. However, links or references to this site may be freely posted.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url>http://data.gios.asu.edu/cap/HarvestListFileShow.php?id=378</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <singleDateTime>
          <calendarDate>2000-04-19</calendarDate>
        </singleDateTime>
      </temporalCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Central Arizona Phoenix</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-112.786534</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-111.571667</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>33.844955</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>33.191274</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <purpose>
      <para>The purpose of this dataset is to provide the CAP-LTER research community with remotely sensed estimation of percent impervious surface, soil, and green vegetation. The file has 5 layers: Layer 1 = Number of models Layer 2 = RMS errors Layer 3 = Percent soil Layer 4 = Percent impervious Layer 5 = Percent vegetation</para>
    </purpose>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>This geospatial analysis thas been concluded</para>
      </description>
      <maintenanceUpdateFrequency>asNeeded</maintenanceUpdateFrequency>
    </maintenance>
    <contact id="378.Datamanager">
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Global Institute of Sustainability</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>Arizona State University</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>POB 875402</deliveryPoint>
        <city>TEMPE</city>
        <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>85287-5402</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(480) 965 2975</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">(480) 965-8087</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>caplter.data@asu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Background information on subpixel analysis</title>
            <para>The traditional hard classifiers (e.g., minimum distance, Mahalanobis distance, maximum likelihood) can label each pixel only with one class. Information on the fractional amount of spatially mixed spectral signatures from different ground-cover features is not possible with the per-pixel classifiers (hard classifiers). Hence, the traditional classification of mixed pixels may lead to information loss, degradation of classification accuracy, and degradation of modeling quality in successive applications. Sub-pixel analysis that can provide the relative abundance of surface materials within a pixel is a potential solution to per-pixel classifiers especially when dealing with medium to coarse spatial resolution satellite sensor images.</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Linear Spectral Mixture Analysis (SMA)</title>
            <para>Linear spectral mixture analysis (SMA), which provides sub-pixel endmember abundance information, is probably the most commonly used approach of all subpixel analysis techniques. The approach is based on the assumption that the spectrum at each pixel is a linear combination of the spectra of all ground components within the pixel, and that the linear mixture coefficients are equal to the fractional area of each ground component in a pixel. The mathematical model of linear spectral mixture analysis can be defined as Xi =SUM(fkXik +ei) wher Xi = Total spectral reflectance of band i of a pixel k = number of endmembers fk = fraction of an endmember k within a pixel Xik = known spectral reflectance of endmember k within the pixel in band i ei = error term for band i The root mean square (RMS) error is given by: RMS = ((SUM ((ei)^2)))^0.5) / m where ei are the error terms for each of the m spectral bands considered. The above constrained least-squares estimate assumes the followings. SUM(fk) = 1 and 0&#8804; fk &#8804;1 Limitations of Linear SMA (1) linear spectral mixture classifier does not permit number of representative materials (endmembers) greater than the number of spectral bands. (2) An invariable set of endmembers to model the spectra in all pixels. This assumption could potentially fail to account for the fact that the number and type of land cover components within each pixel are highly variable. The endmembers used in SMA are the same for each pixel, regardless of whether the materials represented by the endmembers are present in the pixel.</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Multiple Endmember Spectral Mixture Analysis</title>
            <para>Multiple Endmember Spectral Mixture Analysis (MESMA) method, enables to establish for each pixel the best mixture model, corrects errors often inevitable in SMA. The MESMA differs from SMA because allows to vary, pixel by pixel, the number and the abundance of endmembers in the image. While SMA method considers only one mixture model, MESMA algorithm generates from endmember all possible subset models. The best-fit model is defined by the linear combination of the endmembers with least error when compared with the spectrum image. For each pixel model is calculated: (a) endmember fraction and (b) the root mean squared (RMS) error. This procedure defines the elements that constitute each pixel plus its relative abundance. The method adjustments a mixture model for each pixel with lowest error and generate abundance images of the endmembers. However, a difficulty to use MESMA method is the computational time that demands supercomputers</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <spatialRaster id="378.19apr2000_24cls_18cls_final">
      <entityName>Surface spectral analysis of vegetation cover</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Spectrally unmixed percent impervious surface, soil, and vegetation cover in CAPLTER</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>378.zip</objectName>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat>
            <formatName>Raster Dataset</formatName>
          </externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>http://data.gios.asu.edu/datasets/cap/378.zip</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList id="378.19apr2000_24cls_18cls_final.attributeList">
        <attribute id="378.19apr2000_24cls_18cls_final.Cell Value">
          <attributeName>Cell Value</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Value for Red Green and Blue bands</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">Integer</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Value for Red Green and Blue bands</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <spatialReference>
        <horizCoordSysName>WGS_1984_UTM_Zone_12N</horizCoordSysName>
      </spatialReference>
      <horizontalAccuracy>
        <accuracyReport>No vertical accuracy information is available for this
                    dataset.</accuracyReport>
      </horizontalAccuracy>
      <verticalAccuracy>
        <accuracyReport>No vertical accuracy information is available for this
                    dataset.</accuracyReport>
      </verticalAccuracy>
      <cellSizeXDirection>28.500000</cellSizeXDirection>
      <cellSizeYDirection>28.500000</cellSizeYDirection>
      <numberOfBands>5</numberOfBands>
      <rasterOrigin>Upper Left</rasterOrigin>
      <rows>2499</rows>
      <columns>3931</columns>
      <verticals>1</verticals>
      <cellGeometry>pixel</cellGeometry>
    </spatialRaster>
  </dataset>
</ns0:eml>