<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.78.255033" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Time Domain Reflectometry at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico, (1996-2005)</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>James</givenName>
      <surName>Gosz</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>jgosz@uidaho.edu </electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Sevilleta</givenName>
      <surName>Information Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Douglas I.</givenName>
      <surName>Moore</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER, 167 Castetter Hall, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>dmoore@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">9661</userId>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <pubDate>2010</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>This file contains hourly time-domain reflectometry (TDR) soil moisture data for 1996-2005.  A key  factor in a spatially explicit water-balance model is a measure of moisture in the soils over time.   This metric is crucial for both calibration and validation of such a model.  One of the best  methods of measuring soil moisture on a continuous basis is TDR.  Therefore, a network of TDR soil  moisture sensors was installed at all meteorological stations on the Sevilleta National Wildlife  Refuge.  At two of the sites the sensors were measured on an hourly basis in conjunction with  the meteorological variables.  At the four other sites the sensors were measured on a much less  frequent basis - about every two weeks.  Sensors were installed in pits in sets of five.   One sensor was installed vertically adjacent to the pit to measure the top 30 cm of soil.  The  other four were installed horizontally in the face of the pit at 5, 10, 20, and 40 cm.  Pits were  then backfilled.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>inorganic nutrients</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>measurements</keyword>
    <keyword>reflectance</keyword>
    <keyword>soil properties</keyword>
    <keyword>soil moisture</keyword>
    <keyword>water balance</keyword>
    <keyword>dataloggers</keyword>
    <keyword>moorings</keyword>
    <keyword>time domain reflectometry</keyword>
    <keyword>modeling</keyword>
    <keyword>soil</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>Personnel associated with the Data Collection / Data Processing: Karen Wetherill, Yang Xia, Terri Koontz, Amaris Swann, Michell Thomey, Jay McLeod,  Jim Elliott, Chelsea Crenshaw</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/1642</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: Deep Well is located on McKenzie Flats and is site of the longest running SEV LTER met station, number 40, which has been active since 1988.&#160; In addition to studies of meteorological variables, core line-intercept vegetation transects and line-intercept transects from the 1995 and 2001 Deep Well fires are sampled here.&#160; The mini-rhizotron study, blue and black grama compositional comparison, blue and black grama patch dynamics investigation, and kangaroo rat population assessement are all ongoing here.&#160; Deep Well Blue/Black Grama Mixed is also the location of the warming and monsoon experiments, as well as portions of the line-intercept and vegetation removal studies.
On August 4, 2009, a lightning-initiated fire began on the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge. By August 5, 2009, the fire had reached the area of Deep Well Blue/Black Grama Mixed.&#160; While portions of this site were burned, the entirety was not.&#160; See individual projects for further information on the effects of the fire.Vegetation: The vegetation of Deep Well Blue/Black Grama Mixed is Chihuahuan Desert Grassland, dominated by black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda) and blue grama (B. gracilis).  Other grasses found at the site include dropseeds (Sporobolus spp.) and threeawns (Aristida spp.).  Shrubs are uncommon but those that occur include Yucca glauca, Ephedra torreyi, and four-wing saltbush (Atriplex canescens). Herbaceous plants include Plantago purshii, Hymenopappus filifolius, and globe mallows (Sphaeralcea spp.).

 , </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1600</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1600</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Rio Salado is an ephemeral tributary of the Rio Grande on the west side of the Sevilleta NWR, flowing west by northwest to east by southeast. Rio Salado Grassland and Rio Salado Larrea are two study sites established in 1989. These sites were established&#160;as counterparts to sites at Five Points. Between 1989 and 1998, vegetation, litter decomposition, and ground dwelling arthropod and rodent populations were studied at both sites. Core studies at these sites were largely terminated in 1998, although rodent populations are still monitored at the Rio Salado Larrea site as the Small Mammal Exclosure Study's Larrea plots are co-located there. Rio Salado Grassland is the location of Met Station 44. The Rio Salado study sites are accessed by taking the San Acacia exit, going west and then taking the frontage road back north to the Sevilleta NWR gate.&#160; After entering the refuge turn left after 0.2 mi and take this road 1.4 mi to a "T" in the road at the power lines.&#160; An earthen berm stops road travel here and the met station is located about 300 m west on the blocked road. &#160; Vegetation: The Rio Salado Grassland site is Plains-Mesa Sand Scrub habitat characterized by
stabilized deep-sand dominated by coppice dunes of honey mesquite (Prosopis
glandulosa). Co-dominant shrubs are sand sagebrush (Artemesia filifolia) and
fourwing saltbush (Atriplex canescens), with winterfat (Krascheninnikovia
lanata), Mormon tea (Ephedra torreyana), broom indigobush (Psorothamnus
scoparius), soapweed yucca (Yucca glauca), and broom snakeweed (Gutierrezia
sarothrae) as other notable shrubs. One-seed juniper (Juniperus monosperma) is
present as well, especially along shallow washes. Compared to the Black Grama
Core Site, grass cover is sparse and dominated by poverty threeawn (Aristida
divaricata), Indian ricegrass (Oryzopsis hymenoides), mesa and spike dropseed
(Sporobolus cryptandrus and S. contractus), as well as patches of black grama
(Bouteloua eriopoda). Notable forbs included spectaclepod (Dimorphocarpa
wislizenii), tansy aster (Machaeranthera tanacetifolia), desert marigold
(Baileya multiradiata), Abert buckwheat (Eriogonum abertianum), dwarf gilia
(Ipomopsis pumila), rattlesnake weed (Chamaesyce albomarginata), blunt
tansymustard (Descarania obtusa), plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala),
and Rocky Mountain zinnia (Zinnia grandiflora)., siteid: 13</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.9267</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.9267</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.269</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.269</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1503</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1503</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: Bronco Well is located near the northern boundary of the Sevilleta NWR, approximately four miles west of the ATandT on the road to Red Tank.siteid: 14</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.934</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.934</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.406</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.406</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1547</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1547</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: Just north of UNM's Sevilleta Field Stationsiteid: 15</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.885</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.885</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.356</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.356</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1466</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1466</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Goat Draw Juniper Savanna Core Site was established in 1998 in order to provide data at the lower end of the transition from the Pinon-Juniper Woodland habitat at the Cerro Montoso site to Juniper Savanna.Vegetation: While the site is positioned between two ridgelines, the vegetation is best characterized as Juniper Savanna, dominated by one-seed juniper (Juniperus monosperma), scrub liveoak (Quercus turbinella), and grama grasses (Bouteloua curtipendula, B. gracilis, B. eriopoda, and B. hirsuta), with scattered Colorado pinyon pine trees (Pinus edulis) in the upper reaches. There is also a significant influence of Arroyo Riparian vegetation in the main arroyo, Goat Draw, and its tributaries., siteid: 39</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.5228246</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.5228246</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.41464054</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.41464054</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1790</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1790</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: This site is located in the foothills of the Sierra Ladrones on the west side of the Sevilleta NWR. Red Tank is a man-made earthen drainage pool and is the location of Met Station 43.  Research conducted at the site includes soil moisture and erosion studies  related to the Sierra Ladrone watershed project.Vegetation: The woody vegetation in this stream bed includes juniper (Juniperus monosperma), Brickellia californica, Apache plume (Fallugia paradoxa).  On the hills are Junipers and shrubs such as cane cholla (Opuntia imbricata), beargrass (Nolina microcarpa), and Oreganillo (Aloysia wrightii). The herbs in the washes include Lesquerella ovalifolia, and Mirabilis multiflora.  The grasses found at this site include three-awn (Aristida sp.), fluff-grass Erioneuron pulchellum, and  four species of grama grass (Bouteloua spp.).
, siteid: 12</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>107.036806</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>107.036806</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.398</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.398</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1766</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1766</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>1996-01-01</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2005-12-31</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <purpose>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>To measure moisture in soils at the field site over time.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </purpose>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>2/19/1996 - Douglas Moore:Jan 12, 1996 Sta 40 Installed probes in two more pits. Reprogrammed so data is being collected from all 15 probes.Jan 19, 1996 Sta 01 Installed probes in two more pits.Jan 19, 1996 Sta 44 Replaced probe w3_30 which had been chewed off by rodent.Jan 30, 1996 Sta 41 Installed probes in Pit 1.Feb 07, 1996 Sta 45 Installed probes in two more pits.Feb 09, 1996 Sta 01 Installed datalogger, TDR enclosure and multiplexer. Installed program to collect data.Feb 14, 1996 Sta 01 Replaced w1_10 probe. Changed program so battery voltage is collected.Feb 23, 1996 Sta 42 Installed probes in two more pits.Feb 28, 1996 Sta 40 Began having problems with data - missing hours or getting -699 due to dying internal battery in reflectometer.Mar 08, 1996 Sta 40 Pulled reflectometer out to send back to Campbell.Mar 12, 1996 Sta 01 Pulled reflectometer out to put in at Sta 40.Mar 12, 1996 Sta 40 Put reflectometer from Sta 1 into Sta 40.Mar 20, 1996 Sta 43 Installed probes in two pits (except w2_30).Mar 27, 1996 Sta 41 Installed probes in a second pit.Apr 01, 1996 Sta 41 Replaced faulty w2_30 probe.Apr 08, 1996 Sta 43 Installed w2_30 probe.12/15/1998: Douglas Moore:&#160;Jan 22, 1997 Sta 44 Replaced TDR meter with one from field station.Jan 22-April 04, 1997 Sta 40 W1_5 bad data replaced with- 999.Apr 16, 1997 Sta 40 New w2_5 - 5 cm probe in pit B.Apr 30-May 07, 1997 Sta 01 Missing data - Lost power to datalogger.May 14-May 21, 1997 Sta 01 Missing data - Forgot to turn reflectometer on after returning to shelter.Aug 01-Aug 20, 1997-Sta 40 w2_30 data bad changed to -999.Aug 20, 1997 Sta 40 Replaced w2_30 sensor.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
      <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Analytical Procedures:Probes were measured every hour and collected propogating velocities were converted to soil moisture values using the Ledieu calibration. Each probe was run in sequence and the 15 probes could take 4 or 5 minutes to read.Sampling Design:Three sites were designated as water-balance monitoring sites: 1.) Deep Well - Met 40, 2.) Rio Salado - Met 44 and 3.) Field Station Sta1. At these sites replicate TDR probes were installed at specific depths while other probes were installed vertically to get an average soil moisture for the top 30 cm of soil.Measurement Techniques: Time Domain Reflectometry:TDR measures the reflectance of an electromagnetic pulse down a probe. This reflectance is affected by the amount of moisture in the soil surrounding the probe. Algorithms have been developed relating reflectance to volumetric soil moisture that work for most soils. The Campbell system has a built in program which reads the inflection points of the wave-form and automatically outputs soil moisture.Locations where measurements were taken by year:1996:1, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44, 451997:1, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44, 451998:1, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44, 451999:40,44,12000:40,422001:40,422002:402003:402004:402005:40</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
      <instrumentation>Instrumentation:   CR10 Datalogger; Tecktronx 1502B Cable Tester; Multiplexer SDMX50; TDR probe 30 cmInstrument Name: Soil Moisture Potential Probe Manufacturer: Campbell Scientific Model Number: 227</instrumentation>
    </methodStep>
    <qualityControl>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>This data was QA'd/QC'd.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </qualityControl>
  </methods>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>sev078_tdr_12092011.txt</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data SEV078</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>sev078_tdr_12092011.txt</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
          <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url>http://sev.lternet.edu/sites/default/files/data/sev-78/sev078_tdr_12092011.txt</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1996-01-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2005-01-01</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Station ID</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Station_ID</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Station ID Number</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>40</code>
                  <definition>Deep Well Site</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>41</code>
                  <definition>South Gate Site</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>42</code>
                  <definition>Cerro Montosa Site</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>43</code>
                  <definition>Watersheds Site</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>44</code>
                  <definition>Rio Salado Site</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>45</code>
                  <definition>Bronco Well Site</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>46</code>
                  <definition>Langmuir Site</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>47</code>
                  <definition>Bosque Del Apache</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>48</code>
                  <definition>Blue Springs</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>49</code>
                  <definition>Five Points</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>50</code>
                  <definition>Blue Grama</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>01</code>
                  <definition>Headquarters</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Year</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Year</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The year in which the data were collected.  </attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Julian Day</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Jul_Day</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Interval of time in days since the beginning of the year. Day of the year data collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>DDD</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Hour</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Hour</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Hour data logged in Military Time. Time basis is Mountain Standard Time.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>hour</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">24</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Soil Moisture 0-30 cm Pit A</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>w1_30</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil Moisture (volumetric) in 0-30 cm horizon</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Soil Moisture 5 cm Pit A</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>w1_5</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil Moisture (volumetric) at 5 cm</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Soil Moisture 10 cm Pit A</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>w1_10</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil Moisture (volumetric) at 10 cm </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Soil Moisture 20 cm Pit A</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>w1_20</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil Moisture (volumetric) at 20 cm</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Soil Moisture 40 cm Pit A</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>w1_40</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil Moisture (volumetric) at 40 cm</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Soi Moisture 0-30 cm Pit B</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>w2_30</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil Moisture (volumetric) in 0-30 cm horizon</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Soil Moisture 5 cm Pit B</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>w2_5</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil Moisture (volumetric) at 5 cm</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Soil Moisture 10 cm Pit B</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>w2_10</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil moisture (volumetric) at 10 cm </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Soil Moisture 20 cm Pit B</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>w2_20</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil moisture (volumetric) at 20 cm</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Soil Moisture 40 cm Pit B</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>w2_40</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil Moisture (volumetric) at 40 cm</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Soil Moisture 0-30 cm Pit C</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>w3_30</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil moisture (volumetric) in 0-30 cm horizon</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Soil Moisture 5 cm Pit C</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>w3_5</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil moisture (volumetric) at 5 cm</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Soil Moisture 10 cm Pit C</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>w3_10</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil moisture (volumetric) at 10 cm</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Soil Moisture 20 cm Pit C</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>w3_20</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil moisture (volumetric) at 20 cm</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Soil Moisture 40 cm Pit C</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>w3_40</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Soil Moisture (volumetric) at 40 cm</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit abbreviation="%" constantToSI="0" id="percent" multiplierToSI="100" name="percent" parentSI="numberPerNumber" unitType="dimensionless"><ns2:description>ratio of two quantities as percent composition (1:100)</ns2:description></ns2:unit>
    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>