<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.154.259233" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Hydraulic Constraints on Two Life History Stages of Larrea tridentata in a Chihuahuan Desert Creosote Shrubland at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico (2002-2003)</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Juliana</givenName>
      <surName>Medeiros</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>jmedeiros@ku.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">13117</userId>
  </creator>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Juliana</givenName>
      <surName>Medeiros</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>jmedeiros@ku.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">13117</userId>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Juliana</givenName>
      <surName>Medeiros</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>jmedeiros@ku.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">13117</userId>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <pubDate>2010</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>Maintaining high rates of water loss during times of high resource availability could allow  establishing woody desert perennials to grow quickly by allowing them to take advantage of the  fleeting but abundant monsoonal moisture typical of warm deserts like the Chihuahuan.  However, a  plant cannot endlessly increase water loss in order to grow faster --there are hydraulic  constraints on rates of water loss.  The hydraulic properties of each particular plant xylem and  soil microsite, as well as the AR:AL  absorbing root area to transpiring leaf area ratio) interact  to set limits on rates of water loss. If transpiration rates become too high, cavitation may limit  the ability of the xylem to supply water to the leaves.  The main objective of this study was to  test two hypotheses on a population of Larrea tridentata at the Sevilleta LTER in central New  Mexico (1) do small plants grow faster and use water less conservatively than large, and (2) are  there  differences in the hydraulic constraints on small and large plants. Measurements were made  every six weeks in the spring, summer and fall from April 2002 - August 2003. Field measurements of  shoot growth, gas exchange and plant and soil water potentials were made to determine growth rates  and water use.  Measurements of leaf specific conductance determined the ability of the xylem to  supply water to the leaves. Excavation findings were used to estimate (AR:AL).  Xylem vulnerability  curves and soil texture analysis were used to determine the hydraulic properties of the plant xylem  and soil.  A model determined where the limiting conductance occurred in the plant-soil continuum.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>inorganic nutrients</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>measurements</keyword>
    <keyword>conductivity</keyword>
    <keyword>specific conductivity</keyword>
    <keyword>transpiration</keyword>
    <keyword>water</keyword>
    <keyword>soil</keyword>
    <keyword>deserts</keyword>
    <keyword>plants</keyword>
    <keyword>leaves</keyword>
    <keyword>roots</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>&#160;Additional Information on the personnel associated with the Data Collection / Data Processing &#160;Joy Francis, a post-doc with Jim Gosz, was instrumental in setting up this study.  </literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/1458</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Five Points area emcompasses both the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote study sites.&#160; Five Points falls along the transition between the Chihuahuan Desert Scrub and Desert Grassland habitats.&#160; Both core sites are subject to intensive research activities, including NPP measurements, phenology observations, pollinator diversity studies, and ground dwelling arthropod and rodent population assessments.&#160; There are rain-out shelters for drought studies in both the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote sites.Vegetation: The Five Points Creosote site is characterized as Chihuahuan Desert Scrub, dominated by a creosote overstory, with broom snakeweed, purple pricklypear (Opuntia macrocentra), and soapweed yucca as co-occurring shrubs. The site is also characterized by numerous, dense, grass-dominated patches, reflecting proximity to the Five Points Black Grama Site.  Dominant grasses are black grama, fluffgrass (Dasyochloa pulchellum), burrograss (Scleropogon brevifolia), bushmuhly (Muhlenbergia porteri), and galleta (Pleuraphis jamesii).  Notable forbs include field bahia (Bahia absinthifolia), baby aster (Chaetopappa ericoides), plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala), Indian rushpea (Hoffmannseggia glauca), Fendlers bladderpod (Lesquerella fendleri), and globemallows (Sphaeralcea spp.)., siteid: 3</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2002-07-01</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2003-08-01</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
      <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Field Methods:For gas exchange measurements a LiCor 6400 portable gas exchange system was used.  Measurements  took place in June, August and September 2002 and May, June, and August 2003.  Two measurements  were made on each plant at approximately 7-9:30AM and 10-12:30PM.  One branch tip was chosen and  marked on each 10 small and 10 large plants.  The same branch tip was used for measurement  throughout the day unless it broke, at which time another branch tip was chosen and marked.   Stomatal Ratio was set to one because stomates are present on both sides of the leaf in this  species. Because of the small size of the leaves, an energy balance approach was used to calculate  the leaf temperature in the chamber.Chamber temperature and humidity were controlled at ambient  and reference CO2 was set to 400ppm.  Using natural light plants were clamped into the chamber,  oriented in their original direction, chamber conditions were allowed to stabilize.  Leaf area was  set to one during measurement.   Because of the small leaves of the species, a branch tip had to be  measured.  Measured branch tips were cut and returned to the lab where their leaf area was  measured.A Vista Scan Scanner was used to create an image of the leaves.  The bitmap image was  then analyzed for number of pixels using Scion Image.  A regression equation was developed which  converted pixel number into leaf area in cm2.The gas exchange data was then recalculated to  adjust for leaf area.For plant water potential a Scholander Pressure bomb was used to measure  branched stem tips consisting of 15-20 leaves and a woody base.  Predawn water potential samples  were collected between 4AM and 5AM.  Midday water potentials were collected between 11AM and 1PM.   Samples were placed into a plastic baggie with a moist paper towel during transport.  Samples were  collected in May, June, August, September and December 2002 as well as January, March, May, June  and August 2003.For whole plant hydraulic conductance measurements large sections of the xylem  were measured using a vacuum canister to generate known vacuum pressures.  The plant was attached  to a water filled container on a balance via tiagon tubing.  Changes in weight on the balance, and  thus flow rate (mg/s) through the plant were measured by a computer using a program written in  Turbo Pascal.   Each sample was measured at four or five pressures and the change in flow rate with  pressure was calculated as the total hydraulic conductance of all tissues contained in the sample.   All samples were immediately placed into a plastic bag with a wet paper towel and transported to  the lab where they were measured within 48 hours of collection.For large plants an entire stem of  the plant was cut at the base.  The stems were cut under water at the lab, to about 30cm.  For  small plants the entire plant was excavated, and any roots larger than about 2mm in diameter were  kept intact.  Back at the lab, most of the root system was cut off under water, leaving the root  collar and the initial un-branched portion of the main root which obviously supplied the entire  plant.  For both sizes, all green material was removed from the tips of the branches, leaving only  woody stems.The green portion of the plant included all leaves and sometimes large (up to 150mm) branched  sections.   For root hydraulic conductance measurements root segments +AD4-50cm were cut in the  field and transported to the lab wrapped tightly in 3 plastic bags containing wet paper towel.   Segments were re-cut underwater and the ends shaved off with a razor blade.  They were then placed  on a manifold and flow through the segment was measured.  Segments were then flushed for 15 minutes  with distilled water at 100kPa. Flow was then re-measured.  Percent loss of conductivity is  calculated as the difference between pre and post flush flow divided by post flush flow and  multiplied by 100.  Due to time constraints only one flush was performed on each sample.  For soil  water potential monitoring soil thermocouple psychrometers were placed under 4 large and 4 small  plants at 30cm and 45cm below the soil surface.  Measurements were made at or around 2AM when  temperature gradients were at a minimum.  A Campbell datalogger reported millivolt output which was  converted to MPa using calibrations determined in the lab.   Calibration involved regression of  millivolt output against solutions of known salt concentration for each psychrometer.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
  </methods>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>sev154_waterpot_07132009.txt</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data for SEV154</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>sev154_waterpot_07132009.txt</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url>http://sev.lternet.edu/sites/default/files/data/sev-154/sev154_waterpot_07132009_0.txt</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2002-07-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2003-08-01</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>id</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>id</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Plant identification number</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Plant identification number</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>height</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>height</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Height of plant canopy.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>centimeters</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>dia1</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>dia1</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Diameter of plant canopy</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>centimeters</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>dia2</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>dia2</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Diameter of plant canopy perpendicular to dia1.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>centimeters</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>canvol</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>canvol</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Volume of plant canopy calculated from height, dia1, and dia2 as the volume of a cone.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>cubic centimeters</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>size</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>size</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Size of creosote bush.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1 </code>
                  <definition> Large</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>2 </code>
                  <definition> Small</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>date</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>date</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Date of observation</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>MM-YY</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>photoam</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>photoam</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>AM measure of photosynthesis.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>micromol CO2/m2sec</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>condam</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>condam</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>AM measurement of stomatal conductance.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mol H20/m2sec</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>transam</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>transam</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>AM measurement of transpiration.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mmol H2O/m2/s</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>photomid</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>photomid</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Midday measurement of transpiration</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>micromol CO2/m2sec</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>conmid</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>conmid</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Midday measurement of stomatal conductance.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mol CO2 m-2 s-1</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>transmid</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>transmid</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Midday measurement of transpiration.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mmol CO2/m2/s</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>predawn</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>predawn</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Predawn water potential</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>megapascal</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>midday</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>midday</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Midday water potential.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>megapascal</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>presdrop</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>presdrop</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Difference between predawn and midday water potential.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>megapascal</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>LSC1</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>LSC1</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Native leaf specific conductance.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mg/s/m</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.0001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>LSC2</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>LSC2</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Leaf specific conductance after flushing to remove embolism.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>mg/s/m</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.0001</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>LSPLC</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>LSPLC</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Percent loss leaf specific conductivity, difference between native leaf specific conductance and leaf specific conductance after flushing embolism.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>+ACU-</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>rootPLC</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>rootPLC</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Root percent loss in conductivity</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>+ACU-</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>psy30</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>psy30</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Psychrometer reading at 30cm.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>megapascal</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1e-06</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>psy45</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>psy45</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Psychrometer reading at 45cm.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>megapascal</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1e-06</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit id="centimeters" />
<ns2:unit id="cubic centimeters" />
<ns2:unit id="micromol CO2/m2sec" />
<ns2:unit id="mol H20/m2sec" />
<ns2:unit id="mmol H2O/m2/s" />
<ns2:unit id="mol CO2 m-2 s-1" />
<ns2:unit id="mmol CO2/m2/s" />
<ns2:unit id="mg/s/m" />
<ns2:unit id="+ACU-" />
    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>