<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.166.122108" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>2003 Prescribed Burn Effect on Chihuahuan Desert Grasses and Shrubs at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico: Species Composition Study (2004- )</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Esteban</givenName>
      <surName>Muldavin</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>New Mexico Natural Heritage Program, Biology Department Castetter Hall 167, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>muldavin@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">9896</userId>
  </creator>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Scott</givenName>
      <surName>Collins</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, MSC03 2020, 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>scollins@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">12275</userId>
  </creator>
  <pubDate>2011</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>Disturbance from fire can affect the abundance and distribution of shrubs and grasses in arid ecosystems. In particular, fire may increase grass and forb production while hindering shrub  encroachment. Therefore, prescribed fires are a common management tool for maintaining grassland  habitats in the southwest. However, Bouteloua eriopoda (black grama), a dominant species in  Chihuahuan Desert grassland, is highly susceptible to fire resulting in death followed by slow  recovery rates.  A prescribed fire on the Sevilleta National Wildlife refuge in central New Mexico  in 2003 provided the opportunity to study the effects of infrequent fires on vegetation in this  region. This study was conducted along a transition zone where creosote bushes (Larrea tridentata)  are encroaching on a black grama grassland. Before and after the fire, above ground plant productivity  and composition were monitored from 2003 to present. Following the prescribed fire, there were fewer  individual grass clumps and less above ground grass cover in burned areas compared to unburned areas.  This decrease in productivity was primarily from a loss of B. eriopoda. Specifically, B. eriopoda  density and cover were significantly lower following the fire with a slow recovery rate in the five  years following the fire. Other grasses showed no such adverse response to burning.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>disturbance</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>species</keyword>
    <keyword>fires</keyword>
    <keyword>measurements</keyword>
    <keyword>field methods</keyword>
    <keyword>transects</keyword>
    <keyword>burning</keyword>
    <keyword>grasslands</keyword>
    <keyword>plants</keyword>
    <keyword>grasses</keyword>
    <keyword>shrubs</keyword>
    <keyword>vegetation</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>Additional Information on the personnel associated with the Data Collection/Data Processing:Mike Friggens 1999-September 2001Karen Wetherill February 7, 2000-August 2009Terri Koontz February 2000-August 2003 August 2006-PresentShana Pennington February 2000-August 2000Heather Simpson August 2000-August 2002Chris Roberts September 2001-August 2002Caleb Hickman September 9, 2002-November 15, 2004Seth Munson September 9, 2002-June 2004Maya Kapoor August 9, 2003-January 21, 2005Tessa Edelen August 15, 2004-August 15, 2005Charity Hall January 31, 2005-January 3, 2006Yang Xia January 31, 2005-August 2009Michell Thomey September 3, 2005-August 2008Jay McLeod January 2006-August 2006Amaris Swann August 25, 2008-January 2013John Mulhouse August 2009-PresentAmanda Boutz August 2009-2010Maya Kapoor April 2010-August 2010Stephanie Baker October 2010-PresentMegan McClung &#160;April 2013-Present</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/1500</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: McKenzie Flats is located within the northeastern section of the Sevilleta NWR, encompassing an area from Black Butte south  to Palo Duro Canyon and east to the Los Pinos.Landform: McKenzie Flats is a broad, nearly flat grassland plain between the Los Pinos Mountains and the breaks on the east side of the Rio Grande., Geology: Deep (20,000 ft) alluvial and aeolian deposits., Soils: Turney Series:  fine-loamy, mixed, thermic Typic Calciorthids.  Berino Series:  fine-loamy, mixed, thermic Typic Haplargids., Hydrology: Surface water only during rain events, no arroyos.  Run-on plain for Los Pinos Mountains., Vegetation: The terrain is generally a mixed-species desert grassland, dominated by black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda), blue grama (B. gracilis), sand muhly (Muhlenbergia arenicola), various drop seeds and sacatons (Sporobolus spp.), purple three-awn (Aristida purpurea), and burrow grass (Scleropogon brevifolia).  Shrubs are common in the area around Five Points, including creosote bush (Larrea tridentata) and snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae)., Climate: Long-term mean annual precipitation is 243 mm, about 60% of which occurs during the summer.  Long-term mean monthly temperatures for January and July are 1.5 degrees C and 25.1 degrees C, respectively., History: McKenzie Flats encompasses an area of approximately 50 square miles and was one of the primary livestock grazing areas within what is now the Sevilleta NWR.  Cattle have been excluded from the site since 1974-76.  The ranch headquarters buildings and corrals were located at the junction of Legs C and D of the coyote survey.  , siteid: 25</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>106.691</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>106.691</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2004-05-18</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2010-04-14</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <purpose>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>To study the effects of infrequent fires on shrub invasion in Chihuahuan desert grassland.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </purpose>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>Data were entered on a palmtop in the field. These files were then downloaded onto the server.   The files were run through a perl script and visually assessed for errors. Earlier data were  collected on paper and entered into an excel file. These data were checked row by row for any  errors. 4 March 2009 tlk Data were qa/qced and obvious errors were corrected. 11 January 2010 tlkData were qa/qc'd and errors corrected. Data was them imported into MySQL database.- A.Swann 14 November 2011</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
      <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Collection Site:The Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge is in Socorro County in central New Mexico. The Refuge is along a transition zone between several biomes: Great Plains Grassland, Colorado Plateau, and Chihuahuan Desert. The Burnx study is along a transition zone in the Chihuahuan Desert where the creosote shrubland is encroaching on the black grama grassland. Burnx plots are specifically located on the southern side of McKenzie Flats approximately 2 km southeast of Five Points. GPS coordinates for the Burnx study are: Datum: NAD-27 Latitude: 34 18' 18.0" N Longitude: 106 41' 09.6" WLocating Permanent Quadrats:Each replicate plot is 300 m x 300 m and contains a standard Sevilleta mammal trapping web which consists of 12 transects radiating from a central point. Each transect contains 12 numbered stakes for a total of 144 sample points per web. Vegetation is sampled in permanently located 50 cm x 50 cm quadrats at four evenly spaced points along each radius of each web transect (48 permanent quadrats per replicate). The end of each transect is marked with a long rebar stake with smaller rebar stakes occurring in 10 m increments towards the center of the web. Vegetation is measured in only the first four even numbered stakes from the end of the transect on the trapping web. For example, stakes 12, 10, 8, and 6 are measured for the transect that ends with stake 12.Data Collection:Vegetation is measured in the spring and fall each year. Spring measurements are taken in May when spring annuals have fully matured; and fall measurements are taken in September or October when summer annuals have fully matured and perennial species have reached their peak biomass for the year before the frost.Taking Measurements:One corner of a 50 cm x 50 cm quadrat is placed over the sampling stake with the diagonal of the quadrat pointing to the center of the web. The quadrat is placed on the inside of the stake relative to the center point. Cover measurements are taken with a quadrat that is divided in 10 cm x 10 cm sections. Cover of each species rooted in each quadrat is visually estimated in 1% intervals from 1-9%, then in 5% intervals from 10-100%. If a species has a cover less  less than 1%, the cover is recorded as 0.1%. Only annual plant species are measured in the spring while in the fall both annual and perennial species are measured.Recording Data:&#160;Data are recorded using a palmtop computer. Either a template for Burnx is already on the palmtop or a template must be created by the user. The template has the following fields: Date, Plot, Quad, Spp, Cover and Comments. Open or create Burnx template; save a file on the palmtop with the following format: burnx.mm.dd.yy.initinit. For example, if data was collected on May 13, 2008 by TK the file name would be burnx.05.13.08.tk.Study Design:Burnx plots were established in 1991 to study the effects of both fire and antelope disturbance. During the summer of 1993, a prescribed fire was applied to half of the fenced plots and half of the unfenced (open) plots. Therefore, the Burnx study includes four replicates of the following treatments: burned fenced (BF), burned open (BO), control fenced (CF), and control open (CO). In addition, a prescribed fire in 2003 was administered on two of the replicates (3 and 4) for all four treatments.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
    <qualityControl>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>Data were qa/qced and obvious errors were  corrected. 11 January 2010 tlk</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </qualityControl>
  </methods>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>sev166_burnxquad_11142013.txt</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data for SEV166.</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>sev166_burnxquad_11142013.txt</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url>http://sev.lternet.edu/sites/default/files/data/sev-166/sev166_burnxquad_11142013_0.txt</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2004-05-03</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2013-09-05</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>SPECIES</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>SPECIES</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The scientific name (genus and species) for each plant encountered in a sampling unit.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The scientific name (genus and species) for each plant encountered in a sampling unit.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>CODE</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>CODE</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Kartez code for species encountered in each sampling unit.  Kartez code is usually a four letter code followed by a number, which represents the first two letters of the genus and species.  For example, Bouteloua eriopoda the code is BOER4.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>NONE</code>
                  <definition>No plant species observed in sampling unit</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>GROWTH</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>GROWTH</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>If the species in ephemeral or not</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>A</code>
                  <definition>Annual plants</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>P</code>
                  <definition>Perennial plants</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code> NA</code>
                  <definition>not applicable meaning that sample unit either has no plants or the growth type is unknown.</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Species Type</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>SPPTYPE</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The 'type' of species that was recorded</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>G</code>
                  <definition>Grass</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>H</code>
                  <definition>Herb</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>S</code>
                  <definition>Shrub</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C</code>
                  <definition>Cactus</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>NA</code>
                  <definition>Not applicable, no species recorded for this sample unit or species type unknown.</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>YEAR</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>YEAR</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The year in which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>SEASON</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>SEASON</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The season that the data were recorded.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1</code>
                  <definition>Spring</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3</code>
                  <definition>Fall</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>PLOT</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>PLOT</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Plots distinctions from an earlier study that measured vegetation responses from a 1993 fire and antelope exclusion.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>XBO</code>
                  <definition>1993 burned opened</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>XCO</code>
                  <definition>control opened</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>XBF</code>
                  <definition>1993 burned fenced</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>XCF</code>
                  <definition>control fenced</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Quadrat</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>QUAD</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Quadrat associated with numbered stakes on the mammal trapping web for each plot. Values range from 1-144</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Quadrat associated with numbered stakes on the mammal trapping web for each plot. Values range from 1-144</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>COVER</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>COVER</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Percent cover for a given species</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">100</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Comments</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>COMMENTS</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Notes or comments for a particular observation for information not included in other data variables</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Notes or comments for a particular observation for information not included in other data variables</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit abbreviation="%" constantToSI="0" id="percent" multiplierToSI="100" name="percent" parentSI="numberPerNumber" unitType="dimensionless"><ns2:description>ratio of two quantities as percent composition (1:100)</ns2:description></ns2:unit>
    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>