<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.148.131882" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>2003 Prescribed Burn Effect on Chihuahuan Desert Grasses and Shrubs at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico: Grass Recovery Study (2003- )</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Esteban</givenName>
      <surName>Muldavin</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>New Mexico Natural Heritage Program, Biology Department Castetter Hall 167, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>muldavin@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">9896</userId>
  </creator>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Esteban</givenName>
      <surName>Muldavin</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>New Mexico Natural Heritage Program, Biology Department Castetter Hall 167, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>muldavin@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">9896</userId>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Douglas I.</givenName>
      <surName>Moore</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER, 167 Castetter Hall, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>dmoore@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">9661</userId>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Lydia</givenName>
      <surName>Zeglin</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>lydia.zeglin@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">13120</userId>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Scott</givenName>
      <surName>Collins</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, MSC03 2020, 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>scollins@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">12275</userId>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <pubDate>2010</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>The U.S. Fish and Wildlife's plan to apply a prescribed burn to a large portion of  Mckenzie Flats was deemed an opportunity to study the effects of fire on vegetation at the  boundary between shrubland and grassland.  This study actually was undertaken on an area that had  prescribed fire applied to 8 of 16 (300 m x 300 m) plots 10 years before in 1993.  This previous  study had also examined the effects of fencing to exclude the indigenous prong-horn antelope.  In  the 2003 study the prescribed fire was applied to the northeastern half of the 16 plots while the  southwestern plots were intentionally protected.  Sampling prior to the prescribed burn included  quantification of cover of grass species in quadrats within all of the 16 plots. Measurements were  made using "niner" quadrat frames that are 30 cm x  30 cm frames that are divided into 9 1-decimeter  squares. Counts of grass species were made just prior to the June 2003 burn. Following the prescribed  burn, quadrats were remeasured in the fall of 2003 to quantify mortality of grass species.  These  measurements continue to be taken each fall.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>disturbance</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>species</keyword>
    <keyword>plant species</keyword>
    <keyword>biology</keyword>
    <keyword>fires</keyword>
    <keyword>measurements</keyword>
    <keyword>burning</keyword>
    <keyword>grasslands</keyword>
    <keyword>plants</keyword>
    <keyword>grasses</keyword>
    <keyword>shrubs</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>Spring 2003 data were measurements done before the 2003 prescribed fire. Data collection is ongoing.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/1659</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: McKenzie Flats is located within the northeastern section of the Sevilleta NWR, encompassing an area from Black Butte south  to Palo Duro Canyon and east to the Los Pinos.Landform: McKenzie Flats is a broad, nearly flat grassland plain between the Los Pinos Mountains and the breaks on the east side of the Rio Grande., Geology: Deep (20,000 ft) alluvial and aeolian deposits., Soils: Turney Series:  fine-loamy, mixed, thermic Typic Calciorthids.  Berino Series:  fine-loamy, mixed, thermic Typic Haplargids., Hydrology: Surface water only during rain events, no arroyos.  Run-on plain for Los Pinos Mountains., Vegetation: The terrain is generally a mixed-species desert grassland, dominated by black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda), blue grama (B. gracilis), sand muhly (Muhlenbergia arenicola), various drop seeds and sacatons (Sporobolus spp.), purple three-awn (Aristida purpurea), and burrow grass (Scleropogon brevifolia).  Shrubs are common in the area around Five Points, including creosote bush (Larrea tridentata) and snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae)., Climate: Long-term mean annual precipitation is 243 mm, about 60% of which occurs during the summer.  Long-term mean monthly temperatures for January and July are 1.5 degrees C and 25.1 degrees C, respectively., History: McKenzie Flats encompasses an area of approximately 50 square miles and was one of the primary livestock grazing areas within what is now the Sevilleta NWR.  Cattle have been excluded from the site since 1974-76.  The ranch headquarters buildings and corrals were located at the junction of Legs C and D of the coyote survey.  , siteid: 25</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>106.691</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>106.691</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2003-06-09</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2009-10-22</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <purpose>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>To study the effects of fire on the vegetation at the boundary between shrubland and grassland.</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </purpose>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>2003 through 2008 data files were merged into one file.  Then, they were checked for obvious errors.  20 January 2009.  TLKchecked and corrected 2009 data for obvious errors, appended data to Navicat table. 12 January 2010 tlk&#160;</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
      <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Sampling:Within each 300 m x 300 m plot, 3 m  x 4 m quadrats were marked off with rebar for use in a previous burn experiment. Each of these quadrats also had a piece of rebar on the southern edge  of the quadrat with a numbered tag.  Six of these quadrats were randomly selected in each plot.  Measurements were made using a niner quadrat frame.  These frames are PVC squares that are 30 cm  x 30  cm and are divided off into 10 cm  x 10 cm squares with string.  This gives nine 1-decimeter squares  within the "niner".  The niner was placed over a corner rebar and aligned with the edge of the  larger 3 m x 4 m quadrat.  Counts were then made of the number of decimeters in which each species of grass was rooted.  Values can be 0 to 9. The designation for the 4 niners in each quadrat was A  through D starting with A in the SW corner, moving clockwise to D in the SE corner.Note: For the fall collection in 2003 it was virtually impossible to identify the species  of grass that had regrown following the fire. It was decided to just give a count of  decimeters with live grass rooted in them and identify them as "GRASS". &#160;With the fall moisture of  2003 there was a flush of annuals and it was decided to enumerate these with counts of any "forbs"  rooted in decimeters of each quadrat. &#160;This methodology was not repeated in subsequent years.Also, Quad 3084 was not recorded in the 2003 season 2 and any years following 2005. For Quad 3141, data were not measured for years following 2006. This was done to balance the dataset; each "pre" plot has six quadrats rather than some having seven.Specific location:&#160;Data were collected from 16  (300 m x 300 m) plots designated as the "Burn Antelope Exclosure" plots.  These plots are located on the southern end of Mckenzie Flats.  The plots are  laid out in a 4 by 4 square with 300 m buffer between each plot.  The plots are enclosed within a  440 ha box.The bounding coordinates of this large box are:&#160;&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; Latitude           LongitudeNW corner    34.3138           106.6926NE corner     34.3202           106.6711SE corner     34.3024           106.6634SW corner    34.2960           106.2960This large expanse has a variable mix of grass species.  The 2 dominant species are black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda) and blue grama (Bouteloua gracilis).  There are also sizeable  patches of mule grass (Scleropogon brevifolius).  A mixture of the dropseed species are present as well. These include Sporobolus cryptandrus, Sporobolus contractus, Sporobolus flexuosus and  Sporobolus airoides.  Galleta grass (Pleuraphis jamesii) and a couple of Muhlenbergia species are also present.  Into this grass matrix are mixed several shrubs and subshrubs.  The most noticeable shrub is creosote  bush (Larrea tridentata).  Other common non-grasses include Yucca glauca, Ephedra torreyana and Gutierrezia sarothrae.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
    <qualityControl>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>Data were recorded on paper datasheets.  Then this data were entered into an excel worksheet and  assessed for errors. Data are stored in Navicat table niners_grass in directory burnx. In 2009,  started distinguishing between field comments and QAQC comments. An '*' designates a QAQC comment.  SAS program is used to check for duplicates and that all data points have been recorded and entered.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </qualityControl>
  </methods>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>sev148_burnxgrass_12112013.txt</entityName>
    <physical>
      <objectName>sev148_burnxgrass_12112013.txt</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
          <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url>http://sev.lternet.edu/sites/default/files/data/sev-148/sev148_burnxgrass_12112013_0.txt</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2003-12-09</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2013-11-19</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Date</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Date</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Date when data were taken</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>DD/MM/YYYY</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Year</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Year</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The year in which the data were collected.  </attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Season</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Seas</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Season when data were taken</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>2</code>
                  <definition>Spring</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3</code>
                  <definition>Fall</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Line</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Line</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Line of plots where data were taken</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3</code>
                  <definition>Line of plots furthest from the road: these plots were given a prescribed fire in 2003</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>4</code>
                  <definition>Line of plots furthest from the road: these plots were given a prescribed fire in 2003</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1</code>
                  <definition>Line of plots closest to the road: these plots were not burned in 2003</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>2</code>
                  <definition> Line of plots closest to the road: these plots were not burned in 2003</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Pre-treatment</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Pre</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Treatment of previous experiment</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C-O</code>
                  <definition>Control open</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>B-O</code>
                  <definition>Burned open</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C-F</code>
                  <definition>Control fenced</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>B-F</code>
                  <definition>Burned fenced</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Quadrat</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Quad</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Quadrat that data were recorded from.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Quadrat that data were recorded from.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Corner</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Corner</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Corner of quadrat</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>A</code>
                  <definition>Southwest corner</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>B</code>
                  <definition>Northwest corner</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C</code>
                  <definition>Northeast corner</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>D</code>
                  <definition>Southeast corner</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Species</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Species</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Kartez code for species being sampled  based on the USDA  plants data base.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>LATR2 </code>
                  <definition> Larrea tridentata</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>NONE</code>
                  <definition> No plants were encountered on these plots</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>Annual</code>
                  <definition>Only could identify to annual</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>Grass</code>
                  <definition>Grass species that could not be identified to genus or species level</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>Forb</code>
                  <definition>Forb plant species that could not be identified to genus or species</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>UK1</code>
                  <definition>unknown plant species</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>UK2</code>
                  <definition>Unknown plant species</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>UKGR</code>
                  <definition>unknown plant species</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>SPORO</code>
                  <definition>Unknown Sporobolus species</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>JUMO</code>
                  <definition>Juniperus monosperma</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>PIED</code>
                  <definition>Pinus edulis</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>QUTU2</code>
                  <definition>Quercus turbinella</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Count</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Count</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Number of decimeters occupied by a species</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">9</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Burn status</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Sta</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Condition of area following the prescribed fire</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>U</code>
                  <definition>unburned</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>B</code>
                  <definition>burned</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>na</code>
                  <definition>not applicable, measurements taken before burn</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>NS</code>
                  <definition>not sure</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Comments</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Comment</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Any relevant comments during data collecting or QA/QC</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>NA</code>
                  <definition>no comment</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>*</code>
                  <definition>an asterisk designates that a comment is QA/QC comment, this was initiated in 2009</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
</ns0:eml>