<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.185.205949" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Burn Study Sites Seasonal Biomass and Seasonal and Annual NPP Data for the Net Primary Production Study at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico (2004- )</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Esteban</givenName>
      <surName>Muldavin</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>New Mexico Natural Heritage Program, Biology Department Castetter Hall 167, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>muldavin@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">9896</userId>
  </creator>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Kristin</givenName>
      <surName>Vanderbilt</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, MSC03 2020, 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>vanderbi@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">11054</userId>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Stephanie</givenName>
      <surName>Baker</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-8119</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>srbaker@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Megan</givenName>
      <surName>McClung</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico, 167 Castetter Hall, MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>mmcclung@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>John</givenName>
      <surName>Mulhouse</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico, 167 Castetter Hall, MSC03 2020</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      <country>United States of America</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>mulhouse@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">15417</userId>
    <role>field crew</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <pubDate>2011</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>In 2003, the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service  conducted a prescribed burn  over a large part of the northeastern  corner of the Sevilleta NWR. This  study was designed to look at the  effect of fire on above-ground net primary productivity (ANPP) within  different  vegetation types. Net primary production (NPP) is a  fundamental ecological variable that  measures rates of carbon  consumption and fixation. Estimates of NPP are  important in  understanding energy flow at a community level as well as  spatial and  temporal responses to a range of ecological processes. While measures of both below- and   above-ground biomass are important  in estimating total NPP, this study   focuses on above-ground net  primary production (ANPP).  Above-ground net  primary production (ANPP) is equal to the change in  plant mass,  including loss to death and decomposition, over a given  period of time.  To measure this change, ANPP is sampled twice a year  (spring and fall)  for all species in each of three vegetation types. In  addition,  volumetric measurements are obtained from adjacent areas to  build  regressions correlating biomass and volume. Three vegetation types were chosen for this study: mixed grass (MG),   mixed shrub (MS) and black grama (G). Forty permanent 1m x 1m plots  were installed in both  burned and unburned sections of each habitat  type. The core black grama site  included in SEV129 was incorporated  into this dataset as an unburned  control, so an additional  unburned G  site was not created. The data for this site is noted as site=G and  treatment=C (i.e., control). The  original mixed-grass unburned plot  caught fire unexpectedly in the fall of  2009 and was subsequently moved  to the south.Volumetric measurements are  made using vegetation data from permanent plots collected in SEV156,  "Burn Study Sites Quadrat Data for the Net Primary Production Study&#160;" and regressions  correlating biomass and volume constructed using seasonal harvest  weights from SEV157, "Net Primary Productivity (NPP) Weight Data."</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>disturbance</keyword>
    <keyword>primary production</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>community patterns</keyword>
    <keyword>plant communities</keyword>
    <keyword>plant ecology</keyword>
    <keyword>vegetation dynamics</keyword>
    <keyword>successional dynamics</keyword>
    <keyword>plant species composition</keyword>
    <keyword>species richness</keyword>
    <keyword>plant cover</keyword>
    <keyword>net primary productivity</keyword>
    <keyword>plant biomass</keyword>
    <keyword>aboveground biomass</keyword>
    <keyword>population and community properties</keyword>
    <keyword>long term</keyword>
    <keyword>seasonality</keyword>
    <keyword>permanent plots</keyword>
    <keyword>plant growth</keyword>
    <keyword>succession</keyword>
    <keyword>disturbance</keyword>
    <keyword>harvesting</keyword>
    <keyword>recovery</keyword>
    <keyword>deserts</keyword>
    <keyword>grasslands</keyword>
    <keyword>plants</keyword>
    <keyword>foliage</keyword>
    <keyword>grasses</keyword>
    <keyword>herbs</keyword>
    <keyword>forbs</keyword>
    <keyword>shrubs</keyword>
    <keyword>vegetation</keyword>
    <keyword>stems</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout>Other researchers involved with collecting samples/data: Megan McClung (MAM; 04/2013-present), Stephanie Baker    (SRB; 09/2010-present), John Mulhouse (JMM; 08/2010-present), Amaris Swann    (ALS; 08/2008-01/2013), Maya Kapoor (MLK; 08/2003-01/2005,    05/2010-03/2011), Terri Koontz (TLK; 02/2000-08/2003, 08/2006-08/2010), Yang Xia (YX; 01/2005-03/2010), Karen Wetherill (KRW;    02/2000-08/2009);  Michell Thomey (MLT; 09/2005-08/2008); Seth Munson (SMM; 09/2002-06/2004), Jay McLeod (JRM; 01/2006-08/2006); Caleb Hickman (CRH; 09/2002-11/2004), Charity Hall (CLH;  01/2005-01/2006); Tessa Edelen (MTE, 08/2004-08/2005).</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/1702</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: Five Points is the area which encompasses the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote Core study sites and falls along the transition between Chihuahuan Desert Scrub and Desert Grassland habitats. Both sites are subject to intensive research activity, including NPP measurement, phenology observation, pollinator diversity studies, and ground dwelling arthropod and rodent population assessments. There are drought rain-out shelters in both the Black Grama and Creosote sites, as well as the mixed-ecotone, with co-located ET Towers.Vegetation: The Five Points Creosote site is characterized as Chihuahuan Desert Scrub, dominated by a creosotebush overstory with broom snakeweed, purple pricklypear (O. macrocentra) and soapweed yucca as notable shrubs. The site is also characterized by numerous dense grass dominated patches, reflecting proximity to the Five Points Black Grama site and the relatively recent appearance of creosotebush. Dominant grasses are black grama, fluffgrass (Dasyochloa pulchellum), burrograss (Scleropogon brevifolia), bush muhly (M. porteri), and galleta (Pleuraphis jamesii). Notable forb species include field bahia (Bahia absinthifolia), baby aster (Chaetopappa ericoides), plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala), Indian rushpea (Hoffmannseggia glauca), Fendlers bladderpod (Lesquerella fendleri), and globemallow (Sphaeralcea spp.).  Five Points Black Grama habitat is ecotonal in nature, bordering Chihuahuan Desert Scrub at its southern extent and Plains-Mesa Grassland at its northern, more mesic boundary.  There is also a significant presence of shrubs, particularly broom snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae), along with less abundant fourwing saltbush (Atriplex canescens), Mormon tea (Ephedra torreyana), winterfat (Krascheninnikovia lanata), tree cholla (Opuntia imbricata), club cholla (O. clavata), desert pricklypear (O. phaeacantha), soapweed yucca (Yucca glauca), and what are presumed to be encroaching, yet sparsely distributed, creosotebush (Larrea tridentata).  Characteristically, the dominant grass is black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda). Spike, sand, and mesa dropseed grasses (Sporobolus contractus, S. cryptandrus, S. flexuosus) and sand muhly (Muhlenbergia arenicola) could be considered co-dominant throughout, along with blue grama (B. gracilis) in a more mesic, shallow swale on the site.  Notable forb species include trailing four o&#8217;clock (Allionia incarnata), horn loco milkvetch (Astragalus missouriensis), sawtooth spurge (Chamaesyce serrula), plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala), blunt tansymustard (Descarania obtusa), wooly plaintain (Plantago patagonica), globemallow (Sphaeralcea wrightii), and mouse ear (Tidestromia lanuginosa)., siteid: 2</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>106.717</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>106.717</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3381</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3381</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: Five Points Black Grama is on the transition between Chihuahuan Desert Scrub and Desert Grassland habitat. The site is subject to intensive research activity, including assessments of net primary productivity, phenology, and pollinator diversity, amongst other projects.&#160; It is the site of the unburned black grama (GU) component of the Burn NPP study.
On August 4, 2009, a lightning-initiated fire began on the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge. By August 5, 2009, the fire had reached the Five Points Black Grama site.&#160; Portions of this site were burned, but not the entirety.&#160; See individual projects for further information on the effects of the burn.
&#160;Vegetation: The Five Points Black Grama site is ecotonal in nature, bordering Chihuahuan Desert Scrub at its southern extent and Plains-Mesa Grassland at its northern, more mesic boundary. Characteristically, the dominant grass is black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda)., </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.736</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.736</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: McKenzie Flats is located within the northeastern section of the Sevilleta NWR, encompassing an area from Black Butte south  to Palo Duro Canyon and east to the Los Pinos.Landform: McKenzie Flats is a broad, nearly flat grassland plain between the Los Pinos Mountains and the breaks on the east side of the Rio Grande., Geology: Deep (20,000 ft) alluvial and aeolian deposits., Soils: Turney Series:  fine-loamy, mixed, thermic Typic Calciorthids.  Berino Series:  fine-loamy, mixed, thermic Typic Haplargids., Hydrology: Surface water only during rain events, no arroyos.  Run-on plain for Los Pinos Mountains., Vegetation: The terrain is generally a mixed-species desert grassland, dominated by black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda), blue grama (B. gracilis), sand muhly (Muhlenbergia arenicola), various drop seeds and sacatons (Sporobolus spp.), purple three-awn (Aristida purpurea), and burrow grass (Scleropogon brevifolia).  Shrubs are common in the area around Five Points, including creosote bush (Larrea tridentata) and snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae)., Climate: Long-term mean annual precipitation is 243 mm, about 60% of which occurs during the summer.  Long-term mean monthly temperatures for January and July are 1.5 degrees C and 25.1 degrees C, respectively., History: McKenzie Flats encompasses an area of approximately 50 square miles and was one of the primary livestock grazing areas within what is now the Sevilleta NWR.  Cattle have been excluded from the site since 1974-76.  The ranch headquarters buildings and corrals were located at the junction of Legs C and D of the coyote survey.  , siteid: 25</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>106.691</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>106.691</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The grassland burn (GB) site is located on the east side of the road toward Five Points from Deep Well.Vegetation: This is a Chihuahuan desert grassland dominated by black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda) with some dropseed (Sporobolus spp.)., siteid: 34</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.69596</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.69596</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.33498</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.33498</southBoundingCoordinate>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The mixed grass (MG) site includes a burned and an unburned area.&#160; The mixed grass unburned (MGU) site is located just to the southeast of the Deep Well weather station. The mixed grass burned (MGB) site is on the east side of the road north of Deep Well.On August 4, 2009, a  lightning-initiated fire began on the Sevilleta    National Wildlife  Refuge.&#160; The fire reached the mixed-grass unburned plots on August 5, 2009, consuming them in their entirety.&#160; As a result, in the spring of 2010, the mixed-grass unburned plots were moved to a different area within Deep Well, to the southwest of the Warming site.&#160;Vegetation: This is a mixed grass area dominated by black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda) and blue grama (B. gracilis) with dropseed (Sporobolus spp.) and galleta grass (Pleuraphis jamesii) also prominent., History: In 2003, the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service conducted a prescribed fire over a large part of the northeast corner of the Sevilleta NWR, including the area near Deep Well containing the mixed grass site., siteid: 32</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.691</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.691</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.35787</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.35787</southBoundingCoordinate>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The mixed shrub (MS) location consists of burned and unburned areas.&#160; Both the mixed shrub burned (MSB) and mixed shrub unburned (MSU) areas are on the north side of the road running southeast from Five Points.Vegetation: This area is dominated by creosotebush (Larrea tridenta) but also maintains a relatively dense understory of black grama in comparison to true shrub land., History: The northwest half of the site was burned in June 2003. The southeast half was used as the control. Plots were established in spring 2004., siteid: 33</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.696</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.696</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.31426</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.31426</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1640</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1640</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2004-02-15</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2010-10-30</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>02/08/10 (JM) Metadata updated and data compiled from 1999 to 2009. All data put on-line and in navicat anpp table.02/03/09 (YX) Metadata entered and compiled from 1999 to 2008 based on a File info from Doug Moore (12/19/08).</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
      <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Derivation of Biomass and NPP: Data from SEV156 and SEV157 are used used to calculate seasonal and  annual production of each species in each quadrat for a given year.  Allometric equations derived from harvested samples of each species for  each season are applied to the measured cover, height, and count of each  species in each quadrat. This provides seasonal biomass for winter,  spring, and fall. Seasonal NPP is derived by subtracting the previous season's biomass  from the biomass for the current season. For example, spring NPP is  calculated by subtracting the winter weight from the spring weight for  each species in a given quadrat.  Negative differences are considered to  be 0. Likewise, fall production is computed by subtracting spring  biomass from fall biomass. Annual biomass is taken as the sum of spring  and fall NPP.August 2009 Burn:On August 4, 2009, a   lightning-initiated fire began on the Sevilleta    National Wildlife   Refuge.&#160; The fire reached the Mixed-Grass Unburned plots on August 5,   2009, consuming them in their entirety.&#160; As a result, in the spring of   2010, the Mixed-Grass Unburned plots were moved to a different area   within Deep Well, southwest of the Warming site.&#160;Also, on August  4, 2009, some of the webs and quadrats within the unburned Black Grama  site were impacted by the fire.&#160; Thus, webs 2 and 3 were abandoned and  extra plots added to areas within webs 1, 4, and 5 that were not  burned.&#160; Changes were as follows:Webs 1, 4, and 5: A plot was added to the northeast to compensate for the loss of all plots at webs 2 and 3.Web 4: A plot was added to the northwest to compensate for the northern plot, which was burned.This update supercedes the description of plot layout provided above and is applicable to the Black Grama site only.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
  </methods>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>sev185_nppburnbiomass_20131211.txt</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Seasonal biomass and seasonal and annual npp data for the burn study.</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>sev185_nppburnbiomass_20131211.txt</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
          <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url>http://sev.lternet.edu/sites/default/files/data/sev-185/sev185_nppburnbiomass_20131211.txt</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2004-02-15</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2012-10-30</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>year</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>year</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The year in which data was collected.  </attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>date</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <dateTime>
            <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
          </dateTime>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>site</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>site</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The site at which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>G </code>
                  <definition> Black grama site</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>MG </code>
                  <definition> Mixed grass site</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>MS </code>
                  <definition> Mixed shrub site</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>treatment</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>treatment</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The treatment applied to a site.
</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>B </code>
                  <definition> burned </definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C </code>
                  <definition> control</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>quad</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>quad</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The quadrat at which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The quadrat at which data was collected.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>species</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>species</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The Kartez code for a plant species as designated by the USDA Plants Database. </attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The Kartez code for a plant species as designated by the USDA Plants Database. </definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>wwt</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>wwt</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The calculated weight of live green biomass for a species in a quadrat in the winter. </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>swt</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>swt</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The calculated weight of live green biomass for a species in a quadrat in the spring.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>fwt</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>fwt</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The calculated weight of live green biomass for a species in a quadrat in the fall.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>snpp</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>snpp</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The calculated primary production of a species in a quadrat in the spring.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>fnpp</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>fnpp</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The calculated primary production of a species in a quadrat in the fall.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>anpp</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>anpp</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The calculated annual primary production of a species in a quadrat.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
</ns0:eml>