<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.227.275478" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>Local Adaptation to Freezing in High and Low Latitude Populations of L. tridentata (Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico; Higuerillas, Mexico) and L. divaricata (Bajada del Diablo and Chamical, Argentina) (2006-2009))</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Juliana</givenName>
      <surName>Medeiros</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>, </deliveryPoint>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>jmedeiros@ku.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">13117</userId>
  </creator>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Kristin</givenName>
      <surName>Vanderbilt</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, MSC03 2020, 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>vanderbi@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">11054</userId>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>If freezing limits establishment of warm desert shrubs at high latitudes, shrubland distributions  may be altered as a result of rising global temperatures. However, variation in plant physiology  and morphology can be observed across climate gradients and may be acted on by selection to produce  adaptation to local climate conditions, thereby ameliorating low temperature stress.  Freezing  damage in evergreens is closely linked to vessel size distribution because larger xylem  conduits are more likely to become air-filled during freezing.  In addition, plastic variation,  rather than genetic, may be responsible for differences in freezing tolerance among populations.   In order to determine if local adaptation to freezing is present in two species of the genus  Larrea, L. tridentata and L. divaricata, we investigated xylem vessel size distributions in field  grown L. tridentata adults and saplings grown in a common garden from high latitude (Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge) and low  latitude (Higuerillas, Mexico) sites in the Chihuahuan Desert in North America. High latitude (Bajada del Diablo, Argentina) and low latitude (Chamical,  Argentina) populations of Larrea divaricata were selected for investigation from the Monte Desert in South America.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>populations</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>plant physiology</keyword>
    <keyword>disturbances</keyword>
    <keyword>frost</keyword>
    <keyword>winter</keyword>
    <keyword>physiological processes</keyword>
    <keyword>survival</keyword>
    <keyword>deserts</keyword>
    <keyword>grasslands</keyword>
    <keyword>plants</keyword>
    <keyword>shrubs</keyword>
    <keyword>vegetation</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/4015</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: Bajada del Diablo, Chubut, Argentina.Landform: Mountain foothills., Vegetation: Desert shrubland., Climate: Cold arid with a dry season., </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-68.25</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-68.25</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>-42.52</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>-42.52</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1503</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1503</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: Chamical, La Rioja, Argentina.Landform: Mountain valley., Vegetation: Grassland with mixed Larrea/Fabaceae shrubland., Climate: Subtropical dry., History: Grazing, now a government agricultural station., </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-29.417</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-29.417</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>-66.867</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>-66.867</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1503</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1503</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: The Five Points area emcompasses both the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote study sites.&#160; Five Points falls along the transition between the Chihuahuan Desert Scrub and Desert Grassland habitats.&#160; Both core sites are subject to intensive research activities, including NPP measurements, phenology observations, pollinator diversity studies, and ground dwelling arthropod and rodent population assessments.&#160; There are rain-out shelters for drought studies in both the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote sites.Vegetation: The Five Points Creosote site is characterized as Chihuahuan Desert Scrub, dominated by a creosote overstory, with broom snakeweed, purple pricklypear (Opuntia macrocentra), and soapweed yucca as co-occurring shrubs. The site is also characterized by numerous, dense, grass-dominated patches, reflecting proximity to the Five Points Black Grama Site.  Dominant grasses are black grama, fluffgrass (Dasyochloa pulchellum), burrograss (Scleropogon brevifolia), bushmuhly (Muhlenbergia porteri), and galleta (Pleuraphis jamesii).  Notable forbs include field bahia (Bahia absinthifolia), baby aster (Chaetopappa ericoides), plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala), Indian rushpea (Hoffmannseggia glauca), Fendlers bladderpod (Lesquerella fendleri), and globemallows (Sphaeralcea spp.)., siteid: 3</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3331</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: Higurillas, Queretaro, Mexico.Landform: Montane., Vegetation: Subtropical mixed-savannah with scrub and succulents., History: Mixed-use, low-impact resource harvesting (cacti, firewood, etc.). Grazing data from this site has been published in Duran et al. 2005., </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-99.45</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-99.45</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>20.54</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>20.54</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1580</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1580</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: GAN   represents samples collected at a fifth study area located in Gan Gan,   Chubut, Argentina at 42&#176; 30' 0" South, 68&#176; 16' 0" West, altitude   907 m. The landform is montane and the vegetation is mixed cold desert scrub.   The site has a history of sheep grazing.Landform: Montane, Vegetation: Mixed cold desert scrub, History: History of sheep grazing, </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-68.27</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-68.27</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>-42.5</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>-42.5</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>907</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>907</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2006-12-01</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2007-01-30</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2008-06-01</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2008-06-08</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>2009-06-01</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>2009-06-30</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
      <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Field sample collection: Seed and wood samples were collected at two North American sites in the winter of 2006 and at two South  American sites in the winter of 2008.  Wood samples were wrapped in plastic to reduce dehydration.   Following their return to the lab, wood samples were placed in a freezer until they could be  analyzed. Seeds were sown within three weeks of collection.Plant propagation: Seeds were germinated in the University of New Mexico research greenhouse within one month of  collection and received only natural light.  Seeds were sown in flats containing a 4:1:1  mixture of sand, peat, and perlite, then individual seedlings were transplanted to 1 L containers  within seven days of germination. Seedlings were kept well-watered and received spray irrigation once  or twice daily depending on temperatures and evaporative demand. One teaspoon of slow release fertilizer (Osmocote 14:14:14) was applied immediately after and every four months following  transplanting.Xylem vessel size distributions: Both field and lab samples were sectioned and imaged in June 2009. A total of 44,672 vessels  from 72 branches were counted (eight branches from each field and greenhouse population).  Wood was cut into sections  26 micrometer thick using a sliding microtome. Sections were stained with a 70% solution of  toluidine blue and wet-mounted on a slide.  Sections were magnified 100x and imaged using a digital  camera attached to a dissecting microscope.We defined four rings of equal diameter and took a  single image of each ring.  We counted all the vessels contained in the images of the four rings  moving from the edge to the center of the section, making sure not to include individual vessels in  more than one image.  For each day that images were generated we also made an image of a micrometer  scale.  The image of the scale was opened in ImageJ and the function "Set Scale" was used to  determine the number of micrometers/pixel.  Images of xylem were then analyzed in ImageJ using the  appropriate scale.  They were inverted, then thresholded so that only the vessels were represented  by colored pixels.  To verify that the particles measured by ImageJ represented actual vessels a  drawing of the measured particles, generated by the software, was compared to the original  .jpg image.When objects appeared in the thresholded image that did not correspond to intact  vessels appearing in the original image, such as small cracks in the section or occasional torn  vessels, these objects were manually erased and the analysis was redone.  The image was analyzed  using the "Analyze Particles" function, which determined an area and the x and y diameters of a  best fit ellipse for each individual xylem vessel.  We excluded particle measurements with shapes touching the edges of the image, exhibiting a circularity  less than 0.1, or exhibiting a major diameter of the best fit  elipse less than 7.5 micrometers, which corresponds to the lower size limit of vessels measured by  Martinez-Villalta and Pockman (2002).Instrument Name: Sliding Microtome.Manufacturer: American Optics.Model Number: 860.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
  </methods>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>sev227_larreafreeze_20140107.csv</entityName>
    <physical>
      <objectName>sev227_larreafreeze_20140107.csv</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
          <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url>http://sev.lternet.edu/sites/default/files/data/sev-227/sev227_larreafreeze_20140107.csv</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <singleDateTime>
          <calendarDate>2014-01-06</calendarDate>
        </singleDateTime>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>latitude</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>latitude</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>the latitude at which the sample or seeds were collected</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>high</code>
                  <definition>high latitude</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>low</code>
                  <definition>low latitude</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>species</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>species</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>species of the wood sample or sapling</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>DIVAR</code>
                  <definition>L. divaricata</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>TRIDE</code>
                  <definition>L. tridentata</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>NITID</code>
                  <definition>L. nitida</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>population</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>population</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>population where the samples were collected</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>BBD</code>
                  <definition>Bajada del Diablo</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>CHA</code>
                  <definition>Chemical</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>SEV</code>
                  <definition>Sevilleta</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>QRO</code>
                  <definition>Higurillas</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>GAN</code>
                  <definition>Gan Gan</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>growth_environment</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>growth_environment</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>place where the sample was propagated</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>field</code>
                  <definition>propagated in field</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>lab</code>
                  <definition>propagated in lab</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>sample_id</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>sample_id</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>the number of the individual wood sample, from 1 to 8</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>the number of the individual wood sample, from 1 to 8</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>sector</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>sector</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>the portion of the xylem section contained in the image</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>a</code>
                  <definition>outer ring</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>b</code>
                  <definition>ring between a and c</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>c</code>
                  <definition>ring between b and d</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>d</code>
                  <definition>inner ring</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>vessel#</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>vessel#</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>an individual vessel, numbered 1 to 493</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>an individual vessel, numbered 1 to 493</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>area</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>area</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>area of an individual vessel</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>squareMicrometer</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>XM</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>XM</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>the x coordinate (within the image) for each vessel determined by ImageJ</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>micrometer</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>YM</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>YM</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>the y coordinate for each vessel determined by ImageJ</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>micrometer</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>perimeter</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>perimeter</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>the perimeter of a best fit ellipse for each vessel determined by ImageJ</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>micrometer</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>maj</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>maj</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>the major diameter of a best fit ellipse as determined by ImageJ</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>micrometer</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>min</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>min</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>the minor diameter of a best fit ellipse as determined by ImageJ</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>micrometer</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>angle</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>angle</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>the angle between the major and minor diameters of a best fit ellipse as determined by ImageJ</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">180</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit id="squareMicrometer" />
    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>