<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.169.439287" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <title>The Effect of Kangaroo-Rat Activity on Plant Species Composition at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico (1999)</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Gyuri</givenName>
      <surName>Kroel-Dulay</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <electronicMailAddress>gyuri@botanika.hu </electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Debra</givenName>
      <surName>Peters</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> Box 30003, MSC 3JER New Mexico State University Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>USA</country>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(575) 646-2777</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(575) 646.5889</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>debpeter@nmsu.edu </electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Tamara</givenName>
      <surName>Hochstrasser</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> Agriculture Builiding, University College Dublin Belfield</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Dublin</city>
      <postalCode>0</postalCode>
      <country>Dublin</country>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(531) 716-7719</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(531) 716.1102</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>tamara.hochstrasser@ucd.ie </electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <associatedParty>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Kristin</givenName>
      <surName>Vanderbilt</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, MSC03 2020, 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Albuquerque</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>vanderbi@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">11054</userId>
    <role>data manager</role>
  </associatedParty>
  <pubDate>2010</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para>Our objective was to evaluate the effects of kangaroo rat mounds on species diversity and  composition at a semiarid-arid grassland ecotone. We expected that source populations of plants  occurring on kangaroo rat mounds have important influences on the species composition of vegetation at  the landscape scale, and that these influences differ by grassland type. Our study was conducted  at the Sevilleta LTER in New Mexico, where a grassland type dominated by Bouteloua gracilis, a  shortgrass steppe species, and a grassland type dominated by B. eriopoda, a desert grassland  species, meet to form patches across the landscape.Four 0.4 ha plots were sampled for species  diversity and composition in a regular 7m x 7m grid in each grassland type. Kangaroo rat mounds  were also mapped and sampled for vegetation measures in four areas of 1.6 ha in each type. The  landscape scale abundance of many subordinate species was increased significantly by  populations occurring on kangaroo rat mounds in both grassland types. However, the area affected  by the burrowing activity of kangaroo rats was twice as large in the B. eriopoda dominated  grassland type. Furthermore, dominant plants on mounds in the B. eriopoda type were also abundant  in off-mound areas whereas dominant plants on mounds in the B. gracilis type were not as abundant  off-mound. These results indicate that the presence of mounds in the B. gracilis dominated type is  creating islands of plant communities that are distinct from the rest of the grassland. Therefore,  the occurrence of certain plant species in this grassland type may be intimately associated with  the disturbance regime at this ecotone. This study demonstrates that effects of small burrowing  animals may facilitate the coexistence of species at this ecotone.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>disturbance</keyword>
    <keyword>populations</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>community patterns</keyword>
    <keyword>plant communities</keyword>
    <keyword>plant ecology</keyword>
    <keyword>vegetation dynamics</keyword>
    <keyword>community dynamics</keyword>
    <keyword>plant species composition</keyword>
    <keyword>disturbances</keyword>
    <keyword>plant cover</keyword>
    <keyword>population and community properties</keyword>
    <keyword>permanent plots</keyword>
    <keyword>species interactions</keyword>
    <keyword>herbivory</keyword>
    <keyword>seed dispersal</keyword>
    <keyword>disturbance</keyword>
    <keyword>deserts</keyword>
    <keyword>grasslands</keyword>
    <keyword>animals</keyword>
    <keyword>fauna</keyword>
    <keyword>mammals</keyword>
    <keyword>small mammals</keyword>
    <keyword>plants</keyword>
    <keyword>grasses</keyword>
    <keyword>herbs</keyword>
    <keyword>forbs</keyword>
    <keyword>vegetation</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/2657</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: Deep Well is located on McKenzie Flats and is site of the longest running SEV LTER met station, number 40, which has been active since 1988.&#160; In addition to studies of meteorological variables, core line-intercept vegetation transects and line-intercept transects from the 1995 and 2001 Deep Well fires are sampled here.&#160; The mini-rhizotron study, blue and black grama compositional comparison, blue and black grama patch dynamics investigation, and kangaroo rat population assessement are all ongoing here.&#160; Deep Well Blue/Black Grama Mixed is also the location of the warming and monsoon experiments, as well as portions of the line-intercept and vegetation removal studies.
On August 4, 2009, a lightning-initiated fire began on the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge. By August 5, 2009, the fire had reached the area of Deep Well Blue/Black Grama Mixed.&#160; While portions of this site were burned, the entirety was not.&#160; See individual projects for further information on the effects of the fire.Vegetation: The vegetation of Deep Well Blue/Black Grama Mixed is Chihuahuan Desert Grassland, dominated by black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda) and blue grama (B. gracilis).  Other grasses found at the site include dropseeds (Sporobolus spp.) and threeawns (Aristida spp.).  Shrubs are uncommon but those that occur include Yucca glauca, Ephedra torreyi, and four-wing saltbush (Atriplex canescens). Herbaceous plants include Plantago purshii, Hymenopappus filifolius, and globe mallows (Sphaeralcea spp.).

 , </geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.7358</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1600</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1600</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <geographicCoverage>
      <geographicDescription>Location: McKenzie Flats is located within the northeastern section of the Sevilleta NWR, encompassing an area from Black Butte south  to Palo Duro Canyon and east to the Los Pinos.Landform: McKenzie Flats is a broad, nearly flat grassland plain between the Los Pinos Mountains and the breaks on the east side of the Rio Grande., Geology: Deep (20,000 ft) alluvial and aeolian deposits., Soils: Turney Series:  fine-loamy, mixed, thermic Typic Calciorthids.  Berino Series:  fine-loamy, mixed, thermic Typic Haplargids., Hydrology: Surface water only during rain events, no arroyos.  Run-on plain for Los Pinos Mountains., Vegetation: The terrain is generally a mixed-species desert grassland, dominated by black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda), blue grama (B. gracilis), sand muhly (Muhlenbergia arenicola), various drop seeds and sacatons (Sporobolus spp.), purple three-awn (Aristida purpurea), and burrow grass (Scleropogon brevifolia).  Shrubs are common in the area around Five Points, including creosote bush (Larrea tridentata) and snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae)., Climate: Long-term mean annual precipitation is 243 mm, about 60% of which occurs during the summer.  Long-term mean monthly temperatures for January and July are 1.5 degrees C and 25.1 degrees C, respectively., History: McKenzie Flats encompasses an area of approximately 50 square miles and was one of the primary livestock grazing areas within what is now the Sevilleta NWR.  Cattle have been excluded from the site since 1974-76.  The ranch headquarters buildings and corrals were located at the junction of Legs C and D of the coyote survey.  , siteid: 25</geographicDescription>
      <boundingCoordinates>
        <westBoundingCoordinate>106.691</westBoundingCoordinate>
        <eastBoundingCoordinate>106.691</eastBoundingCoordinate>
        <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</northBoundingCoordinate>
        <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3592</southBoundingCoordinate>
        <boundingAltitudes>
          <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
          <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
          <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
        </boundingAltitudes>
      </boundingCoordinates>
    </geographicCoverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <singleDateTime>
        <calendarDate>1999-08-01</calendarDate>
      </singleDateTime>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Debra</givenName>
      <surName>Peters</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint> Box 30003, MSC 3JER New Mexico State University Ecosystems Center</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>USA</country>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">(575) 646-2777</phone>
    <phone phonetype="fax">(575) 646.5889</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>debpeter@nmsu.edu </electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>Experimental Design - We selected eight stands, four dominated by Bouteloua eriopoda and four by Bouteloua gracilis (stands were marked with A1, A2, A3, A4 in the data set for the Bouteloua eriopoda type, and U1, U2, U3, U4 for Bouteloua gracilis type). Study areas were selected using aerial photos to ensure that they were located in well-defined black grama- or blue grama-dominated belts.&#160; Study areas were 126 m x 126 m in size and were placed so that they contained a randomly selected, average-sized, and recently abandoned kangaroo rat mound in the center. Field Methods - In each patch type, we mapped all kangaroo-rat mounds and measured their size within the four 1.6 ha (126 m x 126 m) areas (total areas = 8). We classified each mound as active, recently abandoned, or old according to the level of small mammal activity. We noted the dominant and co-dominant plant species on each mound (i.e. species with at least 5% relative cover). In the center of each 1.6 ha plot, we estimated canopy cover (visual cover estimation) by species in 100 2m2 quadrats arranged in a regular 7 m x 7 m grid centered on a randomly selected and recently abandoned mound. Each grid covered a 63 m x 63 m area in the centre of the 1,6 ha stands. For each quadrat, we noted its location as being on a mound proper, at the edge of a mound, or in the off-mound vegetation.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
  </methods>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>sev169_krat_07312012.txt</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data for SEV169, the effect of kangaroo-rat activity on plant species composition in central New Mexico. </entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>sev169_krat_07312012.txt</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
          <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url>http://sev.lternet.edu/sites/default/files/data/sev-169/sev169_krat_07312012.txt</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <singleDateTime>
          <calendarDate>2012-03-07</calendarDate>
        </singleDateTime>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>patch</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Patch</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The number of the patch sampled.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1</code>
                  <definition>black grama patch</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>2</code>
                  <definition>blue grama patch</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>mound#</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Mound #</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The number of the mound associated with a sampled location.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The number of the mound associated with a sampled location.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>transect#</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Transect #</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The number of the transect along which sampling occurred.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The number of the transect along which sampling occurred.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>distance_from_mound</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Distance from Mound</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The distance that a location sampled is from the associated kangaroo rat mound.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>meters</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.5</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">25</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>location</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Location</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The numerical representation of the position of a sampled location.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>1</code>
                  <definition>on mound</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>2</code>
                  <definition>transition zone</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>3</code>
                  <definition>off mound</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>%bogr</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>%bogr</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The percent cover of blue grama (Bouteloua gracilis) observed at a sampled location.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">49</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>%boer</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>%boer</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The percent cover of black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda) observed at a sampled location. </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">73</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>%gusa</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>%gusa</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The percent cover of snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae) observed at a sampled location. </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">16</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>n_gusa</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>n_gusa</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The number (density) of snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae) plants observed at a sampled location.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The number (density) of snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae) plants observed at a sampled location.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>%herbs+sub-shrubs</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>%herbs+sub-shrubs</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The percent of herbaceous plants and sub-shrubs observed at a sampled location. </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">26</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>n_herbs+sub-shrubs</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>n_herbs+sub-shrubs</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The number (density) of herbaceous plants and sub-shrubs observed at a sampled location. </attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The number (density) of herbaceous plants and sub-shrubs observed at a sampled location. </definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>%cacti</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>%cacti</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The percent cover of cacti observed at a sampled location. </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">5</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>n_cacti</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>n_cacti</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The number (density) of cacti plants observed at a sampled location.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The number (density) of cacti plants observed at a sampled location.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>%yugl</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>%yugl</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The percent cover of Yucca glauca observed at a sampled location.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">58</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>n_yugl</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>n_yugl</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The number (density) of Yucca glauca plants observed at a sampled location. </attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The number (density) of Yucca glauca plants observed at a sampled location. </definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>%_other_grass</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>%_other_grass</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The percent cover of unidentified grass species observed at a sampled location.  For SEV169, this variable is redundant with "combined grass." </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">26</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>%hija</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>%hija</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The percent cover of James' galleta (Hilaria jamesii, now Pleuraphis jamesii) observed at a sampled location. </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">16</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>%spfl</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>%spfl</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The percent cover of mesa dropseed (Sporobolus flexuosus) observed at a sampled location. </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">5</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>%arpu</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>%arpu</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The percent cover of purple three-awn (Aristida purpurea) observed at a sampled location. </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">11</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>%epvi</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>%epvi</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The percent cover of mormon tea (Ephedra viridis) observed at a sampled location. </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">17</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>n_epvi</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>n_epvi</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The number (density) of mormon tea (Ephedra viridis) plants observed at a sampled location. </attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The number (density) of mormon tea (Ephedra viridis) plants observed at a sampled location. </definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>%combined grass</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>%combined_grass</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The percent cover of unidentified grass species observed at a sampled location. For SEV169, this variable is redundant with "% other grass." </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">26</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>%bare ground+litter</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>%bare_ground+litter</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The percent cover of bare ground and litter observed at a sampled location.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">100</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>%F+S+S</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>%F+S+S</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The sum of %gusa, %herbs+sub-shrubs. %cacti, %yugl, and %epvi (i.e., forbs and sub-shrubs) observed at a sampled location.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">66</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>#F+S+S</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>#F+S+S</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The sum of n gusa, n herbs+sub-shrubs, n cacti, n yugl, and n epvi (i.e., forbs and sub-shrubs) observed at a sampled location.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The sum of n gusa, n herbs+sub-shrubs, n cacti, n yugl, and n epvi (i.e., forbs and sub-shrubs) observed at a sampled location.</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>total</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Total</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The total percentage of vegetative cover (i.e., 100-%bare ground+litter) observed at a sampled location.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percentage</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>1</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">74</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>diameter1</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Diameter1 (m)</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The first measured diameter of a mound associated with a sampling location.</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>meters</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">2.3</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">4.82</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>diameter2</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Diameter2</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The diameter perpendicular to "diameter1" of a mound associated with a sampling location. </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>meters</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">2.86</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">5.7</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>mound_area</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Mound Area</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The area of a mound associated with a sampled location. </attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>square meters</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
              <bounds>
                <minimum exclusive="false">5.56</minimum>
                <maximum exclusive="false">19.4</maximum>
              </bounds>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>fill_numbers</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>Fill Numbers</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>The sequential number associated with a sampling event for SEV169, the effect of kangaroo-rat activity on plant species composition in central New Mexico. </attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>The sequential number associated with a sampling event for SEV169, the effect of kangaroo-rat activity on plant species composition in central New Mexico. </definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit abbreviation="" id="meters" name="meters" unitType=""><ns2:description /></ns2:unit>

<ns2:unit abbreviation="" id="percentage" name="percentage" unitType=""><ns2:description /></ns2:unit>

<ns2:unit id="square meters" />
    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>