<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-jrn.20050210.9796" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
    <principal>uid=JRN, o=lter, dc=ecoinformatics, dc=org</principal>
    <permission>all</permission>
  </allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset>
  <shortName>JornadaStudy_120_boundary_fence_plant_line_intercept_percent_cover_9_species_1982-1992_data</shortName>
  <title>East and west boundary fence plant line intercepts - percent cover for 9 species 1982-1992</title>
  <creator>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>John</givenName>
      <surName>Anderson</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>
	Jornada LTER

	New Mexico State University

	P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>United States</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>janderso@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <metadataProvider>
    <organizationName>The Jornada</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>2995 Knox Street</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-4842</phone>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    <onlineUrl>http://jornada.nmsu.edu</onlineUrl>
  </metadataProvider>
  <pubDate>1982</pubDate>
  <language>english</language>
  <abstract>
    <section>
      <para> BACKGROUND.
 In the spring of 1982, as part of the establishment of
 the Jornada Long-Term Ecological Research site in southern
 New Mexico, a 135 ha portion of a 1500 ha, internally
 drained, watershed was exclosed from grazing by domestic
 livestock. Prior to exclosure the watershed, as well as the
 rest of the Jornada basin, had been moderately to heavily
 grazed for the past 100 years. Concurrent with grazing, the
 vegetation had undergone a dramatic change from desert
 grassland, with an almost continuous cover of C4 perennial
 grasses, to isolated patches of the original grassland in a
 mosaic with desert shrub dominated plant communities
 (Buffington and Herbel, 1965).
 The exclosure lies along a northeast facing piedmont
 slope at the base of a steep isolated mountain peak, and
 covers a variety of component landforms from the foot of the
 mountain to the basin floor. This provided the opportunity
 to investigate the response of vegetation with respect to
 landscape characteristics as well as release from grazing.

 This summary data set consists of percent cover of 9 species
 from the plant line intercept measurements on either side of the
 LTER-I exclosure East and West boundary fence. Data is sorted by
 station, species i.d., then line segment. Along the East
 Boundary fence, the east side is ungrazed (control) and the west
 side is grazed (treatment). Along the West Boundary fence, the
 east side is grazed and the west side is ungrazed. Each plant
 line transect is divided into 6 5-meter segments. All perennials
 were measured at about 5 year intervals as the length of
 intercept along a 30-meter line perpendicular to the fence.
 Summary data includes only four of the 6 5-meter intervals due to
 disturbance along fenceline. Data from the 5-meter segment on
 either side of the fence was not included in summarizing the
 data. Summary data includes only 9 of the perennial species.</para>
    </section>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
    <keyword>completed</keyword>
    <keyword>disturbance</keyword>
    <keyword>fence line</keyword>
    <keyword>grazing effects</keyword>
    <keyword>line intercept</keyword>
    <keyword>longterm</keyword>
    <keyword>plant</keyword>
    <keyword>plant cover</keyword>
    <keyword>primary production</keyword>
    <keyword>signature</keyword>
    <keyword>vegetation dynamics</keyword>
    <keyword>vegetative cover</keyword>
    <keywordThesaurus>Jornada Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
  </keywordSet>
  <additionalInfo>
    <para>
      <literalLayout> In the spring of 1982, as part of the establishment of
 the Jornada Long-Term Ecological Research site in southern
 New Mexico, a 135 ha portion of a 1500 ha, internally
 drained, watershed was exclosed from grazing by domestic
 livestock. Prior to exclosure the watershed, as well as the
 rest of the Jornada basin, had been moderately to heavily
 grazed for the past 100 years. Concurrent with grazing, the
 vegetation had undergone a dramatic change from desert
 grassland, with an almost continuous cover of C4 perennial
 grasses, to isolated patches of the original grassland in a
 mosaic with desert shrub dominated plant communities
 (Buffington and Herbel, 1965).
 The exclosure lies along a northeast facing piedmont
 slope at the base of a steep isolated mountain peak, and
 covers a variety of component landforms from the foot of the
 mountain to the basin floor. The northeast side of the
 exclosure is immediately upslope of the College Playa
 located near the NMSU College Ranch.
 Permanently marked 30m line transects were located at
 50m intervals along the two parallel long axis fences of the
 exclosure. These fences run from north to south (more or
 less) up the slope of the watershed, traversing the
 component landforms characteristic of the bajadas of the
 Basin and Range Province. The transects are thus
 perpendicular to the direction of major drainage flow.
 There are 31 30-meter line intercepts located along the
 west boundary fence and 30 30-meter line intercepts located
 along the east boundary fence.
 Line intercepts are located at every 5th fence pole
 (except where noted) starting near the ranch headquarters
 access road which passes by the playa. Fence poles are not
 marked and transects E01 and W01 are located several fence
 poles south of the road. [W04 is 6 posts from W03; W19 is 4
 posts from W18.]

 Each line intercept is 30 meters in length and divided
 into 6 5-meter segments; 3 segments of each line (15 meters)
 are inside the fence and ungrazed, the other 3 segments are
 outside the fence and is subject to grazing when pastures
 are stocked. Segments are numbered 1 - 6 beginning from the
 west end of the line (or if facing upslope while standing at
 the fence, segment 1 begins at the end of the intercept line
 to your right).</literalLayout>
    </para>
  </additionalInfo>
  <intellectualRights>
    <section>
      <title>Data Policies</title>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>Objectives:
The Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System (JIMS) provides protocol and services for data collection, verification, organization, archives, and distribution in accordance with recommendations and guidelines developed by the LTER Information Managers Committee (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html).

Disclaimer:
While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is". The Jornada Basin LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of data sets.

Quality Assurance Policy:
Data managers interact with researchers during the entire scientific process--from the initial planning of sampling designs and field data collection to archiving and distribution of data. The goal of data management is to build and maintain an archive of Jornada Basin LTER data files that are fully documented, error free, and organized in useful ways. Our protocol for data collection and processing seeks maximum interaction between researchers and data management personnel to avoid confusion and potential loss of data or problems with integrity of data; e.g., identification of historical site treatments that may impact a proposed study or incomplete data set variable descriptions. Site and Data Manager involvement begins during the Project Design phase with the completion of the Jornada Notification of Research form by the researcher prior to the start of work; this alerts both Site and Data Manager to the new study and potential LTER data sets. Upon initiation of a new study, the researcher completes Project Documentation that provides the second level of "metadata" documentation.
In the Data Collection phase, the data manager helps researchers design field and laboratory data sheets that facilitate data entry and analysis. Prior to JIMS data entry the investigator completes Data Set Documentation to provide the metadata that fully describe the data set. Both Project and Data set documentation are provided with the data set when it is requested or obtained from our Web site. JIMS data entry programs error-check and verify data as they are entered. Computer files are subjected to further verification by graphing and/or error-checking programs, and/or examination by field investigators. Final quality assurance of the data rests with the investigator who submits data for inclusion in the Data Management System. Direct communication with the Site Manager, or through a collaborating JRN P.I., is used to encourage the timely submission of documentation and of data by researchers.

Error-checked data files are stored with associated documentation files on the file server. Archived data files are maintained in ASCII format on 30-yr magneto-optical (MO) disks, portable hard drives, CD-R media, and DVD media to guard against loss of data access that can result from changing technology. This may also include proprietary binary format files to facilitate recovery of working versions. Image data are archived on 8mm tape. Routine tape data backups of the file server are done daily, weekly, and monthly. One set of off-site copies are maintained elsewhere on the NMSU campus of routine backup tapes, MO disks, CD disks, and DVD disks with a second set of MO, CD and DVD disks maintained off-campus in case of a catastrophe on campus. The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data manag ement staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

The final responsibility for quality assurance (both in data and documentation content) rests with the principal investigator who submits the data for inclusion in the Jornada Basin LTER Information Management System. To facilitate quality assurance, the data management staff will provide copies of data and documentation submitted by a principal investigator to that investigator upon request.

Policy on Submission of data:
Data submission into JIMS is expected from LTER researchers, LTER collaborators, and their graduate students where data and information is derived from publicly funded research in the U.S. LTER Network, totally or partially from LTER funds from NSF, Institutional Cost-Share, or Partner Agency or Institution where a formal memorandum of understanding with LTER has been established. Other Jornada Basin researchers are encouraged to submit their documented data for inclusion within JIMS to provide them with an archived backup, ensure its longevity, and provide online access to encourage synthesis efforts. Minimally, for non-LTER associated researchers, we request that publications be provided of research conducted on the Jornada Basin.
Initial documentation for a data set must be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager within 90 days of initiation of data collection. Documentation forms are available at http://jornada-www.nmsu.edu/site/dm/readme.php . These consist of Project Abstract and Data Set and Attribute documentation forms, which include objectives of the study, methods, as well as format and content of the data. All data collected during a calendar year should be submitted to the Jornada Basin LTER data manager prior to July first of the following year. First time data submissions must be submitted with updated standard Jornada Basin LTER forms previously submitted.

Data Access Policy:
Data will be made publicly available no later than 2 years after submission of the data unless an earlier date is specified by the principal investigator. In the event that an extension of the 2 year period is necessary, the principal investigator may petition the Jornada Basin LTER Executive Committee for a longer protected period. Graduate student research data will be available online after degree completion and they have the opportunity to publish their research.

Policies for re-use, distribution, or the production of derivatives:
Data re-use, distribution and production of derivative products are governed by the LTER Network data policies (http://www.lternet.edu/data/netpolicy.html) in the spirit of having the potential to increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines. Appropriate citation, acknowledgement, notification and collaboration are outlined and recommended. No commercial redistribution of data and derived products are allowed.

Data Acknowledgment Policy:
Please send notification to the Information Manager and Responsible Investigator(s) of the data sets you are downloading and your intended use.
Individuals and institutions utilizing data from the Jornada Basin LTER database are requested to place the following acknowledgment in any publication in which these data are mentioned:
Data sets were provided by the Jornada Basin Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) project. Funding for these data was provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210).

Please send 1 copy of any publication that cites Jornada Basin LTER data to:
     John P. Anderson
     Jornada Experimental Range
     P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER
     New Mexico State University
     Las Cruces, NM 88003-0003</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </section>
  </intellectualRights>
  <distribution>
    <online>
      <url function="download">http://jornada-data.nmsu.edu/files/dataset_packages/JornadaStudy_120_boundary_fence_plant_line_intercept_percent_cover_9_species_1982-1992_data.zip</url>
    </online>
  </distribution>
  <coverage>
    <temporalCoverage>
      <rangeOfDates>
        <beginDate>
          <calendarDate>1982-10-08</calendarDate>
        </beginDate>
        <endDate>
          <calendarDate>1992-09-11</calendarDate>
        </endDate>
      </rangeOfDates>
    </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <maintenance>
    <description>
      <para>
        <literalLayout> mm/dd/yyyy - Date of Comment
 Int - Initials of person making Comment
 JPA = John P. Anderson
 MAB = Michelle A. Buonopane
 KR = Ken Ramsey

 Changes/Updates - List any changes made to document

 mm/dd/yyyy Int Changes/Updates
 ---------- --- -----------------------------------------------
 10/28/1986 JPA Form completed
 10/04/1992 JPA Updated
 02/02/1994 JPA Updated
 10/09/1998 JPA Converted to new documentation form
 06/24/2002 MAB Corrected data file and variable information
 Added information on associated data files
 08/21/2003 JPA Added clarification to Data Set Description.
 07/19/2005 KR Added Dataset ID and Project ID to top of form.
 Changed format for Attributes and Associated
 Files section.
 Removed Missing/Questionable data section and
 incorporated into Attributes section.
 Changed format of Responsible Investigators and
 Researchers sections.
 08/01/2005 JPA Updated Responsible Investigator section.
 01/23/2006 JPA Corrected and edited data set description.
 Changed reference to T-test to percent cover
 to correctly describe data set content.
 01/23/2006 JPA Corrected Data Set Access to UNRESTRICTED.
 01/23/2006 JPA Moved individual week files (LT9SP041.SUM,
 LT9SP247.SUM, LT9SP559.SUM) from Data file
 section to Other file section and changed
 their file type flag from DS to OT.
 11/17/2011 JPA Changed responsible investigator for contact person
 to John Anderson per Deb Peters
 02/02/2012 JPA Changed dataset title to better reflect data</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </description>
  </maintenance>
  <contact>
    <individualName>
      <givenName>Data</givenName>
      <surName>Manager</surName>
    </individualName>
    <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
    <address>
      <deliveryPoint>PO Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
      <city>Las Cruces</city>
      <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
      <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
      <country>US</country>
    </address>
    <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </contact>
  <pubPlace>The Jornada</pubPlace>
  <methods>
    <methodStep>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout> 1982 and 1986 data recorded using field data sheets.
 1992 and 1998 data recorded on audio tape and transcribed to floppy
 disk.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout> METHODS
 1. Permanently marked 30m line transects were located at about
 50m intervals along the two parallel long axis fences of the
 LTER exclosure which begins immediately above the College
 Playa and extends toward Mt. Summerford. These fences run from north
 to south up the slope of the watershed, traversing the component
 landforms characteristic of the bajadas of the Basin and Range Province.
 The line transects are perpendicular to the fences and cross them at
 a fence post (either T-post or wood post) on the downslope side. They
 are thus perpendicular to the direction of major drainage flow. The
 line transects are identified by an aluminum tag wired to the fence
 post. The letter on the tag i.d. identifies the fence (East or West);
 the number is the station number (East: 1-30; West: 1-31).

 Canopy cover of only perennial species intercepted by
 a line stretched the length of the 30-meter line transect are measured
 and recorded for each of 6 5-meter segments. The ends of the line
 are anchored by 3/8" rebar extending about 6 inches out of the ground.
 When measurements are to be made, a length of clothesline is stretched
 between the two rebar so it is taut. Before making readings, ensure
 the line is freed from obstructions so it is perfectly straight
 between the two rebar. This may require threading the line through
 large plants or lifting free where sections are snagged.

 The clothesline used is pre-stretched overnight when new to
 minimize changes in length when stretched tight in the field. It is
 marked in 5 meter increments with enamel paint to indicate segment
 lengths. The length of the line should be checked before beginning a
 new season of measurements to ensure that stretching has not distorted
 line.
 Data is recorded by identifying Station number (metal
 tag is located on fence post) and Segment number. The 5-meter
 segments are numbered 1 through 6 beginning at the west end of
 the line (right end if facing upslope). Length of each plant species
 that is intercepted by line is recorded. Multiple readings (intercept
 observation) can occur for a single plant if vegetation is broken up
 with open areas along the line intercept. Each new 5-meter line
 segment is identified as it is encountered. Plant species are
 recorded as a 4 letter acronym consisting of first 2 letters of genus
 and first 2 letters of species epithet. If a duplicate acronym
 results for 2 different species, generally the 3rd letter of the
 species epithet is then used. Acronyms used are found in the Plant
 Checklist for the NSF/LTER Jornada Sites.
 Data sheets were used to record the data until Week 559. At this
 time tape recorders were used to record the field data. This data
 was entered and processed using several programs. INPUT.EXE (Fortran)
 is used to input tape recorded data. CONVERT.EXE (Fortran) is used
 to convert the entered tape recorded data to a format that matches
 that entered from data sheets. SRELCHEK.EXE (QuickBasic) error checks
 data. LTERCOVR.EXE (Fortran) summarizes and calculates mean percent
 cover for each species on each 30-meter line transect at each station.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </description>
    </methodStep>
    <qualityControl>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout> History of Responsible investigator(s):
 Gary Cunningham, 1982-1987;
 Walter G. Whitford, 1982-1989;
 Laura F. Huenneke, 1989-2004;
 Debra Peters, 2005-present
 ******************************</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </qualityControl>
  </methods>
  <project>
    <title>Jornada LTER</title>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
        <givenName>Debra</givenName>
        <surName>Peters</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">575-646-2777</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">575-646-5889</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>debpeter@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Lead Principal Investigator</role>
    </personnel>
    <personnel>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Data</givenName>
        <surName>Manager</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Jornada LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003-8003</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>datamanager@jornada-vmail.nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Information Manager</role>
    </personnel>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>The Jornada Basin Long Term Ecological Research program, in collaboration with 
                         the USDA ARS Jornada Experimental Range, studies the causes and consequences of 
                         desertification: the broad scale expansion of woody plants into grasslands that 
                         results in more "desert like" conditions. We are interested in spatial and 
                         temporal variation in desertification dynamics, and how historic legacies, the 
                         geomorphic template, transport vectors (wind, water, animals), and environmental 
                         drivers (climate, land use, disturbance) interact with the patch structure of the 
                         vegetation to determine past, present, and future ecosystem dynamics across 
                         scales.
                        
                         Our study site is located in the northern Chihuahuan Desert, approximately 25 km 
                         northeast of Las Cruces, New Mexico, USA (+32.5 N, -106.8 W, elevation 1188 m). 
                         Annual precipitation is 24 cm and maximum temperatures average 13 C in January 
                         and 36 C in June. Our study site includes the 78,000 ha Jornada Experimental 
                         Range operated by the USDA Agricultural Research Service, and the 22,000 ha 
                         Chihuahuan Desert Rangeland Research Center (CDRRC) operated by New Mexico State 
                         University. The Jornada Basin LTER project was established in 1982, and is 
                         administered by New Mexico State University. This site is a member of the LTER 
                         Network, one of  more than 25 long term sites funded by the U.S. National Science 
                         Foundation.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <funding>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>U.S. National Science Foundation (Grant DEB-0618210)</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </funding>
  </project>
  <dataTable>
    <entityName>JornadaStudy_120_boundary_fence_plant_line_intercept_percent_cover_9_species_1982-1992_data.csv</entityName>
    <entityDescription>Data file information for the following Jornada data set: East and west boundary fence plant line intercepts - percent cover for 9 species 1982-1992
</entityDescription>
    <physical>
      <objectName>JornadaStudy_120_boundary_fence_plant_line_intercept_percent_cover_9_species_1982-1992_data.csv</objectName>
      <dataFormat>
        <textFormat>
          <numHeaderLines>57</numHeaderLines>
          <numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
          <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
          <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
          <simpleDelimited>
            <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
          </simpleDelimited>
        </textFormat>
      </dataFormat>
      <distribution>
        <online>
          <url function="download">http://jornada-data.nmsu.edu/sites/jornada-data.nmsu.edu/files/data_files/JornadaStudy_120_boundary_fence_plant_line_intercept_percent_cover_9_species_1982-1992_data.csv</url>
        </online>
      </distribution>
    </physical>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1982-10-08</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1992-09-11</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <attributeList>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>file</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_boundary_fence_plant_line_intercept_percent_cover_9_species_1982-1992_file</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>file name</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>file name</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Week</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_boundary_fence_plant_line_intercept_percent_cover_9_species_1982-1992_week</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>week number</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>week number</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Fenceline</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_boundary_fence_plant_line_intercept_percent_cover_9_species_1982-1992_fenceline</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Fenceline</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>E</code>
                  <definition>east</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>W</code>
                  <definition>west</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Station</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_boundary_fence_plant_line_intercept_percent_cover_9_species_1982-1992_station</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>Station (E = 1-30, W = 1-31)</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>Station (E = 1-30, W = 1-31)</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>spp</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_boundary_fence_plant_line_intercept_percent_cover_9_species_1982-1992_spp</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>plant species i.d.</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>*</code>
                  <definition>see LTER plant species list (PLNTALFA.HTM) @ https://jornada.nmsu.edu/jornada/species/lter-plants</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>pathway</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_boundary_fence_plant_line_intercept_percent_cover_9_species_1982-1992_pathway</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>photosynthetic pathway</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <textDomain>
                <definition>photosynthetic pathway</definition>
              </textDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Habit</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_boundary_fence_plant_line_intercept_percent_cover_9_species_1982-1992_habit</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>habit</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>P </code>
                  <definition> perennial</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>form</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_boundary_fence_plant_line_intercept_percent_cover_9_species_1982-1992_form</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>form</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>GRASS </code>
                  <definition> Grass</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>S-SHR </code>
                  <definition> Subshrub</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>FORB  </code>
                  <definition> Forb</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>SHRUB </code>
                  <definition> Shrub</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>Percent Cover</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_boundary_fence_plant_line_intercept_percent_cover_9_species_1982-1992_cover_percent</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>plant cover in percent (%)</attributeDefinition>
        <measurementScale>
          <ratio>
            <unit>
              <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
            </unit>
            <precision>0.01</precision>
            <numericDomain>
              <numberType>real</numberType>
            </numericDomain>
          </ratio>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
        <attributeName>treatment</attributeName>
        <attributeLabel>variable_jornada_boundary_fence_plant_line_intercept_percent_cover_9_species_1982-1992_treatment</attributeLabel>
        <attributeDefinition>treatment</attributeDefinition>
        <storageType>string</storageType>
        <measurementScale>
          <nominal>
            <nonNumericDomain>
              <enumeratedDomain>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>C </code>
                  <definition> control,ungrazed</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
                <codeDefinition>
                  <code>T </code>
                  <definition> treatment,grazed</definition>
                </codeDefinition>
              </enumeratedDomain>
            </nonNumericDomain>
          </nominal>
        </measurementScale>
      </attribute>
    </attributeList>
  </dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
  <metadata>
    <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
<ns2:unit abbreviation="%" constantToSI="0" id="percent" multiplierToSI="100" name="percent" parentSI="numberPerNumber" unitType="dimensionless"><ns2:description>ratio of two quantities as percent composition (1:100)</ns2:description></ns2:unit>
    </ns2:unitList>
  </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>