<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-cap.369.6" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://data.gios.asu.edu/eml2_1_0/eml.xsd">
<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
<allow>
            <principal>uid=CAP,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
            <principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
    <dataset id="369.369_1" system="gios_dataset">
        <alternateIdentifier system="gios_dataset">369</alternateIdentifier>
        <shortName>exlu00_utm</shortName>
        <title>Landuse map of the Maricopa County (2000)</title>
        <creator>
            <organizationName>Maricopa Association of Governments</organizationName>
            <address>
                <deliveryPoint>302 North 1st Avenue, Suite 300</deliveryPoint>
                <city>Phoenix</city>
                <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
                <postalCode>85003</postalCode>
                <country>USA</country>
            </address>
        </creator>
        <pubDate>2007</pubDate>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>
            <para>The Year 2000 Land Use coverage was created as a joint effort of MAG and MAG member agency staff. Land Use components were classified into 46 categories. The Year 2000 Land Use coverage is used for a variety of planning purposes including socioeconomic forecasting and air quality modeling.</para>
        </abstract><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="place">sonoran desert</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">phoenix</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">urban</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">metropolitan area</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">gis</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">land use</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">maricopa county</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">MAG</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">maricopa association of governments</keyword><keywordThesaurus>Creator Defined Keyword Set</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">land use</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">geographic information systems</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">maps</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">air quality</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">modeling</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">air</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">buildings</keyword><keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary Keyword Set</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword keywordType="theme">caplter</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">central arizona phoenix longterm ecological research</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">arizona</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">caplter created</keyword><keyword keywordType="place">az</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">cap</keyword><keyword keywordType="theme">arid land</keyword><keywordThesaurus>CAPLTER Keyword Set List</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet>
        
        <intellectualRights>
            <section>
                <para>Copyright Board of Regents, Arizona State University. This dataset is released
                    to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes
                    subject to the following restrictions:</para>
                <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>While CAP LTER will make every effort possible to control and
                                document the quality of the data it publishes, the data are made
                                available "as is".</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER cannot assume responsibility for damages resulting from
                                mis-use or mis-interpretation of datasets or from errors or
                                omissions that may exist in the data.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge
                                the work of other scientists that has resulted in data used in
                                subsequent research.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER expects that any use of data from this server will be
                                accompanied with the appropriate citations and
                                acknowledgments.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER encourages users to contact the original investigator
                                responsible for the data that they are accessing. Where appropriate,
                                researchers whose projects are integrally dependent on CAP LTER data
                                are encouraged to consider collaboration and/or co-authorship with
                                original investigators.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER requests that users submit to the Global Institute of
                                Sustainability, ASU, one copy of any publication resulting from the
                                use of data obtained from this site.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>CAP LTER requests that users not redistribute data obtained from
                                this site. However, links or references to this site may be freely
                                posted.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </section>
        </intellectualRights>
        <distribution>
            <online>
                <url>http://data.gios.asu.edu/cap/HarvestListFileShow.php?id=369</url>
            </online>
        </distribution>
        
        <coverage>
            <temporalCoverage>
                <singleDateTime>
                    <calendarDate>2000-01-01</calendarDate>
                </singleDateTime>
            </temporalCoverage>
            <geographicCoverage>
                <geographicDescription>Maricopa County, Arizona</geographicDescription>
                <boundingCoordinates>
                    <westBoundingCoordinate>-113.373861</westBoundingCoordinate>
                    <eastBoundingCoordinate>-111.038825</eastBoundingCoordinate>
                    <northBoundingCoordinate>34.053691</northBoundingCoordinate>
                    <southBoundingCoordinate>32.490768</southBoundingCoordinate>
                </boundingCoordinates>
            </geographicCoverage>
        </coverage>
        <purpose>
            <para>The Land Use coverage is used for a variety of planning purposes including
                socioeconomic forecasting and air quality modeling.</para>
        </purpose>
        <maintenance>
            <description>
                <para>This research has been concluded</para>
            </description>
            <maintenanceUpdateFrequency>asNeeded</maintenanceUpdateFrequency>
        </maintenance>
        <contact id="369.Datamanager">
            <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
            <address>
                <deliveryPoint>Global Institute of Sustainability</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>Arizona State University</deliveryPoint>
                <deliveryPoint>POB 875402</deliveryPoint>
                <city>TEMPE</city>
                <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
                <postalCode>85287-5402</postalCode>
                <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <phone phonetype="voice">(480) 965 2975</phone>
            <phone phonetype="fax">(480) 965-8087</phone>
            <electronicMailAddress>caplter.data@asu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        </contact>
        <methods>
            <methodStep>
                <description>
                    <section>
                        <title>A. First Steps</title>
                        <para>a) Identify contacts for information and review at each city. MAG uses
                            the MAG Population Technical Advisory Committee contacts unless informed
                            otherwise. b) Create and update a MAG Land Use classification file in
                            conjunction with MAG member agencies. This file should include minimum,
                            target, and maximum densities for each land use category. This file also
                            includes three levels of display for mapping, modeling and data
                            collection. c) Create and update default multiple use split information
                            for each MAG member agency in conjunction with the member
                            agencies.</para>
                    </section>
                    <section>
                        <title>B. Data Collection - Regularly collect from MAG Member
                            Agencie</title>
                        <para>a) Existing Land Use dataset (if available) o Land use maps with
                            description of land use categories o Intensity of use for each land use
                            category b) Known Development projects o Detailed plans and documents o
                            Status of development project (Active, Planned or Proposed) o Land use
                            maps for the project with land use description and intensity of use for
                            each subdivision (or part of development) o Size of the project
                            including number of housing units, sq. ft. and type of non-residential
                            space o Anticipated start year for the project c) General Plans and
                            Major/Minor Amendments to General Plans o Detailed Plans and/or
                            Amendment documents o Land use maps with description of planned land use
                            categories o Intensity of use for each land use category (e.g.
                            residential density) o Multiple use categories .</para>
                    </section>
                    <section>
                        <title>C. Common Steps</title>
                        <para>a) Create and maintain a Municipal Planning Area (MPA) boundary file.
                            MPAs include the corporate limits of a municipality plus any adjacent
                            areas that are anticipated to become a part of those corporate limits in
                            the future. Member agency MPAs are mutually exclusive. b) Create and
                            update a look-up table of MAG Member agency land use classification to
                            MAG land use description look-up for every member agency. This table
                            also includes minimum, target, and maximum densities for each land use
                            category as described in the General Plan. c) Create and update the
                            multiple use split information for each multiple use polygon in the
                            member agency plans, starting with the default information. d) Review
                            everything with MAG member agencies on a regular basis. Provide member
                            agencies with information that will help in their review, such as
                            buildout by the agency land use categories..</para>
                    </section>
                    <section>
                        <title>D. Data Creation/Update</title>
                        <para>a) Existing Land Use o Digitize Existing Land Use polygons using the
                            100+ land use classification and coincident with the street centerline
                            file o Ensure that the Existing Land Use dataset is consistent with the
                            housing counts from Census and residential completions. o Ensure that
                            the dataset is also consistent with the employer database and other
                            databases of hotels/motels, industrial/office/commercial buildings and
                            any other known information. b) Development Projects o Digitize the
                            major developments and the internal land use information (if available)
                            o Internal land use of the developments should be digitized such that
                            the development polygons identify separate land use types, start and end
                            years, development status, development names, and redevelopment status.
                            o Attribute data fields should include, at a minimum: development name,
                            each subdivision name, status, size (number of units or sq. ft. of
                            space), land use codes for each piece, and start year. o Ensure
                            consistency of the Development database with the Existing Land Use
                            dataset. c) General Plan and General Plan Amendments o Digitize General
                            Plans and currently available major and minor amendments using the 100+
                            land use classification and the land use look-up tables o Attribute data
                            fields should include, at a minimum: land use code from the member
                            agency, MAG land use code, minimum/target/maximum density, and mixed use
                            split. o Ensure consistency of the General Plan Land Use database with
                            the Development database and with the Existing Land Use dataset</para>
                    </section>
                    <section>
                        <title>E. Data Review &#226;&#8364;&#8220; On a regular basis review with every member
                            agency</title>
                        <para>a. The documents and data received by MAG b. The land use
                            classification look-up table c. Minimum/Target/Maximum Densities d.
                            Existing Land Use e. General Plan Land Use f. Development database with
                            such information like name of project, size, start year, and
                            status.</para>
                    </section>
                    <section>
                        <title>F. Data sources</title>
                        <para>1. MAG Member Agencies o General Plans and Amendments o Municipal
                            Planning Area (MPA) description o Existing Land Use (if available) o
                            Known Developments (active, planned or proposed) o Ongoing data review.
                            2. Aerial Imagery 3. Outside Sources, such as: o Newspaper articles o
                            Proprietary databases &#194;&#167; Kammrath and Associates &#194;&#167; COSTAR &#194;&#167; ASU &#194;&#167;
                            Maricopa County Assessors Parcel and Subdivisions Data o Developer
                            information 4. Street centerline file 5. Other MAG Geographic
                            Information Systems (GIS) datasets o Employment database o Residential
                            completions o Hotels/motels o Commercial, Office, Industrial
                            buildings</para>
                    </section>
                </description>
            </methodStep>
        </methods>
        <spatialVector id="369.exlu00_utm">
            <entityName>Landuse map of the Maricopa County (2000)</entityName>
            <entityDescription>The Year 2000 Land Use coverage was created as a joint effort of MAG and MAG member agency staff. Land Use components were classified into 46 categories. The Year 2000 Land Use coverage is used for a variety of planning purposes including socioeconomic forecasting and air quality modeling.</entityDescription>
            <physical>
                <objectName>exlu00_utm</objectName>
                <dataFormat>
                    <externallyDefinedFormat>
                        <formatName>Shapefile</formatName>
                    </externallyDefinedFormat>
                </dataFormat>
                <distribution>
                    <online>
                        <url>http://data.gios.asu.edu/datasets/cap/369.zip</url>
                    </online>
                </distribution>
            </physical>
            <attributeList>
                <attribute id="369.FID">
                    <attributeName>FID</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Internal feature number.</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">OID</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Sequential unique whole numbers that are
                                        automatically generated.</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="369.Shape">
                    <attributeName>Shape</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>Feature geometry.</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">Geometry</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Coordinates defining the features.</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="369.LUPOLYID">
                    <attributeName>LUPOLYID</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>LUPOLYID</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">integer</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>unique polygon identifier</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="369.LUCODE">
                    <attributeName>LUCODE</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>LUCODE</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">integer</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>MAG land use code</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="369.MPA">
                    <attributeName>MPA</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>MPA</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Municipal Planning Area abbreviation</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="369.LUCODEMPA">
                    <attributeName>LUCODEMPA</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>LUCODEMPA</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Municipal Planning Area abbreviation</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="369.ACRES">
                    <attributeName>ACRES</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>ACRES</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">float</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Polygon area in acres</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="369.LASTUPDATE">
                    <attributeName>LASTUPDATE</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>LASTUPDATE</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html">Date</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>date of last update</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="369.CLASS">
                    <attributeName>CLASS</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>CLASS</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Land use class definition</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
                <attribute id="369.DESCRIPTIO">
                    <attributeName>DESCRIPTIO</attributeName>
                    <attributeDefinition>DESCRIPTIO</attributeDefinition>
                    <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">string</storageType>
                    <measurementScale>
                        <nominal>
                            <nonNumericDomain>
                                <textDomain>
                                    <definition>Detailed description of land use
                                        classes</definition>
                                </textDomain>
                            </nonNumericDomain>
                        </nominal>
                    </measurementScale>
                </attribute>
            </attributeList>
            <geometry>Polygon</geometry>
            <geometricObjectCount>23537</geometricObjectCount>
            <spatialReference>
                <horizCoordSysName>WGS_1984_UTM_Zone_12N</horizCoordSysName>
            </spatialReference>
            <horizontalAccuracy>
                <accuracyReport>not assessed</accuracyReport>
            </horizontalAccuracy>
            <verticalAccuracy>
                <accuracyReport>not assessed</accuracyReport>
            </verticalAccuracy>
        </spatialVector>
    </dataset>
</ns0:eml>